<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20058</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>58</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>31167, 20468, 15097, 11331, 10961, 10949,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عيسى، حدثنا هشيم، أخبرنا حصين، عن حبيب
بن أبي ثابت، عن محمد بن علي بن عبد الله بن عباس، عن أبيه، عن جده
عبد الله بن عباس، قال بت ليلة عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما
استيقظ من منامه أتى طهوره فأخذ سواكه فاستاك ثم تلا هذه الآيات ‏{‏
إن في خلق السموات والأرض واختلاف الليل والنهار لآيات لأولي الألباب
‏}‏ حتى قارب أن يختم السورة أو ختمها ثم توضأ فأتى مصلاه فصلى ركعتين
ثم رجع إلى فراشه فنام ما شاء الله ثم استيقظ ففعل مثل ذلك ثم رجع إلى
فراشه فنام ثم استيقظ ففعل مثل ذلك ثم رجع إلى فراشه فنام ثم استيقظ
ففعل مثل ذلك كل ذلك يستاك ويصلي ركعتين ثم أوتر ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
رواه ابن فضيل عن حصين قال فتسوك وتوضأ وهو يقول ‏{‏ إن في خلق
السموات والأرض ‏}‏ حتى ختم السورة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: I spent a night with the Prophet
(sal Allaahu alayhi wa sallam). When he woke up from his sleep (in
the latter part of the night for prayer) he came to his ablution
water. He took the tooth-stick and used it. He then recited the
verse: "Verily in the creation of the heavens and the earth and the
alternation of the night and the day are tokens (of His
Sovereignty) for men of understanding" (iii-190). He recited these
verses up to the end of the chapter or he finished the whole
chapter. He then performed ablution and came to the place of
prayer. He then said two rak'ahs of prayer. He then lay down on the
bed and slept as much as Allaah wished. He then got up and did the
same. He then lay down and slept. He then got up and did the same.
Every time he used the tooth-stick and offered two rak'ah of
prayer. He then offered the prayer known as witr.Abu Dawud said:
Fudail on the authority if Husain reported the wording: He then
used the tooth-stick and performed ablution while he was reciting
the verses: "Verily in the creation of the heaves and the earth..."
until he finished the chapter.</english-text>
</hadith>
