<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20067</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>67</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30301, 38349, 20672, 11107, 12156, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن أبي شعيب، وعبد العزيز بن يحيى الحرانيان،
قالا حدثنا محمد بن سلمة، عن محمد بن إسحاق، عن سليط بن أيوب، عن عبيد
الله بن عبد الرحمن بن رافع الأنصاري، ثم العدوي عن أبي سعيد الخدري،
قال سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو يقال له إنه يستقى لك من
بئر بضاعة وهي بئر يلقى فيها لحوم الكلاب والمحايض وعذر الناس ‏.‏ قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الماء طهور لا ينجسه شىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال أبو داود وسمعت قتيبة بن سعيد قال سألت قيم بئر بضاعة عن عمقها
قال أكثر ما يكون فيها الماء إلى العانة ‏.‏ قلت فإذا نقص قال دون
العورة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وقدرت أنا بئر بضاعة بردائي مددته عليها ثم
ذرعته فإذا عرضها ستة أذرع وسألت الذي فتح لي باب البستان فأدخلني
إليه هل غير بناؤها عما كانت عليه قال لا ‏.‏ ورأيت فيها ماء متغير
اللون ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuSa'id al-Khudri: I heard that the people
asked the Prophet of Allah (ﷺ): Water is brought for you from the
well of Buda'ah. It is a well in which dead dogs, menstrual clothes
and excrement of people are thrown. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
replied: Verily water is pure and is not defiled by anything.Abu
Dawud said I heard Qutaibah b. Sa'id say: I asked the person in
charge of the well of Bud'ah about the depth of the well. He
replied: At most the water reaches pubes. Then I asked: Where does
it reach when its level goes down ? He replied: Below the private
part of the body.Abu Dawud said: I measured the breadth of the well
of Buda'ah with my sheet which I stretched over it. I them measured
it with the hand. It measured six cubits in breadth. I then asked
the man who opened the door of garden for me and admitted me to it:
Has the condition of this well changed from what it had originally
been in the past ? He replied: No. I saw the color of water in this
well had changed.</english-text>
</hadith>
