<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20117</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>117</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>38349, 20672, 11107, 13110, 11706, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن يحيى الحراني، حدثنا محمد، - يعني
ابن سلمة - عن محمد بن إسحاق، عن محمد بن طلحة بن يزيد بن ركانة، عن
عبيد الله الخولاني، عن ابن عباس، قال دخل على علي - يعني ابن أبي
طالب - وقد أهراق الماء فدعا بوضوء فأتيناه بتور فيه ماء حتى وضعناه
بين يديه فقال يا ابن عباس ألا أريك كيف كان يتوضأ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قلت بلى ‏.‏ قال فأصغى الإناء على يده فغسلها ثم أدخل يده
اليمنى فأفرغ بها على الأخرى ثم غسل كفيه ثم تمضمض واستنثر ثم أدخل
يديه في الإناء جميعا فأخذ بهما حفنة من ماء فضرب بها على وجهه ثم
ألقم إبهاميه ما أقبل من أذنيه ثم الثانية ثم الثالثة مثل ذلك ثم أخذ
بكفه اليمنى قبضة من ماء فصبها على ناصيته فتركها تستن على وجهه ثم
غسل ذراعيه إلى المرفقين ثلاثا ثلاثا ثم مسح رأسه وظهور أذنيه ثم أدخل
يديه جميعا فأخذ حفنة من ماء فضرب بها على رجله وفيها النعل ففتلها
بها ثم الأخرى مثل ذلك ‏.‏ قال قلت وفي النعلين قال وفي النعلين ‏.‏
قال قلت وفي النعلين قال وفي النعلين ‏.‏ قال قلت وفي النعلين قال وفي
النعلين ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وحديث ابن جريج عن شيبة يشبه حديث علي لأنه
قال فيه حجاج بن محمد عن ابن جريج ومسح برأسه مرة واحدة ‏.‏ وقال ابن
وهب فيه عن ابن جريج ومسح برأسه ثلاثا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn’Abbas said: ‘Ali b. Abi Talib entered upon me
after he has passed water. He then called for water for ablution.
We brought to him a vessel containing water, and placed it before
him. He said: O Ibn’Abbas, may I not show you how the Messenger of
Allah(ﷺ) used to perform ablution? I replied : Why not? He then
inclined the vessel to his hand and washed it. He then put his
right hand in the vessel and poured water over the other hand and
washed his hands up to the wrist. He then rinsed his mouth and
snuffed up water. He then put both of his hands together in the
water and took out a handful of water and threw it upon the face.
He then inserted both of his thumbs in the front part of the ears.
He did like that twice and thrice. He then took a handful of water
and poured it over his forehead and left it running down his face.
He then washed his forearms up to the elbow three times. He then
wiped his head and the back of his ears. He then put both of his
hands together in the water and took a handful of it and threw it
on his foot. He had a shoe foot like that. Do you wash your foot
while it is in the shoe? He replied : Yes, while it is in the shoe.
This question and answer were repeated thrice. Abu Dawud said: The
version transmitted by Ibn Juraij from Shaibah is similar to the
one narrated by ‘ Ali. In this version Hajjaj reported on the
authority of Ibn Juraij the wording: He wiped his head once. Ibn
Wahb narrated from Ibn Juraij the wording: he wiped his head three
times.</english-text>
</hadith>
