<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20149</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>149</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20029, 20475, 11013, 10927, 11373</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا عبد الله بن وهب، أخبرني يونس
بن يزيد، عن ابن شهاب، حدثني عباد بن زياد، أن عروة بن المغيرة بن
شعبة، أخبره أنه، سمع أباه المغيرة، يقول عدل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأنا معه في غزوة تبوك قبل الفجر فعدلت معه فأناخ النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فتبرز ثم جاء فسكبت على يده من الإداوة فغسل كفيه ثم غسل
وجهه ثم حسر عن ذراعيه فضاق كما جبته فأدخل يديه فأخرجهما من تحت
الجبة فغسلهما إلى المرفق ومسح برأسه ثم توضأ على خفيه ثم ركب فأقبلنا
نسير حتى نجد الناس في الصلاة قد قدموا عبد الرحمن بن عوف فصلى بهم
حين كان وقت الصلاة ووجدنا عبد الرحمن وقد ركع بهم ركعة من صلاة الفجر
فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصف مع المسلمين فصلى وراء عبد
الرحمن بن عوف الركعة الثانية ثم سلم عبد الرحمن فقام رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم في صلاته ‏.‏ ففزع المسلمون فأكثروا التسبيح لأنهم
سبقوا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالصلاة فلما سلم رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال لهم ‏"‏ قد أصبتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو ‏"‏ قد أحسنتم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Mughirah b. Shu’bah reported: I was in the company
of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) in the expedition of Tabuk. He
abandoned the main road before the dawn prayer, and I also did the
same along with him. The Prophet (ﷺ) made his camel kneel down and
(went to ) relieve himself. He then came back and I poured water
upon his hands from the skin-vessel. He then washed his hands and
face. He tried to get his forearms out (of the gown), but the
sleeves of the gown were too narrow, so he entered back both his
hands, and brought them out from beneath the gown. He washed his
forearms up to the elbows and wiped his head and wiped over his
socks.80 He then mounted (his camel) and we began to proceed until
we found people offering the prayer. They brought forward ‘Abd
al-Rahman b. ‘Awf who was leading them in prayer. The Prophet(ﷺ)
stood in the row side by side with other Muslims. He performed the
second rak’ah of the prayer behind ‘Abd al-Rahman b. ‘Awf. Then
‘Abd al-Rahman uttered salutation. The Prophet(ﷺ) stood to perform
the remaining rak’ah of the prayer. The Muslims were alarmed. They
began to utter tasbih (Subhan Allah) presuming that they had
offered prayer before the Prophet (ﷺ) had done. When he uttered the
salutation (i.e. finished his prayer), he said: You were right, or
(he said) you did well.</english-text>
</hadith>
