<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20238</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>238</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ابن شهاب،
عن عروة، عن عائشة، رضى الله عنها أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
كان يغتسل من إناء - هو الفرق - من الجنابة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال معمر
عن الزهري في هذا الحديث قالت كنت أغتسل أنا ورسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم من إناء واحد فيه قدر الفرق ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وروى ابن عيينة نحو
حديث مالك ‏.‏ قال أبو داود سمعت أحمد بن حنبل يقول الفرق ستة عشر
رطلا ‏.‏ وسمعته يقول صاع ابن أبي ذئب خمسة أرطال وثلث ‏.‏ قال فمن
قال ثمانية أرطال قال ليس ذلك بمحفوظ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وسمعت أحمد
يقول من أعطى في صدقة الفطر برطلنا هذا خمسة أرطال وثلثا فقد أوفى ‏.‏
قيل الصيحاني ثقيل قال الصيحاني أطيب ‏.‏ قال لا أدري
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Aishah said: The Messenger of Allah (May peace be
upon him) used to take bath with from a vessel (which contained
seven to eight seers, i.e., fifteen to sixteen pounds) because of
sexual intercourse.Abu Dawud said: The version narrated by Mu’ammar
on the authority of al-Zuhri has: She (‘A’ishah) said: I and the
Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him) took a bath from a
vessel which was equal to al-faraq in measurement (i.e., containing
water about seven or eight seers).Abu Dawud said: Ibn ‘Uyainah also
narrated like the version of Malik.Abu Dawud said; I heard Ahmad b.
Hanbal say: Al-Faraq contains sixteen rotls (of water). I also
heard him say: The sa’of of Ibn Abi Dhi’b contained 5 rotls (of
water). The view that a sa’ contains eight rotls (of water) is not
safe.Abu Dawud said: I heard Ahmad (b. Hanbal) say: Whoever gave 5
1/3 rotls (measuring) with our rotl alms of fitr (sadaqat al-fitr),
he gave in full, Thereupon he was questioned: Are the dates called
al-saihani heavier (can one sa’ of them be given as alms of fitr)?
He replied: The dates called al-saihani are good. But I do not know
(whether water is heavier or the dates).</english-text>
</hadith>
