<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20245</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>245</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20330, 11060, 11011, 11211, 17,
61</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد بن مسرهد، حدثنا عبد الله بن داود، عن
الأعمش، عن سالم، عن كريب، حدثنا ابن عباس، عن خالته، ميمونة قالت
وضعت للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم غسلا يغتسل به من الجنابة فأكفأ الإناء
على يده اليمنى فغسلها مرتين أو ثلاثا ثم صب على فرجه فغسل فرجه
بشماله ثم ضرب بيده الأرض فغسلها ثم تمضمض واستنشق وغسل وجهه ويديه ثم
صب على رأسه وجسده ثم تنحى ناحية فغسل رجليه فناولته المنديل فلم
يأخذه وجعل ينفض الماء عن جسده ‏.‏ فذكرت ذلك لإبراهيم فقال كانوا لا
يرون بالمنديل بأسا ولكن كانوا يكرهون العادة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال
مسدد فقلت لعبد الله بن داود كانوا يكرهونه للعادة فقال هكذا هو ولكن
وجدته في كتابي هكذا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Maimunah reported: I placed (the vessel of) water for
the Prophet (May peace be upon him) to wash himself because of
sexual intercourse. He lowered down the vessel and poured water on
his right hand. He then washed it twice or thrice. He then poured
water over his private parts and washed them with his left hand.
Then he put it on the ground and wiped it. He then rinsed his mouth
and snuffed up water, and washed his face and hands. He then poured
water over his head and body. Then he moved aside and washed his
feet. I handed him a garment, but he began to shake he moved aside
and washed his feet. I handed him a garment, but he began to shake
off water from his body. I mentioned it to Ibrahim. He said that
they (companions) did not think there was any harm in using the
garment (to wipe the water), but they disliked its use as a
habit.Abu Dawud said: Musaddad said: I asked ‘Abd Allah b. Dawud
whether they (the companions) disliked to make it a habit. He
replied: it (the tradition) goes in a similar way and I found it in
a similar way in this book of mine.</english-text>
</hadith>
