<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20286</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>0</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20276, 11220, 11013, 10511, 414</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا محمد بن أبي عدي، عن محمد،
- يعني ابن عمرو - قال حدثني ابن شهاب، عن عروة بن الزبير، عن فاطمة
بنت أبي حبيش، أنها كانت تستحاض فقال لها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إذا كان دم الحيضة فإنه دم أسود يعرف فإذا كان ذلك فأمسكي عن
الصلاة فإذا كان الآخر فتوضئي وصلي فإنما هو عرق ‏"‏ ‏.1قال أبو داود
قال ابن المثنى حدثنا به ابن أبي عدي من كتابه هكذا ثم حدثنا به بعد
حفظا قال حدثنا محمد بن عمرو عن الزهري عن عروة عن عائشة أن فاطمة
كانت تستحاض ‏.‏ فذكر معناه ‏.‏قال أبو داود وقد روى أنس بن سيرين عن
ابن عباس في المستحاضة قال إذا رأت الدم البحراني فلا تصلي وإذا رأت
الطهر ولو ساعة فلتغتسل وتصلي ‏.‏2وقال مكحول إن النساء لا تخفى عليهن
الحيضة إن دمها أسود غليظ فإذا ذهب ذلك وصارت صفرة رقيقة فإنها
مستحاضة فلتغتسل ولتصلي ‏.3قال أبو داود وروى حماد بن زيد عن يحيى بن
سعيد عن القعقاع بن حكيم عن سعيد بن المسيب في المستحاضة إذا أقبلت
الحيضة تركت الصلاة وإذا أدبرت اغتسلت وصلت ‏.2‏‏ وروى سمى وغيره عن
سعيد بن المسيب تجلس أيام أقرائها ‏.2‏وكذلك رواه حماد بن سلمة عن
يحيى بن سعيد عن سعيد بن المسيب ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وروى يونس عن الحسن
الحائض إذا مد بها الدم تمسك بعد حيضتها يوما أو يومين فهي مستحاضة
‏.‏ وقال التيمي عن قتادة إذا زاد على أيام حيضها خمسة أيام فلتصلي
‏.‏ قال التيمي فجعلت أنقص حتى بلغت يومين فقال إذا كان يومين فهو من
حيضها ‏.‏ وسئل ابن سيرين عنه فقال النساء أعلم بذلك
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Fatimah daughter of AbuHubaysh: Urwah ibn
az-Zubayr reported from Fatimah daughter of AbuHubaysh that her
blood kept flowing, so the Prophet (ﷺ) said to her: When the blood
of the menses comes, it is black blood which can be recognised; so
when that comes, refrain from prayer; but when a different type of
blood comes, perform ablution and pray, for it is (due only to) a
vein.Abu Dawud said: Ibn al-Muthanna narrates this tradition from
his book on the authority of Ibn 'Adi in a similar way. Later on he
transmitted it to us from his memory: Muhammad b. 'Amr reported to
us from al-Zuhri from 'Urwah on the authority of 'Aishah who said:
Fatimah used to have her blood flowing. He then reported the
tradition conveying the same meaning.Abu Dawud said: Anas b. Sirin
reported from Ibn 'Abbas about the woman who has a prolonged flow
of blood. He said: If she sees thick blood, she should not pray; if
she finds herself purified even for a moment, she should was an
pray.Makhul said: Menses are not hidden from women. Their blood is
black and thick. When it (blackness and thickness) goes away and
there appears yellowness and liquidness, that is the flow of blood
(from vein). She should wash and pray.Abu Dawud said: This
tradition has been transmitted by Sa'id b. al-Musayyab through a
different chain of narrators, saying: The woman who has a prolonged
flow of blood should abandon prayer when the menstruation begins;
when it is finished, she should wash and pray.Sumayy and others
have also reported it from Sa'id b. al-Musayyab. This version adds:
She should refrain (from prayer) during her menstrual period.Hammad
b. Salamah has reported it similarly from Yahya b. Sa'id on the
authority of Sa'id b. al-Musayyab.Abu Dawud said: Yunus has
reported from Al-Hasan: When the bleeding of a menstruating woman
extends (beyond the normal period), she should refrain (from
prayer), after her menses are over, for one or two days. Now she
becomes the woman who has a prolonged flow of blood.Al-Taimi
reported from Qatadah: If her menstrual period is prolonged by five
days, she should pray. Al-Taimi said: I kept on reducing (the
number of days) until I reached two days. He said: If the period
extends by two days, they will be counted from the menstrual
period. When Ibn Sirin was questioned about it, he said: Women have
better knowledge of that.</english-text>
</hadith>
