<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20321</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>321</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>31160, 20354, 11060, 11353</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سليمان الأنباري، حدثنا أبو معاوية
الضرير، عن الأعمش، عن شقيق، قال كنت جالسا بين عبد الله وأبي موسى
فقال أبو موسى يا أبا عبد الرحمن أرأيت لو أن رجلا أجنب فلم يجد الماء
شهرا ‏.‏ أما كان يتيمم فقال لا وإن لم يجد الماء شهرا فقال أبو موسى
فكيف تصنعون بهذه الآية التي في سورة المائدة ‏{‏ فلم تجدوا ماء
فتيمموا صعيدا طيبا ‏}‏ فقال عبد الله لو رخص لهم في هذا لأوشكوا إذا
برد عليهم الماء أن يتيمموا بالصعيد ‏.‏ فقال له أبو موسى وإنما كرهتم
هذا لهذا قال نعم فقال له أبو موسى ألم تسمع قول عمار لعمر بعثني رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في حاجة فأجنبت فلم أجد الماء فتمرغت في
الصعيد كما تتمرغ الدابة ثم أتيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك
له فقال ‏"‏ إنما كان يكفيك أن تصنع هكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فضرب بيده على الأرض
فنفضها ثم ضرب بشماله على يمينه وبيمينه على شماله على الكفين ثم مسح
وجهه ‏.‏ فقال له عبد الله أفلم تر عمر لم يقنع بقول
عمار</arabic-text>
<english-text>Shaqiq said: While I was sitting between 'Abd Allah
and Abu Musa, the latter said: Abu 'Abd al-Rahman, what do you
think if a man becomes defiled (because of seminal omission) and
does not find water for a month; should he not perform tayammum ?
He replied: No, even if he does not find water for a month. Abu
Musa then said: How will you do with the Qur'anic version (about
tayammum) in the chapter al-Ma'idah which says: "... and you find
no water, then go to clean, high ground" (5:6)? 'Abd Allah (b.
Mas'ud) then said: If they (the people) are granted concession in
this respect, they might perform tayammum with pure earth when
water is cold. Abu Musa said: For this (reason) you forbade it ? He
said: Yes. Abu Musa then said: Did you not hear what 'Ammar said to
'Umar ? (He said): The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sent me on some
errand. I had seminal emission and I did not find water. Therefore,
I rolled on the ground just as an animal rolls down. I then came to
the Prophet (ﷺ) and made a mention of that to him. He said: It
would have been enough for you to do thus. Then he struck the
ground with his hands and shook them off and then stuck the right
hand with his left hand and his left hand with his right hand (and
wiped) over his hands (up to the wrist) and wiped his face. 'Abd
Allah then said to him: Did you not see that 'Umar was not
satisfied with the statement of 'Ammar ?</english-text>
</hadith>
