<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20333</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>333</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11015, 11047</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، أخبرنا حماد، عن أيوب، عن أبي
قلابة، عن رجل، من بني عامر قال دخلت في الإسلام فأهمني ديني فأتيت
أبا ذر فقال أبو ذر إني اجتويت المدينة فأمر لي رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بذود وبغنم فقال لي ‏"‏ اشرب من ألبانها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال حماد
وأشك في ‏"‏ أبوالها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ هذا قول حماد ‏.‏ فقال أبو ذر فكنت أعزب
عن الماء ومعي أهلي فتصيبني الجنابة فأصلي بغير طهور فأتيت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بنصف النهار وهو في رهط من أصحابه وهو في ظل
المسجد فقال ‏"‏ أبو ذر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت نعم هلكت يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ وما أهلكك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت إني كنت أعزب عن الماء ومعي أهلي فتصيبني
الجنابة فأصلي بغير طهور فأمر لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بماء
فجاءت به جارية سوداء بعس يتخضخض ما هو بملآن فتسترت إلى بعيري
فاغتسلت ثم جئت فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر إن
الصعيد الطيب طهور وإن لم تجد الماء إلى عشر سنين فإذا وجدت الماء
فأمسه جلدك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود رواه حماد بن زيد عن أيوب لم يذكر
‏"‏ أبوالها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود هذا ليس بصحيح وليس في أبوالها إلا
حديث أنس تفرد به أهل البصرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A man from Banu 'Amir said: I embraced Islam and my
(ignorance of the) religion made me anxious (to learn the
essentials). I came to Abu Dharr. Abu Dharr said: The climate of
Medina did not suit me. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) ordered me to
have a few camels and goats. He said to me: Drink their milk. (The
narrator Hammad said): I doubt whether he (the Prophet) said:
"their urine." Abu Dharr said: I was away from the watering place
and I had my family with me. I would have sexual defilement and
pray without purification. I came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) at
noon. He was resting in the shade of the mosque along with a group
of Companions. He (the Prophet) said: Abu Dharr. I said: Yes, I am
ruined, Messenger of Allah. He said: What ruined you ? I said: I
was away from the watering place and I had family with me. I used
to be sexually defiled and pray without purification. He commanded
(to bring) water for me. Then a black slave-girl brought a vessel
of water that was shaking as the vessel was not full. I concealed
myself behind a camel and took bath and them came (to the Prophet).
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Abu Dharr, clean earth is a means
of ablution, even if you do not find water for ten years. When you
find water, you should make it touch your skin.Abu Dawud said: This
is transmitted by Hammad b. Zaid from Ayyub. This version does not
mention the words "their urine." This is not correct. The words
"their urine" occur only in the version reported by Anas and
transmitted only by the people of Basrah.</english-text>
</hadith>
