<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20332</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>332</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30154, 20423, 11282, 11047, 30175, 20423, 11282,
11047, 19856, 23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمرو بن عون، أخبرنا خالد الواسطي، عن خالد
الحذاء، عن أبي قلابة، ح وحدثنا مسدد، أخبرنا خالد، - يعني ابن عبد
الله الواسطي - عن خالد الحذاء، عن أبي قلابة، عن عمرو بن بجدان، عن
أبي ذر، قال اجتمعت غنيمة عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏
يا أبا ذر ابد فيها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فبدوت إلى الربذة فكانت تصيبني الجنابة
فأمكث الخمس والست فأتيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أبو ذر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فسكت فقال ‏"‏ ثكلتك أمك أبا ذر لأمك الويل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فدعا لي
بجارية سوداء فجاءت بعس فيه ماء فسترتني بثوب واستترت بالراحلة
واغتسلت فكأني ألقيت عني جبلا فقال ‏"‏ الصعيد الطيب وضوء المسلم ولو
إلى عشر سنين فإذا وجدت الماء فأمسه جلدك فإن ذلك خير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال
مسدد غنيمة من الصدقة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وحديث عمرو أتم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Dharr said: A few goats got collected with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He said: Abu Dharr, drive them to the wood.
I drove them to Rabadhah (a place near Medina). I would have sexual
defilement (during my stay there) and I would remain (in this
condition) for five or six days. Then I came to the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ). He said: O Abu Dharr. I kept silence. He then said: May
your mother bereave you, Abu Dharr: woe be to your mother. He then
called a black slave-girl for me. She brought a vessel which
contained water. She then concealed me by drawing a curtain and I
concealed myself behind a she-camel, and took a bath. I felt as if
I had thrown away a mountain from me. He said: Clean earth is a
means for ablution for a Muslim, even for ten years (he does not
find water); but when you find water, you should make it touch your
skin, for that is better.The version of Musaddad has: "the goats
(were collected) from the alms," and the tradition reported by 'Amr
is complete.</english-text>
</hadith>
