<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20353</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>353</hadith-number>
<chapter>Purification (Kitab Al-Taharah) - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20167, 11209, 11023</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، حدثنا عبد العزيز، - يعني ابن
محمد - عن عمرو بن أبي عمرو، عن عكرمة، أن أناسا، من أهل العراق جاءوا
فقالوا يا ابن عباس أترى الغسل يوم الجمعة واجبا قال لا ولكنه أطهر
وخير لمن اغتسل ومن لم يغتسل فليس عليه بواجب وسأخبركم كيف بدء الغسل
كان الناس مجهودين يلبسون الصوف ويعملون على ظهورهم وكان مسجدهم ضيقا
مقارب السقف إنما هو عريش فخرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في يوم
حار وعرق الناس في ذلك الصوف حتى ثارت منهم رياح آذى بذلك بعضهم بعضا
فلما وجد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تلك الريح قال ‏"‏ أيها الناس
إذا كان هذا اليوم فاغتسلوا وليمس أحدكم أفضل ما يجد من دهنه وطيبه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن عباس ثم جاء الله بالخير ولبسوا غير الصوف وكفوا
العمل ووسع مسجدهم وذهب بعض الذي كان يؤذي بعضهم بعضا من العرق
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Amr b. Abi 'Amr and 'Ikrimah reported: Some people
of Iraq came and said: Ibn 'Abbas, do you regard taking a bath on
Friday as obligatory ? He said: No, it is only a means of
cleanliness, and is better for one who washes oneself. Anyone who
does not take a bath, it is not essential for him. I inform you how
the bath (on Friday) commenced. The people were poor and used to
wear woolen clothes, and would carry loads on their backs. Their
mosque was small and its rood was lowered down. It was a sort of
trellis of vine. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) once came out on a hot
day and the people perspired profusely in the woolen clothes so
much so that foul smell emitted from them and it caused trouble to
each other. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) found the foul smell,
he said: O people, when this day (Friday) comes, you should take
bath and every one should anoint the best oil and perfume one has.
Ibn 'Abbas then said: Then Allah, the Exalted, provided wealth (to
the people) and they wore clothes other than the woolen, and were
spared from work, and their mosque became vast. The foul smell that
caused trouble to them became non-existent.</english-text>
</hadith>
