<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20485</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>485</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20159</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن الفضل السجستاني، وهشام بن عمار، وسليمان
بن عبد الرحمن الدمشقيان، بهذا الحديث - وهذا لفظ يحيى بن الفضل
السجستاني - قالوا حدثنا حاتم بن إسماعيل حدثنا يعقوب بن مجاهد أبو
حزرة عن عبادة بن الوليد بن عبادة بن الصامت أتينا جابرا - يعني ابن
عبد الله - وهو في مسجده فقال أتانا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
مسجدنا هذا وفي يده عرجون ابن طاب فنظر فرأى في قبلة المسجد نخامة
فأقبل عليها فحتها بالعرجون ثم قال ‏"‏ أيكم يحب أن يعرض الله عنه
بوجهه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ إن أحدكم إذا قام يصلي فإن الله قبل وجهه
فلا يبصقن قبل وجهه ولا عن يمينه وليبزق عن يساره تحت رجله اليسرى فإن
عجلت به بادرة فليقل بثوبه هكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ووضعه على فيه ثم دلكه ثم قال
‏"‏ أروني عبيرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقام فتى من الحى يشتد إلى أهله فجاء بخلوق
في راحته فأخذه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجعله على رأس العرجون
ثم لطخ به على أثر النخامة ‏.‏ قال جابر فمن هناك جعلتم الخلوق في
مساجدكم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ubadah ibn as-Samit: We came to Jabir ibn
Abdullah who was sitting in his mosque. He said: The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) came to us in this mosque and he had a twig of date-palm
of the kind of Ibn Tab. He looked and saw phlegm on the wall
towards qiblah. He turned to it and scraped it with the twig. He
then said: Who of you likes that Allah turns His face from him? He
further said: When any of you stands for praying, Allah faces him.
So he should not spit before him, nor on his right side. He should
spit on his left side under his left foot. If he is in a hurry
(i.e. forced to spit immediately), he should do with his cloth in
this manner. He then placed the cloth on his mouth and rubbed it
off. He then said: Bring perfume. A young man of the tribe stood
and hurried to his house and returned with perfume in his palm. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) took it and put it at the end of the twig.
He then stained the mark of phlegm with it. Jabir said: This is the
reason you use perfume in your mosques.</english-text>
</hadith>
