<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20498</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>498</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30255, 30249, 20468, 11419, 11339, 11419</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عباد بن موسى الختلي، وزياد بن أيوب، - وحديث عباد
أتم - قالا حدثنا هشيم، عن أبي بشر، - قال زياد أخبرنا أبو بشر، - عن
أبي عمير بن أنس، عن عمومة، له من الأنصار قال اهتم النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم للصلاة كيف يجمع الناس لها فقيل له انصب راية عند حضور
الصلاة فإذا رأوها آذن بعضهم بعضا فلم يعجبه ذلك قال فذكر له القنع -
يعني الشبور - وقال زياد شبور اليهود فلم يعجبه ذلك وقال ‏"‏ هو من
أمر اليهود ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فذكر له الناقوس فقال ‏"‏ هو من أمر النصارى
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانصرف عبد الله بن زيد بن عبد ربه وهو مهتم لهم رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأري الأذان في منامه - قال - فغدا على رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبره فقال له يا رسول الله إني لبين نائم ويقظان
إذ أتاني آت فأراني الأذان ‏.‏ قال وكان عمر بن الخطاب - رضى الله عنه
- قد رآه قبل ذلك فكتمه عشرين يوما - قال - ثم أخبر النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال له ‏"‏ ما منعك أن تخبرني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال سبقني عبد الله
بن زيد فاستحييت فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا بلال قم
فانظر ما يأمرك به عبد الله بن زيد فافعله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأذن بلال ‏.‏
قال أبو بشر فأخبرني أبو عمير أن الأنصار تزعم أن عبد الله بن زيد
لولا أنه كان يومئذ مريضا لجعله رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مؤذنا
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuUmayr ibn Anas: AbuUmayr reported on the
authority of his uncle who was from the Ansar (the helpers of the
Prophet): The Prophet (ﷺ) was anxious as to how to gather the
people for prayer. The people told him: Hoist a flag at the time of
prayer; when they see it, they will inform one another. But he (the
Prophet) did not like it. Then someone mentioned to him the horn.
Ziyad said: A horn of the Jews. He (the Prophet) did not like it.
He said: This is the matter of the Jews. Then they mentioned to him
the bell of the Christians. He said: This is the matter of the
Christians. Abdullah ibn Zayd returned anxiously from there because
of the anxiety of the Apostle (ﷺ). He was then taught the call to
prayer in his dream. Next day he came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
and informed him about it. He said: Messenger of Allah, I was
between sleep and wakefulness; all of a sudden a newcomer came (to
me) and taught me the call to prayer. Umar ibn al-Khattab had also
seen it in his dream before, but he kept it hidden for twenty days.
The Prophet (ﷺ) said to me (Umar): What did prevent you from saying
it to me? He said: Abdullah ibn Zayd had already told you about it
before me: hence I was ashamed. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: Bilal, stand up, see what Abdullah ibn Zayd tells you (to
do), then do it. Bilal then called them to prayer. AbuBishr
reported on the authority of AbuUmayr: The Ansar thought that if
Abdullah ibn Zayd had not been ill on that day, the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) would have made him mu'adhdhin.</english-text>
</hadith>
