<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20502</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>502</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 30106, 20232, 20297, 10693, 11066</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي، حدثنا عفان، وسعيد بن عامر، وحجاج،
- والمعنى واحد - قالوا حدثنا همام، حدثنا عامر الأحول، حدثني مكحول،
أن ابن محيريز، حدثه أن أبا محذورة حدثه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم علمه الأذان تسع عشرة كلمة والإقامة سبع عشرة كلمة الأذان ‏"‏
الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله
أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول
الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن محمدا
رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة حى على الصلاة حى
على الفلاح حى على الفلاح الله أكبر الله أكبر لا إله إلا الله
والإقامة الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا
الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا
رسول الله حى على الصلاة حى على الصلاة حى على الفلاح حى على الفلاح
قد قامت الصلاة قد قامت الصلاة الله أكبر الله أكبر لا إله إلا الله
‏"‏ ‏.‏ كذا في كتابه في حديث أبي محذورة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Mahdhurah reported ; The Messenger of Allah (May
peace be upon him) taught him nineteen phrases in ADHAN and
seventeen phrases in IQAMAH. ADHAN runs; Allah is most great. Allah
is most great. Allah is most great. Allah is most great; I testify
that there is no god but Allah. I testify that Muhammad is the
Messenger of Allah. I testify that Muhammad is the Messenger of
Allah; I testify that there is no god but Allah. I testify that
there is no god but Allah; I testify that Muhammad is the Messenger
of Allah, I testify that Muhammad is Messenger of Allah: come to
prayer, come to prayer, come to salvation; Allah is most great,
Allah is most great: there is no god but Allah. IQAMAH runs: Allah
is most great, Allah is most great. Allah is most great, Allah is
most great: I testify that there is no god but Allah, I testify
that there is no god but Allah; I testify that Muhammad is the
Messenger of Allah, I testify that Muhammad is the Messenger of
Allah; come to prayer; come to prayer: come to salvation. Come to
salvation; the time for prayer has come the time for prayer has
come: Allah is most great, Allah is most great: there is no god but
Allah. This is recorded in his collection (i.e., in the collection
of the narrator Hammam b. Yahya) according to the tradition
reported by Abu Mahdhurah (i.e., IQAMAH contains seventeen
phrases)</english-text>
</hadith>
