<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20507</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>507</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 30002, 20472, 20724, 11381, 11196,
32</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، عن أبي داود، ح وحدثنا نصر بن
المهاجر، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، عن المسعودي، عن عمرو بن مرة، عن ابن
أبي ليلى، عن معاذ بن جبل، قال أحيلت الصلاة ثلاثة أحوال وأحيل الصيام
ثلاثة أحوال وساق نصر الحديث بطوله واقتص ابن المثنى منه قصة صلاتهم
نحو بيت المقدس قط قال الحال الثالث أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قدم المدينة فصلى - يعني نحو بيت المقدس - ثلاثة عشر شهرا فأنزل الله
تعالى هذه الآية ‏{‏ قد نرى تقلب وجهك في السماء فلنولينك قبلة ترضاها
فول وجهك شطر المسجد الحرام وحيث ما كنتم فولوا وجوهكم شطره ‏}‏ فوجهه
الله تعالى إلى الكعبة ‏.‏ وتم حديثه وسمى نصر صاحب الرؤيا قال فجاء
عبد الله بن زيد رجل من الأنصار وقال فيه فاستقبل القبلة قال الله
أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد
أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة مرتين حى
على الفلاح مرتين الله أكبر الله أكبر لا إله إلا الله ثم أمهل هنية
ثم قام فقال مثلها إلا أنه قال زاد بعد ما قال ‏"‏ حى على الفلاح ‏"‏
‏.‏ قد قامت الصلاة قد قامت الصلاة ‏.‏ قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لقنها بلالا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأذن بها بلال وقال في الصوم قال
فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يصوم ثلاثة أيام من كل شهر
ويصوم يوم عاشوراء فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏ كتب عليكم الصيام كما كتب على
الذين من قبلكم ‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏ طعام مسكين ‏}‏ فكان من شاء أن يصوم
صام ومن شاء أن يفطر ويطعم كل يوم مسكينا أجزأه ذلك وهذا حول فأنزل
الله تعالى ‏{‏ شهر رمضان الذي أنزل فيه القرآن ‏}‏ إلى ‏{‏ أيام أخر
‏}‏ فثبت الصيام على من شهد الشهر وعلى المسافر أن يقضي وثبت الطعام
للشيخ الكبير والعجوز اللذين لا يستطيعان الصوم وجاء صرمة وقد عمل
يومه وساق الحديث ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Mu'adh ibn Jabal: Prayer passed through
three stages and fasting also passed through three stages. The
narrator Nasr reported the rest of the tradition completely. The
narrator, Ibn al-Muthanna, narrated the story of saying prayer
facing in the direction of Jerusalem. He said: The third stage is
that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came to Medina and prayed, i.e.
facing Jerusalem, for thirteen months. Then Allah, the Exalted,
revealed the verse: "We have seen thee turning thy face to Heaven
(for guidance, O Muhammad). And now verily We shall make thee turn
(in prayer) toward a qiblah which is dear to thee. So turn thy face
toward the Inviolable Place of Worship, and ye (O Muslims),
wherever ye may be, turn your face (when ye pray) toward it"
(ii.144). And Allah, the Reverend and the Majestic, turned (them)
towards the Ka'bah. He (the narrator) completed his tradition. The
narrator, Nasr, mentioned the name of the person who had the dream,
saying: And Abdullah ibn Zayd, a man from the Ansar, came. The same
version reads: And he turned his face towards the qiblah and said:
Allah is most great, Allah is most great; I testify that there is
no god but Allah, I testify that there is no god but Allah; I
testify that Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah, I testify that
Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah; come to prayer (he pronounced
it twice), come to salvation (he pronounced it twice); Allah is
Most Great, Allah is most great. He then paused for a while, and
then got up and pronounced in a similar way, except that after the
phrase "Come to salvation" he added. "The time for prayer has come,
the time for prayer has come." The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
Teach it to Bilal, then pronounce the adhan (call to prayer) with
the same words. As regards fasting, he said: The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) used to fast for three days every month, and would fast on the
tenth of Muharram. Then Allah, the Exalted, revealed the verse:
".......Fasting was prescribed for those before you, that ye may
ward off (evil)......and for those who can afford it there is a
ransom: the feeding of a man in need (ii.183-84). If someone wished
to keep the fast, he would keep the fast; if someone wished to
abandon the fast, he would feed an indigent every day; it would do
for him. But this was changed. Allah, the Exalted, revealed: "The
month of Ramadan in which was revealed the Qur'an ..........(let
him fast the same) number of other days" (ii.185). Hence the fast
was prescribed for the one who was present in the month (of
Ramadan) and the traveller was required to atone (for them);
feeding (the indigent) was prescribed for the old man and woman who
were unable to fast. (The narrator, Nasr, further reported): The
companion Sirmah, came after finishing his day's work......and he
narrated the rest of the tradition.</english-text>
</hadith>
