<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20634</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>634</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 30587, 20159, 12201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، وسليمان بن عبد الرحمن الدمشقي،
ويحيى بن الفضل السجستاني، قالوا حدثنا حاتم، - يعني ابن إسماعيل -
حدثنا يعقوب بن مجاهد أبو حزرة، عن عبادة بن الوليد بن عبادة بن
الصامت، قال أتينا جابرا - يعني ابن عبد الله - قال سرت مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم في غزوة فقام يصلي وكانت على بردة ذهبت أخالف بين
طرفيها فلم تبلغ لي وكانت لها ذباذب فنكستها ثم خالفت بين طرفيها ثم
تواقصت عليها لا تسقط ثم جئت حتى قمت عن يسار رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فأخذ بيدي فأدارني حتى أقامني عن يمينه فجاء ابن صخر حتى قام عن
يساره فأخذنا بيديه جميعا حتى أقامنا خلفه قال وجعل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يرمقني وأنا لا أشعر ثم فطنت به فأشار إلى أن أتزر بها
فلما فرغ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ يا جابر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
قلت لبيك يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إذا كان واسعا فخالف بين طرفيه
وإذا كان ضيقا فاشدده على حقوك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Ubadah b. al-Samit said: we came to Jabir b. ‘Abd
Allah. He said : I (Jabir) accompanied the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
in a battle. He got up to pray. I had a sheet of cloth upon me, and
I began to cross both the ends, but they did not reach (my
shoulders). It had fringes which I turned over and crossed the two
ends, and bowed down retaining it with my neck lest it should fall
down. Then I came and stood on the left side of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ). He then took and brought me around him and set me on his
right side. Then Ibn Sakhr came and stood on his left side. he then
took us with his both hands and made us stand behind him. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) began to look at me furtive glances, but I
could not understand. When I understood, he hinted at me tie the
wrapper. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) finished the prayer, he
said (to me): O Jabir. I said; Yes, Messenger of Allah. He said; if
it (the sheet) is wide, cross both its ends (over the shoulders);
if it is tight, tie it over your loins.</english-text>
</hadith>
