<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20704</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>704</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>34188, 32, 11065, 20031, 11023, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن إسماعيل البصري، حدثنا معاذ، حدثنا هشام،
عن يحيى، عن عكرمة، عن ابن عباس، قال أحسبه عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إذا صلى أحدكم إلى غير سترة فإنه يقطع صلاته الكلب
والحمار والخنزير واليهودي والمجوسي والمرأة ويجزئ عنه إذا مروا بين
يديه على قذفة بحجر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود في نفسي من هذا الحديث شىء
كنت أذاكر به إبراهيم وغيره فلم أر أحدا جاء به عن هشام ولا يعرفه ولم
أر أحدا يحدث به عن هشام وأحسب الوهم من ابن أبي سمينة - يعني محمد بن
إسماعيل البصري مولى بني هاشم - والمنكر فيه ذكر المجوسي وفيه ‏"‏ على
قذفة بحجر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذكر الخنزير وفيه نكارة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود ولم أسمع
هذا الحديث إلا من محمد بن إسماعيل وأحسبه وهم لأنه كان يحدثنا من
حفظه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Abbas: Ikrimah reported on the
authority of Ibn Abbas, saying: I think the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: When one of you prays without a sutrah, a dog, an ass, a pig,
a Jew, a Magian, and a woman cut off his prayer, but it will
suffice if they pass in front of him at a distance of over a
stone's throw.Abu Dawud said: There is something about this
tradition in my heart. I used to discuss it with Ibrahim and
others. I did not find anyone who narrated it from Hisham and knew
it. I did not know anyone who reported it from Hisham and knew it.
I did not know anyone who related it from Hisham. I think the
confusion is on the part of Ibn Abi Saminah that is, Muhammad b.
Isma'il al-Basri, the freed slave of Banu Hisham. In this tradition
the mention of words "a Magian" is rejected; the mention of the
words "at a stone's throw" and "a pig" is rejected.Abu Dawud said:
I did not hear this tradition except from Muhammad b. Isma'il b.
Samurrah and I think he was mistaken because he used to narrate to
us from his memory.</english-text>
</hadith>
