<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20723</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>723</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20258, 18897, 10940</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن عمر بن ميسرة الجشمي، حدثنا عبد
الوارث بن سعيد، قال حدثنا محمد بن جحادة، حدثني عبد الجبار بن وائل
بن حجر، قال كنت غلاما لا أعقل صلاة أبي قال فحدثني وائل بن علقمة عن
أبي وائل بن حجر قال صليت مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فكان إذا
كبر رفع يديه - قال - ثم التحف ثم أخذ شماله بيمينه وأدخل يديه في
ثوبه قال فإذا أراد أن يركع أخرج يديه ثم رفعهما وإذا أراد أن يرفع
رأسه من الركوع رفع يديه ثم سجد ووضع وجهه بين كفيه وإذا رفع رأسه من
السجود أيضا رفع يديه حتى فرغ من صلاته ‏.‏ قال محمد فذكرت ذلك للحسن
بن أبي الحسن فقال هي صلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فعله من فعله
وتركه من تركه ‏.‏ قال أبو داود روى هذا الحديث همام عن ابن جحادة لم
يذكر الرفع مع الرفع من السجود ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abd al-Jabbar b. Wa’il (b.Hujr) said: I was a small
boy and I did not understand the prayer of my father. So Wa’Il b.
‘Alqamah reported Wa’il b. Hujr as saying: I offered prayer along
with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He used to raise his hands when he
pronounced the takbir (Allah is most great), then pulled his
garment around him, then placed his right hand on his left, and
entered his hands in his garment. When he was about to bow he took
his hands out of his garment, and then raised them. And when he
raised his head after bowing, he raised his hands. He then
prostrated himself and placed his face (forehead on the ground)
between his hands. And when he raised his head after prostration,
he also raised his hands until he finished his prayer. Muhammad (a
narrator) said: I mentioned it to al-Hasan b. Abu al-Hasan who
said: This is how the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) offered prayer; some
did it and others abandoned it.Abu Dawud said: This tradition has
been narrated by Hammam from ibn Juhadah, but he did not mention
the raising of hands after he raised his head at the end of the
prostration.</english-text>
</hadith>
