<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20734</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>734</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 20443, 20169, 11697</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن حنبل، حدثنا عبد الملك بن عمرو، أخبرني
فليح، حدثني عباس بن سهل، قال اجتمع أبو حميد وأبو أسيد وسهل بن سعد
ومحمد بن مسلمة فذكروا صلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال أبو
حميد أنا أعلمكم بصلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكر بعض هذا قال
ثم ركع فوضع يديه على ركبتيه كأنه قابض عليهما ووتر يديه فتجافى عن
جنبيه قال ثم سجد فأمكن أنفه وجبهته ونحى يديه عن جنبيه ووضع كفيه حذو
منكبيه ثم رفع رأسه حتى رجع كل عظم في موضعه حتى فرغ ثم جلس فافترش
رجله اليسرى وأقبل بصدر اليمنى على قبلته ووضع كفه اليمنى على ركبته
اليمنى وكفه اليسرى على ركبته اليسرى وأشار بأصبعه ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
روى هذا الحديث عتبة بن أبي حكيم عن عبد الله بن عيسى عن العباس بن
سهل لم يذكر التورك وذكر نحو حديث فليح وذكر الحسن بن الحر نحو جلسة
حديث فليح وعتبة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abbas b. Sahl. Said: Abu Humaid, Abu Usaid, Sahl. B
Sa’d and Muhammad b. Maslamah (once) got together and discussed how
the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) used to offer his prayer. Abu Humaid
said: I am more informed than any of you regarding the prayer
offered by the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). Then he mentioned a part of
it, and said: He then bowed and placed his hands upon his knees as
if he caught hold of them; and bent them, keeping (his arms) away
from his sides. He them prostrated himself and placed his nose and
forehead (on the ground); and kept his arms away from his side, and
placed his palms (on the ground opposite his shoulders; he then
raised his head that every bone returned to its proper place; (he
then prostrated twice) until he finished this prostrations). Then
he sat down and spread out his left foot, putting forward the front
of his right foot towards the qiblah placing the palm of his right
hand on his right knee, and the palm of his left hand on his left
knee, and he pointed with his finger.Abu Dawud said: This tradition
has been narrated by Ibn al-Mubarak from Fulaih who heard ‘Abbas .
Sahl narrating it; but I do not remember it. I think he made the
mention of ‘Isa b. ‘Abd Allah who heard ‘Abbas b. Sahl saying: I
accompanied Abu Humaid al-Sa’idi.</english-text>
</hadith>
