<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20741</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>741</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20246, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي، أخبرنا عبد الأعلى، حدثنا عبيد الله،
عن نافع، عن ابن عمر، أنه كان إذا دخل في الصلاة كبر ورفع يديه وإذا
ركع وإذا قال سمع الله لمن حمده وإذا قام من الركعتين رفع يديه ويرفع
ذلك إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو داود الصحيح قول
ابن عمر وليس بمرفوع ‏.‏ قال أبو داود روى بقية أوله عن عبيد الله
وأسنده ورواه الثقفي عن عبيد الله أوقفه على ابن عمر وقال فيه وإذا
قام من الركعتين يرفعهما إلى ثدييه وهذا هو الصحيح ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
ورواه الليث بن سعد ومالك وأيوب وابن جريج موقوفا وأسنده حماد بن سلمة
وحده عن أيوب ولم يذكر أيوب ومالك الرفع إذا قام من السجدتين وذكره
الليث في حديثه قال ابن جريج فيه قلت لنافع أكان ابن عمر يجعل الأولى
أرفعهن قال لا سواء ‏.‏ قلت أشر لي ‏.‏ فأشار إلى الثديين أو أسفل من
ذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Nafi’ said on the authority of Ibn ‘Umar that when he
began prayer, he uttered the takbir( Allah is most great) and
raised his hands; and when he bowed( he raised his hands); and when
he said: “Allah listens to him who praises Him,” (he raised his
hands); and when he stood up at the end of two rak’ahs, he raised
his hands. He (Ibn ‘Umar) traced that back to the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ).Abu Dawud said: What is correct is that the tradition
reported by Ibn ‘Umar does not go back to the Prophet (may peace
beupon him).Abu Dawud said: The narrator Baqiyyah reported the
first part of this tradition from ‘Ubaid Allah and traced it back
to the Prophet (ﷺ); and the narrator al-Thaqafi reported it from
‘Ubaid Allah as a statement of Ibn ‘Umar himself(not from the
Porphet). In this version he said: When he stood at the end of two
rak’ahs he raised them up to his breasts. And this is the correct
version.Abu Dawud said: This tradition has been transmitted as a
statement of Ibn ‘Umar (and not of the Prophet) by al-Laith b.
Sa’d, Malik, Ayyub, and Ibn Juraij; and this has been narrated as a
statement of the Prophet (ﷺ) by Hammad b. Salamah alone on the
authority of Ayyub. Ayyub and Malik did not mention his raising of
hands when he stood after two prostrations, but al-Laith mentioned
it in his version. Ibn Juraij said in this version: I asked Nafi’:
Did Ibn ‘Umar raise (his hands) higher for the first time? He said:
No, I said: Point out to me. He then pointed to the breasts or
lower than that.</english-text>
</hadith>
