<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20760</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>760</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 20286, 32017, 11197, 11199, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا عبد العزيز
بن أبي سلمة، عن عمه الماجشون بن أبي سلمة، عن عبد الرحمن الأعرج، عن
عبيد الله بن أبي رافع، عن علي بن أبي طالب، - رضى الله عنه - قال كان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا قام إلى الصلاة كبر ثم قال ‏"‏ وجهت
وجهي للذي فطر السموات والأرض حنيفا مسلما وما أنا من المشركين إن
صلاتي ونسكي ومحياى ومماتي لله رب العالمين لا شريك له وبذلك أمرت
وأنا أول المسلمين اللهم أنت الملك لا إله لي إلا أنت أنت ربي وأنا
عبدك ظلمت نفسي واعترفت بذنبي فاغفر لي ذنوبي جميعا إنه لا يغفر
الذنوب إلا أنت واهدني لأحسن الأخلاق لا يهدي لأحسنها إلا أنت واصرف
عني سيئها لا يصرف سيئها إلا أنت لبيك وسعديك والخير كله في يديك
والشر ليس إليك أنا بك وإليك تباركت وتعاليت أستغفرك وأتوب إليك ‏"‏
‏.‏ وإذا ركع قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك ركعت وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت خشع لك سمعي
وبصري ومخي وعظامي وعصبي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا رفع قال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده
ربنا ولك الحمد ملء السموات والأرض وملء ما بينهما وملء ما شئت من شىء
بعد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا سجد قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك سجدت وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت سجد
وجهي للذي خلقه وصوره فأحسن صورته وشق سمعه وبصره وتبارك الله أحسن
الخالقين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا سلم من الصلاة قال ‏"‏ اللهم اغفر لي ما قدمت
وما أخرت وما أسررت وما أعلنت وما أسرفت وما أنت أعلم به مني أنت
المقدم والمؤخر لا إله إلا أنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Ali b. Ali Talib said: When the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) stood up for prayer, he uttered the takbir (Allah is most
great), then said: I have turned my face, breaking with all others,
towards Him Who created the heavens and the earth, and I am not a
polytheist. My prayer and my devotion, my life and my death belong
to Allah, the Lord of the Universe, Who has no partner. That is
what I have been commanded, and I am first of Muslims (those who
surrender themselves). O Allah, Thou art the King. There is no God
but Thee. Thou art my Lord and I am Thy servant. I have wronged
myself, but I acknowledge my sin, so forgive me all my sins; Thou
Who alone canst forgive sins; and guide me to the best qualities.
Thou Who alone canst guide to the best of them; and turn me from
evil ones. Thou who alone canst turn from evil qualities. I come to
serve and please Thee. All good is in Thy Hands, and evil does not
pertain to Thee. I seek refuge in Thee and turn to Thee, Who art
blessed and exalted. I ask Thy forgiveness and turn to thee in
repentance. When he bowed, he said: O Allah, to Thee I bow, in Thee
I trust, and to Thee I submit myself. My hearing, my sight, my
brain, my bone and my sinews humble themselves before Thee. When he
raised his head, he said: Allah listens to him who praises Him. O
our lord, and all praises be to Thee in the whole of the heavens
and the earth, and what is between them, and in whatever Thou
creates afterwards. When he prostrated himself, he said: O Allah,
to Thee I prostrate myself, to Thee I trust, and to Thee I submit
myself. My face prostrated itself before Him Who created it,
fashioned it, and fashioned it in the best shape, and brought forth
its hearing and seeing. Blessed is Allah, the best of creators.
When he saluted at the end of the prayer, he said: O Allah, forgive
me my former and my latter sins, my open and secret sins, my sins
in exceeding the limits, and what Thou knowest better than I. Thou
art He Who puts forward and puts back. There is deity but
Thee.</english-text>
</hadith>
