<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20786</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>786</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30154, 20468, 11298, 14432, 17, 4</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمرو بن عون، أخبرنا هشيم، عن عوف، عن يزيد
الفارسي، قال سمعت ابن عباس، قال قلت لعثمان بن عفان ما حملكم أن
عمدتم، إلى براءة وهي من المئين وإلى الأنفال وهي من المثاني
فجعلتموهما في السبع الطول ولم تكتبوا بينهما سطر ‏{‏ بسم الله الرحمن
الرحيم ‏}‏ قال عثمان كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مما ينزل عليه
الآيات فيدعو بعض من كان يكتب له ويقول له ‏"‏ ضع هذه الآية في السورة
التي يذكر فيها كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وتنزل عليه الآية والآيتان فيقول مثل
ذلك وكانت الأنفال من أول ما أنزل عليه بالمدينة وكانت براءة من آخر
ما نزل من القرآن وكانت قصتها شبيهة بقصتها فظننت أنها منها فمن هناك
وضعتهما في السبع الطول ولم أكتب بينهما سطر ‏{‏ بسم الله الرحمن
الرحيم ‏}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Uthman ibn Affan: :Yazid al-Farisi said: I
heard Ibn Abbas say: I asked Uthman ibn Affan: What moved you to
put the (Surah) al-Bara'ah which belongs to the mi'in (surahs)
(containing one hundred verses) and the (Surah) al-Anfal which
belongs to the mathani (Surahs) in the category of as-sab'u
at-tiwal (the first long surah or chapters of the Qur'an), and you
did not write "In the name of Allah, the Compassionate, the
Merciful" between them? Uthman replied: When the verses of the
Qur'an were revealed to the Prophet (ﷺ), he called someone to write
them down for him and said to him: Put this verse in the surah in
which such and such has been mentioned; and when one or two verses
were revealed, he used to say similarly (regarding them). (Surah)
al-Anfal is the first surah that was revealed at Medina, and
(Surah) al-Bara'ah was revealed last in the Qur'an, and its
contents were similar to those of al-Anfal. I, therefore, thought
that it was a part of al-Anfal. Hence I put them in the category of
as-sab'u at-tiwal (the seven lengthy surahs), and I did not write
"In the name of Allah, the Compassionate, the Merciful" between
them.</english-text>
</hadith>
