<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20821</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>821</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 10606, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن العلاء بن عبد الرحمن، أنه
سمع أبا السائب، مولى هشام بن زهرة يقول سمعت أبا هريرة، يقول قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من صلى صلاة لم يقرأ فيها بأم
القرآن فهي خداج فهي خداج فهي خداج غير تمام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقلت يا أبا
هريرة إني أكون أحيانا وراء الإمام ‏.‏ قال فغمز ذراعي وقال اقرأ بها
يا فارسي في نفسك فإني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏
قال الله تعالى قسمت الصلاة بيني وبين عبدي نصفين فنصفها لي ونصفها
لعبدي ولعبدي ما سأل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
اقرءوا يقول العبد ‏{‏ الحمد لله رب العالمين ‏}‏ يقول الله عز وجل
حمدني عبدي يقول العبد ‏{‏ الرحمن الرحيم ‏}‏ يقول الله عز وجل أثنى
على عبدي يقول العبد ‏{‏ مالك يوم الدين ‏}‏ يقول الله عز وجل مجدني
عبدي يقول العبد ‏{‏ إياك نعبد وإياك نستعين ‏}‏ يقول الله وهذه بيني
وبين عبدي ولعبدي ما سأل يقول العبد ‏{‏ اهدنا الصراط المستقيم * صراط
الذين أنعمت عليهم غير المغضوب عليهم ولا الضالين ‏}‏ يقول الله
فهؤلاء لعبدي ولعبدي ما سأل ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah reported the Messenger of Allah (May
peace be upon him) as saying: If anyone observes a prayer in which
he does not recite Umm al-Qur’an, it is incomplete, it is
incomplete, it is incomplete, and deficient. (The narrator said) I
said: Abu Hurairah, sometime I pray behind the imam(then what
should I do)? Pressing my hand he replied: O Persian, recite it
inwardly, for I heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) as saying that
Allah, Most High, has said: I have Me and the Half for my servant
and My servant will receive what he asks. The Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)
said: Recite. When the servant says: “praise be to Allah, the Lord
of the Universe,” Allah, Most High says: “My servant has praised
me.” When the servant says: “ The Compassionate, the merciful,
“Allah Most High says: “My servant has lauded me.” When the servant
says: “Owner of the Day of Judgment,” Allah, Most High, says: “My
servant has glorified Me” When the servant says: “ Thee do we
worship and of thee we ask help. “ (Allah says) “This is between Me
and My servant, and My servant will receive what he asks.” When the
servant says: “ Guide us to the Straight Path, the path of those
whom thou hast favoured, not ( the path) of those who earn thine
anger nor of those who go astray,”(Allah says: ) “This is for My
servant, and My servant will receive what he asks.”</english-text>
</hadith>
