<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20824</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>824</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30583, 30355, 20744, 11671, 11066</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الربيع بن سليمان الأزدي، حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف،
حدثنا الهيثم بن حميد، أخبرني زيد بن واقد، عن مكحول، عن نافع بن
محمود بن الربيع الأنصاري، قال نافع أبطأ عبادة بن الصامت عن صلاة
الصبح، فأقام أبو نعيم المؤذن الصلاة فصلى أبو نعيم بالناس وأقبل
عبادة وأنا معه، حتى صففنا خلف أبي نعيم وأبو نعيم يجهر بالقراءة فجعل
عبادة يقرأ بأم القرآن فلما انصرف قلت لعبادة سمعتك تقرأ بأم القرآن
وأبو نعيم يجهر قال أجل صلى بنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعض
الصلوات التي يجهر فيها بالقراءة قال فالتبست عليه القراءة فلما انصرف
أقبل علينا بوجهه وقال ‏"‏ هل تقرءون إذا جهرت بالقراءة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
بعضنا إنا نصنع ذلك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فلا وأنا أقول ما لي ينازعني القرآن
فلا تقرءوا بشىء من القرآن إذا جهرت إلا بأم القرآن ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Nafi’b. Mahmudb. Al-Rabi’ Al-Ansari said: “Ubadah b.
al-samit came to late to lead the morning prayer. Abu Nu’aim, the
mu’adhdhin, pronounced the takbir and he led the people in prayer.
Then Ubadah came and I was with him. We Joined the row behind Abu
Nu’aim, while Abu Nu’aim was reciting the Qur’an loudly. Then
‘Ubadah began to recite the Umm al-Quran (I.e Surah al Fatihah).
When he finished, I said to Ubadah: I heard you reciting the Umm
al-Qur’an while Abu Nu’aim was reciting Qur’an loudly. He replied:
yes&gt; The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) led us in a certain prayer in
which the Qur’an is recited loudly, but he became confused in the
recitation. When he finished he turned his face to us and said: Do
you recite when I recite the Qur’an loudly? Some of us said: we do
so; this is why I said to myself: What is that which confused me
(in the recitation of ) the Qur’an. Do not recite anything from the
Qur’an when I recite it loudly except the Umm
al-Qur’an.</english-text>
</hadith>
