<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20827</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>827</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 30304, 30560, 30485, 20005, 11013, 11002,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، وأحمد بن محمد المروزي، ومحمد بن أحمد بن
أبي خلف، وعبد الله بن محمد الزهري، وابن السرح، قالوا حدثنا سفيان،
عن الزهري، سمعت ابن أكيمة، يحدث سعيد بن المسيب قال سمعت أبا هريرة،
يقول صلى بنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاة نظن أنها الصبح
بمعناه إلى قوله ‏"‏ ما لي أنازع القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال
مسدد في حديثه قال معمر فانتهى الناس عن القراءة فيما جهر به رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقال ابن السرح في حديثه قال معمر عن الزهري
قال أبو هريرة فانتهى الناس ‏.‏ وقال عبد الله بن محمد الزهري من
بينهم قال سفيان وتكلم الزهري بكلمة لم أسمعها فقال معمر إنه قال
فانتهى الناس ‏.‏ قال أبو داود ورواه عبد الرحمن بن إسحاق عن الزهري
وانتهى حديثه إلى قوله ‏"‏ ما لي أنازع القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ورواه الأوزاعي
عن الزهري قال فيه قال الزهري فاتعظ المسلمون بذلك فلم يكونوا يقرءون
معه فيما يجهر به صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو داود سمعت محمد بن
يحيى بن فارس قال قوله فانتهى الناس ‏.‏ من كلام الزهري
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said: The Messenger of Allah(May peace
be upon him) led us in prayer, that was, we think, the dawn prayer,
He further narrated this tradition up to the words “what is the
matter with me that I have been contended with in (the recitation
of ) the Qur’an.”Abu Dawud said: Musaddad in his tradition said
that Ma’mar said: The people ceased to recit (the Qur’an) at the
prayer in which the Messenger of Allah(May peace be upon him)
recited aloud. Ibn al-Sarh said in his version that Ma’mar reported
from al-Zuhrl on the authority of Ab Hurairah. Then the people
ceased (to recite behind the imam).Another version says: Sufyan
said: Al-Zuhrl spoke a word that I could not hear. Then Ma’mar
said; He said: Then people ceased (to recite the Qur’an)Abu Dawud
said: This tradition has been narrated by ‘Abd al-Raman b. Ishaq on
the authority of al-Zuhrl. This version ends at the words: “What is
the matter with me that I am contended with in (the recitation of )
the Qur’an. Al-Awza’ I also narrated it on the authority of
al-Zuhri. This version has: Al-Zuhrl said: The Muslims took lesson
from that and thenceforth they did not recite (the Qur’an) at the
prayer in which he (the Prophet) recited a loud.Abu Dawud said: I
heard Muhammad b. Yaya b. Faris say: The words “ the people ceased
to recite (the Qur’an)” is a statement of al-zuhri.</english-text>
</hadith>
