<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20856</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>856</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20157, 30170, 20031, 11201, 11168, 11212,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني القعنبي، حدثنا أنس يعني ابن عياض، ح وحدثنا ابن
المثنى، حدثني يحيى بن سعيد، عن عبيد الله، - وهذا لفظ ابن المثنى -
حدثني سعيد بن أبي سعيد، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم دخل المسجد فدخل رجل فصلى ثم جاء فسلم على رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فرد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عليه السلام
وقال ‏"‏ ارجع فصل فإنك لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجع الرجل فصلى كما كان صلى
ثم جاء إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسلم عليه فقال له رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعليك السلام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ارجع فصل فإنك لم
تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى فعل ذلك ثلاث مرار فقال الرجل والذي بعثك بالحق ما
أحسن غير هذا فعلمني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إذا قمت إلى الصلاة فكبر ثم اقرأ ما
تيسر معك من القرآن ثم اركع حتى تطمئن راكعا ثم ارفع حتى تعتدل قائما
ثم اسجد حتى تطمئن ساجدا ثم اجلس حتى تطمئن جالسا ثم افعل ذلك في
صلاتك كلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال القعنبي عن سعيد بن أبي سعيد
المقبري عن أبي هريرة وقال في آخره ‏"‏ فإذا فعلت هذا فقد تمت صلاتك
وما انتقصت من هذا شيئا فإنما انتقصته من صلاتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال فيه ‏"‏
إذا قمت إلى الصلاة فأسبغ الوضوء ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said: When the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)
entered the mosque, a man also entered it and prayed. He then came
and saluted the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)
returned the salutation and said to him: Go back and pray, for you
have not prayed. The man returned and prayed as he prayed before.
He then came to prophet(ﷺ) and saluted him. The Messenger of
Allah(ﷺ) said to him: “ And upon you be peace. “ Go back and pray,
for you have not prayed. He did so three times. Then the man said:
By Him who has sent you(as a Prophet) with truth; I cannot do
better than this; so teach me. He said: When you get up to pray,
utter the takbir(Allah is most great); then recite a convenient
portion of the Qur’an; then bow and remain quietly in that
position; then sit and remain quietly in that position; then raise
yourself and stand erect: then prostrate yourself and remain
quietly in that position; then sit and remain quietly in that
position; then do that throughout all your prayer.Abu Dawud said:
Al-Qa’nabi reported this tradition from Sa’id b. Abi Sa’Id on the
authority of Abu Hurairah. This version has the wording in the
last: When you do this, then your prayer is completed. If you omit
anything form this, you omit that much from your prayer. This
version also has the wording: when you get up for praying, perform
the abulation perfectly.</english-text>
</hadith>
