<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20858</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>858</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20219, 20297, 11151, 11710, 325,
323</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي، حدثنا هشام بن عبد الملك، والحجاج
بن منهال، قالا حدثنا همام، حدثنا إسحاق بن عبد الله بن أبي طلحة، عن
علي بن يحيى بن خلاد، عن أبيه، عن عمه، رفاعة بن رافع بمعناه قال فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنها لا تتم صلاة أحدكم حتى يسبغ
الوضوء كما أمره الله عز وجل فيغسل وجهه ويديه إلى المرفقين ويمسح
برأسه ورجليه إلى الكعبين ثم يكبر الله عز وجل ويحمده ثم يقرأ من
القرآن ما أذن له فيه وتيسر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذكر نحو حديث حماد قال ‏"‏ ثم
يكبر فيسجد فيمكن وجهه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال همام وربما قال ‏"‏ جبهته من الأرض
حتى تطمئن مفاصله وتسترخي ثم يكبر فيستوي قاعدا على مقعده ويقيم صلبه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فوصف الصلاة هكذا أربع ركعات حتى فرغ ‏"‏ لا تتم صلاة أحدكم
حتى يفعل ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Rifa'ah ibn Rafi': This version (of Hadith
No 856) adds: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: The prayer of any of
you is not complete until he performs ablution perfectly, as Allah,
the Exalted, has ordered you. He should wash his face and hands up
to the elbows, and wipe his head and (wash) his feet up to the
ankles. Then he should exalt Allah and praise Him. Then he should
recite the Qur'an as much as it is convenient for him. (Narrator
then narrated the tradition like Hammad's, No. 856). He said: He
then utter the takbir and prostration himself so that his face is
at rest. Hammam (sub-narrator) said: Sometimes he reported: So that
his forehead is at rest on the ground, and his joints return to
their places and are loosened. Then he should say the takbir and
then sit right on his hips and erect his back. He described the
nature of prayer in this way by offering four rak'ahs until he
finished it. The prayer of any of you is not complete unless he
does so.</english-text>
</hadith>
