<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20874</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>874</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20296, 20386, 20020, 11381, 11633, 145</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو الوليد الطيالسي، وعلي بن الجعد، قالا حدثنا
شعبة، عن عمرو بن مرة، عن أبي حمزة، مولى الأنصار عن رجل، من بني عبس
عن حذيفة، أنه رأى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي من الليل فكان
يقول ‏"‏ الله أكبر - ثلاثا - ذو الملكوت والجبروت والكبرياء والعظمة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم استفتح فقرأ البقرة ثم ركع فكان ركوعه نحوا من قيامه وكان
يقول في ركوعه ‏"‏ سبحان ربي العظيم سبحان ربي العظيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم رفع
رأسه من الركوع فكان قيامه نحوا من ركوعه يقول ‏"‏ لربي الحمد ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ثم سجد فكان سجوده نحوا من قيامه فكان يقول في سجوده ‏"‏ سبحان ربي
الأعلى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم رفع رأسه من السجود وكان يقعد فيما بين السجدتين
نحوا من سجوده وكان يقول ‏"‏ رب اغفر لي رب اغفر لي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصلى أربع
ركعات فقرأ فيهن البقرة وآل عمران والنساء والمائدة أو الأنعام شك
شعبة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hudhayfah: Hudhayfah saw the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) praying at night. He said: Allah is most great" three
times, "Possessor of kingdom, grandeur, greatness and majesty." He
then began (his prayer) and recited Surah al-Baqarah; then he bowed
and he paused in bowing as long as he stood up; he said while
bowing, "Glory be to my mighty Lord," "Glory be to my mighty Lord"
; then he raised his head, after bowing: then he stood up and he
paused as long as he paused in bowing and said, "Praise be to my
Lord" ; then he prostrated and paused in prostration as long as he
paused in the standing position; he said while prostrating: "Glory
be to my most high Lord"; then he raised his head after
prostration, and sat as long as he prostrated, and said while
sitting: "O my Lord forgive me." He offered four rak'ahs of prayer
and recited in them Surah al-Baqarah, Aal Imran, an-Nisa,
al-Ma'idah, or al-An'am. The narrator Shu'bah
doubted.</english-text>
</hadith>
