<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>20941</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>940</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن أبي حازم بن دينار، عن سهل
بن سعد، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذهب إلى بني عمرو بن عوف
ليصلح بينهم وحانت الصلاة فجاء المؤذن إلى أبي بكر - رضى الله عنه -
فقال أتصلي بالناس فأقيم قال نعم ‏.‏ فصلى أبو بكر فجاء رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم والناس في الصلاة فتخلص حتى وقف في الصف فصفق الناس
وكان أبو بكر لا يلتفت في الصلاة فلما أكثر الناس التصفيق التفت فرأى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأشار إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم أن امكث مكانك فرفع أبو بكر يديه فحمد الله على ما أمره به رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من ذلك ثم استأخر أبو بكر حتى استوى في الصف
وتقدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى فلما انصرف قال ‏"‏ يا أبا
بكر ما منعك أن تثبت إذ أمرتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو بكر ما كان لابن أبي
قحافة أن يصلي بين يدى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما لي رأيتكم أكثرتم من التصفيح من نابه
شىء في صلاته فليسبح فإنه إذا سبح التفت إليه وإنما التصفيح للنساء
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وهذا في الفريضة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl b. Sa’d said : The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) went
to Banu ‘Amr b. ‘Awf to effect reconciliation between them . in the
meantime the time of prayer came and the Mu’adhdhin came to Abu
Bakr and asked : Will you lead the people in prayer? I pronounce
the Iqamah. He said ; Yes. So Abiu Bakr led the prayer , and the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came back while the people were praying. He
penetrated through the rows and stood in the first row. The people
clapped but Abu Bakr did not pay any attention to it during prayer.
When the people clapped increasingly, he paid attention. He saw the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) made a sign to
him (saying); Stay at your place. Abu BAkr raised his hands and
praised Allah for the commandment the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had
given him (to lead the people in prayer). Abu Bakr then stepped
back and stood in the row. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) stepped
forward and led the prayer. When he finished the prayer, he said;
Abu Bakr, what prevented you staying (at your place) when I already
commented you to do so? Abu Bakr said ; it was not befitting for
the son of Abu Quhafah (Abu Bakr) to lead the prayer in the
presence of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said; What is the matter that I saw you clapping frequently during
prayer? If anything happens to someone during prayer, he should say
“Glory be to Allah,” for when he glorifies Allah. He pays attention
to him. Clapping applies only to women.Abu Dawud said: This is
operative in the obligatory prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
