<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21008</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1007</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer (Kitab Al-Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>38363, 28050, 25316, 11574</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الوهاب بن نجدة، حدثنا أشعث بن شعبة، عن
المنهال بن خليفة، عن الأزرق بن قيس، قال صلى بنا إمام لنا يكنى أبا
رمثة فقال صليت هذه الصلاة - أو مثل هذه الصلاة - مع النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال وكان أبو بكر وعمر يقومان في الصف المقدم عن يمينه
وكان رجل قد شهد التكبيرة الأولى من الصلاة فصلى نبي الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم سلم عن يمينه وعن يساره حتى رأينا بياض خديه ثم انفتل
كانفتال أبي رمثة - يعني نفسه - فقام الرجل الذي أدرك معه التكبيرة
الأولى من الصلاة يشفع فوثب إليه عمر فأخذ بمنكبه فهزه ثم قال اجلس
فإنه لم يهلك أهل الكتاب إلا أنه لم يكن بين صلواتهم فصل ‏.‏ فرفع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بصره فقال ‏"‏ أصاب الله بك يا ابن الخطاب
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وقد قيل أبو أمية مكان أبي رمثة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Azraq ibn Qays: An imam of ours, whose
kunyah (surname) was AbuRimthah, led us in prayer and said: I
prayed this prayer, or one like it, with the Prophet (ﷺ). AbuBakr
and Umar were standing in the front row on his right and there was
a man who had been present at the first takbir in the prayer. The
Prophet of Allah (ﷺ) offered the prayer, then gave the salutation
to his right and his left so that we saw the whiteness of his
cheeks, then turned away as AbuRimthah (meaning himself) had done.
The man who has been present with him at the first takbir in the
prayer then got up to pray another prayer, whereupon Umar leaped up
and, seizing him by the shoulders, shook him and said: Sit down,
for the People of the Book perished for no other reason than that
there was no interval between their prayers. The Prophet (ﷺ) raised
his eyes and said: Allah has made you say what is right, son of
al-Khattab.Abu Dawud said: Sometimes the name of Abu Umayyah is
narrated instead of Abu Rimthah.</english-text>
</hadith>
