<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21185</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1184</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Of The Prayer For Rain (Kitab al-Istisqa') - كتاب
الاستسقاء</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 20321, 11323, 19841, 394</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن يونس، حدثنا زهير، حدثنا الأسود بن قيس،
حدثني ثعلبة بن عباد العبدي، من أهل البصرة أنه شهد خطبة يوما لسمرة
بن جندب قال قال سمرة بينما أنا وغلام من الأنصار نرمي غرضين لنا حتى
إذا كانت الشمس قيد رمحين أو ثلاثة في عين الناظر من الأفق اسودت حتى
آضت كأنها تنومة فقال أحدنا لصاحبه انطلق بنا إلى المسجد فوالله
ليحدثن شأن هذه الشمس لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في أمته حدثا قال
فدفعنا فإذا هو بارز فاستقدم فصلى فقام بنا كأطول ما قام بنا في صلاة
قط لا نسمع له صوتا قال ثم ركع بنا كأطول ما ركع بنا في صلاة قط لا
نسمع له صوتا ثم سجد بنا كأطول ما سجد بنا في صلاة قط لا نسمع له صوتا
‏.‏ ثم فعل في الركعة الأخرى مثل ذلك قال فوافق تجلي الشمس جلوسه في
الركعة الثانية قال ثم سلم ثم قام فحمد الله وأثنى عليه وشهد أن لا
إله إلا الله وشهد أنه عبده ورسوله ثم ساق أحمد بن يونس خطبة النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Samurah ibn Jundub: When, a boy from the
Ansar and I were shooting (arrows) towards two of our targets, the
sun was sighted by the people at the height of two or three lances
above the horizon. It became black like the black herb called
tannumah. One of us said to his companion: Let us go to the mosque;
by Allah, this incident of the sun will surely bring something new
in the community of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). As we reached it,
we suddenly saw that he (the Prophet) had already come out (of his
house). He stepped forward for a long time as much as he could do
so in the prayer. But we did not hear his voice. He then performed
a bowing and prolonged it as much as he could do in the prayer. But
we did not hear his voice. He then prostrated himself with us and
prolonged it which he never did in the prayer before. But we did
not hear his voice. He then did similarly in the second rak'ah. The
sun became bright when he sat after the second rak'ah. Then he
uttered the salutation. He then stood up, praised Allah, and
extolled Him, and testified that there was no god but Allah and
testified that he was His servant and apostle. Ahmad ibn Yunus then
narrated the address of the Prophet (ﷺ).</english-text>
</hadith>
