<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21243</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1242</hadith-number>
<chapter>Detailed Rules of Law about the Prayer during Journey -
كتاب صلاة السفر</chapter>
<chain-index>11107, 11215, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>قال أبو داود وأما عبيد الله بن سعد فحدثنا قال حدثني
عمي، حدثنا أبي، عن ابن إسحاق، حدثني محمد بن جعفر بن الزبير، أن عروة
بن الزبير، حدثه أن عائشة حدثته بهذه القصة، قالت كبر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وكبرت الطائفة الذين صفوا معه ثم ركع فركعوا ثم سجد
فسجدوا ثم رفع فرفعوا ثم مكث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جالسا ثم
سجدوا هم لأنفسهم الثانية ثم قاموا فنكصوا على أعقابهم يمشون القهقرى
حتى قاموا من ورائهم وجاءت الطائفة الأخرى فقاموا فكبروا ثم ركعوا
لأنفسهم ثم سجد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسجدوا معه ثم قام رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسجدوا لأنفسهم الثانية ثم قامت الطائفتان
جميعا فصلوا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فركع فركعوا ثم سجد
فسجدوا جميعا ثم عاد فسجد الثانية وسجدوا معه سريعا كأسرع الإسراع
جاهدا لا يألون سراعا ثم سلم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسلموا
فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقد شاركه الناس في الصلاة كلها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Dawud said: This tradition has been transmitted
by 'Aishah through a different chain of narrators. She said: The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) uttered the takbir and the section that was
in the same row with him also uttered the takbir. He then bowed and
they also bowed, and he prostrated and they also prostrated. Then
he raised his head and they also raised (their heads). The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then remained seated. They prostrated alone
and stood up and retraced their footsteps and stood behind them.
Then the other section came; they stood up and uttered the takbir
and bowed by themselves. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) prostrated
himself and they also prostrated with him. Then the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) stood up and they performed the second prostration by
themselves. Then both the sections stood up and prayed with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He bowed and they also bowed, and then he
prostrated himself and they also prostrated themselves. Then he
returned and performed the second prostration and they also
prostrated with him as quickly as possible, showing no slackness in
quick prostration. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then uttered the
salutation. After that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) stood up. Thus
everyone participated in the entire prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
