<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21274</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1273</hadith-number>
<chapter>Voluntary Prayers - كتاب التطوع</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20029, 20377, 11154, 11211, 17,
2216</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا عبد الله بن وهب، أخبرني عمرو
بن الحارث، عن بكير بن الأشج، عن كريب، مولى ابن عباس أن عبد الله بن
عباس، وعبد الرحمن بن أزهر، والمسور بن مخرمة، أرسلوه إلى عائشة زوج
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا اقرأ عليها السلام منا جميعا وسلها
عن الركعتين بعد العصر وقل إنا أخبرنا أنك تصلينهما وقد بلغنا أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نهى عنهما ‏.‏ فدخلت عليها فبلغتها ما
أرسلوني به فقالت سل أم سلمة ‏.‏ فخرجت إليهم فأخبرتهم بقولها فردوني
إلى أم سلمة بمثل ما أرسلوني به إلى عائشة فقالت أم سلمة سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينهى عنهما ثم رأيته يصليهما أما حين صلاهما
فإنه صلى العصر ثم دخل وعندي نسوة من بني حرام من الأنصار فصلاهما
فأرسلت إليه الجارية فقلت قومي بجنبه فقولي له تقول أم سلمة يا رسول
الله أسمعك تنهى عن هاتين الركعتين وأراك تصليهما فإن أشار بيده
فاستأخري عنه ‏.‏ قالت ففعلت الجارية فأشار بيده فاستأخرت عنه فلما
انصرف قال ‏"‏ يا بنت أبي أمية سألت عن الركعتين بعد العصر إنه أتاني
ناس من عبد القيس بالإسلام من قومهم فشغلوني عن الركعتين اللتين بعد
الظهر فهما هاتان ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Kuraib, the client of Ibn 'Abbas: That 'Abd
Allah b. Abbas, 'Abd al-Rahman b. Azhar and al-Miswar b. Makhramah
sent him to 'Aishah, wife of the Prophet (ﷺ). They said: Convey our
regards to her from all of us and ask her about the two rak'ahs
after the 'Asr prayer, and tell her that we have been informed that
she prays them, and we are told that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
prohibited them. I entered upon her and told her that for which
they had sent me to her. She said: Ask Umm Salamah. I returned to
them (Ibn 'Abbas and others) and informed them about her opinion.
They sent me back to Umm Salamah with the same mission for which
they had sent me to 'Aishah. Umm Salamah said: I heard the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) prohibiting them, but later on I saw him
praying them. When he prayed them, he had offered the 'Asr prayer.
He then came to me while a number of women from Banu Haram from the
Ansar were sitting with me. He prayed these two rak'ahs. I sent a
slave girl to him and I told her: Stand beside him and tell him
that Umm Salamah has asked: Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), I heard you
prohibiting these two rak'ahs (after the afternoon prayer) but I
see you praying them yourself. If he makes a sign with his hand,
step backward from him. The slave girl did so. When he finished
prayer, he said: O daughter of Abu Umayyah, you asked about the
praying of two rak'ahs after the 'Asr prayer, in fact, some people
of 'Abd al-Qais has come to me with the news that their people had
embraced Islam. They hindered me from praying the two rak'ahs after
Zuhr prayer. It is those two rak'ahs (which I offered after the
'Asr prayer)</english-text>
</hadith>
