<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21347</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1346</hadith-number>
<chapter>Voluntary Prayers - كتاب التطوع</chapter>
<chain-index>11045, 20276, 19901, 11284, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن حسين الدرهمي، حدثنا ابن أبي عدي، عن بهز
بن حكيم، حدثنا زرارة بن أوفى، ‏:‏ أن عائشة، - رضى الله عنها - سئلت
عن صلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في جوف الليل، فقالت ‏:‏ كان
يصلي صلاة العشاء في جماعة، ثم يرجع إلى أهله فيركع أربع ركعات، ثم
يأوي إلى فراشه وينام وطهوره مغطى عند رأسه، وسواكه موضوع حتى يبعثه
الله ساعته التي يبعثه من الليل، فيتسوك ويسبغ الوضوء، ثم يقوم إلى
مصلاه فيصلي ثمان ركعات يقرأ فيهن بأم الكتاب وسورة من القرآن وما شاء
الله، ولا يقعد في شىء منها حتى يقعد في الثامنة، ولا يسلم، ويقرأ في
التاسعة، ثم يقعد فيدعو بما شاء الله أن يدعوه، ويسأله ويرغب إليه
ويسلم تسليمة واحدة شديدة، يكاد يوقظ أهل البيت من شدة تسليمه، ثم
يقرأ وهو قاعد بأم الكتاب، ويركع وهو قاعد، ثم يقرأ الثانية فيركع
ويسجد وهو قاعد، ثم يدعو ما شاء الله أن يدعو، ثم يسلم وينصرف، فلم
تزل تلك صلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى بدن فنقص من التسع
ثنتين، فجعلها إلى الست والسبع وركعتيه وهو قاعد حتى قبض على ذلك صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha, Ummul Mu'minin: Zurarah ibn Awfa said
that Aisha was asked about the midnight prayer of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ). She said: He used to offer his night prayer in
congregation and then return to his family (in his house) and pray
four rak'ahs. Then he would go to his bed and sleep, but the water
for his ablution was placed covered near his head and his
tooth-stick was also kept there until Allah awakened him at night.
He then used the tooth-stick, performed ablution perfectly then
came to the place of prayer and would pray eight rak'ahs, in which
he would recite Surah al-Fatihah, and a surah from the Qur'an as
Allah willed. He would not sit during any of them but sit after the
eighth rak'ah, and would not utter the salutation, but recite (the
Qur'an) during the ninth rak'ah. Then he would sit and supplicate
as long as Allah willed, and beg Him and devote his attention to
Him; He would utter the salutation once in such a loud voice that
the inmates of the house were almost awakened by his loud
salutation. He would then recite Surah al-Fatihah while sitting,
bow while sitting, and then recite the Qur'an during the second
rak'ah, and would bow and prostrate while sitting. He would
supplicate Allah as long as He willed, then utter the salutation
and turn away. This amount of prayer of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
continued till he put a weight. During that period he retrenched
two rak'ahs from nine and began to pray six and seven rak'ahs
standing and two rak'ahs sitting. This continued till he
died.</english-text>
</hadith>
