<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21354</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1353</hadith-number>
<chapter>Voluntary Prayers - كتاب التطوع</chapter>
<chain-index>31167, 20468, 15097, 11331, 30203, 20356, 15097,
11331, 10961, 10949</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عيسى، حدثنا هشيم، أخبرنا حصين، عن حبيب
بن أبي ثابت، ح وحدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا محمد بن فضيل، عن
حصين، عن حبيب بن أبي ثابت، عن محمد بن علي بن عبد الله بن عباس، عن
أبيه، عن ابن عباس، ‏:‏ أنه رقد عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فرآه
استيقظ فتسوك وتوضأ وهو يقول ‏:‏ ‏{‏ إن في خلق السموات والأرض ‏}‏
حتى ختم السورة، ثم قام فصلى ركعتين أطال فيهما القيام والركوع
والسجود، ثم إنه انصرف فنام حتى نفخ، ثم فعل ذلك ثلاث مرات بست ركعات،
كل ذلك يستاك ثم يتوضأ ويقرأ هؤلاء الآيات، ثم أوتر - قال عثمان ‏:‏
بثلاث ركعات، فأتاه المؤذن فخرج إلى الصلاة - وقال ابن عيسى ‏:‏ ثم
أوتر فأتاه بلال فآذنه بالصلاة حين طلع الفجر، فصلى ركعتى الفجر ثم
خرج إلى الصلاة - ثم اتفقا - وهو يقول ‏:‏ ‏"‏ اللهم اجعل في قلبي
نورا، واجعل في لساني نورا، واجعل في سمعي نورا، واجعل في بصري نورا،
واجعل خلفي نورا، وأمامي نورا، واجعل من فوقي نورا، ومن تحتي نورا،
اللهم وأعظم لي نورا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abd Allah b. 'Abbas said that he slept with the
Prophet (ﷺ). He saw that he (the Prophet) awoke, used tooth-stick,
performed ablution, and recited: "In the creation of the heavens
and earth" [3:190] to the end of the surah. Then he stood up and
prayed two rak'ahs in which he prolonged the standing, bowing, and
prostrations. He then uttered turned away and slept till he bagan
to snore. This he did three times. This made six rak'ahs in all. He
would use tooth-stick, then perform ablution, and recite those
verses. He then observed the witr prayer. The version of 'Uthman
has: with three rak'ahs. The mu'adhdhin then came to him and he
went out for prayer. The version of Ibn 'Isa adds: He then observed
witr prayer ; then Bilal came to him and called him for prayer when
the dawn broke. He then prayed the two rak'ahs of the dawn prayer.
He then went out for prayer. Then both the narrators were agreed:
He beagan to supplicate saying: O Allah, place light in my heart,
light in my tongue, light in my hearing, light in my eyesight,
light on my right hand, light on my left hand, light in front of
me, light behing me, light below me, O Allah, give me abundant
light.</english-text>
</hadith>
