<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21368</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1367</hadith-number>
<chapter>Voluntary Prayers - كتاب التطوع</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11223, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن مخرمة بن سليمان، عن كريب،
مولى ابن عباس أن عبد الله بن عباس، أخبره ‏:‏ أنه، بات عند ميمونة
زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وهي خالته - قال - فاضطجعت في عرض
الوسادة، واضطجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأهله في طولها، فنام
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى إذا انتصف الليل - أو قبله بقليل،
أو بعده بقليل - استيقظ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجلس يمسح النوم
عن وجهه بيده، ثم قرأ العشر الآيات الخواتم من سورة آل عمران، ثم قام
إلى شن معلقة فتوضأ منها فأحسن وضوءه، ثم قام يصلي، قال عبد الله ‏:‏
فقمت فصنعت مثل ما صنع، ثم ذهبت فقمت إلى جنبه، فوضع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يده اليمنى على رأسي فأخذ بأذني يفتلها، فصلى ركعتين،
ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، قال القعنبي
‏:‏ ست مرات، ثم أوتر، ثم اضطجع، حتى جاءه المؤذن فقام فصلى ركعتين
خفيفتين، ثم خرج فصلى الصبح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Abd Allah b. 'Abbas: That he spent a night
with Maimunah, wife of the Prophet (ﷺ), who was also his (Ibn
'Abbas's) maternal aunt. I lay towards the width of the pillow and
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and his wife slept towards its length.
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) slept. When half the night passed, or a
little before it or a little after it, the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
awoke and began to rub his face (eyes) to remove the sleep. He then
recited ten verses from the last part of Surah 'Al-Imran. Hen then
came to a bag of water that was hanging. He performed ablution from
it and performed his ablution well. He then stood up and prayed. I
also got up and did as he did. I then went and stood at his side.
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) placed his right hand upon my head and
took me by my ear twisting it. He then prayed two rak'ahs, then two
rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs, then
two rak'ahs. The narrator al-Qa'nabi said: Six times. He observed
the witr prayer, and then slept until the mu'adhdhin came. He got
up and prayed two light rak'ahs and then came out and offered the
dawn prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
