<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21380</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1379</hadith-number>
<chapter>Detailed Injunctions about Ramadan - كتاب شهر
رمضان</chapter>
<chain-index>30293, 20420, 20187, 20176, 12190, 1048</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن حفص بن عبد الله السلمي، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
إبراهيم بن طهمان، عن عباد بن إسحاق، عن محمد بن مسلم الزهري، عن ضمرة
بن عبد الله بن أنيس، عن أبيه، قال كنت في مجلس بني سلمة وأنا أصغرهم،
فقالوا من يسأل لنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن ليلة القدر وذلك
صبيحة إحدى وعشرين من رمضان ‏.‏ فخرجت فوافيت مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم صلاة المغرب ثم قمت بباب بيته فمر بي فقال ‏"‏ ادخل ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فدخلت فأتي بعشائه فرآني أكف عنه من قلته فلما فرغ قال ‏"‏ ناولني
نعلي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقام وقمت معه فقال ‏"‏ كأن لك حاجة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت أجل
أرسلني إليك رهط من بني سلمة يسألونك عن ليلة القدر فقال ‏"‏ كم
الليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت اثنتان وعشرون قال ‏"‏ هي الليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم رجع
فقال ‏"‏ أو القابلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يريد ليلة ثلاث وعشرين ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Unays: I was present at the
gathering of Banu Salamah, and I was the youngest of them. They
(the people) said: Who will ask the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) for us
about Laylat al-Qadr? That was the twenty-first of Ramadan. I went
out and said the sunset prayer along with the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ). I then stood at the door of his house. He passed by me and
said: Come in. I entered (the house) and dinner was brought for
him. I was prevented from taking food as it was scanty. When he
finished his dinner, he said to me: Give me my shoes. He then stood
up and I also stood up with him. He said: Perhaps you have some
business with me. I said: Yes. Some people of Banu Salamah have
sent me to you to ask you about Laylat al-Qadr. He asked: Which
night: Is it tonight? I said: Twenty-second. He said: This is the
very night. He then withdrew and said: Or the following night,
referring to the twenty-third night.</english-text>
</hadith>
