<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21557</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1556</hadith-number>
<chapter>Zakat (Kitab Al-Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11207, 11013, 11004, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد الثقفي، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن
الزهري، أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، عن أبي هريرة، قال لما
توفي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم واستخلف أبو بكر بعده وكفر من كفر
من العرب قال عمر بن الخطاب لأبي بكر كيف تقاتل الناس وقد قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أمرت أن أقاتل الناس حتى يقولوا لا إله
إلا الله فمن قال لا إله إلا الله عصم مني ماله ونفسه إلا بحقه وحسابه
على الله عز وجل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر والله لأقاتلن من فرق بين
الصلاة والزكاة فإن الزكاة حق المال والله لو منعوني عقالا كانوا
يؤدونه إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لقاتلتهم على منعه ‏.‏ فقال
عمر بن الخطاب فوالله ما هو إلا أن رأيت الله عز وجل قد شرح صدر أبي
بكر للقتال - قال - فعرفت أنه الحق ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال أبو عبيدة
معمر بن المثنى العقال صدقة سنة والعقالان صدقة سنتين ‏.‏ قال أبو
داود ورواه رباح بن زيد وعبد الرزاق عن معمر عن الزهري بإسناده وقال
بعضهم عقالا ‏.‏ ورواه ابن وهب عن يونس قال عناقا ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
وقال شعيب بن أبي حمزة ومعمر والزبيدي عن الزهري في هذا الحديث لو
منعوني عناقا ‏.‏ وروى عنبسة عن يونس عن الزهري في هذا الحديث قال
عناقا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said When the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) died
and Abu Bakr was made his successor after him and certain Arab
clans apostatized. Umar bin Al Khattab said to Abu Bakr How can you
fight with the people until they say “There is no God but Allah” so
whoever says “There is no God but Allah”, he has protected his
property and his person from me except for what is due from him,
and his reckoning is left to allah. Abu Bak replied I swear by
Allah that I will certainly fight with those who make a distinction
between prayer and zakat, for zakat is what is due from property. I
swear by Allah that if they were to refuse me a rope of camel (or a
female kid, according to another version)which they used to pay the
Messenger of Allah, I will fight with them over the refusal of it.
Umar bin Al Khattab said I swear by Allah, I clearly saw Allah had
made Abu Bakr feel justified in tighting and I recognized that it
was right.Abu Dawud said This tradition has been transmitted by
Rabah bin Zaid from Ma’mar and Al Zaubaidi from Al Zuhri has “If
they were to refuse me a female kid.” The version transmitted by
‘Anbasah from Yunus on the authority of Al Zuhri has “a female
kid”.</english-text>
</hadith>
