<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21571</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1570</hadith-number>
<chapter>Zakat (Kitab Al-Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20025, 20475, 11013</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن العلاء، أخبرنا ابن المبارك، عن يونس بن
يزيد، عن ابن شهاب، قال هذه نسخة كتاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
الذي كتبه في الصدقة وهي عند آل عمر بن الخطاب قال ابن شهاب أقرأنيها
سالم بن عبد الله بن عمر فوعيتها على وجهها وهي التي انتسخ عمر بن عبد
العزيز من عبد الله بن عبد الله بن عمر وسالم بن عبد الله بن عمر فذكر
الحديث قال ‏"‏ فإذا كانت إحدى وعشرين ومائة ففيها ثلاث بنات لبون حتى
تبلغ تسعا وعشرين ومائة فإذا كانت ثلاثين ومائة ففيها بنتا لبون وحقة
حتى تبلغ تسعا وثلاثين ومائة فإذا كانت أربعين ومائة ففيها حقتان وبنت
لبون حتى تبلغ تسعا وأربعين ومائة فإذا كانت خمسين ومائة ففيها ثلاث
حقاق حتى تبلغ تسعا وخمسين ومائة فإذا كانت ستين ومائة ففيها أربع
بنات لبون حتى تبلغ تسعا وستين ومائة فإذا كانت سبعين ومائة ففيها
ثلاث بنات لبون وحقة حتى تبلغ تسعا وسبعين ومائة فإذا كانت ثمانين
ومائة ففيها حقتان وابنتا لبون حتى تبلغ تسعا وثمانين ومائة فإذا كانت
تسعين ومائة ففيها ثلاث حقاق وبنت لبون حتى تبلغ تسعا وتسعين ومائة
فإذا كانت مائتين ففيها أربع حقاق أو خمس بنات لبون أى السنين وجدت
أخذت وفي سائمة الغنم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذكر نحو حديث سفيان بن حسين وفيه ‏"‏
ولا يؤخذ في الصدقة هرمة ولا ذات عوار من الغنم ولا تيس الغنم إلا أن
يشاء المصدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Shihab (Al Zuhri) said This is the copy of the
letter of the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ), which he had written about
sadaqah(zakat). This was in the custody of the descendants of ‘Umar
bin Al Khattab. Ibn Shihab said Salim bin Abdallah bin Umar read it
to me and I memorized it properly. Umar bin Abdul Aziz got it
copied from ‘Abdallah, ‘Abdallah bin Umar and Salim bin ‘Abdallah
bin ‘Umar. He (Ibn Shihab) then narrated the tradition like the
former(i.e., up to one hundred and twenty camels). He further said
if they (the camels) reach one hundred and twenty one to one
hundred and twenty nine, three she camels in their third year are
to be given. When they reach one hundred and thirty to one hundred
and thirty nine, two she camels in their third year and one she
Camel in her fourth year are to be given. When they reach one
hundred and forty to one hundred and forty nine, two she camels in
their fourth year and one she Camel in her third year are to be
given. When they reach one hundred and fifty to one hundred and
fifty nine, three she camels in their fourth year are to be given.
When they reach one hundred and sixty to one hundred and sixty nine
four she camels in their fourth year are to be given. When they
reach one hundred and seventy to one hundred and seventy nine,
three she camels in their third year and one she Camel in her
fourth year are to be given. When they reach one hundred and eighty
to one hundred and eighty nine, two she camels in their fourth year
and two she Camel in their third year are to be given. When they
reach one hundred and ninety to one hundred and ninety nine, three
she camels in their fourth year and one she Camel in her third year
are to be given. When they reach two hundred, four she camels in
their fourth year or five she Camels in their third year, camels of
whichever age are available, are to be accepted. For the pasturing
goats, he narrated the tradition similar to that transmitted by
Sufyan bin Husain. This version adds “An old goat, one with defect
in the eye or a male goat is not to be accepted in sadaqah(zakat)
unless the collector wishes.”</english-text>
</hadith>
