<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21630</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1629</hadith-number>
<chapter>Zakat (Kitab Al-Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30352, 20463, 11414, 11669, 1824</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد النفيلي، حدثنا مسكين، حدثنا
محمد بن المهاجر، عن ربيعة بن يزيد، عن أبي كبشة السلولي، حدثنا سهل
ابن الحنظلية، قال قدم على رسول الله عيينة بن حصن والأقرع بن حابس
فسألاه فأمر لهما بما سألا وأمر معاوية فكتب لهما بما سألا فأما
الأقرع فأخذ كتابه فلفه في عمامته وانطلق وأما عيينة فأخذ كتابه وأتى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مكانه فقال يا محمد أتراني حاملا إلى قومي
كتابا لا أدري ما فيه كصحيفة المتلمس ‏.‏ فأخبر معاوية بقوله رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من
سأل وعنده ما يغنيه فإنما يستكثر من النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال النفيلي في
موضع آخر ‏"‏ من جمر جهنم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا يا رسول الله وما يغنيه وقال
النفيلي في موضع آخر وما الغنى الذي لا تنبغي معه المسألة قال ‏"‏ قدر
ما يغديه ويعشيه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال النفيلي في موضع آخر ‏"‏ أن يكون له شبع
يوم وليلة أو ليلة ويوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكان حدثنا به مختصرا على هذه الألفاظ
التي ذكرت ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl ibn Hanzaliyyah: Uyaynah ibn Hisn and
Aqra' ibn Habis came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). They begged
from him. He commanded to give them what they begged. He ordered
Mu'awiyah to write a document to give what they begged. Aqra' took
his document, wrapped it in his turban, and went away. As for
Uyaynah, he took his document and came to the Prophet (ﷺ) at his
home, and said to him: Muhammad, do you see me? I am taking a
document to my people, but I do not know what it contains, just
like the document of al-Mutalammis. Mu'awiyah informed the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) of his statement. Thereupon the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said: He who begs (from people) when he has sufficient is
simply asking for a large amount of Hell-fire. (An-Nufayl (a
transmitter) said elsewhere: "embers of Hell".) They asked:
Messenger of Allah, what is a sufficiency? (Elsewhere an-Nufayl
said: What is a sufficiency which makes begging unfitting?) He
replied: It is that which would provide a morning and an evening
meal. (Elsewhere an-Nufayl said: It is when one has enough for a
day and night, or for a night and a day.) He (an-Nufayl) narrated
to us this tradition briefly in the words that I have
mentioned.</english-text>
</hadith>
