<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21659</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1658</hadith-number>
<chapter>Zakat (Kitab Al-Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11173, 11161, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا حماد، عن سهيل بن أبي
صالح، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ ما من صاحب كنز لا يؤدي حقه إلا جعله الله يوم القيامة يحمى عليها
في نار جهنم فتكوى بها جبهته وجنبه وظهره حتى يقضي الله تعالى بين
عباده في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة مما تعدون ثم يرى سبيله إما
إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار وما من صاحب غنم لا يؤدي حقها إلا جاءت يوم
القيامة أوفر ما كانت فيبطح لها بقاع قرقر فتنطحه بقرونها وتطؤه
بأظلافها ليس فيها عقصاء ولا جلحاء كلما مضت أخراها ردت عليه أولاها
حتى يحكم الله بين عباده في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة مما تعدون
ثم يرى سبيله إما إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار وما من صاحب إبل لا يؤدي
حقها إلا جاءت يوم القيامة أوفر ما كانت فيبطح لها بقاع قرقر فتطؤه
بأخفافها كلما مضت عليه أخراها ردت عليه أولاها حتى يحكم الله تعالى
بين عباده في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة مما تعدون ثم يرى سبيله
إما إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah reported that Messenger of Allah (SWAS)
as saying If any owner of treasure (gold and silver) does not pay
what is due on it, Allah will make it heated in the Hell fire on
the Day of Judgment, and his side, forehead and back will be
cauterized with it until Allah gives His Judgment among mankind
during a day whose extent will be fifty thousand years of your
count and he sees whether his path is to take him to Paradise or to
Hell. If any owner does not pay zakat on them, the sheep wilkl
appear on the Day or Judgment most strong and in great number, a
soft sandy plain will be spread out for them ; they will gore him
with their horns and trample him with their hoofs; there will be
none of them with twisted horns or without horns. As often as the
last of them passes him, the first of them will be brought back to
him, until Allah pronounces His Judgment among mankind during a day
whose extent will be fifty thousand years that you count, and he
sees whether his path is to take him to Paradise or to Hell. If any
owner of camels does not pay what is due on them, they will appear
in on the Day or Judgment most strong and in great number, a soft
sandy plain will be spread out for them ; they will gore him with
their horns and trample him with their hoofs; there will be none of
them with twisted horns or without horns. As often as the last of
them passes him, the first of them will be brought back to him,
until Allah pronounces His Judgment among mankind during a day
whose extent will be fifty thousand years that you count, and he
sees whether his path is to take him to Paradise or to
Hell.</english-text>
</hadith>
