<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21773</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1772</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11168, 11887</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن سعيد بن أبي سعيد المقبري،
عن عبيد بن جريج، أنه قال لعبد الله بن عمر يا أبا عبد الرحمن رأيتك
تصنع أربعا لم أر أحدا من أصحابك يصنعها ‏.‏ قال ما هن يا ابن جريج
قال رأيتك لا تمس من الأركان إلا اليمانيين ورأيتك تلبس النعال
السبتية ورأيتك تصبغ بالصفرة ورأيتك إذا كنت بمكة أهل الناس إذا رأوا
الهلال ولم تهل أنت حتى كان يوم التروية ‏.‏ فقال عبد الله بن عمر أما
الأركان فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يمس إلا اليمانيين
وأما النعال السبتية فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يلبس
النعال التي ليس فيها شعر ويتوضأ فيها فأنا أحب أن ألبسها وأما الصفرة
فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصبغ بها فأنا أحب أن أصبغ
بها وأما الإهلال فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يهل حتى
تنبعث به راحلته ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ubayd ibn Jurayj said to Abdullah ibn Umar:
AbuAbdurRahman, I saw you doing things which I did not see being
done by your companions. He asked: What are they, Ibn Jurayj? He
replied: I saw you touching only the two Yamani corners; and I saw
you wearing shoes having no hair; I saw you dyeing in yellow
colour; and I saw you wearing ihram on the eighth of Dhul-Hijjah,
whereas the people had worn ihram when they sighted the moon.
Abdullah ibn Umar replied: As regards the corners, I have not seen
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) touching anything (in the Ka'bah) but
the two Yamani corners. As for the tanned leather shoes, I have
seen the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) wearing tanned leather shoes, and
he would wear them after ablution. Therefore I like to wear them.
As regards wearing yellow, I have seen the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
wearing yellow, so I like to wear with it. As regards shouting the
talbiyah, I have seen the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) raising his voice
in talbiyah when his she-camel stood up with him on its
back.</english-text>
</hadith>
