<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21782</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1781</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن عروة بن
الزبير، عن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أنها قالت خرجنا مع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في حجة الوداع فأهللنا بعمرة ثم قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من كان معه هدى فليهل بالحج مع
العمرة ثم لا يحل حتى يحل منهما جميعا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقدمت مكة وأنا حائض
ولم أطف بالبيت ولا بين الصفا والمروة فشكوت ذلك إلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ انقضي رأسك وامتشطي وأهلي بالحج ودعي العمرة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ففعلت فلما قضينا الحج أرسلني رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم مع عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر إلى التنعيم فاعتمرت فقال ‏"‏ هذه مكان
عمرتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فطاف الذين أهلوا بالعمرة بالبيت وبين الصفا
والمروة ثم حلوا ثم طافوا طوافا آخر بعد أن رجعوا من منى لحجهم وأما
الذين كانوا جمعوا الحج والعمرة فإنما طافوا طوافا واحدا ‏.‏ قال أبو
داود رواه إبراهيم بن سعد ومعمر عن ابن شهاب نحوه لم يذكروا طواف
الذين أهلوا بعمرة وطواف الذين جمعوا الحج والعمرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ai’shah the wife of the Prophet (SWAS) said : We went
out with the Messenger of Allah (SWAS) at the farewell pilgrimage
and raised the voice in talbiyah for an ‘Umrah. The Apostel of
Allah (SWAS) said those who have brought the sacrificial animals
with them should raise their voices in talbiyah for Hajj along with
an ‘Umrah and they should not put off their Ihram till they do so
after performing them both. I came to Makkah while I was
menstruating and I did not go round the House (the Ka’bah) or run
between al-Safa and al-Marwah. I complained about this to the
Messenger of Allah (SWAS) he said: Undo your hair, comb it and
raise your voice in talbiyah for Hajj and let `Umrah go. She said I
did so. When we performed Hajj, the Messenger of Allah (SWAS) sent
me along with `Abd al-Rahman bin Abu Bakr to al-Ta’nim and I
performed `Umrah. He said, this is `Umrah in place of the one you
had missed. She said those who had raised their voices in talbiyah
for `Umrah put off Ihram after circumambulating the House (the
Ka’bah) and after running between al-Safa and al-Marwa. Then they
performed another circumambulation for their Hajj after they
returned from Mina but those who combined Hajj and `Umrah performed
only one circumambulation.</english-text>
</hadith>
