<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21800</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1799</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>38573, 30203, 20028, 11067, 11353</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن قدامة بن أعين، وعثمان بن أبي شيبة، قالا
حدثنا جرير بن عبد الحميد، عن منصور، عن أبي وائل، قال قال الصبى بن
معبد كنت رجلا أعرابيا نصرانيا فأسلمت فأتيت رجلا من عشيرتي يقال له
هذيم بن ثرملة فقلت له يا هناه إني حريص على الجهاد وإني وجدت الحج
والعمرة مكتوبين على فكيف لي بأن أجمعهما قال اجمعهما واذبح ما استيسر
من الهدى ‏.‏ فأهللت بهما معا فلما أتيت العذيب لقيني سلمان بن ربيعة
وزيد بن صوحان وأنا أهل بهما جميعا فقال أحدهما للآخر ما هذا بأفقه من
بعيره ‏.‏ قال فكأنما ألقي على جبل حتى أتيت عمر بن الخطاب فقلت له يا
أمير المؤمنين إني كنت رجلا أعرابيا نصرانيا وإني أسلمت وأنا حريص على
الجهاد وإني وجدت الحج والعمرة مكتوبين على فأتيت رجلا من قومي فقال
لي اجمعهما واذبح ما استيسر من الهدى وإني أهللت بهما معا ‏.‏ فقال لي
عمر رضى الله عنه هديت لسنة نبيك صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated As-Subayy ibn Ma'bad: I was a Christian
Bedouin; then I embraced Islam. I came to a man of my tribe, who
was called Hudhaym ibn Thurmulah. I said to him. O brother, I am
eager to wage war in the cause of Allah (i.e. jihad), and I find
that both hajj and umrah are due from me. How can I combine them?
He said: Combine them and sacrifice the animal made easily
available for you. I, therefore, raised my voice in talbiyah for
both of them (i.e. umrah and hajj). When I reached al-Udhayb,
Salman ibn Rabi'ah and Zayd ibn Suhan met me while I was raising my
voice in talbiyah for both of them. One of them said to the other:
This (man) does not have any more understanding than his camel.
Thereupon it was as if a mountain fell on me. I came to Umar ibn
al-Khattab (may Allah be pleased with him) and said to him:
Commander of the Faithful, I was a Christian Bedouin, and I have
embraced Islam. I am eager to wage war in the cause of Allah
(jihad), and I found that both hajj and umrah were due from me. I
came to a man of my tribe who said to me: Combine both of them and
sacrifice the animal easily available for you. I have raised my
voice in talbiyah for both of them. Umar thereupon said to me: You
have been guided to the practice (sunnah) of your Prophet)
(ﷺ).</english-text>
</hadith>
