<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21819</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1818</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 30379, 20102, 11107, 19826, 11250,
70</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن حنبل، ومحمد بن عبد العزيز بن أبي رزمة،
أخبرنا عبد الله بن إدريس، أخبرنا ابن إسحاق، عن يحيى بن عباد بن عبد
الله بن الزبير، عن أبيه، عن أسماء بنت أبي بكر، قالت خرجنا مع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حجاجا حتى إذا كنا بالعرج نزل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ونزلنا فجلست عائشة - رضى الله عنها - إلى جنب رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وجلست إلى جنب أبي وكانت زمالة أبي بكر
وزمالة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم واحدة مع غلام لأبي بكر فجلس أبو
بكر ينتظر أن يطلع عليه فطلع وليس معه بعيره قال أين بعيرك قال أضللته
البارحة ‏.‏ قال فقال أبو بكر بعير واحد تضله قال فطفق يضربه ورسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يتبسم ويقول ‏"‏ انظروا إلى هذا المحرم ما
يصنع ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن أبي رزمة فما يزيد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
على أن يقول ‏"‏ انظروا إلى هذا المحرم ما يصنع ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ويتبسم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Asma' bint AbuBakr: We came out for
performing hajj along with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). When we
reached al-Araj, the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) alighted and we also
alighted. Aisha sat beside the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and I sat
beside my father (AbuBakr). The equipment and personal effects of
AbuBakr and of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) were placed with
AbuBakr's slave on a camel. AbuBakr was sitting and waiting for his
arrival. He arrived but he had no camel with him. He asked: Where
is your camel? He replied: I lost it last night. AbuBakr said:
There was only one camel, even that you have lost. He then began to
beat him while the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was smiling and saying:
Look at this man who is in the sacred state (putting on ihram),
what is he doing? Ibn AbuRizmah said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
spoke nothing except the words: Look at this man who is in the
sacred state (wearing ihram), what is he doing? He was smiling
(when he uttered these words).</english-text>
</hadith>
