<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21886</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1885</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 3660</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو سلمة، موسى بن إسماعيل حدثنا حماد، حدثنا أبو
عاصم الغنوي، عن أبي الطفيل، قال قلت لابن عباس يزعم قومك أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد رمل بالبيت وأن ذلك سنة ‏.‏ قال صدقوا
وكذبوا ‏.‏ قلت وما صدقوا وما كذبوا قال صدقوا قد رمل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وكذبوا ليس بسنة إن قريشا قالت زمن الحديبية دعوا
محمدا وأصحابه حتى يموتوا موت النغف ‏.‏ فلما صالحوه على أن يجيئوا من
العام المقبل فيقيموا بمكة ثلاثة أيام فقدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم والمشركون من قبل قعيقعان فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
لأصحابه ‏"‏ ارملوا بالبيت ثلاثا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وليس بسنة ‏.‏ قلت يزعم قومك
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم طاف بين الصفا والمروة على بعيره وأن
ذلك سنة فقال صدقوا وكذبوا ‏.‏ قلت ما صدقوا وما كذبوا قال صدقوا قد
طاف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بين الصفا والمروة على بعيره وكذبوا
ليس بسنة كان الناس لا يدفعون عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ولا
يصرفون عنه فطاف على بعير ليسمعوا كلامه وليروا مكانه ولا تناله
أيديهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Al Tufail said I said to Ibn ‘Abbas Your people
think that the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) walked proudly with swift
strides while going round the Ka’bah and that it is sunnah
(practice of the Prophet). He said “They spoke the truth (in part)
and told a lie (in part).” I asked “What truth did they speak and
what lie did they tell?” He said “They spoke the truth that the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) walked proudly while going round the Ka’bah
but they told a lie, this is no sunnah. The Quraish asserted during
the days of Al Hudaibiyyah “Forsake Muhammad and his Companions
till they die the death of a Camel which dies of bacteria in its
nose. When they concluded a treaty with him agreeing upon the fact
that they (the Prophet and his Companions) would come (to Makkah)
next year and stay at Makkah three days, the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
said to the Companions “Walk proudly (moving shoulders) while going
round the Ka’bah in first three circuits. (Ibn ‘Abbas said) But
this is not sunnah. I said “Your people think that the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) ran between Al Safa and Al Marwah on a Camel and that is
sunnah.” He said “They spoke the truth (in part) and told a lie (in
part). I asked “What truth did they speak and what lie did they
tell? He said “they spoke the truth that the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
ran between Al Safa and Al Marwah on a Camel. They told a lie that
it is a sunnah. As the people did not move from around the Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) and did not separate themselves from him he did the
sa’i on a Camel so that they may listen to him and see his position
and their hands might not reach him.</english-text>
</hadith>
