<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21906</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1905</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30352, 30203, 30288, 20159, 10898, 11442</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد النفيلي، وعثمان بن أبي شيبة،
وهشام بن عمار، وسليمان بن عبد الرحمن الدمشقيان، - وربما زاد بعضهم
على بعض الكلمة والشىء - قالوا حدثنا حاتم بن إسماعيل حدثنا جعفر بن
محمد عن أبيه قال دخلنا على جابر بن عبد الله فلما انتهينا إليه سأل
عن القوم حتى انتهى إلى فقلت أنا محمد بن علي بن حسين ‏.‏ فأهوى بيده
إلى رأسي فنزع زري الأعلى ثم نزع زري الأسفل ثم وضع كفه بين ثديى وأنا
يومئذ غلام شاب ‏.‏ فقال مرحبا بك وأهلا يا ابن أخي سل عما شئت ‏.‏
فسألته وهو أعمى وجاء وقت الصلاة فقام في نساجة ملتحفا بها يعني ثوبا
ملفقا كلما وضعها على منكبه رجع طرفاها إليه من صغرها فصلى بنا ورداؤه
إلى جنبه على المشجب ‏.‏ فقلت أخبرني عن حجة رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ فقال بيده فعقد تسعا ‏.‏ ثم قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم مكث تسع سنين لم يحج ثم أذن في الناس في العاشرة أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم حاج فقدم المدينة بشر كثير كلهم يلتمس أن يأتم
برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ويعمل بمثل عمله فخرج رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وخرجنا معه حتى أتينا ذا الحليفة فولدت أسماء بنت عميس
محمد بن أبي بكر فأرسلت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كيف أصنع
قال ‏"‏ اغتسلي واستذفري بثوب وأحرمي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في المسجد ثم ركب القصواء حتى إذا استوت به ناقته على
البيداء ‏.‏ قال جابر نظرت إلى مد بصري من بين يديه من راكب وماش وعن
يمينه مثل ذلك وعن يساره مثل ذلك ومن خلفه مثل ذلك ورسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم بين أظهرنا وعليه ينزل القرآن وهو يعلم تأويله فما عمل
به من شىء عملنا به فأهل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالتوحيد ‏"‏
لبيك اللهم لبيك لبيك لا شريك لك لبيك إن الحمد والنعمة لك والملك لا
شريك لك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأهل الناس بهذا الذي يهلون به فلم يرد عليهم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شيئا منه ولزم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
تلبيته ‏.‏ قال جابر لسنا ننوي إلا الحج لسنا نعرف العمرة حتى إذا
أتينا البيت معه استلم الركن فرمل ثلاثا ومشى أربعا ثم تقدم إلى مقام
إبراهيم فقرأ ‏{‏ واتخذوا من مقام إبراهيم مصلى ‏}‏ فجعل المقام بينه
وبين البيت قال فكان أبي يقول قال ابن نفيل وعثمان ولا أعلمه ذكره إلا
عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال سليمان ولا أعلمه إلا قال كان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقرأ في الركعتين ب ‏{‏ قل هو الله أحد
‏}‏ وب ‏{‏ قل يا أيها الكافرون ‏}‏ ثم رجع إلى البيت فاستلم الركن ثم
خرج من الباب إلى الصفا فلما دنا من الصفا قرأ ‏{‏ إن الصفا والمروة
من شعائر الله ‏}‏ ‏"‏ نبدأ بما بدأ الله به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فبدأ بالصفا فرقي
عليه حتى رأى البيت فكبر الله ووحده وقال ‏"‏ لا إله إلا الله وحده لا
شريك له له الملك وله الحمد يحيي ويميت وهو على كل شىء قدير لا إله
إلا الله وحده أنجز وعده ونصر عبده وهزم الأحزاب وحده ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم دعا
بين ذلك وقال مثل هذا ثلاث مرات ثم نزل إلى المروة حتى إذا انصبت
قدماه رمل في بطن الوادي حتى إذا صعد مشى حتى أتى المروة فصنع على
المروة مثل ما صنع على الصفا حتى إذا كان آخر الطواف على المروة قال
‏"‏ إني لو استقبلت من أمري ما استدبرت لم أسق الهدى ولجعلتها عمرة
فمن كان منكم ليس معه هدى فليحلل وليجعلها عمرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فحل الناس
كلهم وقصروا إلا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ومن كان معه هدى فقام سراقة
بن جعشم فقال يا رسول الله ألعامنا هذا أم للأبد فشبك رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أصابعه في الأخرى ثم قال ‏"‏ دخلت العمرة في الحج ‏"‏
‏.‏ هكذا مرتين ‏"‏ لا بل لأبد أبد لا بل لأبد أبد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقدم
علي - رضى الله عنه - من اليمن ببدن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فوجد
فاطمة - رضى الله عنها - ممن حل ولبست ثيابا صبيغا واكتحلت فأنكر علي
ذلك عليها وقال من أمرك بهذا فقالت أبي ‏.‏ فكان علي يقول بالعراق
ذهبت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم محرشا على فاطمة في الأمر الذي
صنعته مستفتيا لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في الذي ذكرت عنه
فأخبرته أني أنكرت ذلك عليها فقالت إن أبي أمرني بهذا ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
صدقت صدقت ماذا قلت حين فرضت الحج ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت اللهم إني أهل بما
أهل به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن معي الهدى فلا
تحلل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وكان جماعة الهدى الذي قدم به علي من اليمن والذي
أتى به النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم من المدينة مائة فحل الناس كلهم
وقصروا إلا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ومن كان معه هدى قال فلما كان
يوم التروية ووجهوا إلى منى أهلوا بالحج فركب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فصلى بمنى الظهر والعصر والمغرب والعشاء والصبح ثم مكث قليلا حتى
طلعت الشمس وأمر بقبة له من شعر فضربت بنمرة فسار رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ولا تشك قريش أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم واقف عند
المشعر الحرام بالمزدلفة كما كانت قريش تصنع في الجاهلية فأجاز رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى أتى عرفة فوجد القبة قد ضربت له بنمرة
فنزل بها حتى إذا زاغت الشمس أمر بالقصواء فرحلت له فركب حتى أتى بطن
الوادي فخطب الناس فقال ‏"‏ إن دماءكم وأموالكم عليكم حرام كحرمة
يومكم هذا في شهركم هذا في بلدكم هذا ألا إن كل شىء من أمر الجاهلية
تحت قدمى موضوع ودماء الجاهلية موضوعة وأول دم أضعه دماؤنا دم ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال عثمان ‏"‏ دم ابن ربيعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال سليمان ‏"‏ دم ربيعة بن
الحارث بن عبد المطلب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال بعض هؤلاء كان مسترضعا في بني سعد
فقتلته هذيل ‏"‏ وربا الجاهلية موضوع وأول ربا أضعه ربانا ربا عباس بن
عبد المطلب فإنه موضوع كله اتقوا الله في النساء فإنكم أخذتموهن
بأمانة الله واستحللتم فروجهن بكلمة الله وإن لكم عليهن أن لا يوطئن
فرشكم أحدا تكرهونه فإن فعلن فاضربوهن ضربا غير مبرح ولهن عليكم رزقهن
وكسوتهن بالمعروف وإني قد تركت فيكم ما لن تضلوا بعده إن اعتصمتم به
كتاب الله وأنتم مسئولون عني فما أنتم قائلون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نشهد أنك
قد بلغت وأديت ونصحت ‏.‏ ثم قال بأصبعه السبابة يرفعها إلى السماء
وينكبها إلى الناس ‏"‏ اللهم اشهد اللهم اشهد اللهم اشهد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم
أذن بلال ثم أقام فصلى الظهر ثم أقام فصلى العصر ولم يصل بينهما شيئا
ثم ركب القصواء حتى أتى الموقف فجعل بطن ناقته القصواء إلى الصخرات
وجعل حبل المشاة بين يديه فاستقبل القبلة فلم يزل واقفا حتى غربت
الشمس وذهبت الصفرة قليلا حين غاب القرص وأردف أسامة خلفه فدفع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقد شنق للقصواء الزمام حتى إن رأسها ليصيب
مورك رحله وهو يقول بيده اليمنى ‏"‏ السكينة أيها الناس السكينة أيها
الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ كلما أتى حبلا من الحبال أرخى لها قليلا حتى تصعد حتى
أتى المزدلفة فجمع بين المغرب والعشاء بأذان واحد وإقامتين - قال
عثمان ولم يسبح بينهما شيئا ثم اتفقوا - ثم اضطجع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم حتى طلع الفجر فصلى الفجر حين تبين له الصبح - قال سليمان
بنداء وإقامة ثم اتفقوا - ثم ركب القصواء حتى أتى المشعر الحرام فرقي
عليه قال عثمان وسليمان فاستقبل القبلة فحمد الله وكبره وهلله زاد
عثمان ووحده فلم يزل واقفا حتى أسفر جدا ثم دفع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قبل أن تطلع الشمس وأردف الفضل بن عباس وكان رجلا حسن الشعر
أبيض وسيما فلما دفع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مر الظعن يجرين
فطفق الفضل ينظر إليهن فوضع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده على وجه
الفضل وصرف الفضل وجهه إلى الشق الآخر وحول رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يده إلى الشق الآخر وصرف الفضل وجهه إلى الشق الآخر ينظر حتى أتى
محسرا فحرك قليلا ثم سلك الطريق الوسطى الذي يخرجك إلى الجمرة الكبرى
حتى أتى الجمرة التي عند الشجرة فرماها بسبع حصيات يكبر مع كل حصاة
منها بمثل حصى الخذف فرمى من بطن الوادي ثم انصرف رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم إلى المنحر فنحر بيده ثلاثا وستين وأمر عليا فنحر ما غبر -
يقول ما بقي - وأشركه في هديه ثم أمر من كل بدنة ببضعة فجعلت في قدر
فطبخت فأكلا من لحمها وشربا من مرقها قال سليمان ثم ركب ثم أفاض رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى البيت فصلى بمكة الظهر ثم أتى بني عبد
المطلب وهم يسقون على زمزم فقال ‏"‏ انزعوا بني عبد المطلب فلولا أن
يغلبكم الناس على سقايتكم لنزعت معكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فناولوه دلوا فشرب منه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ja’far bin Muhammad reported on the authority of his
father “We entered upon Jabir bin ‘Abd Allaah. When we reached him,
he asked about the people (who had come to visit him). When my turn
came I said “I am Muhammad bin Ali bin Hussain. He patted my head
with his hand and undid my upper then lower buttons. He then placed
his hand between my nipples and in those days I was a young boy.”
He then said “welcome to you my nephew, ask what you like. I
questioned him he was blind. The time of prayer came and he stood
wrapped in a mantle. Whenever he placed it on his shoulders its
ends fell due to its shortness. He led us in prayer while his
mantle was placed on a rack by his side. I said “tell me about the
Hajj of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ).”He signed with his hand and
folded his fingers indicating nine. He then said Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) remained nine years (at Madeenah ) during which he did
not perform Hajj, then made a public announcement in the tenth year
to the effect that the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) was about to (go to)
perform Hajj. A large number of people came to Madeenah everyone
desiring to follow him and act like him. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
went out and we too went out with him till we reached Dhu Al
Hulaifah. Asma’ daughter of ‘Umais gave birth to Muhammad bin Abi
Bakr. She sent message to Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) asking him What
should I do?He replied “take a bath, bandage your private parts
with a cloth and put on ihram.” The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) then
prayed (in the masjid) and mounted Al Qaswa’ and his she Camel
stood erect with him on its back. Jabir said “I saw (a large number
of) people on mounts and on foot in front of him and a similar
number on his right side and a similar number on his left side and
a similar number behind him. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) was among us,
the Qur’an was being revealed to him and he knew its
interpretation. Whatever he did, we did it. The Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) then raised his voice declaring Allaah’s unity and saying
“Labbaik ( I am at thy service), O Allaah, labbaik, labbaik, Thou
hast no partner praise and grace are Thine and the Dominion. Thou
hast no partner. The people too raised their voices in talbiyah
which they used to utter. But the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) did not
forbid them anything. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) continued his
talbiyah. Jabir said “We did not express our intention of
performing anything but Hajj, being unaware of ‘Umrah (at that
season), but when we came with him to the House (the Ka’bah), he
touched the corner (and made seven circuits) walking quickly with
pride in three of them and walking ordinarily in four. Then going
forward to the station of Abraham he recited “And take the station
of Abraham as a place of prayer.” (While praying two rak’ahs) he
kept the station between him and the House. The narrator said My
father said that Ibn Nufail and ‘Uthman said I do not know that he
(Jabir) narrated it from anyone except the Prophet (ﷺ). The
narrator Sulaiman said I do not know but he (Jabir) said “The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) used to recite in the two rak’ahs “Say, He is
Allaah, one” and “Say O infidels”. He then returned to the House
(the ka’bah) and touched the corner after which he went out by the
gate to Al Safa’. When he reached near Al Safa’ he recited “Al
Safa’ and Al Marwah are among the indications of Allaah” and he
added “We begin with what Allaah began with”. He then began with Al
Safa’ and mounting it till he could see the House (the Ka’bah) he
declared the greatness of Allaah and proclaimed his Unity. He then
said “there is no god but Allaah alone, Who alone has fulfilled His
promise, helped His servant and routed the confederates. He then
made supplication in the course of that saying such words three
times. He then descended and walked towards Al Marwah and when his
feet came down into the bottom of the valley, he ran, and when he
began to ascend he walked till he reached Al Marwah. He did at al
Marwah as he had done at Al Safa’ and when he came to Al Marwah for
the last time, he said “If I had known before what I have come to
know afterwards regarding this matter of mine, I would not have
brought sacrificial animals but made it an ‘Umrah, so if any of you
has no sacrificial animals, he may take off ihram and treat it as
an ‘Umrah. All the people then took off ihram and clipped their
hair except the Prophet (ﷺ) and those who had brought sacrificial
animals. Suraqah (bin Malik) bin Ju’sham then got up and asked
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)does this apply to the present year or does it
apply for ever? The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) interwined his fingers and
said “The ‘Umarh has been incorporated in Hajj. Adding ‘No’, but
forever and ever. ‘Ali came from Yemen with the sacrificial animals
of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) and found Fathima among one of those
who had taken off their ihram. She said put on colored clothes and
stained her eyes with collyrium. ‘Ali disliked (this action of her)
and asked Who commanded you for this? She said “My father”. Jabir
said ‘Ali said at Iraq I went to Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) to complain
against Fathima for what she had done and to ask the opinion of
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) about which she mentioned to me. I informed
him that I disliked her action and that thereupon she said to me
“My father commanded me to do this.” He said “She spoke the truth,
she spoke the truth.” What did you say when you put on ihram for
Hajj? I said O Allaah, I put on ihram for the same purpose for
which Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) has put it on. He said I have
sacrificial animals with me, so do not take off ihram. He (Jabir)
said “The total of those sacrificial animals brought by ‘Ali from
Yemen and of those brought by the Prophet (ﷺ) from Madeenah was one
hundred.” Then all the people except the Prophet (ﷺ) and those who
had with them the sacrificial animals took off ihram and clipped
their hair. When the 8th of Dhu Al Hijjah (Yaum Al Tarwiyah) came,
they went towards Mina having pit on ihram for Hajj and the Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) rode and prayed at Mina the noon, afternoon, sunset,
night and dawn prayers. After that he waited a little till the sun
rose and gave orders for a tent of hair to be set up at Namrah. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) then sent out and the Quraish did not doubt
that he would halt at Al Mash ‘ar Al Haram at Al Muzdalifah, as the
Quraish used to do in the pre Islamic period but he passed on till
he came to ‘Arafah and found that the tent had been setup at
Namrah. There he dismounted and when the sun had passed the
meridian he ordered Al Qaswa’ to be brought and when it was saddled
for him, he went down to the bottom of the valley and addressed the
people saying “Your lives and your property must be respected by
one another like the sacredness of this day of yours in the month
of yours in this town of yours. Lo! Everything pertaining to the
pre Islamic period has been put under my feet and claims for blood
vengeance belonging to the pre Islamic period have been abolished.
The first of those murdered among us whose blood vengeance I permit
is the blood vengeance of ours (according to the version of the
narrator ‘Uthman, the blood vengeance of the son of Rabi’ah and
according to the version of the narrator Sulaiman the blood
vengeance of the son of Rabi’ah bin Al Harith bin ‘Abd Al
Muttalib). Some (scholars) said “he was suckled among Banu
Sa’d(i.e., he was brought up among Bani Sa’d) and then killed by
Hudhail. The usury of the pre Islamic period is abolished and the
first of usury I abolish is our usury, the usury of ‘Abbas bin ‘Abd
Al Muttalib for it is all abolished. Fear Allaah regarding women
for you have got them under Allah’s security and have the right to
intercourse with them by Allaah’s word. It is a duty from you on
them not to allow anyone whom you dislike to lie on your beds but
if they do beat them, but not severely. You are responsible for
providing them with food and clothing in a fitting manner. I have
left among you something by which if you hold to it you will never
again go astray, that is Allaah’s Book. You will be asked about me,
so what will you say? They replied “We testify that you have
conveyed and fulfilled the message and given counsel. Then raising
his forefinger towards the sky and pointing it at the people, he
said “O Allaah! Be witness, O Allaah! Be witness, O Allaah! Be
witness! Bilal then uttered the call to prayer and the iqamah and
he prayed the noon prayer, he then uttered the iqamah and he prayed
the afternoon prayer, engaging in no prayer between the two. He
then mounted (his she Camel) al Qaswa’ and came to the place of
standing , making his she Camel Al Qaswa‘ turn its back to the
rocks and having the path taken by those who went on foot in front
of him and he faced the qiblah. He remained standing till sunset
when the yellow light had somewhat gone and the disc of the sun had
disappeared. He took Usamah up behind him and picked the reins of
Al Qaswa’ severely so much so that its head was touching the front
part of the saddle. Pointing with is right hand he was saying
“Calmness, O People! Calmness, O people. Whenever he came over a
mound (of sand) he let loose its reins a little so that it could
ascend. He then came to Al Muzdalifah where he combined the sunset
and night prayers, with one adhan and two iqamahs. The narrator
‘Uthamn said He did not offer supererogatory prayers between them.
The narrators are then agreed upon the version He then lay down
till dawn and prayed the dawn prayer when the morning light was
clear. The narrator Sulaiman said with one adhan and one iqamah.
The narrators are then agreed upon the version He then mounted Al
Qaswa’ and came to Al Mash’ar Al Haram and ascended it. The
narrators ‘Uthaman and Sulaiman said He faced the qiblah praised
Allaah, declared His greatness, His uniqueness. ‘Uthamn added in
his version and His Unity and kept standing till the day was very
clear. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) then went quickly before the sun
rose , taking Al Fadl bin ‘Abbas behind him. He was a man having
beautiful hair, white and handsome color. When the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) went quickly, the women in the howdas also began to pass
him quickly. Al Fadl began to look at them. The Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) placed his hand on the face of Al Fadl , but Al fadl
turned his face towards the other side. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
also turned away his hand to the other side. Al Fadl also turned
his face to the other side looking at them till he came to (the
Valley of) Muhassir. He urged the Camel a little and following a
middle road which comes out at the greatest jamrah, he came to the
jamrah which is beside the tree and he threw seven small pebbles at
this (jamrah) saying “Allah is most great” each time he threw a
pebble like bean seeds. He threw them from the bottom of the
valley. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) then went to the place of the
sacrifice and sacrificed sixty three Camels with his own hand. He
then commanded ‘Ali who sacrificed the remainder and he shared him
and his sacrificial animals. After that he ordered that a piece of
flesh from each Camel should be put in a pot and when it was cooked
the two of them ate some of it and drank some of its broth. The
narrator Sulaiman said the he mounted afterwards the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) went quickly to the House (the Ka’bah) and prayed the
noon prayer at Makkah. He came to Banu ‘Abd Al Muttalib who were
supplying water at Zamzam and said draw water Banu ‘Abd Al Muttalib
were it not that people would take from you the right to draw
water, I would draw it along with you. So they handed him a bucket
and he drank from it.</english-text>
</hadith>
