<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21922</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1921</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 20321, 28531, 20012, 11125, 11211,
50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عبد الله بن يونس، حدثنا زهير، ح وحدثنا
محمد بن كثير، أخبرنا سفيان، - وهذا لفظ حديث زهير - حدثنا إبراهيم بن
عقبة، أخبرني كريب، أنه سأل أسامة بن زيد قلت أخبرني كيف، فعلتم - أو
صنعتم - عشية ردفت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال جئنا الشعب الذي
ينيخ الناس فيه للمعرس فأناخ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ناقته ثم
بال - وما قال زهير أهراق الماء - ثم دعا بالوضوء فتوضأ وضوءا ليس
بالبالغ جدا قلت يا رسول الله الصلاة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ الصلاة أمامك ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فركب حتى قدمنا المزدلفة فأقام المغرب ثم أناخ الناس في
منازلهم ولم يحلوا حتى أقام العشاء وصلى ثم حل الناس ‏.‏ زاد محمد في
حديثه قال قلت كيف فعلتم حين أصبحتم قال ردفه الفضل وانطلقت أنا في
سباق قريش على رجلى ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibrahim bin ’Uqabah said “Kuraib told me that he
asked Umamah bin Zaid saying tell me how you did in the evening
when you rode behind the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ). He said “We came to
the valley where the people make their Camels kneel down to take
rest at night.” The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) made his she Camel kneel
down and he then urinated. He then called for water for ablution
and performed the ablution but he did not perform minutely (but
performed lightly). I asked Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ), prayer? He
replied “Prayer ahead of you”. He then mounted (the Camel) till we
came to Al Muzadalifah. There iqamah for the sunset prayer was
called. The people then made their Camels kneel down at their
places. The Camels were not unloaded as yet, iqamah for the night
prayers was called and he prayed. The people then unloaded the
Camels. The narrator Muhammad added in his version of the tradition
How did you do when the morning came? He replied Al Fadl rode
behind him and I walked on foot among the people of the Quraish who
went ahead.</english-text>
</hadith>
