<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>21991</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1990</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20258, 10693, 11267, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا عبد الوارث، عن عامر الأحول، عن بكر
بن عبد الله، عن ابن عباس، قال أراد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
الحج فقالت امرأة لزوجها أحجني مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على
جملك ‏.‏ فقال ما عندي ما أحجك عليه ‏.‏ قالت أحجني على جملك فلان ‏.‏
قال ذاك حبيس في سبيل الله عز وجل ‏.‏ فأتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال إن امرأتي تقرأ عليك السلام ورحمة الله وإنها سألتني الحج
معك قالت أحجني مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقلت ما عندي ما
أحجك عليه ‏.‏ فقالت أحجني على جملك فلان ‏.‏ فقلت ذاك حبيس في سبيل
الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أما إنك لو أحججتها عليه كان في سبيل الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال وإنها أمرتني أن أسألك ما يعدل حجة معك ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أقرئها السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته وأخبرها أنها
تعدل حجة معي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يعني عمرة في رمضان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah Ibn Abbas: The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) intended to perform hajj. A woman said to her husband: Let me
perform hajj along with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He said: I have
nothing on which I can let you perform hajj. She said: You may
perform hajj on your such-and-such camel. He said: That is
dedicated to the cause of Allah, the Exalted. He then came to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: My wife has conveyed her greetings
and the blessings of Allah to you. She has asked about performing
hajj along with you. She said (to me): Let me perform hajj with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). I said (to her): I have nothing upon which
I can let you perform hajj. She said: Let me perform hajj on your
such-and-such camel. I said: That is dedicated to the cause of
Allah, The Exalted. He replied: If you let her perform hajj on it,
that would be in the cause of Allah. He said: She has also
requested me to ask you: What is that action which is equivalent to
performing hajj with you? The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Convey
my greetings, the mercy of Allah and His blessings to her and tell
her that umrah during Ramadan is equivalent to performing hajj
along with me.</english-text>
</hadith>
