<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22018</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2017</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Rites of Hajj (Kitab Al-Manasik Wa'l-Hajj) - كتاب
المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 20733, 20024, 11449, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن حنبل، حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا
الأوزاعي، حدثني يحيى، - يعني ابن أبي كثير - عن أبي سلمة، عن أبي
هريرة، قال لما فتح الله تعالى على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مكة
قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيهم فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال
‏"‏ إن الله حبس عن مكة الفيل وسلط عليها رسوله والمؤمنين وإنما أحلت
لي ساعة من النهار ثم هي حرام إلى يوم القيامة لا يعضد شجرها ولا ينفر
صيدها ولا تحل لقطتها إلا لمنشد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقام عباس أو قال قال العباس
يا رسول الله إلا الإذخر فإنه لقبورنا وبيوتنا ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إلا الإذخر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وزادنا فيه ابن
المصفى عن الوليد فقام أبو شاه - رجل من أهل اليمن - فقال يا رسول
الله اكتبوا لي ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اكتبوا
لأبي شاه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت للأوزاعي ما قوله ‏"‏ اكتبوا لأبي شاه ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال هذه الخطبة التي سمعها من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said “When Allah, the Exalted, granted
the conquest of Makkah to his Apostle, the Prophet(ﷺ) stood among
them(the people) and praised Allaah and extolled Him. He then said,
Verily Allaah stopped the Elephant from Makkah, and gave His
Apostle and the believers sway upon it and it has been made lawful
for me only for one hour on one day then it will remain sacred till
the Day of Resurrection. Its trees are not to be cut, its game is
not to be molested and the things dropped there are to be picked up
only by one who publicly announces it. ‘Abbas or Al ‘Abbas
suggested “Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) except the rush(idhkir) for it is
useful for our graves and our houses. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said
“Except the rush.” Abu Dawud said “Ibn Al Musaffa added on the
authority of Al Walid Abu Shah a man from the people of the Yemen
stood and said “Give me in writing, Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)”. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “Give in writing to Abu Shah. I said to
Al Awza’i “What does the statement mean? Give Abu Shah in writing?”
He said “This was an address which he heard from the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ).”</english-text>
</hadith>
