<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22069</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2068</hadith-number>
<chapter>Marriage (Kitab Al-Nikah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عمرو بن السرح المصري، حدثنا ابن وهب،
أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أنه سأل عائشة
زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن قول الله تعالى ‏{‏ وإن خفتم أن لا
تقسطوا في اليتامى فانكحوا ما طاب لكم من النساء ‏}‏ قالت يا ابن أختي
هي اليتيمة تكون في حجر وليها فتشاركه في ماله فيعجبه مالها وجمالها
فيريد أن يتزوجها بغير أن يقسط في صداقها فيعطيها مثل ما يعطيها غيره
فنهوا أن ينكحوهن إلا أن يقسطوا لهن ويبلغوا بهن أعلى سنتهن من الصداق
وأمروا أن ينكحوا ما طاب لهم من النساء سواهن ‏.‏ قال عروة قالت عائشة
ثم إن الناس استفتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعد هذه الآية فيهن
فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ ويستفتونك في النساء قل الله يفتيكم فيهن وما
يتلى عليكم في الكتاب في يتامى النساء اللاتي لا تؤتونهن ما كتب لهن
وترغبون أن تنكحوهن ‏}‏ قالت والذي ذكر الله أنه يتلى عليهم في الكتاب
الآية الأولى التي قال الله سبحانه وتعالى ‏{‏ وإن خفتم أن لا تقسطوا
في اليتامى فانكحوا ما طاب لكم من النساء ‏}‏ قالت عائشة وقول الله عز
وجل في الآية الآخرة ‏{‏ وترغبون أن تنكحوهن ‏}‏ هي رغبة أحدكم عن
يتيمته التي تكون في حجره حين تكون قليلة المال والجمال فنهوا أن
ينكحوا ما رغبوا في مالها وجمالها من يتامى النساء إلا بالقسط من أجل
رغبتهم عنهن ‏.‏ قال يونس وقال ربيعة في قول الله عز وجل ‏{‏ وإن خفتم
أن لا تقسطوا في اليتامى ‏}‏ قال يقول اتركوهن إن خفتم فقد أحللت لكم
أربعا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Shihab said “’Urwah bin Al Zubair asked A’ishah ,
wife of the Prophet(ﷺ) about the Qur’anic verse “And if ye fear
that ye will not deal fairly by the orphans, marry of the women,
who seem good to you.” She said “O my nephew, this means the female
orphan who is under the protection of her guardian and she holds a
share in his property and her property and beauty attracts him; so
her guardian intends to marry her without doing justice to her in
respect of her dower and he gives her the same amount of dower as
others give her. They (i.e., the guardians) were prohibited to
marry them except that they do justice to them and pay them their
maximum customary dower and they were asked to marry women other
than them (i.e., the orphans) who seem good to them. ‘Urwah
reported that A’ishah said “The people then consulted the Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) about women after revelation of this verse. Thereupon
Allaah the Exalted sent down the verse “They consult thee
concerning women. Say Allaah giveth you decree concerning them and
the scripture which hath been recited unto you(giveth decree)
concerning female orphans unto whom you give not that which is
ordained for them though you desire to marry them. “ She said “The
mention made by Allaah about the Scripture recited to them refers
to the former verse in which Allaah has said “And if ye fear that
ye will not deal fairly by the orphans, marry of the women, who
seem good to you.” A’ishah said “The pronouncement of Allaah , the
Exalted in the latter verse “though you desire to marry them” means
the disinterest of one of you in marrying a female orphan who was
under his protection, but she said little property and beauty. So
they were prohibited to marry them for their interest in the
property and beauty of the female orphans due to their disinterest
in themselves except that they do justice )to them). The narrator
Yunus said “Rabi’ah said explain the Qur’anic verse “And if ye fear
that ye will not deal fairly by the orphans” means “Leave them if
you fear (that you will not do justice to them), for I have made
four women lawful for you.”</english-text>
</hadith>
