<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22118</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2117</hadith-number>
<chapter>Marriage (Kitab Al-Nikah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 30170, 3, 20278, 20672, 11340, 11411,
189</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى بن فارس الذهلي، ومحمد بن المثنى،
وعمر بن الخطاب، - قال محمد - حدثنا أبو الأصبغ الجزري عبد العزيز بن
يحيى، أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، عن أبي عبد الرحيم، خالد بن أبي يزيد عن
زيد بن أبي أنيسة، عن يزيد بن أبي حبيب، عن مرثد بن عبد الله، عن عقبة
بن عامر، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال لرجل ‏"‏ أترضى أن أزوجك
فلانة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم ‏.‏ وقال للمرأة ‏"‏ أترضين أن أزوجك فلانا ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالت نعم ‏.‏ فزوج أحدهما صاحبه فدخل بها الرجل ولم يفرض لها
صداقا ولم يعطها شيئا وكان ممن شهد الحديبية وكان من شهد الحديبية له
سهم بخيبر فلما حضرته الوفاة قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
زوجني فلانة ولم أفرض لها صداقا ولم أعطها شيئا وإني أشهدكم أني
أعطيتها من صداقها سهمي بخيبر فأخذت سهما فباعته بمائة ألف ‏.‏ قال
أبو داود وزاد عمر بن الخطاب - وحديثه أتم - في أول الحديث قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خير النكاح أيسره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم للرجل ثم ساق معناه ‏.‏ قال أبو داود يخاف أن
يكون هذا الحديث ملزقا لأن الأمر على غير هذا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Uqbah ibn Amir: The Prophet (ﷺ) said to a
man: Would you like me to marry you to so-and-so? He said: Yes. He
also said to the woman: Would you like me to marry you to
so-and-so? She said: Yes. He then married one to the other. The man
had sexual intercourse with her, but he did not fix any dower for
her, nor did he give anything to her. He was one of those who
participated in the expedition to al-Hudaybiyyah. One part of the
expedition to al-Hudaybiyyah had a share in Khaybar. When he was
nearing his death, he said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) married me
to so-and-so, and I did not fix a dower for her, nor did I give
anything to her. I call upon you as witness that I have given my
share in Khaybar as her dower. So she took the share and sold it
for one lakh (of dirhams).Abu Dawud said: The version of 'Umar b.
al-Khattab added in the beginning of this tradition, and his
version is more perfect. He reported the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) as
saying: The best marriage is the one that is most easy. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to the man. The narrator then
transmitted the rest of the tradition to the same effect.Abu Dawud
said: I am afraid this tradition has been added later on, for the
matter is otherwise.</english-text>
</hadith>
