<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22132</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2131</hadith-number>
<chapter>Marriage (Kitab Al-Nikah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30567, 30, 20121, 11070, 11177, 11002</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مخلد بن خالد، والحسن بن علي، ومحمد بن أبي السري،
- المعنى - قالوا حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا ابن جريج، عن صفوان بن
سليم، عن سعيد بن المسيب، عن رجل، من الأنصار - قال ابن أبي السري من
أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ولم يقل من الأنصار ثم اتفقوا - يقال
له بصرة قال تزوجت امرأة بكرا في سترها فدخلت عليها فإذا هي حبلى فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لها الصداق بما استحللت من فرجها والولد
عبد لك فإذا ولدت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الحسن ‏"‏ فاجلدها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ابن أبي
السري ‏"‏ فاجلدوها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ فحدوها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
روى هذا الحديث قتادة عن سعيد بن يزيد عن ابن المسيب ورواه يحيى بن
أبي كثير عن يزيد بن نعيم عن سعيد بن المسيب وعطاء الخراساني عن سعيد
بن المسيب أرسلوه كلهم ‏.‏ وفي حديث يحيى بن أبي كثير أن بصرة بن أكثم
نكح امرأة وكلهم قال في حديثه جعل الولد عبدا له ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A man from the Ansar called Basrah said: I married a
virgin woman in her veil. When I entered upon her, I found her
pregnant. (I mentioned this to the Prophet). The Prophet (ﷺ) said:
She will get the dower, for you made her vagina lawful for you. The
child will be your slave. When she has begotten (a child), flog her
(according to the version of al-Hasan). The version of Ibn AbusSari
has: You people, flog her, or said: inflict hard punishment on
him.Abu Dawud said: This tradition has been transmitted by Qatadah
from Sa'd b. Yazid on the authority of Ibn al-Musayyab in a similar
way. This tradition has been narrated by Yahya b. Abi Kathir from
Yazid b. Nu'aim from Sa'id b. al-Musayyab, and 'Ata al-Khurasani
narrated it from Sa'id b. al-Musayyab ; they all narrated this
tradition from the Prophet (ﷺ) omitting the link of the Companion
(i.e. a mursal tradition). The version of Yahya b. Abi Kathir has:
Basrah b. Aktham married a woman. The agreed version has: He made
the child his servant.</english-text>
</hadith>
