<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22166</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2165</hadith-number>
<chapter>Marriage (Kitab Al-Nikah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا حماد، أخبرنا ثابت
البناني، عن أنس بن مالك، أن اليهود، كانت إذا حاضت منهم امرأة
أخرجوها من البيت ولم يؤاكلوها ولم يشاربوها ولم يجامعوها في البيت
فسئل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن ذلك فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏
يسألونك عن المحيض قل هو أذى فاعتزلوا النساء في المحيض ‏}‏ إلى آخر
الآية فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ جامعوهن في البيوت
واصنعوا كل شىء غير النكاح ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت اليهود ما يريد هذا الرجل أن
يدع شيئا من أمرنا إلا خالفنا فيه ‏.‏ فجاء أسيد بن حضير وعباد بن بشر
إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالا يا رسول الله إن اليهود تقول
كذا وكذا أفلا ننكحهن في المحيض فتمعر وجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حتى ظننا أن قد وجد عليهما فخرجا فاستقبلتهما هدية من لبن إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فبعث في آثارهما فسقاهما فظننا أنه لم
يجد عليهما ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas bin Malik said Among the Jews when a woman
menstruated, they did not eat with her and drink with her and did
not associate with her in their houses, so the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
was questioned about it. Hence, Allah the Exalted revealed “And
they ask you about menstruation,. Say “It is harmful, so keep aloof
from women during menstruation till the end of the verse. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “Associate with them in the houses and do
everything except sexual intercourse. The Jews thereupon said “This
man does not leave anything we do without opposing us in it. Usaid
bin Hudair and Abbad bin Bishr came to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) and
said, Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) the Jews are saying such and such. Shall
we not have intercourse with them during their menstruation? The
face of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) underwent such a change that we
thought he was angry with them, so they went out. They were met by
a gift of milk which was being brought to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
and he sent after them, whereby we felt that he was not angry with
them.</english-text>
</hadith>
