<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22197</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2196</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20121, 11070</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا ابن جريج،
أخبرني بعض بني أبي رافع، مولى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن عكرمة
مولى ابن عباس عن ابن عباس قال طلق عبد يزيد - أبو ركانة وإخوته - أم
ركانة ونكح امرأة من مزينة فجاءت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت ما
يغني عني إلا كما تغني هذه الشعرة ‏.‏ لشعرة أخذتها من رأسها ففرق
بيني وبينه فأخذت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حمية فدعا بركانة وإخوته
ثم قال لجلسائه ‏"‏ أترون فلانا يشبه منه كذا وكذا من عبد يزيد وفلانا
يشبه منه - كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم لعبد يزيد ‏"‏ طلقها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعل ثم قال ‏"‏ راجع امرأتك أم
ركانة وإخوته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال إني طلقتها ثلاثا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
قد علمت راجعها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وتلا ‏{‏ يا أيها النبي إذا طلقتم النساء
فطلقوهن لعدتهن ‏}‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وحديث نافع بن عجير وعبد الله بن
علي بن يزيد بن ركانة عن أبيه عن جده أن ركانة طلق امرأته البتة فردها
إليه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أصح لأن ولد الرجل وأهله أعلم به أن
ركانة إنما طلق امرأته البتة فجعلها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم واحدة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Abbas: Abd Yazid, the father of
Rukanah and his brothers, divorced Umm Rukanah and married a woman
of the tribe of Muzaynah. She went to the Prophet (ﷺ) and said: He
is of no use to me except that he is as useful to me as a hair; and
she took a hair from her head. So separate me from him. The Prophet
(ﷺ) became furious. He called on Rukanah and his brothers. He then
said to those who were sitting beside him. Do you see so-and-so who
resembles Abdu Yazid in respect of so-and-so; and so-and-so who
resembles him in respect of so-and-so? They replied: Yes. The
Prophet (ﷺ) said to Abdu Yazid: Divorce her. Then he did so. He
said: Take your wife, the mother of Rukanah and his brothers, back
in marriage. He said: I have divorced her by three pronouncements,
Messenger of Allah. He said: I know: take her back. He then recited
the verse: "O Prophet, when you divorce women, divorce them at
their appointed periods."Abu Dawud said: The tradition narrated by
Nafi' b. 'Ujair and 'Abd Allah b. Yazid b. Rukanah from his father
on the authority of his grandfather reads: Rukanah divorced his
wife absolutely (i.e. irrevocable divorce). The Prophet (ﷺ)
restored her to him. This version is sounder (than other versions),
for they (i.e. these narrators) are the children of his man, and
the members of the family are more aware of his case. Rukanah
divorced his wife absolutely (i.e. three divorces in one
pronouncement) and the Prophet (ﷺ) made it a single
divorce.</english-text>
</hadith>
