<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22198</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2197</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30430, 20208, 11015, 11252, 11028</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حميد بن مسعدة، حدثنا إسماعيل، أخبرنا أيوب، عن
عبد الله بن كثير، عن مجاهد، قال كنت عند ابن عباس فجاء رجل فقال إنه
طلق امرأته ثلاثا ‏.‏ قال فسكت حتى ظننت أنه رادها إليه ‏.‏ ثم قال
ينطلق أحدكم فيركب الحموقة ثم يقول يا ابن عباس يا ابن عباس وإن الله
قال ‏{‏ ومن يتق الله يجعل له مخرجا ‏}‏ وإنك لم تتق الله فلم أجد لك
مخرجا عصيت ربك وبانت منك امرأتك وإن الله قال ‏{‏ يا أيها النبي إذا
طلقتم النساء فطلقوهن ‏}‏ في قبل عدتهن ‏.‏ قال أبو داود روى هذا
الحديث حميد الأعرج وغيره عن مجاهد عن ابن عباس ورواه شعبة عن عمرو بن
مرة عن سعيد بن جبير عن ابن عباس وأيوب وابن جريج جميعا عن عكرمة بن
خالد عن سعيد بن جبير عن ابن عباس ورواه ابن جريج عن عبد الحميد بن
رافع عن عطاء عن ابن عباس ورواه الأعمش عن مالك بن الحارث عن ابن عباس
وابن جريج عن عمرو بن دينار عن ابن عباس كلهم قالوا في الطلاق الثلاث
إنه أجازها قال وبانت منك نحو حديث إسماعيل عن أيوب عن عبد الله بن
كثير ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وروى حماد بن زيد عن أيوب عن عكرمة عن ابن عباس
إذا قال ‏"‏ أنت طالق ثلاثا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ بفم واحد فهي واحدة ورواه إسماعيل
بن إبراهيم عن أيوب عن عكرمة هذا قوله لم يذكر ابن عباس وجعله قول
عكرمة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mujahid said “I was with Ibn ‘Abbas”. A man came to
him and said that he divorced his wife by three pronouncements. I
kept silence and thought that he was going to restore het to him.
He then said “A man goes and commits a foolish act and then says
“O, Ibn ‘Abbas! Alaah has said “And for those who fear Allaah, He
(ever) prepares a way out.” Since you did not keep duty to Allaah I
do not find a way out for you. You disobeyed your Lord and your
wife was separated from you. Allaah has said “O Prophet! When you
divorce women divorce them in the beginning of their waiting
period.”Abu Dawud said “This tradition has been transmitted by
Humaid Al A’raj and by others from Mujahid on the authority of Ibn
‘Abbas. Shu’bjh narrated it from ‘Amr bin Murrah from Sa’id bin
Jubair on the authority of Ibn ‘Abbas. Ayyub and Ibn ‘Jubair both
narrated it from “’Ikrimah bin Khalid from Sa’id bin Jubair on the
authority of Ibn ‘Abbas. Ibn Juraij narrated it from ‘Abd Al Hamid
bin Rafi’ from ‘Ata from Ibn ‘Abbas. Al A’mash narrated it from
Malik bin Al Harith on the authority of Ibn ‘Abbas. They all said
about the divorce by three pronouncements. He allowed it and said”
(Your wife) has been separated from you similar to the tradition
narrated by Isma’il from Ayub from ‘Abd Allaah bin Kathir.”Abu
Dawud said “Hammad bin Zaid narrated it from Ayyub from ‘Ikrimah on
the authority of Ibn ‘Abbas. This version adds If he said “You are
divorced three times saying in one pronouncement, it constitutes a
single (divorce). Isma’il bin Ibrahim narrated it from Ayyub from
‘Ikrimah. This is his (‘Ikrimah’s) statement. He did not mention
the name of Ibn ‘Abbas. He narrated it as a statement of
‘Ikrimah.”</english-text>
</hadith>
