<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22214</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2213</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 30216, 20102, 11107, 11220, 11005</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، ومحمد بن العلاء، - المعنى -
قالا حدثنا ابن إدريس، عن محمد بن إسحاق، عن محمد بن عمرو بن عطاء، -
قال ابن العلاء ابن علقمة بن عياش - عن سليمان بن يسار، عن سلمة بن
صخر، - قال ابن العلاء البياضي - قال كنت امرأ أصيب من النساء ما لا
يصيب غيري فلما دخل شهر رمضان خفت أن أصيب من امرأتي شيئا يتابع بي
حتى أصبح فظاهرت منها حتى ينسلخ شهر رمضان فبينما هي تخدمني ذات ليلة
إذ تكشف لي منها شىء فلم ألبث أن نزوت عليها فلما أصبحت خرجت إلى قومي
فأخبرتهم الخبر وقلت امشوا معي إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏
قالوا لا والله ‏.‏ فانطلقت إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته
فقال ‏"‏ أنت بذاك يا سلمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت أنا بذاك يا رسول الله مرتين
وأنا صابر لأمر الله فاحكم في ما أراك الله قال ‏"‏ حرر رقبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قلت والذي بعثك بالحق ما أملك رقبة غيرها وضربت صفحة رقبتي قال ‏"‏
فصم شهرين متتابعين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وهل أصبت الذي أصبت إلا من الصيام قال
‏"‏ فأطعم وسقا من تمر بين ستين مسكينا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت والذي بعثك بالحق
لقد بتنا وحشين ما لنا طعام قال ‏"‏ فانطلق إلى صاحب صدقة بني زريق
فليدفعها إليك فأطعم ستين مسكينا وسقا من تمر وكل أنت وعيالك بقيتها
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجعت إلى قومي فقلت وجدت عندكم الضيق وسوء الرأى ووجدت عند
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم السعة وحسن الرأى وقد أمرني - أو أمر لي -
بصدقتكم زاد ابن العلاء قال ابن إدريس بياضة بطن من بني زريق
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Salamah ibn Sakhr al-Bayadi: I was a man who
was more given than others to sexual intercourse with women. When
the month of Ramadan came, I feared lest I should have intercourse
with my wife, and this evil should remain with me till the morning.
So I made my wife like my mother's back to me till the end of
Ramadan. But one night when she was waiting upon me, something of
her was revealed. Suddenly I jumped upon her. When the morning came
I went to my people and informed them about this matter. I said: Go
along with me to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). They said: No, by
Allah. So I went to the Prophet (peace be upon him and informed him
of the matter. He said: Have you really committed it, Salamah? I
said: I committed it twice, Messenger of Allah. I am content with
the Commandment of Allah, the Exalted; so take a decision about me
according to what Allah has shown you. He said: Free a slave. I
said: By Him Who sent you with truth, I do not possess a neck other
than this: and I struck the surface of my neck. He said: Then fast
two consecutive months. I said: Whatever I suffered is due to
fasting. He said: Feed sixty poor people with a wasq of dates. I
said: By Him Who sent you with truth, we passed the night hungry;
there was no food in our house. He said: Then go to the collector
of sadaqah of Banu Zurayq; he must give it to you. Then feed sixty
poor people with a wasq of dates; and you and your family eat the
remaining dates. Then I came back to my people, and said (to them):
I found with you poverty and bad opinion; and I found with the
Prophet (ﷺ) prosperity and good opinion. He has commanded me to
give alms to you. Ibn al-Ala' added: Ibn Idris said: Bayadah is a
sub-clan of Banu Zurayq.</english-text>
</hadith>
