<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22246</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2245</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 399, 5215</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ابن شهاب،
أن سهل بن سعد الساعدي، أخبره أن عويمر بن أشقر العجلاني جاء إلى عاصم
بن عدي فقال له يا عاصم أرأيت رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا أيقتله
فتقتلونه أم كيف يفعل سل لي يا عاصم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن
ذلك ‏.‏ فسأل عاصم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فكره رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم المسائل وعابها حتى كبر على عاصم ما سمع من رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما رجع عاصم إلى أهله جاءه عويمر فقال له يا
عاصم ماذا قال لك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال عاصم لم تأتني
بخير قد كره رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المسألة التي سألته عنها
‏.‏ فقال عويمر والله لا أنتهي حتى أسأله عنها ‏.‏ فأقبل عويمر حتى
أتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو وسط الناس فقال يا رسول الله
أرأيت رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا أيقتله فتقتلونه أم كيف يفعل فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد أنزل فيك وفي صاحبتك قرآن فاذهب فأت
بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سهل فتلاعنا وأنا مع الناس عند رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فلما فرغا قال عويمر كذبت عليها يا رسول الله إن أمسكتها
‏.‏ فطلقها عويمر ثلاثا قبل أن يأمره النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏
قال ابن شهاب فكانت تلك سنة المتلاعنين ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl bin Sa’ad Al Sa’idi said that ‘Uwaimir bin
Ashqar Al Ajilani came to ‘Asim bin Adl and said to him “Asim tell
me about a man who finds a man along with his wife. Should he kill
him and then be killed by you, or how should he act? Ask the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) ‘Asim, for me about it. ‘Asim then asked the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) about it. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) disliked
the question and denounced it. What ‘Asim heard from the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) fell heavy on him. When ‘Asim returned to his family
‘Uwaimr came to him and asked ‘Asim “What did the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) say to you”? Asim replied “You did not do good to me”.
The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) disliked the question that I asked him.
Thereupon ‘Uwaimir said “I swear by Allaah, I shall not leave until
I ask him about it. So, ‘Uwaimir came to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
while he was sitting in the midst of the people.” He said “Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) tell me about a man who finds a man along with his
wife. Should he kill him and then be killed by you, or how should
he act?” The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “A revelation has been sent
down about you and your wife so go away and bring her. Sahl said
“So we cursed one another while I was along with the people who
were with the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ). Then when they finished,
‘Umamir said “I shall have lied against her, Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
if I keep her. He pronounced her divorce three times before the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)commanded him (to do so).Ibn Shihab said “Then
this became the method of invoking curses.”</english-text>
</hadith>
