<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22254</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2253</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 20028, 11060, 11051, 11017, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا جرير، عن الأعمش، عن
إبراهيم، عن علقمة، عن عبد الله، قال إنا لليلة جمعة في المسجد إذ دخل
رجل من الأنصار في المسجد فقال لو أن رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا فتكلم
به جلدتموه أو قتل قتلتموه فإن سكت سكت على غيظ والله لأسألن عنه رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فلما كان من الغد أتى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فسأله فقال لو أن رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا فتكلم به جلدتموه
أو قتل قتلتموه أو سكت سكت على غيظ ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اللهم افتح ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وجعل يدعو فنزلت آية اللعان ‏{‏ والذين يرمون أزواجهم ولم يكن لهم
شهداء إلا أنفسهم ‏}‏ هذه الآية فابتلي به ذلك الرجل من بين الناس
فجاء هو وامرأته إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فتلاعنا فشهد الرجل
أربع شهادات بالله إنه لمن الصادقين ثم لعن الخامسة عليه إن كان من
الكاذبين قال فذهبت لتلتعن فقال لها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ مه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأبت ففعلت فلما أدبرا قال ‏"‏ لعلها أن تجيء به أسود جعدا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاءت به أسود جعدا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abd Allah (bin Mas’ud) said “We were in the mosque
on the night of a Friday, suddenly a man from the Ansar entered the
mosque”. And said “If a man finds a man along with wife and
declares (about her adultery) you will flog him. Or if he kills
you, you will kill him or if keeps silence he will keep silence in
anger. I swear by Allaah, I shall ask the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
about it”. On the next day he came to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) and
said “If a man finds a man along with wife and declares (about her
adultery) you will flog him. Or if he kills you, you will kill him
or if keeps silence he will keep silence in anger.” He said “O
Allaah, disclose”. He kept on praying until the verses regarding
invoking curses (li’an) came down “As for those who accuse their
wives but have no witnesses except themselves.” So, the man was
first involved in this trial among the people. He and his wife came
to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ). They invoked curses on each other. The
man bore witness before Allaah four times that the thing he said
was indeed true. He then invoked curse of Allaah on him for the
fifth time if he was a liar. She then wanted to invoke curses of
Allaah on him. The Prophet (ﷺ) said “Do not do that. Bust she
refused and did so (i.e., invoked curses). When they returned he
said “Perhaps she will give birth to a black child with curly
hair.</english-text>
</hadith>
