<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22285</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2284</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11189, 10567, 224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن عبد الله بن يزيد، مولى
الأسود بن سفيان عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، عن فاطمة بنت قيس، أن أبا
عمرو بن حفص، طلقها البتة وهو غائب فأرسل إليها وكيله بشعير فتسخطته
فقال والله ما لك علينا من شىء ‏.‏ فجاءت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فذكرت ذلك له فقال لها ‏"‏ ليس لك عليه نفقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأمرها أن
تعتد في بيت أم شريك ثم قال ‏"‏ إن تلك امرأة يغشاها أصحابي اعتدي في
بيت ابن أم مكتوم فإنه رجل أعمى تضعين ثيابك وإذا حللت فآذنيني ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالت فلما حللت ذكرت له أن معاوية بن أبي سفيان وأبا جهم خطباني
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما أبو جهم فلا يضع عصاه عن
عاتقه وأما معاوية فصعلوك لا مال له انكحي أسامة بن زيد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت
فكرهته ثم قال ‏"‏ انكحي أسامة بن زيد ‏.‏ فنكحته فجعل الله تعالى فيه
خيرا كثيرا واغتبطت به ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Salamah bin ‘Abd Al Rahman reported on the
authority of Fatimah daughter of Qais Abu ‘Amr bin Hafs divorced
her (Fathima daughter of Qais) absolutely when he was away from
home and his agent sent her home barely. She was displeased with
it. He said “I swear by Allaah, you have no claim on us. She then
came to Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) and mentioned that to him. He said to
her “No maintenance is due to you for from him. He ordered her to
spend the waiting period in the house of Umm Sharik but he said
afterwards “that is a woman whom my Companions visits spend the
waiting period in the house of Ibn Umm Maktum for he is blind and
you can undress. Then when you are in a position of being
remarried, tell me.” She said “When I was in a position to remarry,
I mentioned to him that Mu’awiyah bin Abi Sufyan and Abu Jahm had
asked me in marriage. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)said “As for Abu
Jahm, he does not put down his stick from his shoulder, and as for
Mu’awiyah he is a poor man who has no property; marry Usamah bin
Zaid. I disliked him but he said “Maary Usamah bin Zaid. So, I
married him. And Allaah prospered him very much and I was
envied.”</english-text>
</hadith>
