<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22301</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2300</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 19805</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، عن مالك، عن سعد بن
إسحاق بن كعب بن عجرة، عن عمته، زينب بنت كعب بن عجرة أن الفريعة بنت
مالك بن سنان، - وهي أخت أبي سعيد الخدري - أخبرتها أنها، جاءت إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تسأله أن ترجع إلى أهلها في بني خدرة
فإن زوجها خرج في طلب أعبد له أبقوا حتى إذا كانوا بطرف القدوم لحقهم
فقتلوه فسألت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن أرجع إلى أهلي فإني لم
يتركني في مسكن يملكه ولا نفقة ‏.‏ قالت فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فخرجت حتى إذا كنت في الحجرة أو في المسجد
دعاني أو أمر بي فدعيت له فقال ‏"‏ كيف قلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرددت عليه القصة
التي ذكرت من شأن زوجي قالت فقال ‏"‏ امكثي في بيتك حتى يبلغ الكتاب
أجله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فاعتددت فيه أربعة أشهر وعشرا ‏.‏ قالت فلما كان
عثمان بن عفان أرسل إلى فسألني عن ذلك فأخبرته فاتبعه وقضى به
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Zaynab, daughter of Ka'b ibn Ujrah narrated that
Furay'ah daughter of Malik ibn Sinan, told her that she came to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and asked him whether she could return to
her people, Banu Khidrah, for her husband went out seeking his
slaves who ran away. When they met him at al-Qudum, they murdered
him. So I asked the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ): "Should I return to my
people, for he did not leave any dwelling house of his own and
maintenance for me? She said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) replied:
Yes. She said: I came out, and when I was in the apartment or in
the mosque, he called for me, or he commanded (someone to call me)
and, therefore, I was called. He said: what did you say? So I
repeated my story which I had already mentioned about my husband.
Thereupon he said: Stay in your house till the term lapses. She
said: So I passed my waiting period in it (her house) for four
months and ten days. When Uthman ibn Affan became caliph, he sent
for me and asked me about that; so I informed him, and he followed
it and decided cases accordingly.</english-text>
</hadith>
