<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22306</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2305</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce (Kitab Al-Talaq) - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20029</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا ابن وهب، أخبرني مخرمة، عن
أبيه، قال سمعت المغيرة بن الضحاك، يقول أخبرتني أم حكيم بنت أسيد، عن
أمها، أن زوجها، توفي وكانت تشتكي عينيها فتكتحل بالجلاء - قال أحمد
الصواب بكحل الجلاء - فأرسلت مولاة لها إلى أم سلمة فسألتها عن كحل
الجلاء فقالت لا تكتحلي به إلا من أمر لا بد منه يشتد عليك فتكتحلين
بالليل وتمسحينه بالنهار ‏.‏ ثم قالت عند ذلك أم سلمة دخل على رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين توفي أبو سلمة وقد جعلت على عيني صبرا
فقال ‏"‏ ما هذا يا أم سلمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت إنما هو صبر يا رسول الله
ليس فيه طيب ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إنه يشب الوجه فلا تجعليه إلا بالليل
وتنزعينه بالنهار ولا تمتشطي بالطيب ولا بالحناء فإنه خضاب ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت قلت بأى شىء أمتشط يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ بالسدر تغلفين به رأسك
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Umm Hakim, daughter of Usayd, reported on the
authority of her mother that her husband died and she was suffering
from sore eyes. She therefore applied collyrium (jala'). Ahmad
said: The correct version is "glittering collyrium (kuhl al-jala').
She sent her slave-girl to Umm Salamah, and she asked her about the
use of glittering collyrium (kuhl al-jala'). She said: Do not apply
it except in the case of dire need which is troubling you. In that
case you can use it at night, but you should remove it in the
daytime. Then Umm Salamah said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came to
visit me when AbuSalamah died, and I had put the juice of aloes in
my eye. He asked : What is this, Umm Salamah? I replied: It is only
the juice of aloes and contains no perfume. He said: It gives the
face a glow, so apply it only at night and remove it in daytime,
and do not comb yourself with scent or henna, for it is a dye. I
asked: What should I use when I comb myself, Messenger of Allah? He
said: Use lote-tree leaves and smear your head copiously with
them.</english-text>
</hadith>
