<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22339</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2338</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fasting (Kitab Al-Siyam) - كتاب الصوم</chapter>
<chain-index>30252, 20431, 10766</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الرحيم أبو يحيى البزاز، حدثنا سعيد
بن سليمان، حدثنا عباد، عن أبي مالك الأشجعي، حدثنا حسين بن الحارث
الجدلي، - من جديلة قيس أن أمير مكة خطب ثم قال عهد إلينا رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن ننسك للرؤية فإن لم نره وشهد شاهدا عدل نسكنا
بشهادتهما فسألت الحسين بن الحارث من أمير مكة قال لا أدري ‏.‏ ثم
لقيني بعد فقال هو الحارث بن حاطب أخو محمد بن حاطب ثم قال الأمير إن
فيكم من هو أعلم بالله ورسوله مني وشهد هذا من رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وأومأ بيده إلى رجل قال الحسين فقلت لشيخ إلى جنبي من
هذا الذي أومأ إليه الأمير قال هذا عبد الله بن عمر ‏.‏ وصدق كان أعلم
بالله منه فقال بذلك أمرنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Umar: Husayn ibn al-Harith
al-Jadli from the tribe of Jadilah Qays said: The governor of Mecca
delivered a speech and said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) took a
pledge from us that we should perform the rites of hajj after
sighting the moon. If we do not sight it and two reliable persons
bear witness, we should perform the rites of hajj on the basis of
their witness. I then asked al-Husayn ibn al-Harith: Who was the
governor of Mecca? He replied: I do not know. He then met me later
on and told me: He was al-Harith ibn Hatib, brother of Muhammad ibn
Hatib. The governor then said: There is among you a man who is more
acquainted with Allah and His Apostle than I. He witnessed this
from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He then pointed with his hand to a
man. Al-Husayn said: I asked an old man beside me: Who is that man
to whom the governor has alluded? He said: "This is Abdullah ibn
Umar, and he spoke the truth. He was more acquainted with Allah
than he. He (Abdullah ibn Umar) said: For this is what the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) commanded us (to do).</english-text>
</hadith>
