<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22429</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2428</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fasting (Kitab Al-Siyam) - كتاب الصوم</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11286</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا حماد، عن سعيد الجريري، عن
أبي السليل، عن مجيبة الباهلية، عن أبيها، أو عمها أنه أتى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم انطلق فأتاه بعد سنة وقد تغيرت حالته وهيئته
فقال يا رسول الله أما تعرفني قال ‏"‏ ومن أنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أنا
الباهلي الذي جئتك عام الأول ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فما غيرك وقد كنت حسن الهيئة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ما أكلت طعاما إلا بليل منذ فارقتك ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لم عذبت نفسك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ صم شهر الصبر
ويوما من كل شهر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال زدني فإن بي قوة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ صم يومين
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال زدني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ صم ثلاثة أيام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال زدني ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ صم من الحرم واترك صم من الحرم واترك صم من الحرم واترك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وقال بأصابعه الثلاثة فضمها ثم أرسلها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn al-Harith ; or Uncle of Mujibah
al-Bahiliyyah: The father or Uncle of Mujibah al-Bahiliyyah visited
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). He then went away and came to him
(again) after one year when his condition and appearance had
changed. He said: Messenger of Allah, do you not recognize me? He
asked: Who are you? He replied: I am al-Bahili who came to you last
year. He said: What has changed you? You were looking well, then
you were good in appearance? He said: I have only food at night
since I departed from you. Thereupon the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: Why did you torment yourself? Fast during Ramadan (the month
of patience) and fast for one day every month. He said: Increase it
for me, for I have (more) strength. He said: Fast two days. He
again said: Increase it for me. He said: Fast three days. He again
said: Increase it for me. He said: Fast during the inviolable
months and then stop; fast during the inviolable months and then
stop; fast during the inviolable months and then stop. He indicated
by his three fingers, and joined them and then opened
them.</english-text>
</hadith>
