<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22460</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2459</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fasting (Kitab Al-Siyam) - كتاب الصوم</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 20028, 11060, 11161, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا جرير، عن الأعمش، عن أبي
صالح، عن أبي سعيد، قال جاءت امرأة إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ونحن
عنده فقالت يا رسول الله إن زوجي صفوان بن المعطل يضربني إذا صليت
ويفطرني إذا صمت ولا يصلي صلاة الفجر حتى تطلع الشمس ‏.‏ قال وصفوان
عنده ‏.‏ قال فسأله عما قالت فقال يا رسول الله أما قولها يضربني إذا
صليت فإنها تقرأ بسورتين وقد نهيتها ‏.‏ قال فقال ‏"‏ لو كانت سورة
واحدة لكفت الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأما قولها يفطرني فإنها تنطلق فتصوم وأنا
رجل شاب فلا أصبر ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يومئذ ‏"‏ لا
تصوم امرأة إلا بإذن زوجها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأما قولها إني لا أصلي حتى تطلع
الشمس فإنا أهل بيت قد عرف لنا ذاك لا نكاد نستيقظ حتى تطلع الشمس ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإذا استيقظت فصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود رواه حماد - يعني ابن
سلمة - عن حميد أو ثابت عن أبي المتوكل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuSa'id al-Khudri: A woman came to the
Prophet (ﷺ) while we were with him. She said: Messenger of Allah,
my husband, Safwan ibn al-Mu'attal, beats me when I pray, and makes
me break my fast when I keep a fast, and he does not offer the dawn
prayer until the sun rises. He asked Safwan, who was present, about
what she had said. He replied: Messenger of Allah, as for her
statement "he beats me when I pray", she recites two surahs (during
prayer) and I have prohibited her (to do so). He (the Prophet)
said: If one surah is recited (during prayer), that is sufficient
for the people. (Safwan continued:) As regards her saying "he makes
me break my fast," she dotes on fasting; I am a young man, I cannot
restrain myself. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said on that day: A
woman should not fast except with the permission of her husband.
(Safwan said:) As for her statement that I do not pray until the
sun rises, we are a people belonging to a class, and that (our
profession of supplying water) is already known about us. We do not
awake until the sun rises. He said: When you awake, offer your
prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
