<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22491</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2490</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30584, 20022, 20031, 11222, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن داود العتكي، حدثنا حماد، - يعني ابن
زيد - عن يحيى بن سعيد، عن محمد بن يحيى بن حبان، عن أنس بن مالك، قال
حدثتني أم حرام بنت ملحان، أخت أم سليم أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال عندهم فاستيقظ وهو يضحك ‏.‏ قالت فقلت يا رسول الله ما أضحكك
قال ‏"‏ رأيت قوما ممن يركب ظهر هذا البحر كالملوك على الأسرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت قلت يا رسول الله ادع الله أن يجعلني منهم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنك منهم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ثم نام فاستيقظ وهو يضحك ‏.‏ قالت فقلت يا رسول الله ما
أضحكك فقال مثل مقالته ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله ادع الله أن يجعلني منهم
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أنت من الأولين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فتزوجها عبادة بن الصامت فغزا
في البحر فحملها معه فلما رجع قربت لها بغلة لتركبها فصرعتها فاندقت
عنقها فماتت ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas bin Malik (may Allaah be pleased with him) said
“Umm Haram, daughter of Milhan, sister of Umm Sulaim, narrated to
me that the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) took a mid day nap with them. He
then awoke laughing. She said “I asked the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ),
what made you laugh?” He replied “I saw some people who ere sailing
in the midst of the sea like kings on thrones. She said “I said the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) beseech Allaah that He may put me among them.
He replied “You will be among them.” She said “He then slept and
awoke laughing. She said “I asked the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ), what
made you laugh? He replied as he said in the first reply. She said
“I said the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) beseech Allaah that HE may put me
amongst them. He replied “You will be among the first. Then ‘Ubadah
bin Al Samit married her and sailed on the sea on an expedition and
took her with him. When he returned, a riding beast was brought
near her to ride, but it threw her down. Her neck was broken and
she died.</english-text>
</hadith>
