<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22508</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2507</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30116, 20509, 11061, 49</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن منصور، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن أبي الزناد،
عن أبيه، عن خارجة بن زيد، عن زيد بن ثابت، قال ‏:‏ كنت إلى جنب رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فغشيته السكينة فوقعت فخذ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم على فخذي، فما وجدت ثقل شىء أثقل من فخذ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم سري عنه فقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ اكتب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكتبت في كتف ‏:‏ لا
يستوي القاعدون من المؤمنين والمجاهدون في سبيل الله ‏.‏ إلى آخر
الآية، فقام ابن أم مكتوم - وكان رجلا أعمى - لما سمع فضيلة المجاهدين
فقال ‏:‏ يا رسول الله فكيف بمن لا يستطيع الجهاد من المؤمنين فلما
قضى كلامه غشيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم السكينة فوقعت فخذه على
فخذي ووجدت من ثقلها في المرة الثانية كما وجدت في المرة الأولى ثم
سري عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ اقرأ يا زيد ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقرأت ‏{‏ لا يستوي القاعدون من المؤمنين ‏}‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏{‏ غير أولي الضرر ‏}‏ الآية كلها ‏.‏ قال زيد ‏:‏
فأنزلها الله وحدها فألحقتها، والذي نفسي بيده لكأني أنظر إلى ملحقها
عند صدع في كتف ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Zaid bin Thabit said “I was beside the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) when the divinely-inspired calmness overtook him and the
thigh of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) fell on my thigh. I did not find
any weightier than the thigh of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ). He then
regained his composure and said “Write down. I wrote on a shoulder.
Not equal are thise believers who sit (at home), other than those
who have a (disabling) hurt, and those who strive in the way of
Allaah. When Ibn Umm Makhtum who was blind heard the excellence of
the warriors. He stood up and said “Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) how is it
for those believers who are unable to fight (in the path of
Allaah)? When he finished his question his divinely-inspired
calmness overtook him, and his thigh fell on my thigh and I found
its weight the second time as I found the first time.” When the
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) regained his composure, he said “Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) said “Other than those who have a (disabling hurt). Zaid
said “Allaah, the exalted, revealed it alone and I appended it.” By
Him in Whose hands is my life, I am seeing, as it were the place
where I put it (i.e., the verse) at the crack in the
shoulder.”</english-text>
</hadith>
