<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22513</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2512</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30485, 20029, 26010, 20624, 11411</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عمرو بن السرح، حدثنا ابن وهب، عن حيوة بن
شريح، وابن، لهيعة عن يزيد بن أبي حبيب، عن أسلم أبي عمران، قال ‏:‏
غزونا من المدينة نريد القسطنطينية، وعلى الجماعة عبد الرحمن بن خالد
بن الوليد والروم ملصقو ظهورهم بحائط المدينة، فحمل رجل على العدو
فقال الناس ‏:‏ مه، مه، لا إله إلا الله، يلقي بيديه إلى التهلكة ‏.‏
فقال أبو أيوب ‏:‏ إنما نزلت هذه الآية فينا معشر الأنصار لما نصر
الله نبيه وأظهر الإسلام، قلنا ‏:‏ هلم نقيم في أموالنا ونصلحها،
فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏ وأنفقوا في سبيل الله ولا تلقوا بأيديكم إلى
التهلكة ‏}‏ فالإلقاء بالأيدي إلى التهلكة أن نقيم في أموالنا ونصلحها
وندع الجهاد ‏.‏ قال أبو عمران ‏:‏ فلم يزل أبو أيوب يجاهد في سبيل
الله حتى دفن بالقسطنطينية ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuAyyub: AbuImran said: We went out on an
expedition from Medina with the intention of (attacking)
Constantinople. AbdurRahman ibn Khalid ibn al-Walid was the leader
of the company. The Romans were just keeping their backs to the
walls of the city. A man (suddenly) attacked the enemy. Thereupon
the people said: Stop! Stop! There is no god but Allah. He is
putting himself into danger. AbuAyyub said: This verse was revealed
about us, the group of the Ansar (the Helpers). When Allah helped
His Prophet (ﷺ) and gave Islam dominance, we said (i.e. thought):
Come on! Let us stay in our property and improve it. Thereupon
Allah, the Exalted, revealed, "And spend of your substance in the
cause of Allah, and make not your hands contribute to (your
destruction)". To put oneself into danger means that we stay in our
property and commit ourselves to its improvement, and abandon
fighting (i.e. jihad). AbuImran said: AbuAyyub continued to strive
in the cause of Allah until he (died and) was buried in
Constantinople.</english-text>
</hadith>
