<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22613</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2612</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>31160, 20032, 20012, 11374, 10916, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سليمان الأنباري، حدثنا وكيع، عن سفيان،
عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن أبيه، قال كان رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا بعث أميرا على سرية أو جيش أوصاه بتقوى الله
في خاصة نفسه وبمن معه من المسلمين خيرا وقال ‏"‏ إذا لقيت عدوك من
المشركين فادعهم إلى إحدى ثلاث خصال أو خلال فأيتها أجابوك إليها
فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم ادعهم إلى الإسلام فإن أجابوك فاقبل منهم وكف
عنهم ثم ادعهم إلى التحول من دارهم إلى دار المهاجرين وأعلمهم أنهم إن
فعلوا ذلك أن لهم ما للمهاجرين وأن عليهم ما على المهاجرين فإن أبوا
واختاروا دارهم فأعلمهم أنهم يكونون كأعراب المسلمين يجرى عليهم حكم
الله الذي يجري على المؤمنين ولا يكون لهم في الفىء والغنيمة نصيب إلا
أن يجاهدوا مع المسلمين فإن هم أبوا فادعهم إلى إعطاء الجزية فإن
أجابوا فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم فإن أبوا فاستعن بالله تعالى وقاتلهم وإذا
حاصرت أهل حصن فأرادوك أن تنزلهم على حكم الله تعالى فلا تنزلهم فإنكم
لا تدرون ما يحكم الله فيهم ولكن أنزلوهم على حكمكم ثم اقضوا فيهم بعد
ما شئتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سفيان بن عيينة قال علقمة فذكرت هذا الحديث
لمقاتل بن حيان فقال حدثني مسلم - قال أبو داود هو ابن هيصم - عن
النعمان بن مقرن عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مثل حديث سليمان بن
بريدة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sulaiman bin Buraidah reported on the authority of
his father. When the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) appointed a Commander
over an Army or a detachment, he instructed him to fear Allaah
himself and consider the welfare of the Muslims who were with him.
He then said “When you meet the polytheists who are your enemy,
summon them tone of three things and accept whichever of them they
are willing to agree to, and refrain from them. Summon them to
Islam and if they agree, accept it from them and refrain from them.
Then summon them to leave their territory and transfer to the abode
of the Emigrants and tell them that if they do so, they will have
the same rights and responsibilities as the Emigrants, but if they
refuse and choose their own abode, tell them that they will be like
the desert Arabs who are Muslims subject to Allaah’s jurisdiction
which applies to the believers, but will have no spoil or booty
unless they strive with the Muslims. If they refuse demand jizyah
(poll tax) from them, if they agree accept it from them and refrain
from them. But if they refuse, seek Alaah’s help and fight with
them. When you invade the fortress and they (its people) offer to
capitulate and have the matter referred to Allaah’s jurisdiction,
do not grant this, for you do not know whether or not you will hit
on Allaah’s jurisdiction regarding them. But let them capitulate
and have the matter refereed to your jurisdiction and make a
decision about them later on as you wish.Sufyan (bin ‘Uyainah) said
thah ‘Alqamah said “I mentioned this tradition to Muqatil bin
Habban, He said “Muslim narrated it to me.” Abu Dawud said “He is
Ibn Haidam narrated from Al Nu’man in Muqqarin from the Prophet (ﷺ)
like the tradition of Sulaiman bin Buraidah.</english-text>
</hadith>
