<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22661</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2660</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20150, 11013, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا إبراهيم، - يعني ابن سعد -
أخبرنا ابن شهاب، أخبرني عمرو بن جارية الثقفي، - حليف بني زهرة - عن
أبي هريرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال بعث رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم عشرة عينا وأمر عليهم عاصم بن ثابت فنفروا لهم هذيل بقريب
من مائة رجل رام فلما أحس بهم عاصم لجئوا إلى قردد فقالوا لهم انزلوا
فأعطوا بأيديكم ولكم العهد والميثاق أن لا نقتل منكم أحدا فقال عاصم
أما أنا فلا أنزل في ذمة كافر ‏.‏ فرموهم بالنبل فقتلوا عاصما في سبعة
نفر ونزل إليهم ثلاثة نفر على العهد والميثاق منهم خبيب وزيد بن
الدثنة ورجل آخر فلما استمكنوا منهم أطلقوا أوتار قسيهم فربطوهم بها
فقال الرجل الثالث هذا أول الغدر والله لا أصحبكم إن لي بهؤلاء لأسوة
‏.‏ فجروه فأبى أن يصحبهم فقتلوه فلبث خبيب أسيرا حتى أجمعوا قتله
فاستعار موسى يستحد بها فلما خرجوا به ليقتلوه قال لهم خبيب دعوني
أركع ركعتين ثم قال والله لولا أن تحسبوا ما بي جزعا لزدت
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said “The Prophet (ﷺ) sent ten persons
(on an expedition) and appointed ‘Asim bin Thabit their commander.
About one hundred men of Hudhail who were archers came out to
(attack) them. When ‘Asim felt their presence, they took cover in a
hillock. They aid to them “Come down and surrender and we make a
covenant and pact with you that we shall not kill any of you”.
‘Asim said “I do not come to the protection of a disbeliever. Then
they shot them with arrows and killed ‘Asim in a company of seven
persons. The other three persons came down to their covenant and
pact. They were Khubaib, Zaid bin Al Lathnah and another man. When
they overpowered them, they untied their bow strings and tied them
with them”. The third person said “This is the first treachery. I
swear by Allaah, I shall not accompany you. In them (my companions)
is an example for me. They pulled him, but he refused to accompany
them, so they killed him. Khubaib remained their captive until they
agreed to kill him. He asked for a razor to shave his pubes. When
they brought him outside to kill him. Khubaib said to them “Let me
offer two rak’ahs of prayer”. He then said “I swear by Allaah, if
you did not think that I did this out of fear. I would have
increased (the number of rak’ahs).</english-text>
</hadith>
