<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22680</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2679</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30412, 30367, 30367, 20023, 11168, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عيسى بن حماد المصري، وقتيبة، قال قتيبة حدثنا
الليث بن سعد، عن سعيد بن أبي سعيد، أنه سمع أبا هريرة، يقول بعث رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خيلا قبل نجد فجاءت برجل من بني حنيفة يقال
له ثمامة بن أثال سيد أهل اليمامة فربطوه بسارية من سواري المسجد فخرج
إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ماذا عندك يا ثمامة ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال عندي يا محمد خير إن تقتل تقتل ذا دم وإن تنعم تنعم على شاكر
وإن كنت تريد المال فسل تعط منه ما شئت ‏.‏ فتركه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم حتى إذا كان الغد ثم قال له ‏"‏ ما عندك يا ثمامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فأعاد مثل هذا الكلام فتركه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى كان بعد
الغد فذكر مثل هذا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أطلقوا
ثمامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانطلق إلى نخل قريب من المسجد فاغتسل فيه ثم دخل
المسجد فقال أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وأشهد أن محمدا عبده ورسوله ‏.‏
وساق الحديث ‏.‏ قال عيسى أخبرنا الليث وقال ذا ذم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said “ The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) sent
some horsemen to Najd and they brought a man of the Banu Hanifah
called Thumamah bint Uthal who was the chief of the people of Al
Yamamah and bound him to one of the pillars of the mosque. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) came out to him and said “What are you
expecting, Thumamah?”. He replied “I expect good, Muhammad. If you
kill (me), you will kill one whose blood will be avenged, if you
show favor, you will show it to one who is grateful and if you want
property and ask you will be given as much of it as you wish. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) left him till the following day and asked him
”What are you expecting, Thumamah?” He repeated the same words (in
reply). The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)left him till the day after the
following one and he mentioned the same words. The Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) then said “Set Thumamah free.” He went off to some palm
trees near the mosque. He took a bath there and entered the mosque
and said “I testify that there is no god but Allaah and I testify
that Muhammd is His servant and His apostle. He then narrated the
rest of the tradition. The narrator ‘Isa said “Al Laith narrated to
us”. He said “a man of respect and reverence.”</english-text>
</hadith>
