<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22682</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2681</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، قال حدثنا حماد، عن ثابت، عن
أنس، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ندب أصحابه فانطلقوا إلى بدر
فإذا هم بروايا قريش فيها عبد أسود لبني الحجاج فأخذه أصحاب رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فجعلوا يسألونه أين أبو سفيان فيقول والله ما لي
بشىء من أمره علم ولكن هذه قريش قد جاءت فيهم أبو جهل وعتبة وشيبة
ابنا ربيعة وأمية بن خلف ‏.‏ فإذا قال لهم ذلك ضربوه فيقول دعوني
دعوني أخبركم ‏.‏ فإذا تركوه قال والله ما لي بأبي سفيان من علم ولكن
هذه قريش قد أقبلت فيهم أبو جهل وعتبة وشيبة ابنا ربيعة وأمية بن خلف
قد أقبلوا ‏.‏ والنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي وهو يسمع ذلك فلما
انصرف قال ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده إنكم لتضربونه إذا صدقكم وتدعونه إذا
كذبكم هذه قريش قد أقبلت لتمنع أبا سفيان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أنس قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا مصرع فلان غدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ووضع يده على
الأرض ‏"‏ وهذا مصرع فلان غدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ووضع يده على الأرض ‏"‏ وهذا
مصرع فلان غدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ووضع يده على الأرض فقال والذي نفسي بيده ما
جاوز أحد منهم عن موضع يد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأمر بهم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخذ بأرجلهم فسحبوا فألقوا في قليب بدر
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas said “The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) called on his
Companions and they proceeded towards Badr. Suddenly they found the
watering Camels of the Quraish, there was among them a black slave
of Banu Al Hajjaj. The Companions of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
seized him and began to ask “Where is Abu Sufyan?” He said “I swear
by Allaah, I do not know anything about him, but this is the
Quraish who have come here, among them are Abu Jahl, ‘Utbah,
Shaibah the two sons of Rabi’ah and Umayyah bin Khalaf. When he aid
this to them, they beat him and he began to say “Leave me, leave
me. I shall tell you. When they left him he said “I know nothing
about Abu Sufyan, but this is the Quraish who have come (here),
among them are Abu Jahl, ‘Utbah, Shaibah the two sons of Rab’iah
and Umayyah bin Khalaf who have come here. The Prophet (ﷺ) was
praying and hearing all that (dialogue). When he finished, he said
“By Him in Whose hand my soul is, you beat him when he speaks the
truth to you and you leave him when he tells a lie. This is the
Quraish who have come here to defend Abu Sufyan. Anas said, The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “This will be the place of falling of so
and so tomorrow and he placed his hand on the ground. This will be
the place of falling of so and so tomorrow and he put his hand on
the ground. And this will be the place of falling of so and so
tomorrow and he put his hand on the ground. He (Ansas) said “By Him
in Whose hand my soul is, no one fell beyond the place of the hand
of the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ), The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) ordered for
them, and they were caught by their feet and dragged and thrown in
a well at Badr.</english-text>
</hadith>
