<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22694</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2693</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20023, 11207, 11013, 10511, 20201, 2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن أبي مريم، حدثنا عمي، - يعني سعيد بن
الحكم - قال أخبرنا الليث بن سعد، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب، قال وذكر
عروة بن الزبير أن مروان، والمسور بن مخرمة، أخبراه أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال حين جاءه وفد هوازن مسلمين فسألوه أن يرد إليهم
أموالهم فقال لهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ معي من ترون وأحب
الحديث إلى أصدقه فاختاروا إما السبى وإما المال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا نختار
سبينا فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأثنى على الله ثم قال ‏"‏
أما بعد فإن إخوانكم هؤلاء جاءوا تائبين وإني قد رأيت أن أرد إليهم
سبيهم فمن أحب منكم أن يطيب ذلك فليفعل ومن أحب منكم أن يكون على حظه
حتى نعطيه إياه من أول ما يفيء الله علينا فليفعل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال الناس
قد طيبنا ذلك لهم يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال لهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إنا لا ندري من أذن منكم ممن لم يأذن فارجعوا حتى يرفع إلينا
عرفاؤكم أمركم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجع الناس فكلمهم عرفاؤهم فأخبروهم أنهم قد
طيبوا وأذنوا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Marwan and Al Miswar bin Makhramah told that when the
deputation of the Hawazin came to the Muslims and asked the Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) to return to them their property, the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) said to them “with me are those whom you see”. The speech
dearest to me is the one which is true, so choose (one of the two)
either the captives or the property. They said “We choose our
captives. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) stood up, extolled Allaah and
then said “To proceed, your brethren have come repentant I have
considered that I should return their captives to them, so let
those of you who are willing to release the captives act
accordingly, but those who wish to hold on to what they have till
we give them some of the first booty Allaah gives us may do so. The
people said “We are willing for that (to release their captives),
Apostle of Allaah. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “We cannot
distinguish between those of you who have granted that and those
who have not , so return till your headmen may tell us about your
affair. The people then returned and their headmen spoke to them,
then they informed that they were agreeable and had given their
permission.</english-text>
</hadith>
