<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22720</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2719</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 20733, 10921, 10942, 3051</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن محمد بن حنبل، قال حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم،
قال حدثني صفوان بن عمرو، عن عبد الرحمن بن جبير بن نفير، عن أبيه، عن
عوف بن مالك الأشجعي، قال خرجت مع زيد بن حارثة في غزوة مؤتة فرافقني
مددي من أهل اليمن ليس معه غير سيفه فنحر رجل من المسلمين جزورا فسأله
المددي طائفة من جلده فأعطاه إياه فاتخذه كهيئة الدرق ومضينا فلقينا
جموع الروم وفيهم رجل على فرس له أشقر عليه سرج مذهب وسلاح مذهب فجعل
الرومي يغري بالمسلمين فقعد له المددي خلف صخرة فمر به الرومي فعرقب
فرسه فخر وعلاه فقتله وحاز فرسه وسلاحه فلما فتح الله عز وجل للمسلمين
بعث إليه خالد بن الوليد فأخذ من السلب قال عوف فأتيته فقلت يا خالد
أما علمت أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قضى بالسلب للقاتل قال بلى
ولكني استكثرته ‏.‏ قلت لتردنه عليه أو لأعرفنكها عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأبى أن يرد عليه قال عوف فاجتمعنا عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقصصت عليه قصة المددي وما فعل خالد فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا خالد ما حملك على ما صنعت ‏"‏ قال يا رسول
الله استكثرته ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا خالد رد
عليه ما أخذت منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عوف فقلت له دونك يا خالد ألم أف لك
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وما ذلك ‏"‏ فأخبرته قال فغضب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ يا خالد لا ترد عليه هل أنتم
تاركون لي أمرائي لكم صفوة أمرهم وعليهم كدره ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Awf bin malik Al Ashja’I said “I went out with Zaid
bin Harith in the battle of Mutah. For the reinforcement of the
Muslim army a man from the people of Yemen accompanied me. He had
only his sword with him. A man from the Muslims slaughtered a
Camel. The man for the reinforcement asked him for a part of its
skin which he gave him. He made it like the shape of a shield. We
went on and met the Byzantine armies. There was a man among them on
a reddish horse with a golden saddle and golden weapons. This
Byzantinian soldiers began to attack the Muslims desperately. The
man for reinforcement sat behind a rock for (attacking) him. He
hamstrung his horse and overpowered him and then killed him. He
took his horse and weapons. When Allah, Most High, bestowed victory
on the Muslims. Khalid bin Al Walid sent for him and took his
spoils. ‘Awf said “I came to him and said “Khalid, do you know that
the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) had decided to give spoils to the killer?
He said “Yes, I thought it abundant. I said “You should return it
to him, or I shall tell you about it before the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ). But he refused to return it. ‘Awf said “We then
assembled with the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ). I told him the story of
the man of reinforcement and what Khalid had done. The Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) said “Khalid, what made you do the work you have done?”
He said “Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ), I considered it to be abundant. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “Khalid, return it to him what you have
taken from him.” ‘Awf said “I said to him “here you are, Khalid.
Did I not keep my word? The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “What is
that? I then informed him.” He said “The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)
became angry and said “Khalid, do not return it to him. Are you
going to leave my commanders? You may take from them what is best
for you and eave to them what is worst.</english-text>
</hadith>
