<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22718</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2717</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11062, 10601, 11224, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، عن مالك، عن يحيى بن
سعيد، عن عمر بن كثير بن أفلح، عن أبي محمد، مولى أبي قتادة عن أبي
قتادة، قال خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في عام حنين فلما
التقينا كانت للمسلمين جولة - قال - فرأيت رجلا من المشركين قد علا
رجلا من المسلمين - قال - فاستدرت له حتى أتيته من ورائه فضربته
بالسيف على حبل عاتقه فأقبل على فضمني ضمة وجدت منها ريح الموت ثم
أدركه الموت فأرسلني فلحقت عمر بن الخطاب فقلت ما بال الناس قال أمر
الله ‏.‏ ثم إن الناس رجعوا وجلس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقال
‏"‏ من قتل قتيلا له عليه بينة فله سلبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقمت ثم قلت من
يشهد لي ثم جلست ثم قال ذلك الثانية ‏"‏ من قتل قتيلا له عليه بينة
فله سلبه ‏"‏ قال فقمت ثم قلت من يشهد لي ثم جلست ثم قال ذلك الثالثة
فقمت فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما لك يا أبا قتادة ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فاقتصصت عليه القصة فقال رجل من القوم صدق يا رسول الله وسلب
ذلك القتيل عندي فأرضه منه فقال أبو بكر الصديق لاها الله إذا يعمد
إلى أسد من أسد الله يقاتل عن الله وعن رسوله فيعطيك سلبه فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ صدق فأعطه إياه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أبو قتادة
فأعطانيه فبعت الدرع فابتعت به مخرفا في بني سلمة فإنه لأول مال
تأثلته في الإسلام ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Qatadah said “We went out with the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ) in the year of Hunain. And when the armies met, the
Muslims suffered a reverse. I saw one of the polytheists prevailing
over a Muslim, so I went round him till I came to him from behind
and struck him with my sword at the vein between his neck and
shoulder. He came towards me and closed with me, so that I felt
death was near, but he was overtaken by death and let me go. I then
caught upon on “Umar bin Al Khattab and said to him “What is the
matter with the people?” He said “It is what Allaah has commanded.
Then the people returned and the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ)sat down and
said “If anyone kills a man and can prove it, he will get his
spoil. I stood up and said “Who will testify for me? I then sat
down.” He said again “If anyone kills a man and can prove it, he
will get his spoil. I stood up and said “Who will testify for me? I
then sat down.” He then said the same for the third time. I then
stood up. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “What is the matter with
you, Abu Qatadah? I told him the story. A man from the people said
“He has spoken the truth, and I have this spoil with me, so make
him agreeable (to take something in exchange). Abu Bakr said “In
that case I swear by Allaah that he must not do so. One of the
Allaah’s heroes does not fight for Allaah and his Apostle and then
give you his spoil. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “He has spoken
the truth, hand it over to him. Abu Qatadah said “he handed it over
to me, I sold the coat of mail and brought a garden among Banu
Salamh. This was the first property I acquired in the Islamic
period.</english-text>
</hadith>
