<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22712</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2711</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11155, 11165, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ثور بن زيد الديلي، عن أبي
الغيث، مولى ابن مطيع عن أبي هريرة، أنه قال خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم عام خيبر فلم يغنم ذهبا ولا ورقا إلا الثياب والمتاع
والأموال - قال - فوجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نحو وادي القرى
وقد أهدي لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عبد أسود يقال له مدعم حتى
إذا كانوا بوادي القرى فبينا مدعم يحط رحل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إذ جاءه سهم فقتله فقال الناس هنيئا له الجنة ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كلا والذي نفسي بيده إن الشملة التي أخذها يوم
خيبر من المغانم لم تصبها المقاسم لتشتعل عليه نارا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما
سمعوا ذلك جاء رجل بشراك أو شراكين إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ شراك من نار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال
‏"‏ شراكان من نار ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah said “We went out along with the Apostle
of Allaah(ﷺ) in the year of Khaibar. We did not get gold or silver
in the booty of war except clothes, equipment and property. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) sent (a detachment) towards Wadi Al Qura. The
Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) was presented a black slave called Mid’am. And
while they were in Wadi Al Qura and Mid’am was unsaddling a Camel
belonging to the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) he was struck by a random
arrow which killed him. The people said “Congratulations to him, he
will go to paradise. But the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “Not at all.
By Him in Whose hand my soul is the cloak he took on the day of
Khaibar from the spoils which was not among the shares divided will
blaze with fire upon him. When they (the people) heard that, a man
brought a sandal strap or two sandal straps to the Apostle of
Allaah(ﷺ). The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “A sandal strap of fire or
two sandal straps of fire.”</english-text>
</hadith>
