<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22776</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2775</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jihad (Kitab Al-Jihad) - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20172, 20706, 10554, 9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا ابن أبي فديك، حدثني موسى بن
يعقوب، عن ابن عثمانقال أبو داود وهو يحيى بن الحسن بن عثمان عن
الأشعث بن إسحاق بن سعد، عن عامر بن سعد، عن أبيه، قال خرجنا مع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من مكة نريد المدينة فلما كنا قريبا من عزورا
نزل ثم رفع يديه فدعا الله ساعة ثم خر ساجدا فمكث طويلا ثم قام فرفع
يديه فدعا الله ساعة ثم خر ساجدا فمكث طويلا ثم قام فرفع يديه ساعة ثم
خر ساجدا ذكره أحمد ثلاثا قال ‏"‏ إني سألت ربي وشفعت لأمتي فأعطاني
ثلث أمتي فخررت ساجدا شكرا لربي ثم رفعت رأسي فسألت ربي لأمتي فأعطاني
ثلث أمتي فخررت ساجدا لربي شكرا ثم رفعت رأسي فسألت ربي لأمتي فأعطاني
الثلث الآخر فخررت ساجدا لربي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود أشعث بن إسحاق
أسقطه أحمد بن صالح حين حدثنا به فحدثني به عنه موسى بن سهل الرملي
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa'd ibn AbuWaqqas: We went out with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) from Mecca making for Medina. When we were
near Azwara', he alighted, then raised his hands, and made
supplication to Allah for a time, after which he prostrated
himself, remaining a long time in prostration. Then he stood up and
raised his hands for a time, after which he prostrated himself,
remaining a long time in prostration. He then stood up and raised
his hands for a time, after which he prostrated himself. Ahmad
mentioned it three times. He then said: I begged my Lord and made
intercession for my people, and He gave me a third of my people, so
I prostrated myself in gratitude to my Lord. Then I raised my head
and begged my Lord for my people, and He gave me a third of my
people, so I prostrated myself in gratitude to my Lord. Then I
raised my head and begged my Lord for my people and He gave me the
remaining third, so I prostrated myself in gratitude to my Lord.Abu
Dawud said: When Ahmad b. Salih narrated this tradition to us, he
omitted the name of Ash'ath b. Ishaq, but Musa b. Sahl al-Ramli
narrated it to us through him.</english-text>
</hadith>
