<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22822</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2821</hadith-number>
<chapter>Sacrifice (Kitab Al-Dahaya) - كتاب الضحايا</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20327, 20016, 11179, 11506, 1986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا أبو الأحوص، حدثنا سعيد بن مسروق، عن
عباية بن رفاعة، عن أبيه، عن جده، رافع بن خديج قال أتيت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا رسول الله إنا نلقى العدو غدا وليس معنا
مدى أفنذبح بالمروة وشقة العصا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
أرن أو أعجل ما أنهر الدم وذكر اسم الله عليه فكلوا ما لم يكن سنا أو
ظفرا وسأحدثكم عن ذلك أما السن فعظم وأما الظفر فمدى الحبشة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وتقدم به سرعان من الناس فتعجلوا فأصابوا من الغنائم ورسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم في آخر الناس فنصبوا قدورا فمر رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بالقدور فأمر بها فأكفئت وقسم بينهم فعدل بعيرا بعشر شياه
وند بعير من إبل القوم ولم يكن معهم خيل فرماه رجل بسهم فحبسه الله
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن لهذه البهائم أوابد كأوابد
الوحش فما فعل منها هذا فافعلوا به مثل هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Rafi' b. Khadij: I came to the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) and said: Messenger of Allah, we shall meet the enemy
tomorrow and we have no knives with us. May we kill with a
sharp-edged white stone (flint) and with splinter of a staff ? The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Hasten in slaughtering it. When
Allah's name is mentioned you may eat what is killed by anything
which causes the blood to flow except tooth and claw. I shall tell
you about it. The tooth is a bone, and the claw is the knife of
Abyssinians. Some people hastened and went forward, they made haste
and got booty, while the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was in the rear and
they setup cooking pots. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) passed by over
the cooking pots. He ordered to turn them over. He then divided
(the spoils of war) between them, and gave them a camel for ten
goats in equation. One of the camels of the people ran away, and
they had no horses with them at that time. A man shot an arrow at
it, and Allah prevented it from escaping. The Prophet (ﷺ) said:
Among animals (i.e. camels) there are some which bolt like wild
animals ; so when any of them does so, do with it like
this.</english-text>
</hadith>
