<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22865</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>18</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2864</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wills (Kitab Al-Wasaya) - كتاب الوصايا</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 20012, 11013, 10554, 9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، وابن أبي خلف، قالا حدثنا
سفيان، عن الزهري، عن عامر بن سعد، عن أبيه، قال مرض مرضا - قال ابن
أبي خلف - بمكة - ثم اتفقا - أشفى فيه فعاده رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال يا رسول الله إن لي مالا كثيرا وليس يرثني إلا ابنتي
أفأتصدق بالثلثين قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالشطر قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال فبالثلث قال ‏"‏ الثلث والثلث كثير إنك أن تترك ورثتك أغنياء خير
من أن تدعهم عالة يتكففون الناس وإنك لن تنفق نفقة إلا أجرت بها حتى
اللقمة ترفعها إلى في امرأتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله أتخلف عن هجرتي
قال ‏"‏ إنك إن تخلف بعدي فتعمل عملا صالحا تريد به وجه الله لا تزداد
به إلا رفعة ودرجة لعلك أن تخلف حتى ينتفع بك أقوام ويضر بك آخرون ‏"‏
‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ اللهم أمض لأصحابي هجرتهم ولا تردهم على أعقابهم لكن
البائس سعد ابن خولة يرثي له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن مات
بمكة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Amir b. Sa'd: On the authority of his
father (Sa'd b. Abi Waqqas): When he (Sa'd) fell ill at Mecca
(according to the version of Ibn Abi Kkalaf) - then the agreed
version has: which brought him near to death - the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) went to visit him. He said: Messenger of Allah, I have a
large amount of property, and my daughter is my only heir. May I
give two-thirds (of my property) as a sadaqah (charity)? He said:
No. He asked: Then a half ? He replied: No. He asked: Then
one-third ? He replied: (You may will away) a third and third is a
lot. To leave your heirs rich is better than to leave them poor
begging from people. You will not spend anything, seeking thereby
to please Allah, without being rewarded for it, even the mouthful
you give your wife. I said: Messenger of Allah, shall I be left
behind form immigration (to Medina)? He said: If you remain behind
after me and do good works seeking the pleasure of Allah, your rank
will be raised and degree increased. Perhaps you will not remain
behind, and some people will benefit from you and others will be
harmed by you. He then said: O Allah, complete the immigration of
my Companions and do not turn them back. But miserable was Sa'd b.
Khawlah. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) lamented on him as he died at
Mecca.</english-text>
</hadith>
