<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22895</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2894</hadith-number>
<chapter>Shares of Inheritance (Kitab Al-Fara'id) - كتاب
الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 19815</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن عثمان بن إسحاق
بن خرشة، عن قبيصة بن ذؤيب، أنه قال جاءت الجدة إلى أبي بكر الصديق
تسأله ميراثها فقال ما لك في كتاب الله تعالى شىء وما علمت لك في سنة
نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شيئا فارجعي حتى أسأل الناس ‏.‏ فسأل
الناس فقال المغيرة بن شعبة حضرت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أعطاها
السدس ‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر هل معك غيرك فقام محمد بن مسلمة فقال مثل ما
قال المغيرة بن شعبة فأنفذه لها أبو بكر ثم جاءت الجدة الأخرى إلى عمر
بن الخطاب رضى الله عنه تسأله ميراثها فقال ما لك في كتاب الله تعالى
شىء وما كان القضاء الذي قضي به إلا لغيرك وما أنا بزائد في الفرائض
ولكن هو ذلك السدس فإن اجتمعتما فيه فهو بينكما وأيتكما خلت به فهو
لها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Qabisah ibn Dhuwayb: A grandmother came to
AbuBakr asking him for her share of inheritance. He said: There is
nothing prescribed for you in Allah's Book, nor do I know anything
for you in the Sunnah of the Prophet of Allah (ﷺ) Go home till I
question the people. He then questioned the people, and al-Mughirah
ibn Shu'bah said: I had been present with the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) when he gave grandmother a sixth. AbuBakr said: Is there anyone
with you? Muhammad ibn Maslamah stood and said the same as
al-Mughirah ibn Shu'bah had said. So AbuBakr made it apply to her.
Another grandmother came to Umar ibn al-Khattab asking him for her
share of inheritance. He said: Nothing has been prescribed for you
in Allah's Book. The decision made before you was made for a
grandmother other than you. I am not going to add in the shares of
inheritance; but it is that sixth. If there are two of you, it is
shared between you, but whichever of you is the only one left gets
it all.</english-text>
</hadith>
