<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22918</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2917</hadith-number>
<chapter>Shares of Inheritance (Kitab Al-Fara'id) - كتاب
الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>30350, 20258, 11278, 19934, 19911</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عمرو بن أبي الحجاج أبو معمر، حدثنا
عبد الوارث، عن حسين المعلم، عن عمرو بن شعيب، عن أبيه، عن جده، أن
رئاب بن حذيفة، تزوج امرأة فولدت له ثلاثة غلمة فماتت أمهم فورثوها
رباعها وولاء مواليها وكان عمرو بن العاص عصبة بنيها فأخرجهم إلى
الشام فماتوا فقدم عمرو بن العاص ومات مولى لها وترك مالا له فخاصمه
إخوتها إلى عمر بن الخطاب فقال عمر قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ ما أحرز الولد أو الوالد فهو لعصبته من كان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فكتب له
كتابا فيه شهادة عبد الرحمن بن عوف وزيد بن ثابت ورجل آخر فلما استخلف
عبد الملك اختصموا إلى هشام بن إسماعيل أو إلى إسماعيل بن هشام فرفعهم
إلى عبد الملك فقال هذا من القضاء الذي ما كنت أراه ‏.‏ قال فقضى لنا
بكتاب عمر بن الخطاب فنحن فيه إلى الساعة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Amr b. Suh'aib: On his father's authority,
said that his grandfather reported: Rabab ibn Hudhayfah married a
woman and three sons were born to him from her. Their mother then
died. They inherited her houses and had the right of inheritance of
her freed slaves. Amr ibn al-'As was the agnate of her sons. He
sent them to Syria where they died. Amr ibn al-'As then came. A
freed slave of hers died and left some property. Her brothers
disputed with him and brought the case to Umar ibn al-Khattab. Umar
reported the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) as saying: Whatever property a
son or a father receives as an heir will go to his agnates, whoever
they may be. He then wrote a document for him, witnessed by
AbdurRahman ibn Awf, Zayd ibn Thabit and one other person. When
AbdulMalik became caliph, they presented the case to Hisham ibn
Isma'il or Isma'il ibn Hisham (the narrator is doubtful). He sent
them to 'Abd al-Malik who said: This is the decision which I have
already seen. The narrator said: So he ('Abd al-Malik) made the
decision on the basis of the document of Umar ibn al-Khattab, and
that is still with us till this moment.</english-text>
</hadith>
