<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22979</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2978</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>30024, 20033, 20025, 20475, 11013, 11002,
871</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن عمر بن ميسرة، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن
مهدي، عن عبد الله بن المبارك، عن يونس بن يزيد، عن الزهري، أخبرني
سعيد بن المسيب، أخبرني جبير بن مطعم، أنه جاء هو وعثمان بن عفان
يكلمان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيما قسم من الخمس بين بني هاشم
وبني المطلب فقلت يا رسول الله قسمت لإخواننا بني المطلب ولم تعطنا
شيئا وقرابتنا وقرابتهم منك واحدة ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إنما بنو هاشم وبنو المطلب شىء واحد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال جبير ولم يقسم
لبني عبد شمس ولا لبني نوفل من ذلك الخمس كما قسم لبني هاشم وبني
المطلب ‏.‏ قال وكان أبو بكر يقسم الخمس نحو قسم رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم غير أنه لم يكن يعطي قربى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما
كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطيهم ‏.‏ قال وكان عمر بن الخطاب
يعطيهم منه وعثمان بعده ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jubair b. Mut'im: That he and 'Uthman b.
'Affan went to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) talking to him about the
fifth which he divided among the Banu Hisham and Abu 'Abd
al-Muttalib. I said: Messenger of Allah, you have divided (the
fifth) among our brethren Banu 'Abd al-Muttalib, but you have not
given us anything, though our relationship to you is the same as
theirs. The Prophet (ﷺ) said: The Banu Hisham and the Banu 'Abd
al-Muttalib are one. Jubair said: He did not divide the fifth among
the Banu 'Abd Shams and the Banu Nawfal as he divided among the
Banu Hashim and the Banu 'Abd al-Muttalib. He said: Abu Bakr used
to divide the fifth like the division of Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
except that he did not give the relatives of the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ), as he gave them. 'Umar b. al-Khattab and 'Uthman after him
used to give them (a portion) from it.</english-text>
</hadith>
