<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22973</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2972</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>20028, 166</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن الجراح، حدثنا جرير، عن المغيرة، قال
جمع عمر بن عبد العزيز بني مروان حين استخلف فقال إن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم كانت له فدك فكان ينفق منها ويعود منها على صغير بني
هاشم ويزوج منها أيمهم وإن فاطمة سألته أن يجعلها لها فأبى فكانت كذلك
في حياة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى مضى لسبيله فلما أن ولي أبو
بكر رضى الله عنه عمل فيها بما عمل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في حياته
حتى مضى لسبيله فلما أن ولي عمر عمل فيها بمثل ما عملا حتى مضى لسبيله
ثم أقطعها مروان ثم صارت لعمر بن عبد العزيز قال - يعني عمر بن عبد
العزيز - فرأيت أمرا منعه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فاطمة عليها
السلام ليس لي بحق وأنا أشهدكم أني قد رددتها على ما كانت يعني على
عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو داود ولي عمر بن عبد
العزيز الخلافة وغلته أربعون ألف دينار وتوفي وغلته أربعمائة دينار
ولو بقي لكان أقل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Umar ibn AbdulAziz: Al-Mughirah (ibn
Shu'bah) said: Umar ibn AbdulAziz gathered the family of Marwan
when he was made caliph, and he said: Fadak belonged to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), and he made contributions from it, showing
repeated kindness to the poor of the Banu Hashim from it, and
supplying from it the cost of marriage for those who were
unmarried. Fatimah asked him to give it to her, but he refused.
That is how matters stood during the lifetime of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) till he passed on (i.e. died). When AbuBakr was made
ruler he administered it as the Prophet (ﷺ) had done in his
lifetime till he passed on. Then when Umar ibn al-Khattab was made
ruler he administered it as they had done till he passed on. Then
it was given to Marwan as a fief, and it afterwards came to Umar
ibn AbdulAziz. Umar ibn AbdulAziz said: I consider I have no right
to something which the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) refused to Fatimah,
and I call you to witness that I have restored it to its former
condition; meaning in the time of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).Abu
Dawud said: When 'Umar b. 'Abd al-'Aziz was made caliph its revenue
was forty thousand dinars, and when he died its revenue was four
hundred dinars. Had he remained alive, it would have been less than
it.</english-text>
</hadith>
