<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22986</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2985</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 11716, 20475, 11013</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا عنبسة، حدثنا يونس، عن ابن
شهاب، أخبرني عبد الله بن الحارث بن نوفل الهاشمي، أن عبد المطلب بن
ربيعة بن الحارث بن عبد المطلب، أخبره أن أباه ربيعة بن الحارث وعباس
بن عبد المطلب قالا لعبد المطلب بن ربيعة وللفضل بن عباس ائتيا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقولا له يا رسول الله قد بلغنا من السن ما
ترى وأحببنا أن نتزوج وأنت يا رسول الله أبر الناس وأوصلهم وليس عند
أبوينا ما يصدقان عنا فاستعملنا يا رسول الله على الصدقات فلنؤد إليك
ما يؤدي العمال ولنصب ما كان فيها من مرفق ‏.‏ قال فأتى إلينا علي بن
أبي طالب ونحن على تلك الحال فقال لنا إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ‏"‏ لا والله لا نستعمل منكم أحدا على الصدقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
له ربيعة هذا من أمرك قد نلت صهر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلم
نحسدك عليه ‏.‏ فألقى علي رداءه ثم اضطجع عليه فقال أنا أبو حسن القرم
والله لا أريم حتى يرجع إليكما ابناكما بجواب ما بعثتما به إلى النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال عبد المطلب فانطلقت أنا والفضل إلى باب
حجرة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى نوافق صلاة الظهر قد قامت فصلينا
مع الناس ثم أسرعت أنا والفضل إلى باب حجرة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وهو يومئذ عند زينب بنت جحش فقمنا بالباب حتى أتى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأخذ بأذني وأذن الفضل ثم قال أخرجا ما تصرران ثم دخل فأذن
لي وللفضل فدخلنا فتواكلنا الكلام قليلا ثم كلمته أو كلمه الفضل - قد
شك في ذلك عبد الله - قال كلمه بالأمر الذي أمرنا به أبوانا فسكت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ساعة ورفع بصره قبل سقف البيت حتى طال علينا
أنه لا يرجع إلينا شيئا حتى رأينا زينب تلمع من وراء الحجاب بيدها
تريد أن لا تعجلا وإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في أمرنا ثم خفض
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رأسه فقال لنا ‏"‏ إن هذه الصدقة إنما
هي أوساخ الناس وإنها لا تحل لمحمد ولا لآل محمد ادعوا لي نوفل بن
الحارث ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فدعي له نوفل بن الحارث فقال ‏"‏ يا نوفل أنكح عبد
المطلب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأنكحني نوفل ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
ادعوا لي محمية بن جزء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وهو رجل من بني زبيد كان رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم استعمله على الأخماس فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم لمحمية ‏"‏ أنكح الفضل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأنكحه ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قم فأصدق عنهما من الخمس كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ لم يسمه لي
عبد الله بن الحارث ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbdulMuttalib ibn Rabi'ah ibn al-Harith:
AbdulMuttalib ibn Rabi'ah ibn al-Harith said that his father,
Rabi'ah ibn al-Harith, and Abbas ibn al-Muttalib said to
AbdulMuttalib ibn Rabi'ah and al-Fadl ibn Abbas: Go to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and tell him: Messenger of Allah, we are now
of age as you see, and we wish to marry. Messenger of Allah, you
are the kindest of the people and the most skilled in matchmaking.
Our fathers have nothing with which to pay our dower. So appoint us
collector of sadaqah (zakat), Messenger of Allah, and we shall give
you what the other collectors give you, and we shall have the
benefit accruing from it. Ali came to us while we were in this
condition. He said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: No, I swear by
Allah, he will not appoint any of you collector of sadaqah (zakat).
Rabi'ah said to him: This is your condition; you have gained your
relationship with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) by marriage, but we
did not grudge you that. Ali then put his cloak on the earth and
lay on it. He then said: I am the father of Hasan, the chief. I
swear by Allah, I shall not leave this place until your sons come
with a reply (to the question) for which you have sent them to the
Prophet (ﷺ). AbdulMuttalib said: So I and al-Fadl went towards the
door of the apartment of the Prophet (ﷺ). We found that the noon
prayer in congregation had already started. So we prayed along with
the people. I and al-Fadl then hastened towards the door of the
apartment of the Prophet (ﷺ). He was (staying) with Zaynab,
daughter of Jahsh, that day. We stood until the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) came. He caught my ear and the ear of al-Fadl. He then said:
Reveal what you conceal in your hearts. He then entered and
permitted me and al-Fadl (to enter). So we entered and for a little
while we asked each other to talk. I then talked to him, or al-Fadl
talked to him (the narrator, Abdullah was not sure). He said: He
spoke to him concerning the matter about which our fathers ordered
us to ask him. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) remained silent for a
moment and raised his eyes towards the ceiling of the room. He took
so long that we thought he would not give any reply to us.
Meanwhile we saw that Zaynab was signalling to us with her hand
from behind the veil, asking us not to be in a hurry, and that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was (thinking) about our matter. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then lowered his head and said to us: This
sadaqah (zakat) is a dirt of the people. It is legal neither for
Muhammad nor for the family of Muhammad. Call Nawfal ibn al-Harith
to me. So Nawfal ibn al-Harith was called to him. He said: Nawfal,
marry AbdulMuttalib (to your daughter). So Nawfal married me (to
his daughter). The Prophet (ﷺ) then said: Call Mahmiyyah ibn Jaz'i
to me. He was a man of Banu Zubayd, whom the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
had appointed collector of the fifths. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said to Mahmiyyah: Marry al-Fadl (to your daughter). So he married
him to her. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Stand up and pay the
dower from the fifth so-and-so on their behalf. Abdullah ibn
al-Harith did not name it (i.e. the amount of the
dower).</english-text>
</hadith>
