<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>22985</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2984</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 30212, 15581, 11196, 63</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا ابن نمير، حدثنا هاشم بن
البريد، حدثنا حسين بن ميمون، عن عبد الله بن عبد الله، عن عبد الرحمن
بن أبي ليلى، قال سمعت عليا، عليه السلام يقول اجتمعت أنا والعباس،
وفاطمة، وزيد بن حارثة، عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا رسول
الله إن رأيت أن توليني حقنا من هذا الخمس في كتاب الله فأقسمه حياتك
كى لا ينازعني أحد بعدك فافعل ‏.‏ قال ففعل ذلك - قال - فقسمته حياة
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم ولانيه أبو بكر رضى الله عنه حتى إذا
كانت آخر سنة من سني عمر رضى الله عنه فإنه أتاه مال كثير فعزل حقنا
ثم أرسل إلى فقلت بنا عنه العام غنى وبالمسلمين إليه حاجة فاردده
عليهم فرده عليهم ثم لم يدعني إليه أحد بعد عمر فلقيت العباس بعد ما
خرجت من عند عمر فقال يا علي حرمتنا الغداة شيئا لا يرد علينا أبدا
وكان رجلا داهيا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ali ibn AbuTalib: I, al-Abbas, Fatimah and
Zayd ibn Harithah gathered with the Prophet (ﷺ) and I said:
Messenger of Allah, if you think to assign us our right (portion)
in this fifth ( of the booty) as mentioned in the Book of Allah,
and this I may divide during your lifetime so that no one may
dispute me after you, then do it. He said: He did that. He said: I
divided it during the lifetime of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).
AbuBakr then assigned it to me. During the last days of the
caliphate of Umar a good deal of property came to him and took out
our portion. I said to him: We are well to do this year; but the
Muslims are needy, so return it to them. He, therefore, returned it
to them. No one called me after Umar. I met al-Abbas when I came
out from Umar. He said: Ali, today you have deprived us of a thing
that will never be returned to us. He was indeed a man of
wisdom.</english-text>
</hadith>
