<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23007</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3006</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>38673, 20021, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هارون بن زيد بن أبي الزرقاء، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
حماد بن سلمة، عن عبيد الله بن عمر، قال - أحسبه - عن نافع، عن ابن
عمر، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قاتل أهل خيبر فغلب على النخل
والأرض وألجأهم إلى قصرهم فصالحوه على أن لرسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم الصفراء والبيضاء والحلقة ولهم ما حملت ركابهم على أن لا يكتموا
ولا يغيبوا شيئا فإن فعلوا فلا ذمة لهم ولا عهد فغيبوا مسكا لحيى بن
أخطب وقد كان قتل قبل خيبر كان احتمله معه يوم بني النضير حين أجليت
النضير فيه حليهم قال فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لسعية ‏"‏ أين
مسك حيى بن أخطب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أذهبته الحروب والنفقات ‏.‏ فوجدوا المسك
فقتل ابن أبي الحقيق وسبى نساءهم وذراريهم وأراد أن يجليهم فقالوا يا
محمد دعنا نعمل في هذه الأرض ولنا الشطر ما بدا لك ولكم الشطر ‏.‏
وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطي كل امرأة من نسائه ثمانين
وسقا من تمر وعشرين وسقا من شعير ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah Ibn Umar: The Prophet fought with
the people of Khaybar, and captured their palm-trees and land, and
forced them to remain confined to their fortresses. So they
concluded a treaty of peace providing that gold, silver and weapons
would go to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), and whatever they took away
on their camels would belong to them, on condition that they would
not hide and carry away anything. If they did (so), there would be
no protection for them and no treaty (with Muslims). They carried
away a purse of Huyayy ibn Akhtab who was killed before (the battle
of) Khaybar. He took away the ornaments of Banu an-Nadir when they
were expelled. The Prophet (ﷺ) asked Sa'yah: Where is the purse of
Huyayy ibn Akhtab? He replied: The contents of this purse were
spent on battles and other expenses. (Later on) they found the
purse. So he killed Ibn AbulHuqayq, captured their women and
children, and intended to deport them. They said: Muhammad, leave
us to work on this land; we shall have half (of the produce) as you
wish, and you will have half. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used to
make a contribution of eighty wasqs of dates and twenty wasqs of
wheat to each of his wives.</english-text>
</hadith>
