<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23009</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3008</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>30584, 20029, 20500, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن داود المهري، أخبرني ابن وهب، أخبرني
أسامة بن زيد الليثي، عن نافع، عن عبد الله بن عمر، قال لما افتتحت
خيبر سألت يهود رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يقرهم على أن يعملوا
على النصف مما خرج منها فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أقركم
فيها على ذلك ما شئنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكانوا على ذلك وكان التمر يقسم على
السهمان من نصف خيبر ويأخذ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الخمس وكان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أطعم كل امرأة من أزواجه من الخمس مائة
وسق تمرا وعشرين وسقا شعيرا فلما أراد عمر إخراج اليهود أرسل إلى
أزواج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال لهن من أحب منكن أن أقسم لها
نخلا بخرصها مائة وسق فيكون لها أصلها وأرضها وماؤها ومن الزرع مزرعة
خرص عشرين وسقا فعلنا ومن أحب أن نعزل الذي لها في الخمس كما هو فعلنا
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abd Allah bin ‘Umar reported that ‘Umar said “When
Khaibar was conquered, the Jews asked the Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) to
confirm that they would do all the cultivation and have half the
produce. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) said “I shall confirm you on that
condition as long as we wish. So they were confirmed on that
(condition). The dates from half the produce of Khaibar were
divided into a number of portions. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) would
take the fifth. The Apostle of Allaah(ﷺ) used to contribute from
the fifth one hundred wasqs of dates and twenty wasqs of wheat to
each of his wives. When ‘Umar intended to expel the Jews from
Khaibar he sent a message to the wives of the Prophet (ﷺ) and said
to them “If any of you wishes that I divide the palm trees for her
by their assessment that amounts one hundred wasqs (of dates) and
to her belongs their root, their land and their water and
(likewise) twenty wasqs from the produce of the cultivated land by
assessment, I shall (do that). And if any of you wishes that we
take out her portion from the fifth, we shall do
(that).</english-text>
</hadith>
