<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23029</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3028</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>32026, 30524</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن أحمد القرشي، وهارون بن عبد الله، أن عبد
الله بن الزبير، حدثهم حدثنا فرج بن سعيد، حدثني عمي، ثابت بن سعيد عن
أبيه، سعيد - يعني ابن أبيض - عن جده، أبيض بن حمال أنه كلم رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في الصدقة حين وفد عليه فقال ‏"‏ يا أخا سبإ لا بد
من صدقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال إنما زرعنا القطن يا رسول الله وقد تبددت سبأ
ولم يبق منهم إلا قليل بمأرب ‏.‏ فصالح نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
على سبعين حلة بز من قيمة وفاء بز المعافر كل سنة عمن بقي من سبإ
بمأرب فلم يزالوا يؤدونها حتى قبض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وإن
العمال انتقضوا عليهم بعد قبض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيما صالح
أبيض بن حمال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في الحلل السبعين فرد ذلك
أبو بكر على ما وضعه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى مات أبو بكر
فلما مات أبو بكر رضى الله عنه انتقض ذلك وصارت على الصدقة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abyad ibn Hammal: Abyad spoke to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) about sadaqah when he came along with a
deputation to him. He replied: O brother of Saba', sadaqah is
unavoidable. He said: We cultivated cotton, Messenger of Allah. The
people of Saba' scattered, and there remained only a few at
Ma'arib. He therefore concluded a treaty of peace with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) to give seventy suits of cloth, equivalent
to the price of the Yemeni garments known as al-mu'afir, to be paid
every year on behalf of those people of Saba' who remained at
Ma'arib. They continued to pay them till the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
died. The governors after the death of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
broke the treaty concluded by Abyad by Hammal with the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) to give seventy suits of garments. AbuBakr then revived
it as the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had done till AbuBakr died. When
AbuBakr died, it was discontinued and the sadaqah was
levied.</english-text>
</hadith>
