<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23064</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3063</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribute, Spoils, and Rulership (Kitab Al-Kharaj, Wal-Fai'
Wal-Imarah) - كتاب الخراج والإمارة والفىء</chapter>
<chain-index>30386, 22016</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن النضر، قال سمعت الحنيني، قال قرأته غير
مرة يعني كتاب قطيعة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو داود
وحدثنا غير واحد عن حسين بن محمد أخبرنا أبو أويس حدثني كثير بن عبد
الله عن أبيه عن جده أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أقطع بلال بن الحارث
المزني معادن القبلية جلسيها وغوريها - قال ابن النضر وجرسها وذات
النصب ثم اتفقا - وحيث يصلح الزرع من قدس ‏.‏ ولم يعط بلال بن الحارث
حق مسلم وكتب له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا ما أعطى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بلال بن الحارث المزني أعطاه معادن القبلية جلسها
وغورها وحيث يصلح الزرع من قدس ولم يعطه حق مسلم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو أويس
حدثني ثور بن زيد عن عكرمة عن ابن عباس عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
مثله زاد ابن النضر وكتب أبى بن كعب ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Amr ibn Awf al-Muzani: The Prophet (ﷺ)
assigned as a fief to Bilal ibn Harith al-Muzani the mines of
al-Qabaliyyah, both those which lay on the upper side those and
which lay on the lower side. The narrator, Ibn an-Nadr, added:
"also Jars and Dhat an-Nusub." The agreed version reads: "and (the
land) which is suitable for cultivation at Quds". He did not assign
to Bilal ibn al-Harith the right of any Muslim. The Prophet (ﷺ)
wrote a document to him: "This is what the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
assigned to Bilal ibn al-Harith al-Muzani. He gave him the mines of
al-Qabaliyyah both those which lay on the upper and lower side, and
that which is fit for cultivation at Quds. He did not give him the
right of any Muslim." The narrator AbuUways said: A similar
tradition has been transmitted to me by Thawr ibn Zayd from Ikrimah
on the authority of Ibn Abbas from the Prophet (ﷺ). Ibn an-Nadr
added: Ubayy ibn Ka'b wrote it.</english-text>
</hadith>
