<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23271</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>22</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3270</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oaths and Vows (Kitab Al-Aiman Wa Al-Nudhur) - كتاب
الأيمان والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30180, 20208, 11286, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مؤمل بن هشام، حدثنا إسماعيل، عن الجريري، عن أبي
عثمان، أو عن أبي السليل، عنه عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر، قال ‏:‏ نزل
بنا أضياف لنا قال ‏:‏ وكان أبو بكر يتحدث عند رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بالليل فقال ‏:‏ لا أرجعن إليك حتى تفرغ من ضيافة هؤلاء ومن
قراهم فأتاهم بقراهم فقالوا ‏:‏ لا نطعمه حتى يأتي أبو بكر ‏.‏ فجاء
فقال ‏:‏ ما فعل أضيافكم أفرغتم من قراهم قالوا ‏:‏ لا ‏.‏ قلت ‏:‏ قد
أتيتهم بقراهم فأبوا وقالوا ‏:‏ والله لا نطعمه حتى يجيء، فقالوا ‏:‏
صدق قد أتانا به فأبينا حتى تجيء، قال ‏:‏ فما منعكم قالوا ‏:‏ مكانك
‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ والله لا أطعمه الليلة، قال فقالوا ‏:‏ ونحن والله لا
نطعمه حتى تطعمه ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ ما رأيت في الشر كالليلة قط - قال -
قربوا طعامكم ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ فقرب طعامهم فقال ‏:‏ بسم الله فطعم وطعموا
فأخبرت أنه أصبح فغدا على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبره بالذي صنع
وصنعوا، قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ بل أنت أبرهم وأصدقهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Abd al-Rahman b. Abi Bakr: Some guests
visited us, and Abu Bakr was conversing with the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) at night. He (Abu Bakr) said: I will not return to you until
you are free from their entertainment and serving them food. So he
brought them food, but they said: We shall not eat it until Abu
Bakr comes (back). Abu Bakr then came and asked: What did your
guest do? Are you free from their entertainment ? They said: No. I
said: I brought them food, but they refused and said: We swear by
Allah, we shall not take it until he comes. They said: He spoke the
truth. He brought it to us, but we refused (to take it) until you
come. He asked: What did prevent you ? He said: I swear by Allah, I
shall not take food tonight. They said: And we also swear by Allah
that we shall not take food until you take it. He said: I never saw
an evil like the one tonight. He said: Bring your food near (you).
He ('Abd al-Rahman) said: Their food was then brought near them. He
said: In the name of Allah, and he took the food, and they also
took it. I then informed him that the dawn had broken. So he went
to th Prophet (ﷺ) and informed him of what he and they had done. He
said: You are the most obedient and most trustful of
them.</english-text>
</hadith>
