<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23315</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>22</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3314</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oaths and Vows (Kitab Al-Aiman Wa Al-Nudhur) - كتاب
الأيمان والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20472, 4015</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، حدثنا عبد
الله بن يزيد بن مقسم الثقفي، من أهل الطائف قال حدثتني سارة بنت مقسم
الثقفي، أنها سمعت ميمونة بنت كردم، قالت ‏:‏ خرجت مع أبي في حجة رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسمعت
الناس يقولون ‏:‏ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجعلت أبده بصري، فدنا
إليه أبي وهو على ناقة له معه درة كدرة الكتاب، فسمعت الأعراب والناس
يقولون ‏:‏ الطبطبية الطبطبية، فدنا إليه أبي فأخذ بقدمه قالت ‏:‏
فأقر له ووقف فاستمع منه فقال ‏:‏ يا رسول الله إني نذرت إن ولد لي
ولد ذكر أن أنحر على رأس بوانة في عقبة من الثنايا عدة من الغنم ‏.‏
قال ‏:‏ لا أعلم إلا أنها قالت خمسين ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏:‏ ‏"‏ هل بها من الأوثان شىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ لا ‏.‏ قال
‏:‏ ‏"‏ فأوف بما نذرت به لله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ‏:‏ فجمعها فجعل يذبحها
فانفلتت منها شاة فطلبها، وهو يقول ‏:‏ اللهم أوف عني نذري ‏.‏ فظفرها
فذبحها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Maymunah, daughter of Kardam: I went out
with my father to see the hajj performed by the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ). I saw the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). I fixed my eyes on him. My
father came near him while he was riding his she-camel. He had a
whip like the whip of scribes. I heard the bedouin and the people
say: The whip, the whip. My father came near him and held his foot.
She said: He admitted his Prophethood and stood and listened to
him. He said: Messenger of Allah, I have made a vow that if a son
is born to me, I shall slaughter a number of sheep at the end of
Buwanah in the dale of hill. The narrator said: I do not know (for
certain) that she said: Fifty (sheep). The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: Does it contain any idol? He said: No. Then he said: Fulfil
your vow that you have taken for Allah. He then gathered them (i.e.
the sheep) and began to slaughter them. A sheep ran away from them.
He searched for it saying: O Allah, fulfil my vow on my behalf. So
he succeeded (in finding it) and slaughtered it.</english-text>
</hadith>
