<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23642</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3641</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge (Kitab Al-Ilm) - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20330, 28259, 28167, 17054</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد بن مسرهد، حدثنا عبد الله بن داود، سمعت عاصم
بن رجاء بن حيوة، يحدث عن داود بن جميل، عن كثير بن قيس، قال كنت
جالسا مع أبي الدرداء في مسجد دمشق فجاءه رجل فقال يا أبا الدرداء إني
جئتك من مدينة الرسول صلى الله عليه وسلم لحديث بلغني أنك تحدثه عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما جئت لحاجة ‏.‏ قال فإني سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ من سلك طريقا يطلب فيه علما سلك
الله به طريقا من طرق الجنة وإن الملائكة لتضع أجنحتها رضا لطالب
العلم وإن العالم ليستغفر له من في السموات ومن في الأرض والحيتان في
جوف الماء وإن فضل العالم على العابد كفضل القمر ليلة البدر على سائر
الكواكب وإن العلماء ورثة الأنبياء وإن الأنبياء لم يورثوا دينارا ولا
درهما ورثوا العلم فمن أخذه أخذ بحظ وافر ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Kathir ibn Qays: Kathir ibn Qays said: I was
sitting with AbudDarda' in the mosque of Damascus. A man came to
him and said: AbudDarda, I have come to you from the town of the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) for a tradition that I have heard you relate
from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). I have come for no other purpose.
He said: I heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: If anyone travels
on a road in search of knowledge, Allah will cause him to travel on
one of the roads of Paradise. The angels will lower their wings in
their great pleasure with one who seeks knowledge, the inhabitants
of the heavens and the Earth and the fish in the deep waters will
ask forgiveness for the learned man. The superiority of the learned
man over the devout is like that of the moon, on the night when it
is full, over the rest of the stars. The learned are the heirs of
the Prophets, and the Prophets leave neither dinar nor dirham,
leaving only knowledge, and he who takes it takes an abundant
portion.</english-text>
</hadith>
