<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>23693</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3692</hadith-number>
<chapter>Drinks (Kitab Al-Ashribah) - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>20193, 30213, 20022, 30175, 20243, 11309, 17, 30175,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن حرب، ومحمد بن عبيد، قالا حدثنا حماد، ح
وحدثنا مسدد، حدثنا عباد بن عباد، عن أبي جمرة، قال سمعت ابن عباس،
يقول - وقال مسدد عن ابن عباس، وهذا، حديث سليمان قال - قدم وفد عبد
القيس على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا يا رسول الله إنا هذا
الحى من ربيعة قد حال بيننا وبينك كفار مضر ولسنا نخلص إليك إلا في
شهر حرام فمرنا بشىء نأخذ به وندعو إليه من وراءنا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ آمركم
بأربع وأنهاكم عن أربع الإيمان بالله وشهادة أن لا إله إلا الله ‏"‏
‏.‏ وعقد بيده واحدة ‏.‏ وقال مسدد الإيمان بالله ثم فسرها لهم شهادة
أن لا إله إلا الله ‏"‏ وأن محمدا رسول الله وإقام الصلاة وإيتاء
الزكاة وأن تؤدوا الخمس مما غنمتم وأنهاكم عن الدباء والحنتم والمزفت
والمقير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ابن عبيد النقير مكان المقير ‏.‏ وقال مسدد
والنقير والمقير ولم يذكر المزفت ‏.‏ قال أبو داود أبو جمرة نصر بن
عمران الضبعي ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Abbas said: The deputation of 'Abd al-Qais came
to Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: This is the tribe of Rabi'ah,
and the infidels of Mudar are between us and you. We are able to
come to you only in the sacred month. So give a decisive command
which we may follow ourselves and to which we call those at home
behind us. He (the Prophet) said: I command you to observe four
things, and forbade you four things: Belief in Allah. the testimony
that there is no god but Allah, and he expresses one by folding his
hand. Musadad's version has: Faith in Allah, and he explained to
them: The testimony that there is no god but Allah and that
Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah, observance of prayer, payment
of zakat, and your giving the filth of the booty. I forbid you the
use of pumpkins, green jarrs, vessels smeared with pitch, and
hollow stumps of palm-trees. Ibn 'Ubaid's version has word muqayyar
(vessels smeared with pitch) instead of naqir (hollow stumps).
Musaddad's version has naqir and muqayyar (pitch); he did not
mention muzaffat (vessels smeared with pitch).Abu Dawud said: The
name of Abu Jamrah is Nasr bin 'Imran al-Duba'i.</english-text>
</hadith>
