<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24085</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4084</hadith-number>
<chapter>Clothing (Kitab Al-Libas) - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20031, 11597</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا يحيى، عن أبي غفار، حدثنا أبو تميمة
الهجيمي، - وأبو تميمة اسمه طريف بن مجالد - عن أبي جرى، جابر بن سليم
قال رأيت رجلا يصدر الناس عن رأيه، لا يقول شيئا إلا صدروا عنه قلت من
هذا قالوا هذا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قلت عليك السلام يا
رسول الله مرتين ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لا تقل عليك السلام ‏.‏ فإن عليك السلام
تحية الميت قل السلام عليك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت أنت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أنا رسول الله الذي إذا أصابك ضر فدعوته كشفه عنك
وإن أصابك عام سنة فدعوته أنبتها لك وإذا كنت بأرض قفراء أو فلاة فضلت
راحلتك فدعوته ردها عليك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت اعهد إلى ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لا تسبن
أحدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فما سببت بعده حرا ولا عبدا ولا بعيرا ولا شاة ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ ولا تحقرن شيئا من المعروف وأن تكلم أخاك وأنت منبسط إليه
وجهك إن ذلك من المعروف وارفع إزارك إلى نصف الساق فإن أبيت فإلى
الكعبين وإياك وإسبال الإزار فإنها من المخيلة وإن الله لا يحب
المخيلة وإن امرؤ شتمك وعيرك بما يعلم فيك فلا تعيره بما تعلم فيه
فإنما وبال ذلك عليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuJurayy Jabir ibn Salim al-Hujaymi: I saw
a man whose opinion was accepted by the people, and whatever he
said they submitted to it. I asked: Who is he? They said: This is
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). I said: On you be peace, Messenger of
Allah, twice. He said: Do not say "On you be peace," for "On you be
peace" is a greeting for the dead, but say "Peace be upon you". I
asked: You are the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon you)? He
said: I am the Messenger of Allah Whom you call when a calamity
befalls you and He removes it; when you suffer from drought and you
call Him, He grows food for you; and when you are in a desolate
land or in a desert and your she-camel strays and you call Him, He
returns it to you. I said: Give me some advice. He said: Do not
abuse anyone. He said that he did not abuse a freeman, or a slave,
or a camel or a sheep thenceforth. He said: Do not look down upon
any good work, and when you speak to your brother, show him a
cheerful face. This is a good work. Have your lower garment halfway
down your shin; if you cannot do it, have it up to the ankles.
Beware of trailing the lower garment, for it is conceit and Allah
does not like conceit. And if a man abuses and shames you for
something which he finds in you, then do not shame him for
something which you find in him; he will bear the evil consequences
for it.</english-text>
</hadith>
