<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24132</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4131</hadith-number>
<chapter>Clothing (Kitab Al-Libas) - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>38429, 20644, 11282, 30</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمرو بن عثمان بن سعيد الحمصي، حدثنا بقية، عن
بحير، عن خالد، قال وفد المقدام بن معديكرب وعمرو بن الأسود ورجل من
بني أسد من أهل قنسرين إلى معاوية بن أبي سفيان فقال معاوية للمقدام
أعلمت أن الحسن بن علي توفي فرجع المقدام فقال له رجل أتراها مصيبة
قال له ولم لا أراها مصيبة وقد وضعه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
حجره فقال ‏"‏ هذا مني وحسين من علي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال الأسدي جمرة أطفأها
الله عز وجل ‏.‏ قال فقال المقدام أما أنا فلا أبرح اليوم حتى أغيظك
وأسمعك ما تكره ‏.‏ ثم قال يا معاوية إن أنا صدقت فصدقني وإن أنا كذبت
فكذبني قال أفعل ‏.‏ قال فأنشدك بالله هل تعلم أن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم نهى عن لبس الذهب قال نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدك بالله هل سمعت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينهى عن لبس الحرير قال نعم ‏.‏ قال
فأنشدك بالله هل تعلم أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نهى عن لبس
جلود السباع والركوب عليها قال نعم ‏.‏ قال فوالله لقد رأيت هذا كله
في بيتك يا معاوية ‏.‏ فقال معاوية قد علمت أني لن أنجو منك يا مقدام
قال خالد فأمر له معاوية بما لم يأمر لصاحبيه وفرض لابنه في المائتين
ففرقها المقدام في أصحابه قال ولم يعط الأسدي أحدا شيئا مما أخذ فبلغ
ذلك معاوية فقال أما المقدام فرجل كريم بسط يده وأما الأسدي فرجل حسن
الإمساك لشيئه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Khalid said: Al-Miqdam ibn Ma'dikarib and a man of
Banu Asad from the people of Qinnisrin went to Mu'awiyah ibn
AbuSufyan. Mu'awiyah said to al-Miqdam: Do you know that al-Hasan
ibn Ali has died? Al-Miqdam recited the Qur'anic verse "We belong
to Allah and to Him we shall return." A man asked him: Do you think
it a calamity? He replied: Why should I not consider it a calamity
when it is a fact that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used to take him
on his lap, saying: This belongs to me and Husayn belongs to Ali?
The man of Banu Asad said: (He was) a live coal which Allah has
extinguished. Al-Miqdam said: Today I shall continue to make you
angry and make you hear what you dislike. He then said: Mu'awiyah,
if I speak the truth, declare me true, and if I tell a lie, declare
me false. He said: Do so. He said: I adjure you by Allah, did you
hear the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) forbidding use to wear gold? He
replied: Yes. He said: I adjure you by Allah, do you know that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) prohibited the wearing of silk? He replied:
Yes. He said: I adjure you by Allah, do you know that the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) prohibited the wearing of the skins of beasts of prey
and riding on them? He said: Yes. He said: I swear by Allah, I saw
all this in your house, O Mu'awiyah. Mu'awiyah said: I know that I
cannot be saved from you, O Miqdam. Khalid said: Mu'awiyah then
ordered to give him what he did not order to give to his two
companions, and gave a stipend of two hundred (dirhams) to his son.
Al-Miqdam then divided it among his companions, and the man of Banu
Asad did not give anything to anyone from the property he received.
When Mu'awiyah was informed about it, he said: Al-Miqdam is a
generous man; he has an open hand (for generosity). The man of Banu
Asad withholds his things in a good manner.</english-text>
</hadith>
