<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24245</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4244</hadith-number>
<chapter>Trials and Fierce Battles (Kitab Al-Fitan Wa Al-Malahim) -
كتاب الفتن والملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20469, 11019, 10724</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن قتادة، عن نصر بن عاصم،
عن سبيع بن خالد، قال أتيت الكوفة في زمن فتحت تستر أجلب منها بغالا
فدخلت المسجد فإذا صدع من الرجال وإذا رجل جالس تعرف إذا رأيته أنه من
رجال أهل الحجاز قال قلت من هذا فتجهمني القوم وقالوا أما تعرف هذا
هذا حذيفة بن اليمان صاحب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال حذيفة إن
الناس كانوا يسألون رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن الخير وكنت أسأله
عن الشر فأحدقه القوم بأبصارهم فقال إني قد أرى الذي تنكرون إني قلت
يا رسول الله أرأيت هذا الخير الذي أعطانا الله أيكون بعده شر كما كان
قبله قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت فما العصمة من ذلك قال ‏"‏ السيف ‏"‏
‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله ثم ماذا يكون قال ‏"‏ إن كان لله خليفة في الأرض
فضرب ظهرك وأخذ مالك فأطعه وإلا فمت وأنت عاض بجذل شجرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت
ثم ماذا قال ‏"‏ ثم يخرج الدجال معه نهر ونار فمن وقع في ناره وجب
أجره وحط وزره ومن وقع في نهره وجب وزره وحط أجره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت ثم
ماذا قال ‏"‏ ثم هي قيام الساعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hudhayfah ibn al-Yaman: Subay' ibn Khalid
said: I came to Kufah at the time when Tustar was conquered. I took
some mules from it. When I entered the mosque (of Kufah), I found
there some people of moderate stature, and among them was a man
whom you could recognize when you saw him that he was from the
people of Hijaz. I asked: Who is he? The people frowned at me and
said: Do you not recognize him? This is Hudhayfah ibn al-Yaman, the
companion of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). Then Hudhayfah said:
People used to ask the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) about good, and I
used to ask him about evil. Then the people stared hard at him. He
said: I know the reason why you dislike it. I then asked: Messenger
of Allah, will there be evil as there was before, after this good
which Allah has bestowed on us? He replied: Yes. I asked: Wherein
does the protection from it lie? He replied: In the sword. I asked:
Messenger of Allah, what will then happen? He replied: If Allah has
on Earth a caliph who flays your back and takes your property, obey
him, otherwise die holding onto the stump of a tree. I asked: What
will come next? He replied: Then the Antichrist (Dajjal) will come
forth accompanied by a river and fire. He who falls into his fire
will certainly receive his reward, and have his load taken off him,
but he who falls into his river will have his load retained and his
reward taken off him. I then asked: What will come next? He said:
The Last Hour will come.</english-text>
</hadith>
