<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24243</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4242</hadith-number>
<chapter>Trials and Fierce Battles (Kitab Al-Fitan Wa Al-Malahim) -
كتاب الفتن والملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>20442, 35061, 11415, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن عثمان بن سعيد الحمصي، حدثنا أبو المغيرة،
حدثني عبد الله بن سالم، حدثني العلاء بن عتبة، عن عمير بن هانئ
العنسي، قال سمعت عبد الله بن عمر، يقول كنا قعودا عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فذكر الفتن فأكثر في ذكرها حتى ذكر فتنة الأحلاس فقال
قائل يا رسول الله وما فتنة الأحلاس قال ‏"‏ هي هرب وحرب ثم فتنة
السراء دخنها من تحت قدمى رجل من أهل بيتي يزعم أنه مني وليس مني
وإنما أوليائي المتقون ثم يصطلح الناس على رجل كورك على ضلع ثم فتنة
الدهيماء لا تدع أحدا من هذه الأمة إلا لطمته لطمة فإذا قيل انقضت
تمادت يصبح الرجل فيها مؤمنا ويمسي كافرا حتى يصير الناس إلى فسطاطين
فسطاط إيمان لا نفاق فيه وفسطاط نفاق لا إيمان فيه فإذا كان ذاكم
فانتظروا الدجال من يومه أو من غده ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Umar: When we were sitting with
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), he talked about periods of trial
(fitnahs), mentioning many of them. When he mentioned the one when
people should stay in their houses, some asked him: Messenger of
Allah, what is the trial (fitnah) of staying at home? He replied:
It will be flight and plunder. Then will come a test which is
pleasant. Its murkiness is due to the fact that it is produced by a
man from the people of my house, who will assert that he belongs to
me, whereas he does not, for my friends are only the God-fearing.
Then the people will unite under a man who will be like a hip-bone
on a rib. Then there will be the little black trial which will
leave none of this community without giving him a slap, and when
people say that it is finished, it will be extended. During it a
man will be a believer in the morning and an infidel in the
evening, so that the people will be in two camps: the camp of faith
which will contain no hypocrisy, and the camp of hypocrisy which
will contain no faith. When that happens, expect the Antichrist
(Dajjal) that day or the next.</english-text>
</hadith>
