<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24247</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4246</hadith-number>
<chapter>Trials and Fierce Battles (Kitab Al-Fitan Wa Al-Malahim) -
كتاب الفتن والملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20236, 11279, 10724</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، حدثنا سليمان، - يعني
ابن المغيرة - عن حميد، عن نصر بن عاصم الليثي، قال أتينا اليشكري في
رهط من بني ليث فقال من القوم فقلنا بنو ليث أتيناك نسألك عن حديث
حذيفة فذكر الحديث قال قلت يا رسول الله هل بعد هذا الخير شر قال ‏"‏
فتنة وشر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله هل بعد هذا الشر خير قال ‏"‏
يا حذيفة تعلم كتاب الله واتبع ما فيه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث مرار ‏.‏ قال قلت
يا رسول الله هل بعد هذا الشر خير قال ‏"‏ هدنة على دخن وجماعة على
أقذاء فيها أو فيهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله الهدنة على الدخن ما هي
قال ‏"‏ لا ترجع قلوب أقوام على الذي كانت عليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا
رسول الله أبعد هذا الخير شر قال ‏"‏ فتنة عمياء صماء عليها دعاة على
أبواب النار فإن تمت يا حذيفة وأنت عاض على جذل خير لك من أن تتبع
أحدا منهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hudhayfah: The tradition mentioned above
(No. 4232) has also been transmitted through a different chain of
narrators by Nasr ibn Asim al-Laythi who said: We came to
al-Yashkuri with a group of the people of Banu Layth. He asked: Who
are these people? We replied: Banu Layth. We have come to you to
ask you about the tradition of Hudhayfah. He then mentioned the
tradition and said: I asked: Messenger of Allah, will there be evil
after this good? He replied: There will be trial (fitnah) and evil.
I asked: Messenger of Allah, will there be good after this evil? He
replied: Learn the Book of Allah, Hudhayfah, and adhere to its
contents. He said it three times. I asked: Messenger of Allah, will
there be good after this evil? He replied: An illusory truce and a
community with specks in its eye. I asked: Messenger of Allah, what
do you mean by an illusory community? He replied: The hearts of the
people will not return to their former condition. I asked:
Messenger of Allah, will there be evil after this good? He replied:
There will be wrong belief which will blind and deafen men to the
truth in which there will be summoners at the gates of Hell. If
you, Hudhayfah, die adhering to a stump, it will be better for you
than following any of them.</english-text>
</hadith>
