<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24262</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4261</hadith-number>
<chapter>Trials and Fierce Battles (Kitab Al-Fitan Wa Al-Malahim) -
كتاب الفتن والملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20022, 11296, 10695, 23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن أبي عمران الجوني، عن
المشعث بن طريف، عن عبد الله بن الصامت، عن أبي ذر، قال قال لي رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لبيك يا رسول الله
وسعديك ‏.‏ فذكر الحديث قال فيه ‏"‏ كيف أنت إذا أصاب الناس موت يكون
البيت فيه بالوصيف ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت الله ورسوله أعلم أو قال ما خار الله
لي ورسوله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ عليك بالصبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ تصبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ثم قال لي ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لبيك وسعديك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ كيف أنت
إذا رأيت أحجار الزيت قد غرقت بالدم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت ما خار الله لي
ورسوله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ عليك بمن أنت منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله أفلا
آخذ سيفي وأضعه على عاتقي قال ‏"‏ شاركت القوم إذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت فما
تأمرني قال ‏"‏ تلزم بيتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت فإن دخل على بيتي قال ‏"‏ فإن
خشيت أن يبهرك شعاع السيف فألق ثوبك على وجهك يبوء بإثمك وإثمه ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال أبو داود لم يذكر المشعث في هذا الحديث غير حماد بن زيد
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuDharr: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to
me: O AbuDharr. I replied: At thy service and at thy pleasure,
Messenger of Allah. He then mentioned the tradition in which he
said: What will you do when there the death of the people (in
Medina) and a house will reach the value of a slave (that is, a
grave will be sold for a slave). I replied: Allah and His Apostle
know best. Or he said: What Allah and His Apostle choose for me. He
said: You must show endurance. Or he said; you may endure. He then
said to me: What will you do, AbuDharr, when you see the Ahjar
az-Zayt covered with blood? I replied: What Allah and His Apostle
choose for me. He said: You must go to those who are like-minded. I
asked: Should I not take my sword and put it on my shoulder? He
replied: you would then associate yourself with the people. I then
asked: What do you order me to do? You must stay at home. I asked:
(What should I do) if people enter my house and find me? He
replied: If you are afraid the gleam of the sword may dazzle you,
put the end of your garment over your face in order that (the one
who kills you) may bear the punishment of your sins and his.Abu
Dawud said: No one mentioned al-Mush'ath in the chain of this
tradition except Hammad b. Zaid.</english-text>
</hadith>
