<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24271</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4270</hadith-number>
<chapter>Trials and Fierce Battles (Kitab Al-Fitan Wa Al-Malahim) -
كتاب الفتن والملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>38659, 20732, 27506</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مؤمل بن الفضل الحراني، حدثنا محمد بن شعيب، عن
خالد بن دهقان، قال كنا في غزوة القسطنطينية بذلقية فأقبل رجل من أهل
فلسطين - من أشرافهم وخيارهم يعرفون ذلك له يقال له هانئ بن كلثوم بن
شريك الكناني - فسلم على عبد الله بن أبي زكريا وكان يعرف له حقه قال
لنا خالد فحدثنا عبد الله بن أبي زكريا قال سمعت أم الدرداء تقول سمعت
أبا الدرداء يقول سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ كل ذنب
عسى الله أن يغفره إلا من مات مشركا أو مؤمن قتل مؤمنا متعمدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقال هانئ بن كلثوم سمعت محمود بن الربيع يحدث عن عبادة بن الصامت أنه
سمعه يحدث عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه قال ‏"‏ من قتل مؤمنا
فاعتبط بقتله لم يقبل الله منه صرفا ولا عدلا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لنا خالد ثم
حدثني ابن أبي زكريا عن أم الدرداء عن أبي الدرداء أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ لا يزال المؤمن معنقا صالحا ما لم يصب دما
حراما فإذا أصاب دما حراما بلح ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وحدث هانئ بن كلثوم عن محمود
بن الربيع عن عبادة بن الصامت عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مثله
سواء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbudDarda' and Ubadah ibn as-Samit: Khalid
ibn Dihqan said: When we were engaged in the battle of
Constantinople at Dhuluqiyyah, a man of the people of Palestine,
who was one of their nobility and elite and whose rank was known to
them, came forward. He was called Hani ibn Kulthum ibn Sharik
al-Kinani. He greeted Abdullah ibn Zakariyya who knew his rank.
Khalid said to us: Abdullah ibn AbuZakariyya told us: I heard Umm
ad-Darda' say: I heard AbudDarda' say: I heard the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) say: It is hoped that Allah may forgive every sin, except
in the case of one who dies a polytheist, or one who purposely
kills a believer. Hani ibn Kulthum ar-Rabi' then said: I heard
Mahmud ibn ar-Rabi' transmitting a tradition from Ubadah ibn
as-Samit who transmitted from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) who said:
If a man kills a believer unjustly, Allah will not accept any
action or duty of his, obligatory or supererogatory. Khalid then
said to us: Ibn AbuZakariyya transmitted a tradition to us from Umm
ad-Darda' on the authority of AbudDarda' from the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) who said: A believer will continue to go on quickly and
well so long as he does not shed unlawful blood; when he sheds
unlawful blood, he becomes slow and heavy-footed. A similar
tradition has been transmitted by Hani ibn Kulthum from Mahmud ibn
ar-Rabi' on the authority of Ubadah ibn as-Samit from the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ).</english-text>
</hadith>
