<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24287</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4286</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Promised Deliverer (Kitab Al-Mahdi) - كتاب
المهدى</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20287, 20295, 11019, 11291</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا معاذ بن هشام، حدثني أبي،
عن قتادة، عن صالح أبي الخليل، عن صاحب، له عن أم سلمة، زوج النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ يكون اختلاف عند
موت خليفة فيخرج رجل من أهل المدينة هاربا إلى مكة فيأتيه ناس من أهل
مكة فيخرجونه وهو كاره فيبايعونه بين الركن والمقام ويبعث إليه بعث من
الشام فيخسف بهم بالبيداء بين مكة والمدينة فإذا رأى الناس ذلك أتاه
أبدال الشام وعصائب أهل العراق فيبايعونه بين الركن والمقام ثم ينشأ
رجل من قريش أخواله كلب فيبعث إليهم بعثا فيظهرون عليهم وذلك بعث كلب
والخيبة لمن لم يشهد غنيمة كلب فيقسم المال ويعمل في الناس بسنة نبيهم
صلى الله عليه وسلم ويلقي الإسلام بجرانه إلى الأرض فيلبث سبع سنين ثم
يتوفى ويصلي عليه المسلمون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود قال بعضهم عن هشام
‏"‏ تسع سنين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال بعضهم ‏"‏ سبع سنين ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Umm Salamah, Ummul Mu'minin: The Prophet (ﷺ)
said: Disagreement will occur at the death of a caliph and a man of
the people of Medina will come flying forth to Mecca. Some of the
people of Mecca will come to him, bring him out against his will
and swear allegiance to him between the Corner and the Maqam. An
expeditionary force will then be sent against him from Syria but
will be swallowed up in the desert between Mecca and Medina. When
the people see that, the eminent saints of Syria and the best
people of Iraq will come to him and swear allegiance to him between
the Corner and the Maqam. Then there will arise a man of Quraysh
whose maternal uncles belong to Kalb and send against them an
expeditionary force which will be overcome by them, and that is the
expedition of Kalb. Disappointed will be the one who does not
receive the booty of Kalb. He will divide the property, and will
govern the people by the Sunnah of their Prophet (ﷺ) and establish
Islam on Earth. He will remain seven years, then die, and the
Muslims will pray over him.Abu Dawud said: Some transmitted from
Hisham "nine years" and some "seven years".</english-text>
</hadith>
