<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24331</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>39</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4329</hadith-number>
<chapter>Battles (Kitab Al-Malahim) - كتاب الملاحم</chapter>
<chain-index>38204, 20121, 20115, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عاصم، خشيش بن أصرم حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا
معمر، عن الزهري، عن سالم، عن ابن عمر، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
مر بابن صائد في نفر من أصحابه فيهم عمر بن الخطاب وهو يلعب مع
الغلمان عند أطم بني مغالة وهو غلام فلم يشعر حتى ضرب رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ظهره بيده ثم قال ‏"‏ أتشهد أني رسول الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فنظر إليه ابن صياد فقال أشهد أنك رسول الأميين ‏.‏ ثم قال ابن صياد
للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أتشهد أني رسول الله فقال له النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ آمنت بالله ورسله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال له النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما يأتيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يأتيني صادق وكاذب ‏.‏ فقال له
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خلط عليك الأمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني قد خبأت لك خبيئة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وخبأ له
‏{‏ يوم تأتي السماء بدخان مبين ‏}‏ قال ابن صياد هو الدخ ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اخسأ فلن تعدو قدرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
عمر يا رسول الله ائذن لي فأضرب عنقه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن يكن فلن تسلط عليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يعني الدجال ‏"‏ وإلا يكن
هو فلا خير في قتله ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn ‘Umar said : The prophet (ﷺ) passed by Ibn Sa’Id
along with some of his companions. ‘Umar b. al-Kattab was among
them. He was playing with boys near the fortress of Banu Maghalah.
He was near the age of puberty (i.e. a boy). Before he was aware,
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gave him a pat on the back and said : Do
you testify that you are the Messenger of Allah Ibn Sayyad then
looked at him and said: I testify that you are the Apostle of
Gentiles. Ibn Sayyad then said the prophet (ﷺ) then asked him :
What comes to you ? He replied: One who speaks the truth and one
who lies come to me. The prophet (may peace upon him) said: You are
confused. The Messenger of Allah (may peace upon him) said to him:
I have concealed something (in my hand) and he concealed the verse
“the day when the sky will bring forth smoke (dukhan) clearly
visible Ibn Sayyad said: It is smoke (dukhan) .The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said: Away with you, You cannot get farther than your
rank. ‘Umar said: “Messenger of Allah, permit me to cut off his
head. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: If he is the one (the
Dajjal), you will not be given power over him, and if he is not,
you will not do well in killing him.</english-text>
</hadith>
