<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24444</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4442</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prescribed Punishments (Kitab Al-Hudud) - كتاب
الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20347, 10747, 11432, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن موسى الرازي، أخبرنا عيسى بن يونس، عن
بشير بن المهاجر، حدثنا عبد الله بن بريدة، عن أبيه، أن امرأة، - يعني
من غامد - أتت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت إني قد فجرت ‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ ارجعي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجعت فلما كان الغد أتته فقالت لعلك أن تردني كما
رددت ماعز بن مالك فوالله إني لحبلى ‏.‏ فقال لها ‏"‏ ارجعي ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فرجعت فلما كان الغد أتته فقال لها ‏"‏ ارجعي حتى تلدي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجعت
فلما ولدت أتته بالصبي فقالت هذا قد ولدته ‏.‏ فقال لها ‏"‏ ارجعي
فأرضعيه حتى تفطميه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاءت به وقد فطمته وفي يده شىء يأكله
فأمر بالصبي فدفع إلى رجل من المسلمين وأمر بها فحفر لها وأمر بها
فرجمت وكان خالد فيمن يرجمها فرجمها بحجر فوقعت قطرة من دمها على
وجنته فسبها فقال له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ مهلا يا خالد
فوالذي نفسي بيده لقد تابت توبة لو تابها صاحب مكس لغفر له ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وأمر بها فصلي عليها فدفنت ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>) Buraidah said: A woman of Ghamid came to the
Prophet (ﷺ) and said: I have committed fornication. He said: Go
back. She returned, and on the next day she came to him again, and
said: Perhaps you want to send me back as you did to Ma’iz b.
Malik. I swear by Allah, I am pregnant. He said to her: Go back.
She then returned and came to him the next day. He said to her: Go
back until you give birth to a child. She then returned. When she
gave birth to a child, she brought the child to him, and said: Here
it is! I have given birth to it. He said: Go back, and suckle him
until you wean him. When she had weaned him, she brought him (the
boy) to him with something in his hand which he was eating. The boy
was then given to a certain man of the Muslims and he (the Prophet)
commanded regarding her. So a pit was dug for her, and he gave
orders about her and she was stoned to death. Khalid was one of
those who were throwing stones at her. He threw a stone at her.
When a drop blood fell on his cheeks, he abused her. The Prophet
(ﷺ) said to him: Gently, Khalid. By Him in whose hand my soul is,
she has reported to such an extent that if one who wrongfully takes
extra tax were to repent to a like extent, he would be forgiven.
Then giving command regarding her, prayed over her and she was
buried.</english-text>
</hadith>
