<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24447</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4445</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prescribed Punishments (Kitab Al-Hudud) - كتاب
الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 11004, 13, 3625</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، عن مالك، عن ابن شهاب،
عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن مسعود، عن أبي هريرة، وزيد بن
خالد الجهني، أنهما أخبراه أن رجلين اختصما إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال أحدهما يا رسول الله اقض بيننا بكتاب الله ‏.‏ وقال
الآخر وكان أفقههما أجل يا رسول الله فاقض بيننا بكتاب الله وائذن لي
أن أتكلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تكلم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا -
والعسيف الأجير - فزنى بامرأته فأخبروني أنما على ابني الرجم فافتديت
منه بمائة شاة وبجارية لي ثم إني سألت أهل العلم فأخبروني أنما على
ابني جلد مائة وتغريب عام وإنما الرجم على امرأته ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما والذي نفسي بيده لأقضين بينكما بكتاب الله
أما غنمك وجاريتك فرد إليك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وجلد ابنه مائة وغربه عاما وأمر
أنيسا الأسلمي أن يأتي امرأة الآخر فإن اعترفت رجمها فاعترفت فرجمها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah and Zaid b. Khalid al-Juhani said: Two
men brought a dispute before the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). One of
them said: Pronounce judgement between us in accordance with
Allah’s Book, Messenger of Allah! The other who had more
understanding said: Yes, Messenger of Allah! Pronounce judgement
between us in accordance with Allah’s Book, and allow me to speak.
He (the Prophet) said: Speak, He then said: My son who was a hired
servant with this(man) committed fornication with his wife, and
when I was told that my son must be stoned to death, I ransomed him
with a hundred sheep and a slave girl of mine; but when I asked the
learned, they told me that my son should receive a hundred lashes
and be banished for a year, and that stoning to death applied only
to man’s wife. The apostle of Allah (ﷺ) replied: By him in whose
hand my soul is, I shall certainly pronounce judgment between you
in accordance with Allah’s Book. Your sheep and your slave girl
must be returned to you, and your son shall receive a hundred
lashes and be banished for a year. And he commanded Unias al-Aslami
go to that man’s wife, and if she confessed, he should stone her to
death. She confessed and he stoned her.</english-text>
</hadith>
