<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24486</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4484</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prescribed Punishments (Kitab Al-Hudud) - كتاب
الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>38662, 20472, 20177, 19903, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن عاصم الأنطاكي، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون
الواسطي، حدثنا ابن أبي ذئب، عن الحارث بن عبد الرحمن، عن أبي سلمة،
عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إذا سكر
فاجلدوه ثم إن سكر فاجلدوه ثم إن سكر فاجلدوه فإن عاد الرابعة فاقتلوه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وكذا حديث عمر بن أبي سلمة عن أبيه عن أبي هريرة
عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إذا شرب الخمر فاجلدوه فإن عاد
الرابعة فاقتلوه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو داود وكذا حديث سهيل عن أبي صالح عن
أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن شربوا الرابعة فاقتلوهم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكذا حديث ابن أبي نعم عن ابن عمر عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم وكذا حديث عبد الله بن عمرو عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم والشريد
عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وفي حديث الجدلي عن معاوية أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ فإن عاد في الثالثة أو الرابعة فاقتلوه ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuHurayrah: The Prophet (ﷺ) said: If he is
intoxicated, flog him; again if he is intoxicated, flog him; again
if he is intoxicated, flog him if he does it again a fourth time,
kill him. Abu Dawud said: And there is a similar tradition of Umar
ibn AbuSalamah, from his father, on the authority of AbuHurayrah,
from the Prophet (ﷺ): If he drinks wine, flog him if he does it so
again, a fourth time, kill him.Abu Dawud said: And there is similar
tradition of Suhail from Abu Salih on the authority of Abu
Hurairah, from the Prophet (ﷺ): It they drink a fourth time, kill
them. And there is similar tradition of Ibn Abi Nu'm on the
authority of Ibn 'Umar from Prophet (ﷺ). There is also similar
tradition of 'Abd Allah b. 'Amr from the Prophet (ﷺ), and from
Sharid from the Prophet (ﷺ). And in the tradition of al-Jadli from
Mu'awiyah, the Prophet (ﷺ) said: If he does so again third or
fourth time, kill him.</english-text>
</hadith>
