<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24491</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4489</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prescribed Punishments (Kitab Al-Hudud) - كتاب
الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20262, 50, 11013, 2216</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي، حدثنا عثمان بن عمر، حدثنا أسامة بن
زيد، عن الزهري، عن عبد الرحمن بن أزهر، قال رأيت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم غداة الفتح وأنا غلام شاب يتخلل الناس يسأل عن منزل خالد بن
الوليد فأتي بشارب فأمرهم فضربوه بما في أيديهم فمنهم من ضربه بالسوط
ومنهم من ضربه بعصا ومنهم من ضربه بنعله وحثى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم التراب فلما كان أبو بكر أتي بشارب فسألهم عن ضرب النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم الذي ضربه فحزروه أربعين فضرب أبو بكر أربعين فلما كان عمر
كتب إليه خالد بن الوليد إن الناس قد انهمكوا في الشرب وتحاقروا الحد
والعقوبة ‏.‏ قال هم عندك فسلهم ‏.‏ وعنده المهاجرون الأولون فسألهم
فأجمعوا على أن يضرب ثمانين ‏.‏ قال وقال علي إن الرجل إذا شرب افترى
فأرى أن يجعله كحد الفرية ‏.‏ قال أبو داود أدخل عقيل بن خالد بين
الزهري وبين ابن الأزهر في هذا الحديث عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن
الأزهر عن أبيه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbdurRahman ibn Azhar: I saw the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) on the morning of the conquest of Mecca when I was a
young boy. He was walking among the people, seeking the camp of
Khalid ibn al-Walid. A man who had drunk wine was brought (before
him) and he ordered them (to beat him). So they beat him with what
they had in their hands. Some struck him with whips, some with
sticks and some with sandals. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) threw some
dust on his face. When a man who had drunk wine was brought before
AbuBakr, he asked them (i.e. the people) about the number of
beatings which they gave him. They numbered it forty. So AbuBakr
gave him forty lashes. When Umar came to power, Khalid ibn al-Walid
wrote to him: The people have become addicted to drinking wine and
they look down upon the prescribed punishment and its penalty. He
said: They are with you, ask them. The immigrants who embraced
Islam in the beginning were with him. He asked them and they agreed
on the fact that (a drunkard) should be given eighty lashes. Ali
said: When a man drinks wine, he tells lies. I, therefore, think
that he should be prescribed punishment that is prescribed for
telling lies..Abu Dawud said: 'Uqail b. Khalid included in the
chain of this tradition: "Abd Allah b. Abd al-Rahman b. al-Azhar
from his father" between al-Zuhri and Ibn al-Azhar.</english-text>
</hadith>
