<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24505</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>41</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4503</hadith-number>
<chapter>Types of Blood-Wit (Kitab Al-Diyat) - كتاب
الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 11107, 36063, 30296, 20029, 20509, 448,
20173</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا حماد، قال حدثنا محمد بن
إسحاق، فحدثني محمد بن جعفر بن الزبير، قال سمعت زياد بن ضميرة
الضمري، ح وحدثنا وهب بن بيان، وأحمد بن سعيد الهمداني، قالا حدثنا
ابن وهب، أخبرني عبد الرحمن بن أبي الزناد، عن عبد الرحمن بن الحارث،
عن محمد بن جعفر، أنه سمع زياد بن سعد بن ضميرة السلمي، - وهذا حديث
وهب وهو أتم - يحدث عروة بن الزبير عن أبيه - قال موسى - وجده وكانا
شهدا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حنينا - ثم رجعنا إلى حديث وهب
- أن محلم بن جثامة الليثي قتل رجلا من أشجع في الإسلام وذلك أول غير
قضى به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فتكلم عيينة في قتل الأشجعي لأنه
من غطفان وتكلم الأقرع بن حابس دون محلم لأنه من خندف فارتفعت الأصوات
وكثرت الخصومة واللغط فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا عيينة
ألا تقبل الغير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال عيينة لا والله حتى أدخل على نسائه من
الحرب والحزن ما أدخل على نسائي ‏.‏ قال ثم ارتفعت الأصوات وكثرت
الخصومة واللغط فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا عيينة ألا
تقبل الغير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال عيينة مثل ذلك أيضا إلى أن قام رجل من بني
ليث يقال له مكيتل عليه شكة وفي يده درقة فقال يا رسول الله إني لم
أجد لما فعل هذا في غرة الإسلام مثلا إلا غنما وردت فرمي أولها فنفر
آخرها اسنن اليوم وغير غدا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
خمسون في فورنا هذا وخمسون إذا رجعنا إلى المدينة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذلك في بعض
أسفاره ومحلم رجل طويل آدم وهو في طرف الناس فلم يزالوا حتى تخلص فجلس
بين يدى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وعيناه تدمعان فقال يا رسول
الله إني قد فعلت الذي بلغك وإني أتوب إلى الله تبارك وتعالى فاستغفر
الله عز وجل لي يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ أقتلته بسلاحك في غرة الإسلام اللهم لا تغفر لمحلم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ بصوت
عال زاد أبو سلمة فقام وإنه ليتلقى دموعه بطرف ردائه قال ابن إسحاق
فزعم قومه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم استغفر له بعد ذلك ‏.‏ قال
أبو داود قال النضر بن شميل الغير الدية ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ziyad ibn Sa'd ibn Dumayrah as-Sulami: On
the authority of his father (Sa'd) and his grandfather (Dumayrah)
(according to Musa's version) who were present in the battle of
Hunayn with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ): After the advent of Islam,
Muhallam ibn Jaththamah al-Laythi killed a man of Ashja'. That was
the first blood-money decided by the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) (for
payment). Uyaynah spoke about the killing of al-Ashja'i, for he
belonged to Ghatafan, and al-Aqra' ibn Habis spoke on behalf of
Muhallam, for he belonged to Khunduf. The voices rose high, and the
dispute and noise grew. So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Do you
not accept blood-money, Uyaynah? Uyaynah then said: No, I swear by
Allah, until I cause his women to suffer the same fighting and
grief as he caused my women to suffer. Again the voices rose high,
and the dispute and noise grew. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: Do
you not accept the blood-money Uyaynah? Uyaynah gave the same reply
as before, and a man of Banu Layth called Mukaytil stood up. He had
a weapon and a skin shield in his hand. He said: I do not find in
the beginning of Islam any illustration for what he has done except
the one that "some sheep came on, and those in the front were shot;
hence those in the rear ran away". (The other example is that)
"make a law today and change it." The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
Fifty (camels) here immediately and fifty when we return to Medina.
This happened during some of his journeys. Muhallam was a tall man
of dark complexion. He was with the people. They continued (to make
effort for him) until he was released. He sat before the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ), with his eyes flowing. He said: Messenger of Allah! I
have done (the act) of which you have been informed. I repent to
Allah, the Exalted, so ask Allah's forgiveness for me. Messenger of
Allah! The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then said: Did you kill him with
your weapon at the beginning of Islam. O Allah! do not forgive
Muhallam. He said these words loudly. AbuSalamah added: He
(Muhallam) then got up while he was wiping his tears with the end
of his garment. Ibn Ishaq said: His people alleged that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) asked forgiveness for him after that.Abu
Dawud said: Al-Nadr b. Shumail said: al-ghiyar means
blood-wit.</english-text>
</hadith>
