<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24514</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>41</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4512</hadith-number>
<chapter>Types of Blood-Wit (Kitab Al-Diyat) - كتاب
الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30569, 20423, 11220, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا وهب بن بقية، عن خالد، عن محمد بن عمرو، عن أبي
سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقبل
الهدية ولا يأكل الصدقة ‏.‏ وحدثنا وهب بن بقية في موضع آخر عن خالد
عن محمد بن عمرو عن أبي سلمة ولم يذكر أبا هريرة قال كان رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقبل الهدية ولا يأكل الصدقة ‏.‏ زاد فأهدت له
يهودية بخيبر شاة مصلية سمتها فأكل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منها
وأكل القوم فقال ‏"‏ ارفعوا أيديكم فإنها أخبرتني أنها مسمومة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فمات بشر بن البراء بن معرور الأنصاري فأرسل إلى اليهودية ‏"‏ ما حملك
على الذي صنعت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت إن كنت نبيا لم يضرك الذي صنعت وإن كنت
ملكا أرحت الناس منك ‏.‏ فأمر بها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقتلت
ثم قال في وجعه الذي مات فيه ‏"‏ ما زلت أجد من الأكلة التي أكلت
بخيبر فهذا أوان قطعت أبهري ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
would accept a present, but would not accept alms (sadaqah).And
Wahb bin Baqiyyah narrated to us, elsewhere, from Khalid, from
Muhammad ibn Amr said on the authority of AbuSalamah, and he did
not mention the name of Abu Hurairah: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
used to accept presents but not alms (sadaqah). This version adds:
So a Jewess presented him at Khaybar with a roasted sheep which she
had poisoned. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) ate of it and the people
also ate. He then said: Take away your hands (from the food), for
it has informed me that it is poisoned. Bishr ibn al-Bara' ibn
Ma'rur al-Ansari died. So he (the Prophet) sent for the Jewess (and
said to her): What motivated you to do the work you have done? She
said: If you were a prophet, it would not harm you; but if you were
a king, I should rid the people of you. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
then ordered regarding her and she was killed. He then said about
the pain of which he died: I continued to feel pain from the morsel
which I had eaten at Khaybar. This is the time when it has cut off
my aorta.</english-text>
</hadith>
