<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24523</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>41</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4521</hadith-number>
<chapter>Types of Blood-Wit (Kitab Al-Diyat) - كتاب
الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30485, 20029, 20001, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عمرو بن السرح، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني
مالك، عن أبي ليلى بن عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن سهل، عن سهل بن أبي
حثمة، أنه أخبره هو، ورجال، من كبراء قومه أن عبد الله بن سهل ومحيصة
خرجا إلى خيبر من جهد أصابهم فأتي محيصة فأخبر أن عبد الله بن سهل قد
قتل وطرح في فقير أو عين فأتى يهود فقال أنتم والله قتلتموه ‏.‏ قالوا
والله ما قتلناه ‏.‏ فأقبل حتى قدم على قومه فذكر لهم ذلك ثم أقبل هو
وأخوه حويصة - وهو أكبر منه - وعبد الرحمن بن سهل فذهب محيصة ليتكلم
وهو الذي كان بخيبر فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كبر كبر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ يريد السن فتكلم حويصة ثم تكلم محيصة فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إما أن يدوا صاحبكم وإما أن يؤذنوا بحرب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكتب
إليهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بذلك فكتبوا إنا والله ما قتلناه
‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لحويصة ومحيصة وعبد الرحمن ‏"‏
أتحلفون وتستحقون دم صاحبكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فتحلف لكم
يهود ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ليسوا مسلمين فوداه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
من عنده فبعث إليهم مائة ناقة حتى أدخلت عليهم الدار ‏.‏ قال سهل لقد
ركضتني منها ناقة حمراء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl b. Abi Hathmah and some senior men of the tribe
told that 'Abd Allah b. Abi Sahl and Muhayyasah came to Khaibar on
account of the calamity (i.e. famine) that befall them. Muhayyasah
came and told the 'Abd Allah b. Sahl had been killed and thrown in
a well or stream. He hen came to the Jews and said: I swear by
Allah, you have killed him. They said: We swear by Allah, we have
not killed him. He then proceeded and came to his tribe and
mentioned this to them. Then he, his brother Huwayyasah, who was
older to him, and 'Abd al-Rahman b. Sahl came forward (to the
Prophet). Muhayyasah began to speak. It was he who was at Khaibar.
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then said to him: Let the eldest
(speak), let the eldest (speak), meaning age. So Huwayyasah spoke,
and after him Muhayyasah spoke. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then
said: They should either pay the bloodwit for you friend or they
should be prepared for war. So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) wrote to
them about it. They wrote (in reply): We swear by Allah, we have
not killed him. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then said to Huwayyasah,
Muhayyasah and 'Abd al-Rahman: Will you take an oath and thus have
the claim to the blood of your friend ? They said: No. He (the
Prophet) said: The Jews will then take an oath. They said: They are
not Muslims. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) himself paid the
bloodwit. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then sent on one hundred
she-camels and they were entered in their house. Sahl said: A red
she-camel of them gave me a kick.</english-text>
</hadith>
