<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24536</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>41</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4534</hadith-number>
<chapter>Types of Blood-Wit (Kitab Al-Diyat) - كتاب
الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>20121, 20115, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن داود بن سفيان، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا
معمر، عن الزهري، عن عروة، عن عائشة، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث
أبا جهم بن حذيفة مصدقا فلاجه رجل في صدقته فضربه أبو جهم فشجه فأتوا
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا القود يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لكم كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلم يرضوا فقال ‏"‏ لكم
كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلم يرضوا فقال ‏"‏ لكم كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرضوا ‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني خاطب العشية على الناس ومخبرهم
برضاكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا نعم ‏.‏ فخطب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال ‏"‏ إن هؤلاء الليثيين أتوني يريدون القود فعرضت عليهم كذا وكذا
فرضوا أرضيتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا ‏.‏ فهم المهاجرون بهم فأمرهم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يكفوا عنهم فكفوا ثم دعاهم فزادهم فقال
‏"‏ أرضيتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إني خاطب على الناس
ومخبرهم برضاكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ فخطب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال ‏"‏ أرضيتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha, Ummul Mu'minin: The Prophet (ﷺ) sent
AbuJahm ibn Hudhayfah as a collector of zakat. A man quarrelled
with him about his sadaqah (i.e. zakat), and AbuJahm struck him and
wounded his head. His people came to the Prophet (ﷺ) and said:
Revenge, Messenger of Allah! The Prophet (ﷺ) said: You may have so
much and so much. But they did not agree. He again said: You may
have so much and so much. But they did not agree. He again said:
You may have so much and so much. So they agreed. The Prophet (ﷺ)
said: I am going to address the people in the afternoon and tell
them about your consent. They said: Yes. Addressing (the people),
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: These people of faith came to me
asking for revenge. I presented them with so much and so much and
they agreed. Do you agree? They said: No. The immigrants
(muhajirun) intended (to take revenge) on them. But the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) commanded them to refrain and they refrained. He then
called them and increased (the amount), and asked: Do you agree?
They replied: Yes. He said: I am going to address the people and
tell them about your consent. They said: Yes. The Prophet (ﷺ)
addressed and said: Do you agree? They said: Yes.</english-text>
</hadith>
