<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24566</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>41</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4564</hadith-number>
<chapter>Types of Blood-Wit (Kitab Al-Diyat) - كتاب
الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>20240, 20719, 10880, 19934, 19911</chain-index>
<arabic-text>قال أبو داود وجدت في كتابي عن شيبان، - ولم أسمعه منه -
فحدثناه أبو بكر، - صاحب لنا ثقة - قال حدثنا شيبان، حدثنا محمد، -
يعني ابن راشد - عن سليمان، - يعني ابن موسى - عن عمرو بن شعيب، عن
أبيه، عن جده، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقوم دية الخطإ
على أهل القرى أربعمائة دينار أو عدلها من الورق يقومها على أثمان
الإبل فإذا غلت رفع في قيمتها وإذا هاجت رخصا نقص من قيمتها وبلغت على
عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما بين أربعمائة دينار إلى ثمانمائة
دينار أو عدلها من الورق ثمانية آلاف درهم وقضى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم على أهل البقر مائتى بقرة ومن كان دية عقله في الشاء فألفى
شاة قال وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن العقل ميراث بين
ورثة القتيل على قرابتهم فما فضل فللعصبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقضى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في الأنف إذا جدع الدية كاملة وإن جدعت ثندوته
فنصف العقل خمسون من الإبل أو عدلها من الذهب أو الورق أو مائة بقرة
أو ألف شاة وفي اليد إذا قطعت نصف العقل وفي الرجل نصف العقل وفي
المأمومة ثلث العقل ثلاث وثلاثون من الإبل وثلث أو قيمتها من الذهب أو
الورق أو البقر أو الشاء والجائفة مثل ذلك وفي الأصابع في كل أصبع عشر
من الإبل وفي الأسنان في كل سن خمس من الإبل وقضى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أن عقل المرأة بين عصبتها من كانوا لا يرثون منها شيئا إلا
ما فضل عن ورثتها فإن قتلت فعقلها بين ورثتها وهم يقتلون قاتلهم وقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ليس للقاتل شىء وإن لم يكن له وارث
فوارثه أقرب الناس إليه ولا يرث القاتل شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال محمد هذا كله
حدثني به سليمان بن موسى عن عمرو بن شعيب عن أبيه عن جده عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو داود محمد بن راشد من أهل دمشق هرب إلى
البصرة من القتل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Dawud: I found in my notebook from
Shaiban and I did not hear from him ; Abu Bakr, a reliable friend
of ours, said: Shaiban - Muhammad b. Rashid - Sulaiman b. Musad -
'Amr b. Suh'aib, On his father's authority, said that his
grandfather said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) would fix the
blood-money for accidental killing at the rate of four hundred
dinars or their equivalent in silver for townsmen, and he would fix
it according to the price of camels. So when they were dear, he
increased the amount to be paid, and when cheap prices prevailed he
reduced the amount to be paid. In the time of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) they reached between four hundred and eight hundred
dinars, their equivalent in silver being eight thousand dirhams. He
said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gave judgment that those who
possessed cattle should pay two hundred cows, and those who
possessed sheep two thousand sheep. He said: The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) said: The blood-money is to be treated as something to be
inherited by the heirs of the one who has been killed, and the
remainder should be divided among the agnates. He said: The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gave judgment that for cutting off a nose
completely there was full blood-money, one hundred (camels) were to
be paid. If the tip of the nose was cut off, half of the
blood-money,i.e. fifty camels were to be paid, or their equivalent
in gold or in silver, or a hundred cows, or one thousand sheep. For
the hand, when it was cut of,f half of the blood-money was to be
paid; for one foot of half, the blood-money was to be paid. For a
wound in the head, a third of the blood-money was due, i.e.
thirty-three camels and a third of the blood-money, or their
equivalent in gold, silver, cows or sheep. For a head thrust which
reaches the body, the same blood-money was to be paid. Ten camels
were to be paid for every finger, and five camels for every tooth.
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gave judgment that the blood-money for a
woman should be divided among her relatives on her father's side,
who did not inherit anything from her except the residence of her
heirs. If she was killed, her blood-money should be distributed
among her heirs, and they would have the right of taking revenge on
the murderer. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: There is nothing for
the murderer; and if he (the victim) has no heir, his heir will be
the one who is nearest to him among the people, but the murderer
should not inherit anything. Muhammad said: All this has been
transmitted to me by Sulayman ibn Musa on the authority of Amr ibn
Shu'aib who, on his father's authority, said that his grandfather
heard it from the Prophet (ﷺ).Abu Dawud said: Muhammad b. Rashid,
an inhabitant of Damascus, fled from Basrah escaping
murder.</english-text>
</hadith>
