<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24609</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4607</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 20733, 20415, 11422, 17046</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن حنبل، حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا ثور بن
يزيد، قال حدثني خالد بن معدان، قال حدثني عبد الرحمن بن عمرو السلمي،
وحجر بن حجر، قالا أتينا العرباض بن سارية وهو ممن نزل فيه ‏{‏ ولا
على الذين إذا ما أتوك لتحملهم قلت لا أجد ما أحملكم عليه ‏}‏ فسلمنا
وقلنا أتيناك زائرين وعائدين ومقتبسين ‏.‏ فقال العرباض صلى بنا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات يوم ثم أقبل علينا فوعظنا موعظة بليغة
ذرفت منها العيون ووجلت منها القلوب فقال قائل يا رسول الله كأن هذه
موعظة مودع فماذا تعهد إلينا فقال ‏"‏ أوصيكم بتقوى الله والسمع
والطاعة وإن عبدا حبشيا فإنه من يعش منكم بعدي فسيرى اختلافا كثيرا
فعليكم بسنتي وسنة الخلفاء المهديين الراشدين تمسكوا بها وعضوا عليها
بالنواجذ وإياكم ومحدثات الأمور فإن كل محدثة بدعة وكل بدعة ضلالة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Irbad ibn Sariyah: AbdurRahman ibn Amr
as-Sulami and Hujr ibn Hujr said: We came to Irbad ibn Sariyah who
was among those about whom the following verse was revealed: "Nor
(is there blame) on those who come to thee to be provided with
mounts, and when thou saidst: "I can find no mounts for you." We
greeted him and said: We have come to see you to give healing and
obtain benefit from you. Al-Irbad said: One day the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) led us in prayer, then faced us and gave us a lengthy
exhortation at which the eyes shed tears and the hearts were
afraid. A man said: Messenger of Allah! It seems as if it were a
farewell exhortation, so what injunction do you give us? He then
said: I enjoin you to fear Allah, and to hear and obey even if it
be an Abyssinian slave, for those of you who live after me will see
great disagreement. You must then follow my sunnah and that of the
rightly-guided caliphs. Hold to it and stick fast to it. Avoid
novelties, for every novelty is an innovation, and every innovation
is an error.</english-text>
</hadith>
