<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24634</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4632</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 20121, 20115, 11013, 11004, 17,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى بن فارس، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، - قال
محمد كتبته من كتابه - قال أخبرنا معمر عن الزهري عن عبيد الله بن عبد
الله عن ابن عباس قال كان أبو هريرة يحدث أن رجلا أتى إلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال إني أرى الليلة ظلة ينطف منها السمن والعسل
فأرى الناس يتكففون بأيديهم فالمستكثر والمستقل وأرى سببا واصلا من
السماء إلى الأرض فأراك يا رسول الله أخذت به فعلوت به ثم أخذ به رجل
آخر فعلا به ثم أخذ به رجل آخر فعلا به ثم أخذ به رجل آخر فانقطع ثم
وصل فعلا به ‏.‏ قال أبو بكر بأبي وأمي لتدعني فلأعبرنها ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
اعبرها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أما الظلة فظلة الإسلام وأما ما ينطف من السمن
والعسل فهو القرآن لينه وحلاوته وأما المستكثر والمستقل فهو المستكثر
من القرآن والمستقل منه وأما السبب الواصل من السماء إلى الأرض فهو
الحق الذي أنت عليه تأخذ به فيعليك الله ثم يأخذ به بعدك رجل فيعلو به
ثم يأخذ به رجل آخر فيعلو به ثم يأخذ به رجل آخر فينقطع ثم يوصل له
فيعلو به أى رسول الله لتحدثني أصبت أم أخطأت ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أصبت بعضا
وأخطأت بعضا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أقسمت يا رسول الله لتحدثني ما الذي أخطأت
‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقسم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Abbas said: Abu Hurairah said that a man came to
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: I saw (in my dream) a piece of
cloud from which ghee and honey were dropping. I saw the people
spreading their hands. Some of them took much and some a little. I
also saw a rope hanging from Heaven to Earth. I saw, Messenger of
Allah, that you caught hold of it and ascended by it. Then another
man caught hold of it and ascended it. Then another man caught hold
of it and ascended it. Then another man caught hold of it, but it
broke, and then it was joined and he ascended it. AbuBakr said: May
my parents be sacrificed for you, if you allow, I shall interpret
it. He said: Interpret it. He said: The piece of cloud is the cloud
of Islam; the ghee and honey that were dropping from it are the
Qur'an, which contains softness and sweetness. Those who received
much or little of it are those who learn much or little of the
Qur'an. The rope hanging from Heaven to Earth is the truth which
you are following. You catch hold of it and then Allah will raise
you to Him. Then another man will catch hold of it and ascend it,
Then another man will catch hold of it and it will break. But it
will be joined and he will ascend it. Tell me. Messenger of Allah,
whether I am right or wrong. He said: You are partly right and
partly wrong. He said: I adjure you by Allah, you should tell me
where I am wrong. The Prophet (ﷺ) said: Do not take an
oath.</english-text>
</hadith>
