<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24652</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4650</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30559, 20256</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كامل، حدثنا عبد الواحد بن زياد، حدثنا صدقة
بن المثنى النخعي، حدثني جدي، رياح بن الحارث قال كنت قاعدا عند فلان
في مسجد الكوفة وعنده أهل الكوفة فجاء سعيد بن زيد بن عمرو بن نفيل
فرحب به وحياه وأقعده عند رجله على السرير فجاء رجل من أهل الكوفة
يقال له قيس بن علقمة فاستقبله فسب وسب فقال سعيد من يسب هذا الرجل
قال يسب عليا ‏.‏ قال ألا أرى أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يسبون عندك ثم لا تنكر ولا تغير أنا سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يقول وإني لغني أن أقول عليه ما لم يقل فيسألني عنه غدا إذا
لقيته ‏"‏ أبو بكر في الجنة وعمر في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وساق معناه ثم قال
لمشهد رجل منهم مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يغبر فيه وجهه خير من
عمل أحدكم عمره ولو عمر عمر نوح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Rabah ibn al-Harith said: I was sitting with someone
in the mosque of Kufah while the people of Kufah were with him.
Then Sa'id ibn Zayd ibn Amr ibn Nufayl came and he welcomed him,
greeted him, and seated him near his foot on the throne. Then a man
of the inhabitants of Kufah, called Qays ibn Alqamah, came. He
received him and began to abuse him. Sa'id asked: Whom is this man
abusing? He replied: He is abusing Ali. He said: Don't I see that
the companions of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) are being abused, but
you neither stop it nor do anything about it? I heard the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) say--and I need not say for him anything which he did
not say, and then he would ask me tomorrow when I see him --AbuBakr
will go to Paradise and Umar will go to Paradise. He then mentioned
the rest of the tradition to the same effect (as in No. 4632). He
then said: The company of one of their man whose face has been
covered with dust by the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) is better than the
actions of one of you for a whole life time even if he is granted
the life-span of Noah.</english-text>
</hadith>
