<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24696</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4694</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20288, 11067, 11344</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد بن مسرهد، حدثنا المعتمر، قال سمعت منصور بن
المعتمر، يحدث عن سعد بن عبيدة، عن عبد الله بن حبيب أبي عبد الرحمن
السلمي، عن علي، عليه السلام قال كنا في جنازة فيها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ببقيع الغرقد فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجلس
ومعه مخصرة فجعل ينكت بالمخصرة في الأرض ثم رفع رأسه فقال ‏"‏ ما منكم
من أحد ما من نفس منفوسة إلا قد كتب الله مكانها من النار أو من الجنة
إلا قد كتبت شقية أو سعيدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال رجل من القوم يا نبي الله
أفلا نمكث على كتابنا وندع العمل فمن كان من أهل السعادة ليكونن إلى
السعادة ومن كان من أهل الشقوة ليكونن إلى الشقوة قال ‏"‏ اعملوا فكل
ميسر أما أهل السعادة فييسرون للسعادة وأما أهل الشقوة فييسرون للشقوة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال نبي الله ‏"‏ ‏{‏ فأما من أعطى واتقى * وصدق بالحسنى *
فسنيسره لليسرى * وأما من بخل واستغنى * وكذب بالحسنى * ‏.‏ فسنيسره
للعسرى ‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Ali said: We attended a funeral at Baql’ al-Gharqad
which was also attended by the Messenger of Allah (May peace be
upon him). The Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him) came and
sat down. He had a stick (in his hand) by which he began to scratch
up the ground. He then raised his head and said : The place which
every one of you and every soul of you will occupy in Hell or in
Paradise has been recorded, and destined wicked or blesses. A man
from among the people asked : Prophet of Allah! Should we not then
trust simply in what has been recorded for us and abandon (doing
good) deeds? Those who are among the number of the blessed will be
inclined to blessing, and those of us who are among the number of
the wicked will be inclined to wickedness. He replied : Go on doing
good actions, for everyone is helped to do that for which he was
created. Those who are among the number of wicked will be helped to
do wicked deeds. The Prophet of Allah (May peace be upon him) then
recited: “So he who gives (in charity) and fears (Allah), and in
all sincerity testifies to the best, we will indeed make smooth for
him the path to bliss. But he who is a greedy miser and thinks
himself self-sufficient, and gives the lie to the best, We will
indeed make smooth for him the path of misery.”</english-text>
</hadith>
