<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24697</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4695</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 20286, 11303, 11432, 11316</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا كهمس، عن ابن
بريدة، عن يحيى بن يعمر، قال كان أول من تكلم في القدر بالبصرة معبد
الجهني فانطلقت أنا وحميد بن عبد الرحمن الحميري حاجين أو معتمرين
فقلنا لو لقينا أحدا من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسألناه
عما يقول هؤلاء في القدر ‏.‏ فوفق الله لنا عبد الله بن عمر داخلا في
المسجد فاكتنفته أنا وصاحبي فظننت أن صاحبي سيكل الكلام إلى فقلت أبا
عبد الرحمن إنه قد ظهر قبلنا ناس يقرءون القرآن ويتفقرون العلم يزعمون
أن لا قدر والأمر أنف ‏.‏ فقال إذا لقيت أولئك فأخبرهم أني بريء منهم
وهم برآء مني والذي يحلف به عبد الله بن عمر لو أن لأحدهم مثل أحد
ذهبا فأنفقه ما قبله الله منه حتى يؤمن بالقدر ثم قال حدثني عمر بن
الخطاب قال بينا نحن عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ طلع علينا
رجل شديد بياض الثياب شديد سواد الشعر لا يرى عليه أثر السفر ولا
نعرفه حتى جلس إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأسند ركبتيه إلى ركبتيه
ووضع كفيه على فخذيه وقال يا محمد أخبرني عن الإسلام ‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ الإسلام أن تشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وأن
محمدا رسول الله وتقيم الصلاة وتؤتي الزكاة وتصوم رمضان وتحج البيت إن
استطعت إليه سبيلا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال صدقت ‏.‏ قال فعجبنا له يسأله ويصدقه
‏.‏ قال فأخبرني عن الإيمان ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أن تؤمن بالله وملائكته وكتبه
ورسله واليوم الآخر وتؤمن بالقدر خيره وشره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال صدقت ‏.‏ قال
فأخبرني عن الإحسان قال ‏"‏ أن تعبد الله كأنك تراه فإن لم تكن تراه
فإنه يراك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأخبرني عن الساعة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما المسئول عنها
بأعلم من السائل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأخبرني عن أماراتها ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أن تلد
الأمة ربتها وأن ترى الحفاة العراة العالة رعاء الشاء يتطاولون في
البنيان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم انطلق فلبثت ثلاثا ثم قال ‏"‏ يا عمر هل تدري
من السائل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنه جبريل أتاكم
يعلمكم دينكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Yahya b. Ya’mur said : The first to speak on Divine
decree in al-Basrah was Ma’bad al Juhani. I and Humaid b.’Abd
al-Rahman al-Himyari proceeded to perform HAJJ or UMRAH. We said :
would that we meet any of the Companions of the Messenger of Allah
(May peace be upon him) so that we could ask him about what they
say with regard to divine decree. So Allah helped us to meet ‘Abd
Allah b. Umar who was entering the mosque. So I and my companion
surrounded him, and I thought that my companion would entrust me
the task of speaking to him. Then I said : Abu ‘Abd al-Rahman,
there appeared on our side some people who recite the Quran and are
engaged in the hair-splitting of knowledge. They conceive that
there is no Divine decree and everything happens freely without
predestination. He said : When you meet those people, tell them
that I am free from them, and they are free from me. By Him by Whom
swears ‘Abd Allah b. ‘Umar, if one of them has gold equivalent to
Uhud and he spends it, Allah will not accept it from him until he
believes in Divine decree. He then said : ‘Umar b. Khattab
transmitted to me a tradition, saying : One day when we were with
the Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him) a man with very
white clothing and very black hair came up to us. No mark of travel
was visible on him, and we did not recognize him. Sitting down
beside the Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him), leaning his
knees against his and placing his hands on his thighs, he said :
tell me, Muhammad, about Islam. The Messenger of Allah (May peace
be upon him) said : Islam means that you should testify that there
is no god but Allah, and Muhammad is Allah’s Apostle, that you
should observe prayer, pay ZAKAT, fast during RAMADAN, and perform
Hajj to the house (i.e., KABAH), If you have the meant to go. He
said : You have spoken the truth. We were surprised at his
questioning him and then declaring that he spoke the truth. He said
: now tell me about faith. He replied : It means that you should
believe in Allah, his angels, his Books, his Apostles and the last
day, and that you should believe in the decreeing both of good and
evil. He said : you have spoken the truth. He said : now tell me
about doing good (ihsan). He replied: it means that you should
worship Allah as though you are seeing him; if you are not seeing
him, he is seeing you. He said: Now tell me about the hour. He
replied : The one who is asked about it is no better informed than
the one who is asking. He said : Then tell me about its signs. He
replied : That a maidservant should beget her mistress, and that
you should see barefooted, naked, poor men and shepherds exalting
themselves in buildings. ‘Umar said : He then went away, and I
waited for three days, then he said : Do you know who the
questioner was, Umar? I replied : Allah and his Apostle know best.
He said : He was Gabriel who came to you to teach you your
religion.</english-text>
</hadith>
