<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24704</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4702</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20029, 20519, 11163, 11416, 3</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، قال حدثنا ابن وهب، قال أخبرني هشام
بن سعد، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن أبيه، أن عمر بن الخطاب، قال قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن موسى قال يا رب أرنا آدم الذي أخرجنا
ونفسه من الجنة فأراه الله آدم فقال أنت أبونا آدم فقال له آدم نعم
‏.‏ قال أنت الذي نفخ الله فيك من روحه وعلمك الأسماء كلها وأمر
الملائكة فسجدوا لك قال نعم ‏.‏ قال فما حملك على أن أخرجتنا ونفسك من
الجنة فقال له آدم ومن أنت قال أنا موسى ‏.‏ قال أنت نبي بني إسرائيل
الذي كلمك الله من وراء الحجاب لم يجعل بينك وبينه رسولا من خلقه قال
نعم ‏.‏ قال أفما وجدت أن ذلك كان في كتاب الله قبل أن أخلق قال نعم
‏.‏ قال ففيم تلومني في شىء سبق من الله تعالى فيه القضاء قبلي ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عند ذلك ‏"‏ فحج آدم موسى فحج
آدم موسى ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Umar b. al-Khattab reported the Messenger of Allah
(May peace be upon him) as saying : Moses said : My lord, show us
Adam who caused us and himself to come out from Paradise. So Allah
showed him Adam. He asked : Are you our father, Adam? Adam said to
him : Yes. He said : Are you the one into whom Allah breathed of
his spirit, taught you all the names, and commanded angels (to
prostrate) and they prostrated to you? He replied : Yes. He asked :
Then what moved you to cause us and yourself to come out from
paradise? Adam asked him : And who are you? He said : Yes. He asked
: Did you not find that was decreed in the book (records) of Allah
before I was created? He replied : Yes. He asked : Then why do you
blame me about a thing for which Divine decree had already passed
before me ? The Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him) said :
So Adam got the better of Moses in argument (peace be upon
him).</english-text>
</hadith>
