<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24755</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4753</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 20028, 30480, 20354, 11060, 11656, 10911,
400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا جرير، ح وحدثنا هناد بن
السري، حدثنا أبو معاوية، - وهذا لفظ هناد - عن الأعمش، عن المنهال،
عن زاذان، عن البراء بن عازب، قال ‏:‏ خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في جنازة رجل من الأنصار، فانتهينا إلى القبر ولما يلحد،
فجلس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وجلسنا حوله كأنما على رءوسنا
الطير، وفي يده عود ينكت به في الأرض، فرفع رأسه فقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏
استعيذوا بالله من عذاب القبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ مرتين أو ثلاثا - زاد في حديث
جرير ها هنا - وقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ وإنه ليسمع خفق نعالهم إذا ولوا مدبرين
حين يقال له ‏:‏ يا هذا من ربك وما دينك ومن نبيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هناد
قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ ويأتيه ملكان فيجلسانه فيقولان له ‏:‏ من ربك فيقول ‏:‏
ربي الله ‏.‏ فيقولان له ‏:‏ ما دينك فيقول ‏:‏ ديني الإسلام ‏.‏
فيقولان له ‏:‏ ما هذا الرجل الذي بعث فيكم قال فيقول ‏:‏ هو رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فيقولان ‏:‏ وما يدريك فيقول ‏:‏ قرأت
كتاب الله فآمنت به وصدقت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ زاد في حديث جرير ‏:‏ ‏"‏ فذلك قول
الله عز وجل ‏{‏ يثبت الله الذين آمنوا ‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ الآية ‏.‏ ثم
اتفقا قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ فينادي مناد من السماء ‏:‏ أن قد صدق عبدي فأفرشوه
من الجنة، وافتحوا له بابا إلى الجنة وألبسوه من الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
‏:‏ ‏"‏ فيأتيه من روحها وطيبها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ ويفتح له فيها مد
بصره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ وإن الكافر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذكر موته قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏
وتعاد روحه في جسده ويأتيه ملكان فيجلسانه فيقولان ‏:‏ من ربك فيقول
‏:‏ هاه هاه هاه لا أدري ‏.‏ فيقولان له ‏:‏ ما دينك فيقول ‏:‏ هاه
هاه لا أدري ‏.‏ فيقولان ‏:‏ ما هذا الرجل الذي بعث فيكم فيقول ‏:‏
هاه هاه لا أدري ‏.‏ فينادي مناد من السماء ‏:‏ أن كذب فأفرشوه من
النار وألبسوه من النار، وافتحوا له بابا إلى النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏
‏"‏ فيأتيه من حرها وسمومها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ ويضيق عليه قبره حتى
تختلف فيه أضلاعه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ زاد في حديث جرير قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ ثم يقيض له
أعمى أبكم معه مرزبة من حديد، لو ضرب بها جبل لصار ترابا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
‏:‏ ‏"‏ فيضربه بها ضربة يسمعها ما بين المشرق والمغرب إلا الثقلين
فيصير ترابا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ ثم تعاد فيه الروح ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Bara' ibn Azib: We went out with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) accompanying the bier of a man of the Ansar.
When we reached his grave, it was not yet dug. So the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) sat down and we also sat down around him as if birds were
over our heads. He had in his hand a stick with which he was
scratching the ground. He then raised his head and said: Seek
refuge with Allah from the punishment in the grave. He said it
twice or thrice. The version of Jabir adds here: He hears the beat
of their sandals when they go back, and at that moment he is asked:
O so and so! Who is your Lord, what is your religion, and who is
your Prophet? Hannad's version says: Two angels will come to him,
make him sit up and ask him: Who is your Lord? He will reply: My
Lord is Allah. They will ask him: What is your religion? He will
reply: My religion is Islam. They will ask him: What is your
opinion about the man who was sent on a mission among you? He will
reply: He is the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). They will ask: Who made
you aware of this? He will reply: I read Allah's Book, believed in
it, and considered it true; which is verified by Allah's words:
"Allah's Book, believed in it, and considered it true, which is
verified by Allah's words: "Allah establishes those who believe
with the word that stands firm in this world and the next." The
agreed version reads: Then a crier will call from Heaven: My
servant has spoken the truth, so spread a bed for him from
Paradise, clothe him from Paradise, and open a door for him into
Paradise. So some of its air and perfume will come to him, and a
space will be made for him as far as the eye can see. He also
mentioned the death of the infidel, saying: His spirit will be
restored to his body, two angels will come to him, make him sit up
and ask him: Who is your Lord? He will reply: Alas, alas! I do not
know. They will ask him: What is your religion? He will reply:
Alas, alas! I do not know. They will ask: Who was the man who was
sent on a mission among you? He will reply: Alas, alas! I do not
know. Then a crier will call from Heaven: He has lied, so spread a
bed for him from Hell, clothe him from Hell, and open for him a
door into Hell. Then some of its heat and pestilential wind will
come to him, and his grave will be compressed, so that his ribs
will be crushed together. Jabir's version adds: One who is blind
and dumb will then be placed in charge of him, having a
sledge-hammer such that if a mountain were struck with it, it would
become dust. He will give him a blow with it which will be heard by
everything between the east and the west except by men and jinn,
and he will become dust. Then his spirit will be restored to
him.</english-text>
</hadith>
