<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24753</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4751</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>31160, 11168, 11019, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سليمان الأنباري، حدثنا عبد الوهاب بن
عطاء الخفاف أبو نصر، عن سعيد، عن قتادة، عن أنس بن مالك، قال ‏:‏ إن
نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دخل نخلا لبني النجار فسمع صوتا ففزع
فقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ من أصحاب هذه القبور ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ‏:‏ يا رسول الله ناس
ماتوا في الجاهلية ‏.‏ فقال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ تعوذوا بالله من عذاب النار ومن
فتنة الدجال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ‏:‏ ومم ذاك يا رسول الله قال ‏:‏ ‏"‏ إن
المؤمن إذا وضع في قبره أتاه ملك فيقول له ‏:‏ ما كنت تعبد فإن الله
هداه قال ‏:‏ كنت أعبد الله ‏.‏ فيقال له ‏:‏ ما كنت تقول في هذا
الرجل فيقول ‏:‏ هو عبد الله ورسوله فما يسأل عن شىء غيرها فينطلق به
إلى بيت كان له في النار، فيقال له ‏:‏ هذا بيتك كان لك في النار ولكن
الله عصمك ورحمك فأبدلك به بيتا في الجنة فيقول ‏:‏ دعوني حتى أذهب
فأبشر أهلي ‏.‏ فيقال له ‏:‏ اسكن ‏.‏ وإن الكافر إذا وضع في قبره
أتاه ملك فينتهره فيقول له ‏:‏ ما كنت تعبد فيقول ‏:‏ لا أدري ‏.‏
فيقال له ‏:‏ لا دريت ولا تليت ‏.‏ فيقال له ‏:‏ فما كنت تقول في هذا
الرجل فيقول ‏:‏ كنت أقول ما يقول الناس ‏.‏ فيضربه بمطراق من حديد
بين أذنيه فيصيح صيحة يسمعها الخلق غير الثقلين ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik said: The Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) entered
the garden of the palm trees of Banu al-Najjar. He heard a voice
and was terrified. He asked: Who are the people buried in these
graves? The people replied: Messenger of Allah! These are some
people who died in the pre-Islamic times. He said: Seek refuge in
Allah from the punishment of the fire, and the trail of Antichrist.
They asked: Why is it that, Messenger of Allah? He said: When a man
is placed in his grave, an angel comes to him and says to him: Whom
did you worship? Allah then guides him and he says: I worshiped
Allah. He is then asked: What was your opinion of this man? He
replies: He is Allah’s servant and His Apostle. He will not then be
asked about anything else. He will then be taken to his abode in
Hell and will be told: This was your abode in Hell, but Allah
protected you and had mercy on you substituted for you an abode in
Paradise for it. He will say: Leave me so that I may go and give
glad tidings to my family. He will be told: Dwell. When an infidel
is placed in his grave, an angel comes to him, reprimands him and
asks him: Whom did you worship? He replies: I do not know. He will
be told: You neither knew nor did you follow(the believers). He is
then asked: What was your opinion on this man? He replies: I held
the opinion that the other people held. He will then give him a
blow between his ears with an iron hammer and will utter a shout
which will be heard by all the creatures(near him) with the
exception of men and jinn.</english-text>
</hadith>
