<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24777</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4775</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30524, 20443, 12489</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هارون بن عبد الله، حدثنا أبو عامر، حدثنا محمد بن
هلال، سمع أباه، يحدث قال قال أبو هريرة وهو يحدثنا كان النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم يجلس معنا في المجلس يحدثنا فإذا قام قمنا قياما حتى
نراه قد دخل بعض بيوت أزواجه فحدثنا يوما فقمنا حين قام فنظرنا إلى
أعرابي قد أدركه فجبذه بردائه فحمر رقبته قال أبو هريرة وكان رداء
خشنا فالتفت فقال له الأعرابي احمل لي على بعيرى هذين فإنك لا تحمل لي
من مالك ولا من مال أبيك ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا
وأستغفر الله لا وأستغفر الله لا وأستغفر الله لا أحمل لك حتى تقيدني
من جبذتك التي جبذتني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكل ذلك يقول له الأعرابي والله لا
أقيدكها ‏.‏ فذكر الحديث قال ثم دعا رجلا فقال له ‏"‏ احمل له على
بعيريه هذين على بعير شعيرا وعلى الآخر تمرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم التفت إلينا
فقال ‏"‏ انصرفوا على بركة الله تعالى ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuHurayrah: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used
to sit with us in meetings and talk to us. When he stood up we also
used to stand up and see him entering the house of one of his
wives. One day he talked to us and we stood up as he stood up and
we saw that an Arabi (a nomadic Arab) caught hold of him and gave
his cloak a violent tug making his neck red. AbuHurayrah said: The
cloak was coarse. He turned to him and the Arabi said to him: Load
these two camels of mine, for you do not give me anything from your
property or from your father's property. The Prophet (ﷺ) said to
him: No, I ask Allah's forgiveness; no, I ask Allah's forgiveness;
no, I ask Allah's forgiveness. I shall not give you the camel-load
until you make amends for the way in which you tugged at me. Each
time the Arabi said to him: I swear by Allah, I shall not do so. He
then mentioned the rest of the tradition. He (the Prophet), then
called a man and said to him: Load these two camels of his: one
camel with barley and the other with dates. He then turned to us
and said: Go on your way with the blessing of Allah.</english-text>
</hadith>
