<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24770</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4768</hadith-number>
<chapter>Model Behavior of the Prophet (Kitab Al-Sunnah) - كتاب
السنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20121, 10945, 11350, 11341</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، عن عبد الملك بن
أبي سليمان، عن سلمة بن كهيل، قال أخبرني زيد بن وهب الجهني، ‏:‏ أنه
كان في الجيش الذين كانوا مع علي عليه السلام الذين ساروا إلى الخوارج
فقال علي عليه السلام ‏:‏ أيها الناس إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يقول ‏:‏ ‏"‏ يخرج قوم من أمتي يقرءون القرآن ليست قراءتكم
إلى قراءتهم شيئا ولا صلاتكم إلى صلاتهم شيئا ولا صيامكم إلى صيامهم
شيئا، يقرءون القرآن يحسبون أنه لهم وهو عليهم، لا تجاوز صلاتهم
تراقيهم يمرقون من الإسلام كما يمرق السهم من الرمية، لو يعلم الجيش
الذين يصيبونهم ما قضي لهم على لسان نبيهم صلى الله عليه وسلم لنكلوا
على العمل، وآية ذلك أن فيهم رجلا له عضد وليست له ذراع، على عضده مثل
حلمة الثدى عليه شعرات بيض ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أفتذهبون إلى معاوية وأهل الشام
وتتركون هؤلاء يخلفونكم في ذراريكم وأموالكم والله إني لأرجو أن
يكونوا هؤلاء القوم، فإنهم قد سفكوا الدم الحرام، وأغاروا في سرح
الناس فسيروا على اسم الله ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ سلمة بن كهيل ‏:‏ فنزلني زيد
بن وهب منزلا منزلا حتى مر بنا على قنطرة قال فلما التقينا وعلى
الخوارج عبد الله بن وهب الراسبي فقال لهم ‏:‏ ألقوا الرماح وسلوا
السيوف من جفونها، فإني أخاف أن يناشدوكم كما ناشدوكم يوم حروراء قال
‏:‏ فوحشوا برماحهم واستلوا السيوف وشجرهم الناس برماحهم - قال -
وقتلوا بعضهم على بعضهم ‏.‏ قال ‏:‏ وما أصيب من الناس يومئذ إلا
رجلان فقال علي عليه السلام ‏:‏ التمسوا فيهم المخدج فلم يجدوا قال
‏:‏ فقام علي رضى الله عنه بنفسه حتى أتى ناسا قد قتل بعضهم على بعض
فقال ‏:‏ أخرجوهم فوجدوه مما يلي الأرض فكبر وقال ‏:‏ صدق الله وبلغ
رسوله ‏.‏ فقام إليه عبيدة السلماني فقال ‏:‏ يا أمير المؤمنين والله
الذي لا إله إلا هو لقد سمعت هذا من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال ‏:‏ إي والله الذي لا إله إلا هو حتى استحلفه ثلاثا وهو يحلف
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Salamah b. kuhail said: Zaid b. Wahb al-Juhani told
that he was in the army which proceeded to (fight with) the
Khawarij in the company of ‘Ali. All then said: O people! I heard
the Messenger of Allah (May peace be upon him) say: there will
appear from among my community people who recite the Quran, and
your recitation has no comparison with their recitation, and your
prayer has no comparison with their prayer, and your fasts have no
comparison with their fasts. They will recite the Quran thinking
that it is beneficial for them, while it is harmful for them. Their
prayer will not pass their collar-bones. They will swerve from
Islam as an arrow goes through the animal shot at. If the army that
is approaching them knows what (reward) has been decided for them
at the tongue of their prophet (May peace be upon him), they would
leave (other good) activities. The sign of that is that among them
there will be a man who has an upper arm, but not hand; on his
upper arm there will be something like the nipple of a female
breast, having white hair thereon. Will you go to Mu;awiyah and the
people of Syria, and leave them behind among your children and
property? I swear by Allah, I hope these are the same people, for
they shed the blood unlawfully, and attacked the cattle of the
people so go on in the name of Allah. Salamah b. kuhail said: Zaid
b. Wahb then informed me of all the halting places one by one,
(saying): Until we passed a bridge. When we fought with each other,
’Abd Allah b. Wahb al-Rasibi, who was the leader of the Khawarij,
said to them: Throw away the lances and pull out the swards from
their sheaths, for I am afraid they will adjure you as they had
adjured on the day of Harura. So they threw away their lances and
pulled out their swords, and the people pierced them with their
lances. They were killed (lying one on the other). On that day only
two persons of the partisans (of ‘Ali) were afflicted . ‘Ali said:
search for the man with the crippled hand. but they could not find
it. Then ‘All got up himself and went to the people who had been
killed and were lying on one another. He said: Take them out. They
found him just near the ground. So he shouted: Allah is Most Great!
He said: Allah spoke the truth, and His Apostle has conveyed.
‘Ubaidat al-Salmani stood up to him, saying: Commander of the
Faithful! Have you heard it from the Messenger of Allah (May peace
be upon him)? He said: Yes, by him, there is no god but He. He put
to swear thrice and he swore.</english-text>
</hadith>
