<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24958</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4956</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30226, 20121, 20115, 11013, 11002, 2070</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن صالح، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، عن معمر، عن
الزهري، عن سعيد بن المسيب، عن أبيه، عن جده، أن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال له ‏"‏ ما اسمك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال حزن ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أنت سهل ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال لا السهل يوطأ ويمتهن ‏.‏ قال سعيد فظننت أنه سيصيبنا بعده حزونة
‏.‏ قال أبو داود وغير النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم اسم العاص وعزيز
وعتلة وشيطان والحكم وغراب وحباب وشهاب فسماه هشاما وسمى حربا سلما
وسمى المضطجع المنبعث وأرضا تسمى عفرة سماها خضرة وشعب الضلالة سماه
شعب الهدى وبنو الزنية سماهم بني الرشدة وسمى بني مغوية بني رشدة ‏.‏
قال أبو داود تركت أسانيدها للاختصار ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sa'id b. Musayyab told that his father said on the
authority of his grandfather (Hazn): The Prophet (ﷺ) asked: What is
your name? He replied: Hazn (rugged). He said: You are Sahl
(smooth). He said: No, smooth is trodden upon and disgraced. Sa'id
said: I then thought that ruggedness would remain among us after
it. AbuDawud said: The Prophet (ﷺ) changed the names al-'As, Aziz,
Atalah, Shaytan, al-Hakam, Ghurab, Hubab, and Shihab and called him
Hisham. He changed the name Harb (war) and called him Silm (peace).
He changed the name al-Munba'ith (one who lies) and called him
al-Mudtaji' (one who stands up). He changed the name of a land
Afrah (barren) and called it Khadrah (green). He changed the name
Shi'b ad-Dalalah (the mountain path of a stray), the name of a
mountain path and called it Shi'b al-Huda (mountain path of
guidance). He changed the name Banu az-Zinyah (children of
fornication) and called them Banu ar-Rushdah (children of those who
are on the right path), and changed the name Banu Mughwiyah
(children of a woman who allures and goes astray), and called them
Banu Rushdah (children of a woman who is on the right path).
AbuDawud said: I omitted the chains of these for the sake of
brevity.</english-text>
</hadith>
