<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25067</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5065</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30329, 20020, 11068, 19867, 29</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حفص بن عمر، حدثنا شعبة، عن عطاء بن السائب، عن
أبيه، عن عبد الله بن عمرو، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
خصلتان أو خلتان لا يحافظ عليهما عبد مسلم إلا دخل الجنة هما يسير ومن
يعمل بهما قليل يسبح في دبر كل صلاة عشرا ويحمد عشرا ويكبر عشرا فذلك
خمسون ومائة باللسان وألف وخمسمائة في الميزان ويكبر أربعا وثلاثين
إذا أخذ مضجعه ويحمد ثلاثا وثلاثين ويسبح ثلاثا وثلاثين فذلك مائة
باللسان وألف في الميزان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلقد رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يعقدها بيده قالوا يا رسول الله كيف هما يسير ومن يعمل بهما قليل
قال ‏"‏ يأتي أحدكم - يعني الشيطان - في منامه فينومه قبل أن يقوله
ويأتيه في صلاته فيذكره حاجة قبل أن يقولها ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah ibn Amr: The Prophet (ﷺ) said:
There are two qualities or characteristics which will not be
returned by any Muslim without his entering Paradise. While they
are easy, those who act upon them are few. One should say: "Glory
be to Allah" ten times after every prayer, "Praise be to Allah" ten
times and "Allah is Most Great" ten times. That is a hundred and
fifty on the tongue, but one thousand and five hundred on the
scale. When he goes to bed, he should say: "Allah is Most Great"
thirty-four times, "Praise be to Allah" thirty-three times, and
Glory be to Allah thirty-three times, for that is a hundred on the
tongue and a thousand on the scale. (He said:) I saw the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) counting them on his hand. The people asked: Messenger
of Allah! How is it that while they are easy, those who act upon
them are few? He replied: The Devil comes to one of you when he
goes to bed and he makes him sleep, before he utters them, and he
comes to him while he is engaged in prayer and calls a need to his
mind before he utters them.</english-text>
</hadith>
