<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25073</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5071</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30569, 20423, 38573, 20028, 10755, 10887, 20395,
18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا وهب بن بقية، عن خالد، ح وحدثنا محمد بن قدامة بن
أعين، حدثنا جرير، عن الحسن بن عبيد الله، عن إبراهيم بن سويد، عن عبد
الرحمن بن يزيد، عن عبد الله، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يقول
إذا أمسى ‏"‏ أمسينا وأمسى الملك لله والحمد لله لا إله إلا الله وحده
لا شريك له ‏"‏ ‏.‏ زاد في حديث جرير وأما زبيد كان يقول كان إبراهيم
بن سويد يقول ‏"‏ لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له له الملك وله الحمد
وهو على كل شىء قدير رب أسألك خير ما في هذه الليلة وخير ما بعدها
وأعوذ بك من شر ما في هذه الليلة وشر ما بعدها رب أعوذ بك من الكسل
ومن سوء الكبر أو الكفر رب أعوذ بك من عذاب في النار وعذاب في القبر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا أصبح قال ذلك أيضا ‏"‏ أصبحنا وأصبح الملك لله ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال أبو داود رواه شعبة عن سلمة بن كهيل عن إبراهيم بن سويد قال ‏"‏
من سوء الكبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولم يذكر سوء الكفر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abd Allah (b. Mas’ud) told that when the evening
came, the prophet (May peace be upon him) would say: we have come
to the evening, and in the evening the dominion belongs to Allah:
“Praise be to Allah; there is no god but Allah alone who has no
partner”. The version of Jarir adds: Zubaid said that Ibrahim b.
Suwaid said: There is no god but Allah alone who has no partner; to
him belongs the dominion, to him praise is due, and He is
omnipotent. O Allah! I ask thee for the good of what this night
contains, and the good of what comes after it; and I seek refuge in
Thee from the evil of what this night contains, and from the evil
of what comes after it. My Lord! I seek refuge in Thee from
indolence, the evil of old age or of disbelief. My Lord! I seek
refuge in Thee from a punishment in Hell and a punishment in the
grave. In the morning he said that also: we have come to the
morning, and in the morning the dominion belongs to Allah.Abu Dawud
said: Shu’bah transmitted from Salamah b. Kuhail, from Ibrahim b.
Suwaid, saying: from the evil of old age. He did not mention the
evil of disbelief.</english-text>
</hadith>
