<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25187</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5185</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 30170, 10725, 20024, 11449, 11219,
172</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام أبو مروان، ومحمد بن المثنى، - المعنى - قال
محمد بن المثنى حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا الأوزاعي، قال سمعت يحيى
بن أبي كثير، يقول حدثني محمد بن عبد الرحمن بن أسعد بن زرارة، عن قيس
بن سعد، قال زارنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في منزلنا فقال ‏"‏
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرد سعد ردا خفيا ‏.‏ قال قيس فقلت
ألا تأذن لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال ذره يكثر علينا من
السلام فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ السلام عليكم ورحمة
الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرد سعد ردا خفيا ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ السلام عليكم ورحمة الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم رجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم واتبعه سعد فقال يا رسول الله إني كنت أسمع تسليمك وأرد عليك ردا
خفيا لتكثر علينا من السلام ‏.‏ قال فانصرف معه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأمر له سعد بغسل فاغتسل ثم ناوله ملحفة مصبوغة بزعفران أو
ورس فاشتمل بها ثم رفع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يديه وهو يقول
‏"‏ اللهم اجعل صلواتك ورحمتك على آل سعد بن عبادة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم
أصاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من الطعام فلما أراد الانصراف قرب
له سعد حمارا قد وطأ عليه بقطيفة فركب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال سعد يا قيس اصحب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال قيس فقال
لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اركب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأبيت ثم قال ‏"‏
إما أن تركب وإما أن تنصرف ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فانصرفت ‏.‏ قال هشام أبو
مروان عن محمد بن عبد الرحمن بن أسعد بن زرارة ‏.‏ قال أبو داود رواه
عمر بن عبد الواحد وابن سماعة عن الأوزاعي مرسلا ولم يذكرا قيس بن سعد
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Qays ibn Sa'd: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
came to visit us in our house, and said: Peace and Allah's mercy be
upon you! Sa'd returned the greeting in a lower tone. Qays said: I
said: Do you not grant permission to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) to
enter? He said: Leave him, he will give us many greetings. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then said: Peace and Allah's mercy be upon
you! Sa'd again responded in a lower tone. The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) again said: Peace and Allah's mercy be upon you! So the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) went away. Sa'd went after him and said:
Messenger of Allah! I heard your greetings and responded in a lower
tone so that you might give us many greetings. The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) returned with him. Sa'd then offered to prepare
bath-water for him, and he took a bath. He then gave him a long
wrapper dyed with saffron or wars and he wrapped himself in it. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then raised his hands and said: O Allah,
bestow Thy blessings and mercy on the family of Sa'd ibn Ubadah!
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) then shared their meals. When he
intended to return, Sa'd brought near him an ass which was covered
with a blanket. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) mounted it. Sa'd said: O
Qays, accompany the Messenger of Allah. Qays said: The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said to me: Ride. But I refused. He again said: Either
ride or go away. He said: So I went away. Hisham said: AbuMarwan
(transmitted) from Muhammad ibn AbdurRahman ibn As'ad ibn
Zurarah.Abu Dawud said: 'Umar b. 'Abd al-Wahid and Ibn Sama'ah
transmitted it from al-Awzai' in mursal form (the ling of the
Companion being missing), and they did not mention Qais b.
Sa'd.</english-text>
</hadith>
