<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25235</id>
<source>Sunan Abi Da'ud</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5233</hadith-number>
<chapter>General Behavior (Kitab Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20022, 10986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا حماد، أخبرنا يعلى بن
عطاء، عن أبي همام عبد الله بن يسار، أن أبا عبد الرحمن الفهري، قال
شهدت مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حنينا فسرنا في يوم قائظ شديد
الحر فنزلنا تحت ظل الشجرة فلما زالت الشمس لبست لأمتي وركبت فرسي
فأتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو في فسطاطه فقلت السلام عليك
يا رسول الله ورحمة الله وبركاته قد حان الرواح فقال ‏"‏ أجل ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ يا بلال قم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فثار من تحت سمرة كأن ظله ظل طائر فقال
لبيك وسعديك وأنا فداؤك ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أسرج لي الفرس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأخرج
سرجا دفتاه من ليف ليس فيه أشر ولا بطر فركب وركبنا ‏.‏ وساق الحديث
‏.‏ قال أبو داود أبو عبد الرحمن الفهري ليس له إلا هذا الحديث وهو
حديث نبيل جاء به حماد بن سلمة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated AbuAbdurRahman al-Fihri: I was present with
the Messenger of Allah at the battle of Hunayn. We travelled on a
hot day when the heat was extreme. We halted under the shade of a
tree. When the sun passed the meridian, I put on my coat of mail
and rode on my horse. I came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) who was
in a tent. I said: Peace, Allah's mercy and His blessings be upon
you! The time of departure has come. He said: Yes. He then said:
Rise, Bilal. He jumped out from beneath a gum-acacia tree and its
shade was like that of a bird. He said: I am at your service and at
your pleasure, and I make myself a sacrifice for you. He said: Put
the saddle on the horse for me. He then took out a saddle, both
sides of which were stuffed with palm-leaves; it showed no
arrogance and pride. So he rode and we also rode. He then mentioned
the rest of the tradition.Abu Dawud said: Abu 'Abd al-Rahman
al-Fihri did not transmit any tradition except this one. This is a
tradition of an expert transmitted by Hammad b.
Salamah.</english-text>
</hadith>
