<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12739</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2787</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>28603, 10704, 11449</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا عبد الله بن محمد الرومي، حدثنا النضر بن محمد،
حدثنا عكرمة، - وهو ابن عمار - حدثنا يحيى، قال انطلقت أنا وعبد الله
بن يزيد، حتى نأتي أبا سلمة فأرسلنا إليه رسولا فخرج علينا وإذا عند
باب داره مسجد - قال - فكنا في المسجد حتى خرج إلينا ‏.‏ فقال إن
تشاءوا أن تدخلوا وإن تشاءوا أن تقعدوا ها هنا ‏.‏ - قال - فقلنا لا
بل نقعد ها هنا فحدثنا ‏.‏ قال حدثني عبد الله بن عمرو بن العاص - رضى
الله عنهما - قال كنت أصوم الدهر وأقرأ القرآن كل ليلة - قال - فإما
ذكرت للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وإما أرسل إلى فأتيته فقال لي ‏"‏ ألم
أخبر أنك تصوم الدهر وتقرأ القرآن كل ليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت بلى يا نبي
الله ولم أرد بذلك إلا الخير ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن بحسبك أن تصوم من كل شهر
ثلاثة أيام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا نبي الله إني أطيق أفضل من ذلك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فإن لزوجك عليك حقا ولزورك عليك حقا ولجسدك عليك حقا - قال - فصم صوم
داود نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فإنه كان أعبد الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
قلت يا نبي الله وما صوم داود قال ‏"‏ كان يصوم يوما ويفطر يوما ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ واقرإ القرآن في كل شهر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا نبي الله إني
أطيق أفضل من ذلك قال ‏"‏ فاقرأه في كل عشرين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا نبي
الله إني أطيق أفضل من ذلك قال ‏"‏ فاقرأه في كل عشر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت
يا نبي الله إني أطيق أفضل من ذلك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاقرأه في كل سبع ولا
تزد على ذلك ‏.‏ فإن لزوجك عليك حقا ولزورك عليك حقا ولجسدك عليك حقا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فشددت فشدد على ‏.‏ قال وقال لي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إنك لا تدري لعلك يطول بك عمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فصرت إلى الذي قال لي
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما كبرت وددت أني كنت قبلت رخصة نبي الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Yahya reported: I and 'Abdullah b. Yazid set out till
we came to Abu Salama. We sent a messenger to him (in his house in
order to inform him about our arrival) and he came to us. There was
a mosque near the door of his house, and we were in that mosque,
till he came out to us. He said: If you like you may enter (the
house) and, if you like, you may sit here (in the mosque). We said:
We would rather sit here and (you) relate to us. He (Yahya) then
narrated that 'Abdullah b Amr b. al-'As (Allah be pleased with
them) told him: I used to observe fast uninterruptedly and recited
the (whole of the) Qur'an every night. It (the uninterrupted
fasting and recital of the Qur'an every night) was mentioned to the
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) or he sent for me, and I
went to him and he said to me: I have been informed that you fast
continuously and recite (the whole of the Qur'an) every night. I
said: Apostle of Allah, it is right, but I covet thereby nothing
but good, whereupon he said: It suffices for you that you should
observe fast for three days during every mouth. I said: Apostle of
Allah, I am capable of doing more than this. He said: Your wife has
a right upon you, your visitor has a right upon you, your body has
a right upon you; so observe the fast of David, the Apostle of
Allah (peace be upon him), for he was the best worshipper of Allah.
I said: Apostle of Allah, what is the fast of David? He said: He
used to fast one day and did not fast the other day. He (also)
said: Recite the Qur'an during every month. I said: Apostle of
Allah, I am capable of doing more than this, whereupon he said:
Recite it in twenty days; recite it in ten days. I said: I am
capable of doing more than this, whereupon he said: Recite it every
week, and do not exceed beyond this, for your wife has a right upon
you, your visitor has a right upon you, your body has a right upon
you. He ('Amr b. 'As) said: I was hard to myself and thus I was put
to hardship. The Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) had told
me: 'You do not know you may live long (thus and bear the hardships
for a long time), and I accepted that which the Apostle of Allah
(may peace be upon him) had told me. When I grew old I wished I had
availed myself of the concession (granted by) the Apostle of Allah
(may-peace be upon him).</english-text>
</hadith>
