<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12755</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2803</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 30367, 20022, 20031, 20022, 11300,
10697</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى التميمي، وقتيبة بن سعيد، جميعا عن
حماد، - قال يحيى أخبرنا حماد بن زيد، - عن غيلان، عن عبد الله بن
معبد الزماني، عن أبي قتادة، رجل أتى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
كيف تصوم فغضب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما رأى عمر - رضى الله
عنه - غضبه قال رضينا بالله ربا وبالإسلام دينا وبمحمد نبيا نعوذ
بالله من غضب الله وغضب رسوله ‏.‏ فجعل عمر - رضى الله عنه - يردد هذا
الكلام حتى سكن غضبه فقال عمر يا رسول الله كيف بمن يصوم الدهر كله
قال ‏"‏ لا صام ولا أفطر - أو قال - لم يصم ولم يفطر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كيف
من يصوم يومين ويفطر يوما قال ‏"‏ ويطيق ذلك أحد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كيف من
يصوم يوما ويفطر يوما قال ‏"‏ ذاك صوم داود عليه السلام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
كيف من يصوم يوما ويفطر يومين قال ‏"‏ وددت أني طوقت ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم
قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ثلاث من كل شهر ورمضان إلى
رمضان فهذا صيام الدهر كله صيام يوم عرفة أحتسب على الله أن يكفر
السنة التي قبله والسنة التي بعده وصيام يوم عاشوراء أحتسب على الله
أن يكفر السنة التي قبله ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Qatada reported that a person came to the Apostle
of Allah (may peace be upon him) and said: How do you observe fast?
The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) felt annoyed. 1560
When 'Umar (Allah be pleased with him) noticed his annoyance, he
said: We are well pleased with Allah as our Lord, with Islam as our
Code of Life, and with Muhammad as our Prophet. We seek refuge with
Allah from the anger of Allah and that of His Messenger. 'Umar kept
on repeating these words till his (the Prophet's) anger calmed
down. Then Umar said: Messenger of Allah. what is the position of
one who perpetually observes fasts? Thereupon he said: He neither
fasted nor broke it, or he said: He did not fast and he did not
break it. He said: What about him who observes fast for two days
and breaks one day. There- upon he said: Is anyone capable of doing
it? He ('Umar) said: What is the position of him who observes fast
for a day and breaks on the other day? Thereupon he (the Holy
Prophet) said: That is the fast of David (peace be upon him). He
('Umar) said: What about him who observes fast one day and breaks
it for two days. Thereupon he (the Messenger of Allah) said: I
wish, I were given strength to observe that. Thereafter he said:
The observance of three days' fast every Month and that of Ramadan
every year is a perpetual fasting. I seek from Allah that fasting
on the day of 'Arafa may atone for the sins of the preceding and
the coming years. and I seek from Allah that fasting on the day of
Ashura may atone for the sins of the preceding year.</english-text>
</hadith>
