<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12813</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2857</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20208, 30553, 20277, 11070, 30556, 20347,
11070, 11029, 11248, 20372</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، ح وحدثنا
عبد بن حميد، أخبرنا محمد بن بكر، قالا أخبرنا ابن جريج، ح وحدثنا علي
بن خشرم، - واللفظ له - أخبرنا عيسى، عن ابن جريج، قال أخبرني عطاء،
أن صفوان بن يعلى بن أمية، أخبره أن يعلى كان يقول لعمر بن الخطاب -
رضى الله عنه - ليتني أرى نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين ينزل عليه
‏.‏ فلما كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالجعرانة وعلى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثوب قد أظل به عليه معه ناس من أصحابه فيهم عمر إذ جاءه رجل
عليه جبة صوف متضمخ بطيب فقال يا رسول الله كيف ترى في رجل أحرم بعمرة
في جبة بعد ما تضمخ بطيب فنظر إليه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ساعة ثم
سكت فجاءه الوحى فأشار عمر بيده إلى يعلى بن أمية تعال ‏.‏ فجاء يعلى
فأدخل رأسه فإذا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم محمر الوجه يغط ساعة ثم سري
عنه فقال ‏"‏ أين الذي سألني عن العمرة آنفا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فالتمس الرجل
فجيء به فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما الطيب الذي بك فاغسله
ثلاث مرات وأما الجبة فانزعها ثم اصنع في عمرتك ما تصنع في حجك ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Safwan b. Ya'la b. Umayya reported that Ya'la used to
say to 'Umar b. Khattab (Allah be pleased with him): Would that I
see revelation descending upon the Apostle of Allah (may peace be
upon him). (Once) when the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him)
was in Ji'rana and there was a cloth which provided shade over him,
and there were his Companions with him. 'Umar being one of them,
there came a person with a cloak of wool on him daubed with perfume
and he said: Messenger of Allah, what about the person who, entered
upon the state of Ihram with a cloak after daub- ing it with
perfume? The Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) looked at him
for a short while, and then became quiet, and revelation began
descending upon him, and 'Umar gestured (with his hand) to Ya'la b
Umayya to come. Ya'la came and he enter- ed his head (beneath the
cloth and saw) the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) with
his face red, and breathing with a snore. Then he felt relieved (of
that burden) and he said: Where is the man who was just asking me
about Umra? The man was searched for and he was brought, and the
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: So far as the
perfume is concerned, wash it three times, and remove the cloak too
(as it was sewn) and do in 'Umra as you do in Hajj.</english-text>
</hadith>
