<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12830</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2875</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11168, 11887</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن سعيد بن أبي
سعيد المقبري، عن عبيد بن جريج، أنه قال لعبد الله بن عمر رضى الله
عنهما يا أبا عبد الرحمن رأيتك تصنع أربعا لم أر أحدا من أصحابك
يصنعها ‏.‏ قال ما هن يا ابن جريج قال رأيتك لا تمس من الأركان إلا
اليمانيين ورأيتك تلبس النعال السبتية ورأيتك تصبغ بالصفرة ورأيتك إذا
كنت بمكة أهل الناس إذا رأوا الهلال ولم تهلل أنت حتى يكون يوم
التروية ‏.‏ فقال عبد الله بن عمر أما الأركان فإني لم أر رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يمس إلا اليمانيين وأما النعال السبتية فإني رأيت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يلبس النعال التي ليس فيها شعر ويتوضأ
فيها فأنا أحب أن ألبسها وأما الصفرة فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يصبغ بها فأنا أحب أن أصبغ بها وأما الإهلال فإني لم أر
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يهل حتى تنبعث به راحلته
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Ubaid b. Juraij said to 'Ahdullah b. 'Umar (Allah be
pleased with them): 'Abd al-Rahman, I find you doing four things
which I do not see anyone among your companions doing. He said: Son
of Juraij, what are these? Thereupon he said: You (while
circumambulating the Ka'ba) do not touch but the two pillars
situated on the side of yaman (south), and I find you wearing the
sandals of tanned leather, and I find you with dyed beard and head,
and I also found that, when you were at Mecca, the people
pronounced Talbiya as they saw the new moon (Dhu'l-Hijja), but you
did not do it till the 8th of Dhu'l-Hijja. Upon this 'Abdullab b.
'Umar said: (So far as the touching of) the pillars is concerned, I
did not see the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) touching
them but only those situated on the side of yaman. (So far asthe
wearing of) the shoes of tanned leather is concerned, I saw the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) wearing shoes without
hair on them, and he (wore them with wet feet) after performing
ablution, and I like to wear them. So far as the yellowness is
concerned, I saw the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
dyeing (head, beard and cloth) with this colour and I love to dye
(my head, beard or cloth) with this colour. And so far as the
pronouncing of Talbiya is concerned, I did not see the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) pronouncing it until his camel
proceeded on (to Dhu'l-Hulaifa).</english-text>
</hadith>
