<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12867</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2912</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30559, 20469, 11524, 11804, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو كامل الجحدري، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن عثمان بن
عبد الله بن موهب، عن عبد الله بن أبي قتادة، عن أبيه، - رضى الله عنه
- قال خرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حاجا وخرجنا معه - قال - فصرف
من أصحابه فيهم أبو قتادة فقال ‏"‏ خذوا ساحل البحر حتى تلقوني ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فأخذوا ساحل البحر ‏.‏ فلما انصرفوا قبل رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أحرموا كلهم إلا أبا قتادة فإنه لم يحرم فبينما هم يسيرون
إذ رأوا حمر وحش فحمل عليها أبو قتادة فعقر منها أتانا فنزلوا فأكلوا
من لحمها - قال - فقالوا أكلنا لحما ونحن محرمون - قال - فحملوا ما
بقي من لحم الأتان فلما أتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالوا يا
رسول الله إنا كنا أحرمنا وكان أبو قتادة لم يحرم فرأينا حمر وحش فحمل
عليها أبو قتادة فعقر منها أتانا فنزلنا فأكلنا من لحمها فقلنا نأكل
لحم صيد ونحن محرمون ‏.‏ فحملنا ما بقي من لحمها ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ هل منكم
أحد أمره أو أشار إليه بشىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قالوا لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فكلوا
ما بقي من لحمها ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abdullah b. Abo. Qatada reported on the ant 'hority
of his father (Allah be pleased with him): The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) set out for Pil- grimage and we also set
out along with him. He (Abu Qatada) said: There proceeded on some
of his Companions and Abu Qatada was (one of them). He, (the Holy
Prophet) said: You proceed along the coastline till you meet me. He
(Abfl Qatida) said: So they proceeded ahead of the Prophet of God
(may peace be upon him), all of them had entered upon the state of
Ihram, except Abu Qatada; he had not put on ]hram. As they went on
they saw a wild ass, and Abu Qatada attacked it and cut off its
hind legs. They got down and ate its meat. They said: We ate meat
In the state of Ihram. They carried the meat that was left of it.
As they came to the Messenger of Allah (way peace be upon him) they
said: Messenger of Allah, we were in the state of Ibrim where as
Abu Qatada was not. We saw a wild ass and Abu Qatada attacked it
and cut off its hind legs. We got down and ate its meat and we thus
ate the meat of a game while we were In the state of Ihram. We have
(carried to you) what was left out of its meat. There upon he (the
holy Prophet) said: Did anyone among you command him (to hunt) or
point to him with anythiny (to do so)? They said: No. There upon he
said: Then eat what is left out of its meat.</english-text>
</hadith>
