<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12924</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2972</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20337, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبدة بن سليمان، عن
هشام، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، - رضى الله عنها - قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في حجة الوداع موافين لهلال ذي الحجة - قالت -
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أراد منكم أن يهل بعمرة
فليهل فلولا أني أهديت لأهللت بعمرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فكان من القوم من
أهل بعمرة ومنهم من أهل بالحج - قالت - فكنت أنا ممن أهل بعمرة فخرجنا
حتى قدمنا مكة فأدركني يوم عرفة وأنا حائض لم أحل من عمرتي فشكوت ذلك
إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ دعي عمرتك وانقضي رأسك وامتشطي
وأهلي بالحج ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ففعلت فلما كانت ليلة الحصبة - وقد قضى الله
حجنا - أرسل معي عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر فأردفني وخرج بي إلى التنعيم
فأهللت بعمرة فقضى الله حجنا وعمرتنا ولم يكن في ذلك هدى ولا صدقة ولا
صوم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported: We went
with the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him? (in his)
Farewell Pilgrimage near the time of the appearance of the new moon
of Dhu'I-Hijja. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
said: He who amongst you intends to put on Ihram for Umra may do
so; bad I not brought sacrificial animal along with me, I would
have put on Ihram for Umra. She (further said). There were some
persons who put on Ihram for Umrs, and some persons who put on
Ibrim for gajj, and 1 was one of those who put on Ihram for Umra.
We went on till we reached Mecca, and on the day of 'Arafa I found
myself In a state of menses, but I did not put off the Ihram for
Umra. I told about (this state of mine) to the Apostle of Allah
(may peace be upon him). whereupon he said: Abandon your 'Umra, and
undo the hair of your head and comb (them), and put on Ihram for
Hajj 'she ('A'isha) said: I did accordingly. When it was the night
at Hasba and Allah enabled us to complete our Hajj, he (the Holy
Prophet) sent with me Abd al-Rahman b. Abu Bakr, and he mounted me
behind him on his camel and took me to Tan'im and I put on Ihram
for 'Umra, and thus Allah enabled us to complete our Hajj and Umra
and (we wore required to observe) neither sacrifice nor alms nor
fasting.</english-text>
</hadith>
