<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12929</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2977</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20443, 20026, 10530, 10535, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني سليمان بن عبيد الله أبو أيوب الغيلاني، حدثنا أبو
عامر عبد الملك، بن عمرو حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي سلمة الماجشون، عن
عبد الرحمن بن القاسم، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، - رضى الله عنها - قالت
خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا نذكر إلا الحج حتى جئنا سرف
فطمثت فدخل على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنا أبكي فقال ‏"‏ ما
يبكيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت والله لوددت أني لم أكن خرجت العام قال ‏"‏ ما لك
لعلك نفست ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هذا شىء كتبه الله على بنات
آدم افعلي ما يفعل الحاج غير أن لا تطوفي بالبيت حتى تطهري ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت فلما قدمت مكة قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأصحابه ‏"‏
اجعلوها عمرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأحل الناس إلا من كان معه الهدى - قالت - فكان
الهدى مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأبي بكر وعمر وذوي اليسارة ثم
أهلوا حين راحوا - قالت - فلما كان يوم النحر طهرت فأمرني رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأفضت - قالت - فأتينا بلحم بقر ‏.‏ فقلت ما هذا
فقالوا أهدى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن نسائه البقر ‏.‏ فلما
كانت ليلة الحصبة قلت يا رسول الله يرجع الناس بحجة وعمرة وأرجع بحجة
قالت فأمر عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر فأردفني على جمله - قالت - فإني
لأذكر وأنا جارية حديثة السن أنعس فتصيب وجهي مؤخرة الرحل حتى جئنا
إلى التنعيم فأهللت منها بعمرة جزاء بعمرة الناس التي اعتمروا
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported: We went
with the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) with no other
aim but that of Hajj till we came (to the place known as) Sarif;
and there I entered in the state of menses. The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) came to me while I was weeping. He said:
What makes you weep? I said: Would that I had not come (for
Pilgrimage) this year. He (the Holy Prophet) said: What has
happened to you? You have perhaps entered the period of menses. I
said: Yes. He said: This is what has been ordained for the
daughters of Adam. Do what a pilgrim does except that you should
not circumambu- late the House, till you are purified (of the
menses). She ('A'isha) said: When I came to Mecca, the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said to his companions: Make this
(Ihram) the Ihram for 'Umra. So the people put off Ihbaim except
those who had sacrificial animals with them. She ('A'isha) said:
The Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) had the sacrificial
animal with him, and so had Abd Bakr, 'Umar and other persons of
means. They (those who had put off lhram again) put on Ihram (for
Hajj) when they marched (towards Mina), and it was the 8th of
Dhu'I-Hijja. She ('A'isha) said: When it was the day of sacrifice
(10th of Dhu'I-Hijia), I was purified, and the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) commanded me and I did the circumambulation
of Ifada. She said that the flesh of cow was sent to us. I said:
What is It? They said: The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) has offered cow as sacrifice on behalf of his wives. When it
was the might at Hasba, I said: Messenger of Allah, people are
coming back from Hajj and Umra, where as I am coming back from Hajj
(alone). She (IA'isha) reported: He (the Holy Prophet) commanded"
Abd al- Rahman b. Abu Bakr to mount me upon his camel behind him.
She ('A'isha) said: I was very young and I well remember that I
dozed oil and my face touched the bind part of the haudaj (camel
litter) till we came to Tan'im, and entered into the state of Ihram
in lieu of Umra (which I for the time being abandoned) and which
the people had performed.</english-text>
</hadith>
