<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12947</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2996</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 30490, 20023, 30367, 20023, 11263,
34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، ومحمد بن رمح، جميعا عن الليث بن
سعد، - قال قتيبة حدثنا ليث، - عن أبي الزبير، عن جابر، - رضى الله
عنه - أنه قال أقبلنا مهلين مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بحج مفرد
وأقبلت عائشة - رضى الله عنها - بعمرة حتى إذا كنا بسرف عركت حتى إذا
قدمنا طفنا بالكعبة والصفا والمروة فأمرنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم أن يحل منا من لم يكن معه هدى - قال - فقلنا حل ماذا قال ‏"‏
الحل كله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فواقعنا النساء وتطيبنا بالطيب ولبسنا ثيابنا وليس
بيننا وبين عرفة إلا أربع ليال ثم أهللنا يوم التروية ثم دخل رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على عائشة - رضى الله عنها - فوجدها تبكي
فقال ‏"‏ ما شانك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت شاني أني قد حضت وقد حل الناس ولم أحلل
ولم أطف بالبيت والناس يذهبون إلى الحج الآن ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إن هذا أمر
كتبه الله على بنات آدم فاغتسلي ثم أهلي بالحج ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلت ووقفت
المواقف حتى إذا طهرت طافت بالكعبة والصفا والمروة ثم قال ‏"‏ قد حللت
من حجك وعمرتك جميعا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت يا رسول الله إني أجد في نفسي أني
لم أطف بالبيت حتى حججت ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاذهب بها يا عبد الرحمن فأعمرها
من التنعيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذلك ليلة الحصبة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir (Allah be pleased with him) said: We, in the
state of lhram, came with the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) for Hajj Mufrad (with the aim of Hajj only), and 'A'isha set
out for Umra, and when we reached Sarif, she (Hadrat A'isha)
entered in the state of monthly period; we proceeded on till we
reached (Mecca) and circumambulated the Ka'ba and ran between
(al-Safa) and al-Marwa; and the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) commanded that one who amongst us had no sacrificial
animal with him should put off Ihram. We said: What does this"
Putting off" imply? He said: Getting out completely from the state
of lhram, (so we put off Ihram), and we turned to our wives and
applied perfume and put on our clothes. and we were at a four
night's distance from 'Arafa. And we again put on Ihram on the day
of Tarwiya (8th of Dhu'l-Hijja). The Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) came to 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) and found
her weeping, and said: What is the matter with you? She said: The
matter is that I have entered in the monthly period, and the people
had put off lhram, but I did not and I did not circumambulate the
House, and the people are going for Hajj now (but I can't go),
whereupon he said: It is the matter which Allah has ordaiucd for
the daughters of Adam, so now take a bath and put on Ihram for
Hajj. She ('A'isha) did accordingly, and stayed at the places of
staying till the monthly period was over. She then circu-
mambulated the House, and (ran between) al-Safa and al-Marwa. He
(the Holy Prophet) then said: Now both your Hajj and 'Umra are
complete, whereupon she said: I feel in my mind that I did not
circumambulate the House till I performed Hajj (I missed the
circumambulation of 'Umra). Thereupon he (Allah's Apostle) said:
'Abd al- Rahman, take her to Tan'im (so as to enable her) to
perform Umra (separately), and it was the night at
Hasba.</english-text>
</hadith>
