<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12955</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3004</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20348, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا ابن نمير، حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا موسى بن نافع،
قال قدمت مكة متمتعا بعمرة قبل التروية بأربعة أيام فقال الناس تصير
حجتك الآن مكية فدخلت على عطاء بن أبي رباح فاستفتيته فقال عطاء حدثني
جابر بن عبد الله الأنصاري - رضى الله عنهما - أنه حج مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم عام ساق الهدى معه وقد أهلوا بالحج مفردا فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أحلوا من إحرامكم فطوفوا بالبيت
وبين الصفا والمروة وقصروا وأقيموا حلالا حتى إذا كان يوم التروية
فأهلوا بالحج واجعلوا التي قدمتم بها متعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا كيف نجعلها
متعة وقد سمينا الحج قال ‏"‏ افعلوا ما آمركم به فإني لولا أني سقت
الهدى لفعلت مثل الذي أمرتكم به ولكن لا يحل مني حرام حتى يبلغ الهدى
محله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلوا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Musa b. Nafi reported: I came to Mecca as a
Mutamattil for Umra (per- forming Umra first and then putting off
lhram and again entering into the state of Ihram for Hajj) four
days before the day of Tarwiya (i. e. on tee 4th of Dhu'l-Hijja).
Thereupon the people said: Now yours is the Hajj of the Meccans. I
went to 'Ata' b. Abi Rabah and asked his religious verdict. Ata'
said: Jabir b. 'Abdullah al'Ans-ari (Allah be pleased wa'th them)
narrated to me that he peirforfned Hajj with the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) in the year when he took sacrificial
animals with him (i. e. during the 10th year of Hijra known as the
Farewell Pilgrimage) and they had put on Ihram for Hajj only (as
Mufrid). The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Put
off Ihram and circumambulate the House, and (run) between al-Safa
and al-Marwa. and get your hair cut and stay as non-Muhrims. When
it was the day of Tarwiya, then put on Ihram for Hajj and make
lhram for Mut'a (you had put on Ihram i f or Hajj, but take it off
af ter perf orming Umra and then again put on Ihram for Hajj). They
said: How should we make it Mut'a although we entered upon lhram in
the name of Hajj? He said: Do whatever I command you to do. Had I
not brought sacrificial animals with me, I would have done as I
have commanded you to do. But it is not permissible for me to put
off Ihram till tLe sacrifice is offered. Then they also did
accordingly.</english-text>
</hadith>
