<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13044</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3096</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20028, 11067, 11028</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، أخبرنا جرير، عن منصور، عن
مجاهد، قال دخلت أنا وعروة بن الزبير المسجد، فإذا عبد الله بن عمر
جالس إلى حجرة عائشة والناس يصلون الضحى في المسجد فسألناه عن صلاتهم
فقال بدعة ‏.‏ فقال له عروة يا أبا عبد الرحمن كم اعتمر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال أربع عمر إحداهن في رجب ‏.‏ فكرهنا أن نكذبه ونرد
عليه وسمعنا استنان عائشة في الحجرة ‏.‏ فقال عروة ألا تسمعين يا أم
المؤمنين إلى ما يقول أبو عبد الرحمن فقالت وما يقول قال يقول اعتمر
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أربع عمر إحداهن في رجب ‏.‏ فقالت يرحم الله
أبا عبد الرحمن ما اعتمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلا وهو معه
وما اعتمر في رجب قط ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mujihid reported: I and 'Urwa h Zubair entered the
mosque and there found 'Abdullah b. 'Umar sitting near the
apartment of IA'isha and the people were observing the forenood"
prayer (when the sun bad sufficiently risen). We asked him about
their prayer, and he said: It is bid'a (innovation), Urwa said to
him: Abd al-Rahman, how many, 'Umras had Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) performed? He said: Four Umras, one he performed
during the month of Rajab. We were reluctant either to belie him or
reject him. We heard the noise of brushing of her teeth by 'A'isha
in her apartment. 'Urwa said: Mother of the Faithful, are you not
hearing what Abfi 'Abd al-Rahman is saying? She said: What is he
saying? Thereupon he ('Urwa) said: He (Ibn 'Umar) states that
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) performed four Umras and
one of them during the month of Rajab. Thereupon she remarked: May
Allah have merely upon Abu 'Abd al-Rahman. Never did Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) perform 'Umra in which he did not
accompany him, and he (Allah's Apostle) never performed 'Umra
during the month of Rajab.</english-text>
</hadith>
