<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13062</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3114</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30559, 20256, 11286, 3660</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كامل، فضيل بن حسين الجحدري حدثنا عبد الواحد
بن زياد، حدثنا الجريري، عن أبي الطفيل، قال قلت لابن عباس أرأيت هذا
الرمل بالبيت ثلاثة أطواف ومشى أربعة أطواف أسنة هو فإن قومك يزعمون
أنه سنة ‏.‏ قال فقال صدقوا وكذبوا ‏.‏ قال قلت ما قولك صدقوا وكذبوا
قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قدم مكة فقال المشركون إن محمدا
وأصحابه لا يستطيعون أن يطوفوا بالبيت من الهزال وكانوا يحسدونه ‏.‏
قال فأمرهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يرملوا ثلاثا ويمشوا
أربعا ‏.‏ قال قلت له أخبرني عن الطواف بين الصفا والمروة راكبا أسنة
هو فإن قومك يزعمون أنه سنة ‏.‏ قال صدقوا وكذبوا ‏.‏ قال قلت وما
قولك صدقوا وكذبوا قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كثر عليه
الناس يقولون هذا محمد هذا محمد ‏.‏ حتى خرج العواتق من البيوت ‏.‏
قال وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا يضرب الناس بين يديه فلما
كثر عليه ركب والمشى والسعى أفضل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Tufail reported: I said to Ibn Abbas (Allah be
pleased with them): Do you think that walking swiftly round the
House in three circuits, and just walking in four circuits is the
Sunnah (of the Holy Prophet), for your people say that it is
Sunnah? Thereupon he (Ibn 'Abbas) said: They have told the truth
and the lie (too). I said: What do your words" They have told the
truth and the lie (too)" imply? Thereupon he said: Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) came to Mecca and the polytheists
said that Mubammad and his Companions had emaciated and would,
therefore, be unable to circumambulate the House; and they felt
jealous of him (the Holy Prophet). (It was due to this) that
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) commanded them to walk
swiftly in three (circuits) and walk (normally) in four. I said to
him: Inform me if it is Sunnah to observe Tawaf between al-Safa and
al-Marwa while riding, for your people look upon it as Sunnah. He
(Ibn Abbas) said: They have told the truth and the lie too. I said:
What do your words" They have told the truth and the lie tool,
iMply? He said: as Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had
come to Mecca, there was such a large gathering of people around
him that even the virgins had come out of their houses (to catch a
glimpse of his face). and they were saying: He is Muhammad; He is
Muhammad. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) (was so gentle
and kind) that the people were not beaten back (to make way) in
front of him. When there was a; throng (of people) around him, he
rode (the she-camel) but walking and trotting is, however,
better.</english-text>
</hadith>
