<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13094</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3146</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 30367, 20208, 30399, 20155, 11535, 11211,
50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وقتيبة بن سعيد، وابن، حجر قالوا
حدثنا إسماعيل، ح. وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، - واللفظ له - قال أخبرنا
إسماعيل بن جعفر، عن محمد بن، أبي حرملة عن كريب، مولى ابن عباس عن
أسامة بن زيد، قال ردفت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من عرفات فلما
بلغ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الشعب الأيسر الذي دون المزدلفة
أناخ فبال ثم جاء فصببت عليه الوضوء فتوضأ وضوءا خفيفا ثم قلت الصلاة
يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ الصلاة أمامك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فركب رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم حتى أتى المزدلفة فصلى ثم ردف الفضل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم غداة جمع. قال كريب فأخبرني عبد الله بن عباس، عن
الفضل، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لم يزل يلبي حتى بلغ الجمرة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Usama b. Zaid (Allah be pleased with him) reported: I
was sitting behind Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) on the
riding animal from 'Arafat. As Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) reached the left side of the mountain which was situated near
Muzdalifa, he made the camel kneel down and made water and then
came back. I poured water and he, performed light ablution. I then
said: Messenger of Allah, it is time for prayer. Thereupon Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: The prayer awaits you (at
the next station, Muzdalifa). Allah's Messenger (may peaced be upon
him) rode on until he came to Muzdalifa and observed prayer. Then
al-Fadl (Allah be pleased with him) sat behind Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) and reached (Muzdalifa) in the morning.
Kuraib said: 'Abdullah b. 'Abbas (Allah be pleased with them)
narrated from al-Fadl (Allah be pleased with him) that Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) continued pronouncing Talbiya
until he reached al-Jamara (al-'Aqaba).</english-text>
</hadith>
