<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13263</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3310</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>38487, 20277, 11070, 2007</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن حاتم، حدثنا محمد بن بكر، أخبرنا ابن
جريج، قال سمعت عبد، الله بن عبيد بن عمير والوليد بن عطاء يحدثان عن
الحارث بن عبد الله بن أبي ربيعة، قال عبد الله بن عبيد وفد الحارث بن
عبد الله على عبد الملك بن مروان في خلافته فقال عبد الملك ما أظن أبا
خبيب - يعني ابن الزبير - سمع من عائشة ما كان يزعم أنه سمعه منها ‏.‏
قال الحارث بلى أنا سمعته منها ‏.‏ قال سمعتها تقول ماذا قال قالت قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن قومك استقصروا من بنيان البيت
ولولا حداثة عهدهم بالشرك أعدت ما تركوا منه فإن بدا لقومك من بعدي أن
يبنوه فهلمي لأريك ما تركوا منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأراها قريبا من سبعة أذرع
‏.‏ هذا حديث عبد الله بن عبيد وزاد عليه الوليد بن عطاء قال النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ولجعلت لها بابين موضوعين في الأرض شرقيا
وغربيا وهل تدرين لم كان قومك رفعوا بابها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت قلت لا ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ تعززا أن لا يدخلها إلا من أرادوا فكان الرجل إذا هو أراد أن
يدخلها يدعونه يرتقي حتى إذا كاد أن يدخل دفعوه فسقط ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عبد
الملك للحارث أنت سمعتها تقول هذا قال نعم‏.‏ قال فنكت ساعة بعصاه ثم
قال وددت أني تركته وما تحمل.</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. 'Ubaid reported that Harith b. 'Abdullah
led a deputation to 'Abd al-Malik b. Marwan during his caliphate.
'Abd al-Malik said: I do riot think that Abu Khubaib (i. e. Ibn
Zabair) had heard from 'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) (about
the intended wish of the Holy Prophet [may peace be upon him) In
regard to the alteration of the Ka'ba). Harith said: Yes, I myself
did hear from her. He ('Abd al-Malik) said: Well, tell me what you
heard from her. He stated that she (Hadrat 'A'isha) had said that
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) remarked: Verily your
people have reduced (the area) of the House from its (original
foundations, and if they had not recently abandoned polytheism (and
embraced Islam) I would have reversed it to (those foundations)
which they had left out of it. nd if your people would take
initiative after me in rebuilding it, then come along with me so
that I should show you what they have left out of it. He showed her
about fifteen cubits of area from the side of Hatim (that they had
separated). This is the narration transmitted by 'Abdullah b.
Ubaid. Walid b. 'Ata' has, however, made this addition to it:"
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: I would have made two
doors on the level of the ground (facing) the east and the west. Do
you know why your people raised the level of its door (i. e. the
door of the Ka'ba)? She said: No. He said: (They did it) out of
vanity so that (they might be in a position) to grant admittance to
him only whom they wished. When a person intended to get into it,
they let him climb (the stairs), and as he was about to enter, they
pushed him and he fell down." 'Abd al-Malik said to Harith; Did you
yourself hear her saying this? He said: Yes. He (Harith) said that
he ('Abd al-Malik) scratched the ground with his staff for some
time and then said: I wish I had left his (Ibn Zubair's) work
there.</english-text>
</hadith>
