<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13332</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3372</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30313, 20340, 20240, 11449, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق بن منصور، أخبرنا عبيد الله بن موسى، عن
شيبان، عن يحيى، أخبرني أبو سلمة، أنه سمع أبا هريرة، يقول إن خزاعة
قتلوا رجلا من بني ليث عام فتح مكة بقتيل منهم قتلوه فأخبر بذلك رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فركب راحلته فخطب فقال ‏"‏ إن الله عز وجل
حبس عن مكة الفيل وسلط عليها رسوله والمؤمنين ألا وإنها لم تحل لأحد
قبلي ولن تحل لأحد بعدي ألا وإنها أحلت لي ساعة من النهار ألا وإنها
ساعتي هذه حرام لا يخبط شوكها ولا يعضد شجرها ولا يلتقط ساقطتها إلا
منشد ومن قتل له قتيل فهو بخير النظرين إما أن يعطى - يعني الدية -
وإما أن يقاد أهل القتيل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فجاء رجل من أهل اليمن يقال له
أبو شاه فقال اكتب لي يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اكتبوا لأبي شاه ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقال رجل من قريش إلا الإذخر فإنا نجعله في بيوتنا وقبورنا ‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إلا الإذخر ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira (Allah be pleased with him) reported: The
people of the Khuza'ah tribe killed a man of the tribe of Laith in
the Year of Victory as a retaliation for one whom they had killed
(whom the people of the tribe of Laith had killed). It was reported
to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). He mounted his camel
and delivered this address: Verily Allah, the Exalted and Majestic,
held back the Ele- phants from Mecca, and gave its domination to
His Messenger and believers. Behold, it was not violable for anyone
before me and it will not be violable for anyone after me. Behold,
it was made violable for me for an hour of a day; and at this very
hour it has again been made inviolable (for me as well as for
others). So its thorns are not to be cut, its trees are not to be
lopped, and (no one is allowed to) pick up a thing dropped, but the
one who makes an announcement of it. And one whose fellow is killed
is allowed to opt between two alternatives: either he should
receive blood-money or get the life of the (murderer) in return. He
(the narrator said): A person from the Yemen, who was called Abu
Shah, came to him and said: Messenger of Allah, write it down for
me, whereupon he (Allah's Messenger) said: Write it down for Abu
Shah. One of the persons from among the Quraish also said: Except
Idhkhir, for we use it in our houses ant our graves. Thereupon
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Except
Idhkhir.</english-text>
</hadith>
