<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13354</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3393</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Pilgrimage - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30022, 20354, 30216, 20354, 11060, 11322,
11405</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وزهير بن حرب، وأبو كريب
جميعا عن أبي معاوية، - قال أبو كريب حدثنا أبو معاوية، - حدثنا
الأعمش، عن إبراهيم التيمي، عن أبيه، قال خطبنا علي بن أبي طالب فقال
من زعم أن عندنا، شيئا نقرأه إلا كتاب الله وهذه الصحيفة - قال وصحيفة
معلقة في قراب سيفه - فقد كذب فيها أسنان الإبل وأشياء من الجراحات
وفيها قال النبي صلى الله تعالى عليه وسلم ‏"‏ المدينة حرم ما بين عير
إلى ثور فمن أحدث فيها حدثا أو آوى محدثا فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة
والناس أجمعين لا يقبل الله منه يوم القيامة صرفا ولا عدلا وذمة
المسلمين واحدة يسعى بها أدناهم ومن ادعى إلى غير أبيه أو انتمى إلى
غير مواليه فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين لا يقبل الله منه
يوم القيامة صرفا ولا عدلا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وانتهى حديث أبي بكر وزهير عند
قوله ‏"‏ يسعى بها أدناهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولم يذكرا ما بعده وليس في حديثهما
معلقة في قراب سيفه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibrahim al-Taimi reported on the authority of his
father: 'Ali b. Abi Talib (Allah be pleased with him) addressed us
and said: He who thought that we have besides the Holy Qur'an
anything else that we recite, he told a lie. And this document
which is hanging by the sheath of the sword contains but the ages
of the camels, and the nature of the wounds. He (Hadrat 'Ali)
reported Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) as saying: Medina
is sacred from 'Air to Thaur; So if anyone makes an innovation or
accommodates an innovator, the curse of Allah, the angels, and all
persons will fall upon him, and Allah will not accept any
obligatory or supererogatory act as recompense from them. And the
protection granted by the Muslims is one and must be respected by
the humblest of them. If anyone makes a false claim to paternity,
or being a client of other than his own masters, there is upon him
the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people. Allah will not
accept from him any recompense in the form of obligatory acts or
supererogatory acts. The hadith transmitted on the authority of Abu
Bakr and Zabair ends with (these words): The humblest among them
should respect it; and what follows after it is not mentioned
there, and in the hadith transmitted by them (these words are) not
found: (The document was hanging) on the sheath of his
sword.</english-text>
</hadith>
