<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13447</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3486</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30559, 11894, 11847</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كامل، فضيل بن حسين الجحدري حدثنا بشر، - يعني
ابن مفضل - حدثنا عمارة بن غزية، عن الربيع بن سبرة، أن أباه، غزا مع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فتح مكة قال فأقمنا بها خمس عشرة -
ثلاثين بين ليلة ويوم - فأذن لنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
متعة النساء فخرجت أنا ورجل من قومي ولي عليه فضل في الجمال وهو قريب
من الدمامة مع كل واحد منا برد فبردي خلق وأما برد ابن عمي فبرد جديد
غض حتى إذا كنا بأسفل مكة أو بأعلاها فتلقتنا فتاة مثل البكرة
العنطنطة فقلنا هل لك أن يستمتع منك أحدنا قالت وماذا تبذلان فنشر كل
واحد منا برده فجعلت تنظر إلى الرجلين ويراها صاحبي تنظر إلى عطفها
فقال إن برد هذا خلق وبردي جديد غض ‏.‏ فتقول برد هذا لا بأس به ‏.‏
ثلاث مرار أو مرتين ثم استمتعت منها فلم أخرج حتى حرمها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Rabi' b. Sabra reported that his father went on an
expedition with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) during
the Victory of Mecca, and we stayed there for fifteen days (i. e.
for thirteen full days and a day and a night), and Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) permitted us to contract
temporary marriage with women. So I and another person of my tribe
went out, and I was more handsome than he, whereas he was almost
ugly. Each one of us had a cloaks, My cloak was worn out, whereas
the cloak of my cousin was quite new. As we reached the lower or
the upper side of Mecca, we came across a young woman like a young
smart long-necked she-camel. We said: Is it possible that one of us
may contract temporary marriage with you? She said: What will you
give me as a dower? Each one of us spread his cloak. She began to
cast a glance on both the persons. My companion also looked at her
when she was casting a glance at her side and he said: This cloak
of his is worn out, whereas my cloak is quite new. She, however,
said twice or thrice: There is no harm in (accepting) this cloak
(the old one). So I contracted temporary marriage with her, and I
did not come out (of this) until Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) declared it forbidden.</english-text>
</hadith>
