<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13456</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3495</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني حرملة بن يحيى، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس، قال
ابن شهاب أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أن عبد الله بن الزبير، قام بمكة
فقال إن ناسا - أعمى الله قلوبهم كما أعمى أبصارهم - يفتون بالمتعة -
يعرض برجل - فناداه فقال إنك لجلف جاف فلعمري لقد كانت المتعة تفعل
على عهد إمام المتقين - يريد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - فقال له
ابن الزبير فجرب بنفسك فوالله لئن فعلتها لأرجمنك بأحجارك ‏.‏ قال ابن
شهاب فأخبرني خالد بن المهاجر بن سيف الله أنه بينا هو جالس عند رجل
جاءه رجل فاستفتاه في المتعة فأمره بها فقال له ابن أبي عمرة الأنصاري
مهلا ‏.‏ قال ما هي والله لقد فعلت في عهد إمام المتقين ‏.‏ قال ابن
أبي عمرة إنها كانت رخصة في أول الإسلام لمن اضطر إليها كالميتة والدم
ولحم الخنزير ثم أحكم الله الدين ونهى عنها ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب وأخبرني
ربيع بن سبرة الجهني أن أباه قال قد كنت استمتعت في عهد رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم امرأة من بني عامر ببردين أحمرين ثم نهانا رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم عن المتعة ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب وسمعت ربيع بن سبرة
يحدث ذلك عمر بن عبد العزيز وأنا جالس ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Urwa b. Zabair reported that 'Abdullah b. Zubair
(Allah be pleased with him) stood up (and delivered an address) in
Mecca saying: Allah has made blind the hearts of some people as He
has deprived them of eyesight that they give religious verdict in
favour of temporary marriage, while he was alluding to a person
(Ibn 'Abbas). Ibn Abbas called him and said: You are an uncouth
person, devoid of sense. By my life, Mut'a was practised during the
lifetime of the leader of the pious (he meant Allah's Messenger,
may peace be upon him), and Ibn Zubair said to him: just do it
yourselves, and by Allah, if you do that I will stone you with your
stones. Ibn Shihab said. Khalid b. Muhajir b. Saifullah informed
me: While I was sitting in the company of a person, a person came
to him and he asked for a religious verdict about Mut'a and he
permitted him to do it. Ibn Abu 'Amrah al-Ansari (Allah be pleased
with him) said to him: Be gentle. It was permitted in- the early
days of Islam, (for one) who was driven to it under the stress of
necessity just as (the eating of) carrion and the blood and flesh
of swine and then Allah intensified (the commands of) His religion
and prohibited it (altogether). Ibn Shihab reported: Rabi' b. Sabra
told me that his father (Sabra) said: I contracted temporary
marriage with a woman of Banu 'Amir for two cloaks during the
lifetime of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) ; then he
forbade us to do Mut'a. Ibn Shihab said: I heard Rabi' b. Sabra
narrating it to Umar b. 'Abd al-'Aziz and I was sitting
there.</english-text>
</hadith>
