<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13513</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3552</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20185, 11172, 399, 30367, 20165, 11172,
399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد الثقفي، حدثنا يعقوب، - يعني ابن
عبد الرحمن القاري - عن أبي حازم، عن سهل بن سعد، ح وحدثناه قتيبة،
حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي حازم، عن أبيه، عن سهل بن سعد، الساعدي قال
جاءت امرأة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت يا رسول الله جئت
أهب لك نفسي ‏.‏ فنظر إليها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصعد النظر
فيها وصوبه ثم طأطأ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رأسه فلما رأت
المرأة أنه لم يقض فيها شيئا جلست فقام رجل من أصحابه فقال يا رسول
الله إن لم يكن لك بها حاجة فزوجنيها ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ فهل عندك من شىء
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال لا والله يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اذهب إلى أهلك فانظر
هل تجد شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع فقال لا والله ما وجدت شيئا ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ انظر ولو خاتما من حديد ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فذهب ثم رجع ‏.‏ فقال لا والله يا رسول الله ولا خاتما من حديد ‏.‏
ولكن هذا إزاري - قال سهل ما له رداء - فلها نصفه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما تصنع بإزارك إن لبسته لم يكن عليها منه شىء
وإن لبسته لم يكن عليك منه شىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجلس الرجل حتى إذا طال مجلسه
قام فرآه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم موليا فأمر به فدعي فلما جاء
قال ‏"‏ ماذا معك من القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال معي سورة كذا وسورة كذا -
عددها ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ تقرؤهن عن ظهر قلبك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
اذهب فقد ملكتكها بما معك من القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ هذا حديث ابن أبي حازم
وحديث يعقوب يقاربه في اللفظ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl b. Sa'd al-Sa'idi (Allah be pleased with him)
reported: A woman came to Allah's Messenger. (may peace be upon
him) and said: Messenger of Allah, I have come to you to entrust
myself to you (you may contract my marriage with anyone at your
discretion). Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) saw her and
cast a glance at her from head to foot. Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) then lowered his head. When the woman saw that
he had made no decision in regard to her, she sat down. There stood
up a person from amongst his companions and said: Messenger of
Allah, marry her to me if you have no need of her. He (the Prophet)
said: is there anything with you (which you con give as a dower)?
He said: No, Messenger of Allah, by Allah I have nothing. Thereupon
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Go to your people
(family) and see if you can find something. He returned and said: I
have found nothing. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
said: See even if it is an iron ring. He went and returned and
said: No, by Allah, not even an iron ring, but only this lower
garment of mine (Sahl said that he had no upper garment), half of
which (I am prepared to part with) for her. Thereupon Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: How can your lower garment
serve your purpose, for it you wear it, she would not be able to
make any use of it and if she wears it there would not be anything
on you? The man sat down and as the sitting prolonged he stood up
(in disappointment) and as he was going back Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) commanded (him) to be called back, and as he
came, he said to him: Do you know any part of the Qur'an? He said:
I know such and such surahs (and he counted them), whereupon he ()
said: Can you recite them from heart (from your memory)? He said:
Yes, whereupon he (Allah's Messenger) said: Go, I have given her to
you in marriage for the part of the Qur'an which you
know.</english-text>
</hadith>
