<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13523</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3563</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20208, 11295, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا إسماعيل، - يعني ابن علية - عن
عبد العزيز، عن أنس، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غزا خيبر قال
فصلينا عندها صلاة الغداة بغلس فركب نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وركب
أبو طلحة وأنا رديف أبي طلحة فأجرى نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
زقاق خيبر وإن ركبتي لتمس فخذ نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وانحسر
الإزار عن فخذ نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فإني لأرى بياض فخذ نبي
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما دخل القرية قال ‏"‏ الله أكبر خربت خيبر
إنا إذا نزلنا بساحة قوم فساء صباح المنذرين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالها ثلاث مرات
قال وقد خرج القوم إلى أعمالهم فقالوا محمد والله ‏.‏ قال عبد العزيز
وقال بعض أصحابنا محمد والخميس ‏.‏ قال وأصبناها عنوة وجمع السبى
فجاءه دحية فقال يا رسول الله أعطني جارية من السبى ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اذهب
فخذ جارية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأخذ صفية بنت حيى فجاء رجل إلى نبي الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال يا نبي الله أعطيت دحية صفية بنت حيى سيد قريظة
والنضير ما تصلح إلا لك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ادعوه بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فجاء بها
فلما نظر إليها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ خذ جارية من السبى
غيرها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وأعتقها وتزوجها ‏.‏ فقال له ثابت يا أبا حمزة ما
أصدقها قال نفسها أعتقها وتزوجها حتى إذا كان بالطريق جهزتها له أم
سليم فأهدتها له من الليل فأصبح النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عروسا فقال
‏"‏ من كان عنده شىء فليجئ به ‏"‏ قال وبسط نطعا قال فجعل الرجل يجيء
بالأقط وجعل الرجل يجيء بالتمر وجعل الرجل يجيء بالسمن فحاسوا حيسا
‏.‏ فكانت وليمة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas (Allah be pleased with him) reported that
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) set out on an expedition
to Khaibar and we observed our morning prayer in early hours of the
dawn. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) then mounted
and so did Abu Talha ride, and I was seating myself behind Abu
Talha. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) moved in the narrow
street of Khaibar (and we rode so close to each other in the
street) that my knee touched the leg of Allah's Apostle (may peace
be upon him). (A part of the) lower garment of Allah's Apostle (may
peace be upon him) slipped from his leg and I could see the
whiteness of the leg of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him). As
he entered the habitation he called: Allahu Akbar (Allah is the
Greatest). Khaibar is ruined. And when we get down in the valley of
a people evil is the morning of the warned ones. He repeated it
thrice. In the meanwhile the people went out for their work, and
said: By Allah, Muhammad (has come). Abd al-'Aziz or some of our
companions said: Muhammad and the army (have come). He said: We
took it (the territory of Khaibar) by force, and there were
gathered the prisoners of war. There came Dihya and he said:
Messenger of Allah, bestow upon me a girl from among the prisoners.
He said: Go and get any girl. He made a choice for Safiyya daughter
of Huyayy (b. Akhtab). There came a person to Allah's Apostle (may
peace be upon him) and said: Apostle of Allah, you have bestowed
Safiyya bint Huyayy, the chief of Quraiza and al-Nadir, upon Dihya
and she is worthy of you only. He said: Call him along with her. So
he came along with her. When Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon
him) saw her he said: Take any other woman from among the
prisoners. He (the narrator) said: He (the Holy Prophet) then
granted her emancipation and married her. Thabit said to him: Abu
Hamza, how much dower did he (the Holy Prophet) give to her? He
said: He granted her freedom and then married her. On the way Umm
Sulaim embellished her and then sent her to him (the Holy Prophet)
at night. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) appeared as a
bridegroom in the morning. He (the Holy Prophet) said: He who has
anything (to eat) should bring that. Then the cloth was spread. A
person came with cheese, another came with dates, and still another
came with refined butter, and they prepared hais and that was the
wedding feast of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him)</english-text>
</hadith>
