<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13534</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3581</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20121, 20115, 11113, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني محمد بن رافع، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، حدثنا معمر، عن
أبي عثمان، عن أنس، قال لما تزوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زينب أهدت
له أم سليم حيسا في تور من حجارة فقال أنس فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اذهب فادع لي من لقيت من المسلمين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فدعوت له من
لقيت فجعلوا يدخلون عليه فيأكلون ويخرجون ووضع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم يده على الطعام فدعا فيه وقال فيه ما شاء الله أن يقول ولم أدع
أحدا لقيته إلا دعوته فأكلوا حتى شبعوا وخرجوا وبقي طائفة منهم
فأطالوا عليه الحديث فجعل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يستحيي منهم أن
يقول لهم شيئا فخرج وتركهم في البيت فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ يا أيها
الذين آمنوا لا تدخلوا بيوت النبي إلا أن يؤذن لكم إلى طعام غير
ناظرين إناه‏}‏ قال قتادة غير متحينين طعاما ولكن إذا دعيتم فادخلوا
حتى بلغ ‏{‏ ذلكم أطهر لقلوبكم وقلوبهن‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas (Allah be pleased with him) reported: When
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) contracted marriage with
Zainab (Allah be pleased with bet), Umm Sulaim sent him hats in a
vessel of stone as a gift. Anas stated that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said to him: Go and invite on my behalf all the
Muslims whom you meet. So I invited on his behalf everyone whom I
met. They entered (his house) and they ate and went out. And
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had kept his hand on the
food, and he invoked blessing on that, and said whatever Allah
wished him to say, and none whom I met was left uninvited. They ate
to their fill and went out, but a group among them remained there
and was engaged in lengthy discussion. Allah's Apostle (may peace
be upon him) felt shy of saying them anything. So he went out and
left them in his house and Allah the Great and Majestic revealed
this verse:" 0 you who believe, enter not the houses of the Prophet
unless permission is given to you for a meal, not waiting for its
cooking being finished." Qatada (instead of using the word Ghaira
Nazirina) used the word Ghaira Mutahayyinina (i. e. not waiting for
the time of the food). But when you are invited, enter..." up to
this verse. This is purer for your hearts and their
hearts.</english-text>
</hadith>
