<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13531</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3578</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20288, 11289, 11313, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن حبيب الحارثي، وعاصم بن النضر التيمي،
ومحمد بن عبد الأعلى، كلهم عن معتمر، - واللفظ لابن حبيب - حدثنا
معتمر بن سليمان، قال سمعت أبي، حدثنا أبو مجلز، عن أنس بن مالك، قال
لما تزوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زينب بنت جحش دعا القوم فطعموا ثم
جلسوا يتحدثون - قال - فأخذ كأنه يتهيأ للقيام فلم يقوموا فلما رأى
ذلك قام فلما قام قام من قام من القوم ‏.‏ زاد عاصم وابن عبد الأعلى
في حديثهما قال فقعد ثلاثة وإن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم جاء ليدخل
فإذا القوم جلوس ثم إنهم قاموا فانطلقوا - قال - فجئت فأخبرت النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم أنهم قد انطلقوا - قال - فجاء حتى دخل فذهبت أدخل
فألقى الحجاب بيني وبينه - قال - وأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ يا أيها الذين
آمنوا لا تدخلوا بيوت النبي إلا أن يؤذن لكم إلى طعام غير ناظرين
إناه‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏ إن ذلكم كان عند الله عظيما‏}‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik (Allah be pleased with him) reported:
When Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) married Zainab bint
jahsh, he invited people (to the wedding feast) and they ate food.
They then sat there and entered into conversation. He (the Holy
Prophet) made a stir as if he was preparing to stand up, but (the
persons busy in talking) did not stand up. When he (the Holy
Prophet) saw it, he stood up and when he did so, some other persons
stood up. 'Asim and Abd al-A'la in their narrations made this
addition: Three (persons) sat there, and Allah's Apostle (may peace
be upon him) came there to enter (the apartment) but he found the
people sitting there. Then they stood up and went away. He said:
Then I came and informed Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
that they had gone away. He (the Holy Prophet) then came there
until he entered (the apartment). I also went and was about to
enter, when he hung a curtain between me and him (and it was on
this occasion that) Allah, the Exalted and Majestic, revealed this
verse:" O you who believe, enter not the houses of the Prophet
unless permission is given to you for a meal, not waiting for its
cooking being finished to the (words)" Surely this is serious in
the sight of Allah" (xxxiii. 53).</english-text>
</hadith>
