<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13527</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3573</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20426, 20160, 19, 20214, 20236, 11269,
19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا شبابة، حدثنا سليمان،
عن ثابث، عن أنس، ح وحدثني به عبد الله بن هاشم بن حيان، - واللفظ له
- حدثنا بهز، حدثنا سليمان، بن المغيرة عن ثابت، حدثنا أنس، قال صارت
صفية لدحية في مقسمه وجعلوا يمدحونها عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم - قال - ويقولون ما رأينا في السبى مثلها - قال - فبعث إلى دحية
فأعطاه بها ما أراد ثم دفعها إلى أمي فقال ‏"‏ أصلحيها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم
خرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من خيبر حتى إذا جعلها في ظهره نزل
ثم ضرب عليها القبة فلما أصبح قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
من كان عنده فضل زاد فليأتنا به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فجعل الرجل يجيء بفضل
التمر وفضل السويق حتى جعلوا من ذلك سوادا حيسا فجعلوا يأكلون من ذلك
الحيس ويشربون من حياض إلى جنبهم من ماء السماء - قال - فقال أنس
فكانت تلك وليمة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عليها - قال - فانطلقنا
حتى إذا رأينا جدر المدينة هششنا إليها فرفعنا مطينا ورفع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم مطيته - قال - وصفية خلفه قد أردفها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم - قال - فعثرت مطية رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصرع
وصرعت قال فليس أحد من الناس ينظر إليه ولا إليها حتى قام رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فسترها - قال - فأتيناه فقال ‏"‏ لم نضر ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال فدخلنا المدينة فخرج جواري نسائه يتراءينها ويشمتن بصرعتها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas, (Allah be pleased with him) reported: Safiyya
(Allah be pleased with her) fell to the lot of Dihya in the spoils
of war, and they praised her in the presence of Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) and said: We have not seen the like of her
among the captives of war. He sent (a messenger) to Dihya and he
gave him whatever he demanded. He then sent her to my mother and
asked her to embellish her. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) then got out of Khaibar until when he was on the other side of
it, he halted, and a tent was pitched for him. When it was morning
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: He who has surplus
of provision with him should bring that to us. Some persons would
bring the surplus of dates, and the other surplus of mush of barley
until there became a heap of bals. They began to eat the hais and
began to drink out of the pond which had the water of rainfall in
it and which was situated by their side. Anas said that that
constituted the wedding feast of Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him). He (further) said: We proceeded until we saw the walls
of Medina, and we were delighted. We made our mounts run quickly
and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) also made his mount
run quickly. And Safiyya (Allah be pleased with her) was at his
back, and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had seated her
behind him. The camel of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
stumbled and he (the Holy Prophet) fell down and she also fell
down. And none among the people was seeing him and her, until
Allah's Messeuger (may peace be upon him) stood up and he covered
her, and we came to him and he said: We have received no injury. We
entered Medina and there came out the young ladies of the
household. They saw her (hadrat Safiyya) and blamed her for falling
down.</english-text>
</hadith>
