<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13666</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>18</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3713</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Suckling - كتاب الرضاع</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20468, 11429, 11052, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، أخبرنا هشيم، عن سيار، عن الشعبي،
عن جابر بن عبد، الله قال كنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
غزاة فلما أقبلنا تعجلت على بعير لي قطوف فلحقني راكب خلفي فنخس بعيري
بعنزة كانت معه فانطلق بعيري كأجود ما أنت راء من الإبل فالتفت فإذا
أنا برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ما يعجلك يا جابر ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قلت يا رسول الله إني حديث عهد بعرس ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أبكرا تزوجتها أم
ثيبا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت بل ثيبا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هلا جارية تلاعبها وتلاعبك
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فلما قدمنا المدينة ذهبنا لندخل فقال ‏"‏ أمهلوا حتى ندخل
ليلا - أى عشاء - كى تمتشط الشعثة وتستحد المغيبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقال
‏"‏ إذا قدمت فالكيس الكيس ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir b. 'Abdullah (Allah be pleased with them)
reported: We were with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) in
an expedition. When we returned I urged my camel to move quickly as
it was slow. There met me a rider from behind me and he goaded it
with an iron-tipped stick which he had with him. My camel moved
forward like the best that you have ever seen. As I turned (my
face) I found him to be Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
He said: Jabir, what hastens you? I said: Messenger of Allah, I am
newly wedded. whereupon he said: Is it a virgin that you have
married or one previously married? I said: With one previously
married. He said: Why not a young girl so that you could play with
her and she could play with you? Then when we arrived at and were
about to enter Medina he said: Wait, so that we may enter by night
(i. e. in the evening) in order that the woman with dishevelled
hair may comb it, and the woman whose husband had been away may get
herself clean; and when you enter (then you have the) enjoyment (of
tho wife's company).</english-text>
</hadith>
