<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13679</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3726</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 30367, 30367, 20023, 20023, 11014,
18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، وقتيبة، وابن، رمح - واللفظ ليحيى -
قال قتيبة حدثنا ليث، وقال الآخران، أخبرنا الليث بن سعد، - عن نافع،
عن عبد الله، أنه طلق امرأة له وهى حائض تطليقة واحدة فأمره رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يراجعها ثم يمسكها حتى تطهر ثم تحيض عنده حيضة
أخرى ثم يمهلها حتى تطهر من حيضتها فإن أراد أن يطلقها فليطلقها حين
تطهر من قبل أن يجامعها فتلك العدة التي أمر الله أن يطلق لها النساء
‏.‏ وزاد ابن رمح في روايته وكان عبد الله إذا سئل عن ذلك قال لأحدهم
أما أنت طلقت امرأتك مرة أو مرتين فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
أمرني بهذا وإن كنت طلقتها ثلاثا فقد حرمت عليك حتى تنكح زوجا غيرك
وعصيت الله فيما أمرك من طلاق امرأتك ‏.‏ قال مسلم جود الليث في قوله
تطليقة واحدة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah (b. 'Umar) reported that he divorced a wife
of his with the pronouncement of one divorce during the period of
menstruation. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) commanded
him to take her back and keep her until she was purified, and then
she entered the period of menses in his (house) for the second
time. And he should wait until she was purified of her menses. And
then if he would decide to divorce her, he should do so when she
was purified before having a sexual intercourse with her; for that
was the 'Idda which Allah had commanded for the divorce of women.
Ibn Rumh in his narration made this addition: When 'Abdullah was
asked about it, he said to one of them: If you have divorced your
wife with one pronouncement or two (then you can take her back),
for Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) commanded me to do
it; but if you have divorced her with three pronouncements, then
she is forbidden for you until she married another husband, and you
disobeyed Allah in regard to the divorce of your wife what He had
commanded you. (Muslim said: The word" one divorce" used by Laith
is good.)</english-text>
</hadith>
