<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13707</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3754</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 10567,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني أبو الطاهر، حدثنا ابن وهب، ح وحدثني حرملة بن
يحيى التجيبي، - واللفظ له - أخبرنا عبد الله بن وهب، أخبرني يونس بن
يزيد، عن ابن شهاب، أخبرني أبو سلمة بن عبد الرحمن بن عوف، أن عائشة،
قالت لما أمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بتخيير أزواجه بدأ بي فقال
‏"‏ إني ذاكر لك أمرا فلا عليك أن لا تعجلي حتى تستأمري أبويك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت قد علم أن أبوى لم يكونا ليأمراني بفراقه قالت ثم قال ‏"‏ إن
الله عز وجل قال ‏{‏ يا أيها النبي قل لأزواجك إن كنتن تردن الحياة
الدنيا وزينتها فتعالين أمتعكن وأسرحكن سراحا جميلا * وإن كنتن تردن
الله ورسوله والدار الآخرة فإن الله أعد للمحسنات منكن أجرا عظيما‏}‏
قالت فقلت في أى هذا أستأمر أبوى فإني أريد الله ورسوله والدار الآخرة
‏.‏ قالت ثم فعل أزواج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مثل ما فعلت
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha (Allah be pleased with her) reported: When
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) was commanded to
give option to his wives, he started it from me saying: I am going
to mention to you a matter which you should not (decide) in haste
until you have consulted your parents. She said that he already
knew that my parents would never allow me to seek separation from
him She said: Then he said: Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, said:
Prophet, say to thy wives: If you desire this world's life and its
adornment, then come, I will give you a provision and allow you to
depart a goodly departing; and if you desire Allah and His
Messenger and the abode of the Hereafter, then Allah has prepared
for the doers of good among you a great reward She is reported to
have said: About what should I consult my parents, for I desire
Allah and His Messenger and the abode of the Hereafter? She
('A'isha) said: Then all the wives of Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) did as I had done.</english-text>
</hadith>
