<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13725</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3773</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20384, 20240, 11449, 10567, 224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني محمد بن رافع، حدثنا حسين بن محمد، حدثنا شيبان،
عن يحيى، - وهو ابن أبي كثير - أخبرني أبو سلمة، أن فاطمة بنت قيس،
أخت الضحاك بن قيس أخبرته أن أبا حفص بن المغيرة المخزومي طلقها ثلاثا
ثم انطلق إلى اليمن فقال لها أهله ليس لك علينا نفقة ‏.‏ فانطلق خالد
بن الوليد في نفر فأتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في بيت ميمونة
فقالوا إن أبا حفص طلق امرأته ثلاثا فهل لها من نفقة فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ليست لها نفقة وعليها العدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأرسل
إليها ‏"‏ أن لا تسبقيني بنفسك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأمرها أن تنتقل إلى أم شريك
ثم أرسل إليها ‏"‏ أن أم شريك يأتيها المهاجرون الأولون فانطلقي إلى
ابن أم مكتوم الأعمى فإنك إذا وضعت خمارك لم يرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانطلقت إليه
فلما مضت عدتها أنكحها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أسامة بن زيد بن
حارثة.</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Salama reported that Fatima bint Qais, the sister
of al-Dahhak b. Qais informed him that Abu Hafs b. Mughira
al-Makhzumi divorced her three times and then he proceeded on to
the Yemen. The members of his family said to her: There is no
maintenance allowance due to you from us. Khalid b. Walid along
with a group of persons visited Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) in the house of Maimuna and they said: Abu Hafs has
divorced his wife with three pronouncements; is there any
maintenance allowance due to her? Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: No maintenance allowance is due to her,
but she is required to spend the 'Idda; and he sent her the message
that she should not be hasty in making a decision about herself and
commanded her to move to the house of Umm Sharik, and then sent her
the message that as the first immigrants (frequently) visit the
house of Umm Sharik, she should better go to the house of Ibn Umm
Maktum, the blind, (and further said: In case you put off your
head-dress, he (Ibn Umm Makhtum) will not see you. So she went to
his house, and when the 'Idda was over, Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) married her to Usama b. Zaid b.
Haritha.</english-text>
</hadith>
