<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13722</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3770</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11189, 10567, 224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن عبد الله بن
يزيد، مولى الأسود بن سفيان عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، عن فاطمة بنت
قيس، أن أبا عمرو بن حفص، طلقها البتة وهو غائب فأرسل إليها وكيله
بشعير فسخطته فقال والله ما لك علينا من شىء ‏.‏ فجاءت رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك له فقال ‏"‏ ليس لك عليه نفقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فأمرها أن تعتد في بيت أم شريك ثم قال ‏"‏ تلك امرأة يغشاها أصحابي
اعتدي عند ابن أم مكتوم فإنه رجل أعمى تضعين ثيابك فإذا حللت فآذنيني
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فلما حللت ذكرت له أن معاوية بن أبي سفيان وأبا جهم
خطباني ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما أبو جهم فلا
يضع عصاه عن عاتقه وأما معاوية فصعلوك لا مال له انكحي أسامة بن زيد
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكرهته ثم قال ‏"‏ انكحي أسامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فنكحته فجعل الله فيه
خيرا واغتبطت به ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Fatima bint Qais reported that Abu 'Amr b. Hafs
divorced her absolutely when he was away from home, and he sent his
agent to her with some barley. She was displeased with him and when
he said: I swear by Allah that you have no claim on us. she went to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and mentioned that to
him. He said: There is no maintenance due to you from him, and he
commanded her to spend the 'Idda in the house of Umm Sharik, but
then said: That is a woman whom my companions visit. So better
spend this period in the house of Ibn Umm Maktum, for he is a blind
man and yon can put off your garments. And when the 'Idda is over,
inform me. She said: When my period of 'Idda was over, I mentioned
to him that Mu'awiya b. Abu Sufyan and Jahm had sent proposal of
marriage to me, whereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said: As for Abu Jahm, he does not put down his staff from his
shoulder, and as for Mu'awiya, he is a poor man having no property;
marry Usama b. Zaid. I objected to him, but he again said: Marry
Usama; so I married him. Allah blessed there in and I was envied
(by others).</english-text>
</hadith>
