<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13750</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3798</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11104, 11157, 244</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن عبد الله بن
أبي بكر، عن حميد بن نافع، عن زينب بنت أبي سلمة، أنها أخبرته هذه
الأحاديث الثلاثة، قال قالت زينب دخلت على أم حبيبة زوج النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم حين توفي أبوها أبو سفيان فدعت أم حبيبة بطيب فيه صفرة
خلوق أو غيره فدهنت منه جارية ثم مست بعارضيها ثم قالت والله ما لي
بالطيب من حاجة غير أني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول على
المنبر ‏"‏ لا يحل لامرأة تؤمن بالله واليوم الآخر تحد على ميت فوق
ثلاث إلا على زوج أربعة أشهر وعشرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت زينب ثم دخلت على
زينب بنت جحش حين توفي أخوها فدعت بطيب فمست منه ثم قالت والله ما لي
بالطيب من حاجة غير أني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول على
المنبر ‏"‏ لا يحل لامرأة تؤمن بالله واليوم الآخر تحد على ميت فوق
ثلاث إلا على زوج أربعة أشهر وعشرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت زينب سمعت أمي أم
سلمة، تقول جاءت امرأة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت يا
رسول الله إن ابنتي توفي عنها زوجها وقد اشتكت عينها أفنكحلها فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ مرتين أو ثلاثا كل ذلك
يقول لا ثم قال ‏"‏ إنما هي أربعة أشهر وعشر وقد كانت إحداكن في
الجاهلية ترمي بالبعرة على رأس الحول ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال حميد قلت لزينب وما
ترمي بالبعرة على رأس الحول فقالت زينب كانت المرأة إذا توفي عنها
زوجها دخلت حفشا ولبست شر ثيابها ولم تمس طيبا ولا شيئا حتى تمر بها
سنة ثم تؤتى بدابة حمار أو شاة أو طير فتفتض به فقلما تفتض بشىء إلا
مات ثم تخرج فتعطى بعرة فترمي بها ثم تراجع بعد ما شاءت من طيب أو
غيره ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Zainab (bint Abu Salama) (Allah be pleased with her)
reported: I went to Umm Habiba, the wife of Allah's Apostle (may
peace be upon him), when her father Abu Sufyan had died. Umm Habiba
sent for a perfume having yellowness in it or something else like
it, and she applied it to a girl and then rubbed it on her cheeks
and then said: By Allah, I need no perfume but for the fact that I
heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) say on the pulpit:"
It is not permissible for a woman believing in Allah and the
Hereafter to mourn for the dead beyond three days, but (in case of
the death) of the husband it is permissible for four months and ten
days." Zainab said: I then visited Zainab hint Jahsh (Allah be
pleased with her) when her brother died and she sent for perfume
and applied it and then said: By Allah, I don't feel any need for
the perfume but that I heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) say on the pulpit:" It is not permissible for a woman
believing in Allah and the Hereafbler to mourn the dead beyond
three days except in case of her husband (for whom she can mourn)
for four months and ten days." Zainab (Allah be pleased with her)
said: I heard my mother Umm Salama (Allah be pleased with her) as
saying: A woman came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
and said: Allah's Messenger. I have a daughter whose husband has
died and there has developed some trouble in her eye; should we
apply collyrium to it? Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) said: No (repeating it twice or thrice, saying only, NO"
all the time). Then he said: It is only four mouths and ten days,
whereas in the preIslamic period none of you threw away the dung
until one year had passed. Humaid said: I said to Zainab: What is
this throwing of dung until a year is passed? Zainab said: When the
husband of a woman died, she went into a hut and put on her worst
clothes, and did not apply perfume or something like it until a
year was over. Then an animal like a donkey, or a goat, or a bird
was brought to her and she rubbed her hand over it, and it so
happened that one on which she rubbed her hand died. She then came
out of her house and she was given dung and she threw it and then
she made use of anything like perfume or something else as she
liked.</english-text>
</hadith>
