<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13768</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3819</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Invoking Curses - كتاب اللعان</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20331, 20331, 10945, 11050</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا أبي ح، وحدثنا
أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، - واللفظ له - حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا
عبد الملك بن أبي سليمان، عن سعيد بن، جبير قال سئلت عن المتلاعنين،
في إمرة مصعب أيفرق بينهما قال فما دريت ما أقول فمضيت إلى منزل ابن
عمر بمكة فقلت للغلام استأذن لي ‏.‏ قال إنه قائل فسمع صوتي ‏.‏ قال
ابن جبير قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال ادخل فوالله ما جاء بك هذه الساعة إلا حاجة
فدخلت فإذا هو مفترش برذعة متوسد وسادة حشوها ليف قلت أبا عبد الرحمن
المتلاعنان أيفرق بينهما قال سبحان الله نعم إن أول من سأل عن ذلك
فلان بن فلان قال يا رسول الله أرأيت أن لو وجد أحدنا امرأته على
فاحشة كيف يصنع إن تكلم تكلم بأمر عظيم ‏.‏ وإن سكت سكت على مثل ذلك
قال فسكت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلم يجبه فلما كان بعد ذلك أتاه
فقال إن الذي سألتك عنه قد ابتليت به ‏.‏ فأنزل الله عز وجل هؤلاء
الآيات في سورة النور ‏{‏ والذين يرمون أزواجهم‏}‏ فتلاهن عليه ووعظه
وذكره وأخبره أن عذاب الدنيا أهون من عذاب الآخرة قال لا والذي بعثك
بالحق ما كذبت عليها ‏.‏ ثم دعاها فوعظها وذكرها وأخبرها أن عذاب
الدنيا أهون من عذاب الآخرة ‏.‏ قالت لا والذي بعثك بالحق إنه لكاذب
فبدأ بالرجل فشهد أربع شهادات بالله إنه لمن الصادقين والخامسة أن
لعنة الله عليه إن كان من الكاذبين ثم ثنى بالمرأة فشهدت أربع شهادات
بالله إنه لمن الكاذبين والخامسة أن غضب الله عليها إن كان من
الصادقين ثم فرق بينهما.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sa'id b Jubair reported: I was asked about the
invokers of curses during the reign of Mus'ab (b. Zubair) whether
they could separate (themselves by this process). He said: I did
not understand what to say. So I went to the house of Ibn 'Umar
(Allah be pleased with them) in Mecca. I said to his servant: Seek
permission for Me. He said that he (Ibn 'Umar) had been taking
rest. He (Ibn 'Umar) heard my voice. and said: Are you Ibn Jubair?
I said: Yes. He'said: Come in. By Allah, it must be some (great)
need which has brought you here at this Hour. So I got in and found
him lying on a blanket reclining against a pillow stuffed with
fibres of date-palm. I said: O Abu'Abd al-Rahman, should there be
separation between the invokers of curses? He said: Hallowed be
Allah, yes, The first one who asked about it was so and so. he
said: Messenger of Allah, tell me If one of us finds his wife
committing adultery: what should he do? If he talks, that is
something great, and if he keeps quiet that is also (something
great) (which he cannot afford to do). Allah's Prophet (may peace
be upon him) kept quiet (or some time). After some time he (that
very person) came to him (Allah's Messenger) and said: I have been
involved in that very cage about which I had asked you Allah the
Exalted and Majestic then revealed (these) verses of Surah Nur:"
Those who accuse their wives" (verse 6), and he (the Holy Prophet)
recited them to him and admonished him, and exhorted him and
informed him that the torment of the world is less painful than the
torment of the Hereafter. He said: No, by Him Who sent you with
Truth, I did not tell a lie against her. He (the Holy Prophet) then
called her (the wife of that person who had accused her) and
admonished her, and exhorted her, and informed her that the torment
of this world is less painful than the torment of the Hereafter.
She said: No, by Him Who sent thee with Truth, he is a liar. (it
was) the man who started the swearing of oath and he swore in the
name of Allah four times that he was among the truthful. and at the
fifth turn he said: Let there be curse of Allah upon him if he were
among the liars. Then the woman was called and she swore four times
in the name of Allah that he (her husband) was among the liars, and
at the fifth time (she said): Let there be curse upon her if he
were among the truthful. He (the Holy Prophet) then effected
separation between the two.</english-text>
</hadith>
