<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>13777</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3828</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Invoking Curses - كتاب اللعان</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 30203, 30123, 30312, 4057, 11060, 11051, 11017,
16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زهير بن حرب، وعثمان بن أبي شيبة، وإسحاق بن
إبراهيم، - واللفظ لزهير - قال إسحاق أخبرنا وقال الآخران، حدثنا
جرير، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، عن علقمة، عن عبد الله، قال إنا ليلة
الجمعة في المسجد إذ جاء رجل من الأنصار فقال لو أن رجلا وجد مع
امرأته رجلا فتكلم جلدتموه أو قتل قتلتموه وإن سكت سكت على غيظ والله
لأسألن عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فلما كان من الغد أتى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسأله فقال لو أن رجلا وجد مع امرأته
رجلا فتكلم جلدتموه أو قتل قتلتموه أو سكت سكت على غيظ ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
اللهم افتح ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وجعل يدعو فنزلت آية اللعان ‏{‏ والذين يرمون
أزواجهم ولم يكن لهم شهداء إلا أنفسهم‏}‏ هذه الآيات فابتلي به ذلك
الرجل من بين الناس فجاء هو وامرأته إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فتلاعنا فشهد الرجل أربع شهادات بالله إنه لمن الصادقين ثم لعن
الخامسة أن لعنة الله عليه إن كان من الكاذبين فذهبت لتلعن فقال لها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ مه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأبت فلعنت فلما أدبرا
قال ‏"‏ لعلها أن تجيء به أسود جعدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاءت به أسود
جعدا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abdullah reported: We were on the night of Friday
staying in the mosque when a person from the Ansar came there and
said: If a person finds hiswoman along with a man, and he speaks
about it, you would lash him, and if he kills, you will kill him,
and if he keeps quiet he shall have to consume anger. By Allah, I
will definitely ask about him from Allah's Mescenger (may peace be
upon him). On the following day he came to Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) and asked him thus: If a man were to find with
his wife a man and if he were to talk about it, you would lash him;
and if he killed, you would kill him, and if he were to keep quiet.
he would consume anger, whereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said:
Allah, solve (this problem), and he began to supplicate (before
Him), and then the verses pertaining to li'an were revealed:" Those
who accuse their wives and have no witnesses except themselves"
(xxiv. 6). The person was then put to test according to these
verses in the presence of the people. There came he and his wife in
the presence of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), and they
invoked curses (in order to testify their claim). The man swore
four times in the name of Allah that he was one of the truthful and
then invoked curse for the fifth time saying: Let there be curse of
Allah upon him if he were among the liars. Then she began to invoke
curse. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said to her: just
wait (and curse after considering over it), but she refused and
invoked curse and when she turned away, he (Allah's Apostle) said:
It seems that this woman shall give birth to a curly-haired black
child, And so she did gave birth to a curly-haired black
child.</english-text>
</hadith>
