<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14083</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4145</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Masaaqah - كتاب المساقاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30024, 20022, 11015, 11047</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن عمر القواريري، حدثنا حماد بن زيد،
عن أيوب، عن أبي قلابة، قال كنت بالشام في حلقة فيها مسلم بن يسار
فجاء أبو الأشعث قال قالوا أبو الأشعث أبو الأشعث ‏.‏ فجلس فقلت له
حدث أخانا حديث عبادة بن الصامت ‏.‏ قال نعم غزونا غزاة وعلى الناس
معاوية فغنمنا غنائم كثيرة فكان فيما غنمنا آنية من فضة فأمر معاوية
رجلا أن يبيعها في أعطيات الناس فتسارع الناس في ذلك فبلغ عبادة بن
الصامت فقام فقال إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينهى عن بيع
الذهب بالذهب والفضة بالفضة والبر بالبر والشعير بالشعير والتمر
بالتمر والملح بالملح إلا سواء بسواء عينا بعين فمن زاد أو ازداد فقد
أربى ‏.‏ فرد الناس ما أخذوا فبلغ ذلك معاوية فقام خطيبا فقال ألا ما
بال رجال يتحدثون عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أحاديث قد كنا
نشهده ونصحبه فلم نسمعها منه ‏.‏ فقام عبادة بن الصامت فأعاد القصة ثم
قال لنحدثن بما سمعنا من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وإن كره معاوية
- أو قال وإن رغم - ما أبالي أن لا أصحبه في جنده ليلة سوداء ‏.‏ قال
حماد هذا أو نحوه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abil Qiliba reported: I was in Syria (having) a
circle (of friends). in which was Muslim b. Yasir. There came
Abu'l-Ash'ath. He (the narrator) said that they (the friends)
called him: Abu'l-Ash'ath, Abu'l-Ash'ath, and he sat down. I said
to him: Narrate to our brother the hadith of Ubada b. Samit. He
said: Yes. We went out on an expedition, Mu'awiya being the leader
of the people, and we gained a lot of spoils of war. And there was
one silver utensil in what we took as spoils. Mu'awiya ordered a
person to sell it for payment to the people (soldiers). The people
made haste in getting that. The news of (this state of affairs)
reached 'Ubada b. Samit, and he stood up and said: I heard Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) forbidding the sale of gold by
gold, and silver by silver, and wheat by wheat, and barley by
barley, and dates by dates, and salt by salt, except like for like
and equal for equal. So he who made an addition or who accepted an
addition (committed the sin of taking) interest. So the people
returned what they had got. This reached Mu'awiya. and he stood up
to deliver an address. He said: What is the matter with people that
they narrate from the Messenger (may peace be upon him) such
tradition which we did not hear though we saw him (the Holy
Prophet) and lived in his company? Thereupon, Ubida b. Samit stood
up and repeated that narration, and then said: We will definitely
narrate what we heard from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) though it may be unpleasant to Mu'awiya (or he said: Even if
it is against his will). I do not mind if I do not remain in his
troop in the dark night. Hammad said this or something like
this.</english-text>
</hadith>
