<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14108</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4170</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Masaaqah - كتاب المساقاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30263, 20208, 11286, 10721, 17, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عمرو الناقد، حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، عن سعيد
الجريري، عن أبي، نضرة قال سألت ابن عباس عن الصرف، فقال أيدا بيد قلت
نعم ‏.‏ قال فلا بأس به ‏.‏ فأخبرت أبا سعيد فقلت إني سألت ابن عباس
عن الصرف فقال أيدا بيد قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال فلا بأس به ‏.‏ قال أوقال ذلك
إنا سنكتب إليه فلا يفتيكموه قال فوالله لقد جاء بعض فتيان رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بتمر فأنكره فقال ‏"‏ كأن هذا ليس من تمر أرضنا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كان في تمر أرضنا - أو في تمرنا - العام بعض الشىء فأخذت
هذا وزدت بعض الزيادة ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أضعفت أربيت لا تقربن هذا إذا رابك
من تمرك شىء فبعه ثم اشتر الذي تريد من التمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Nadra reported: I asked Ibn Abbas (Allah be
pleased with them) about the conversion (of gold and silver for
silver and gold). We said: Is it hand to hand exchange? I said:
Yes. whereupon he said: There is no harm in it. I informed Abu
Sa'id about it, telling him that I had asked Ibn 'Abbas about it
and he said: Is it hand to hand exchange? I said: Yes, whereupon he
said: There is no harm in it. He (the narrator) said, or he said
like it: We will soon write to him, and he will not give you this
fatwa (religious verdict). He said: By Allah, someone of the
boy-servants of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) brought
dates, but he refused to accept them (on the plea) that those did
not seem to be of the dates of our land. He said: Something had
happened to the dates of our land, or our dates. So I got these
dates (in exchange by giving) excess (of the dates of our land),
whereupon he said: You made an addition for getting the fine dates
(in exchange) which tantamounts, to interest; don't do that (in
future). Whenever you find some doubt (as regards the deteriorating
quality of) your dates, sell them, and then buy the dates that you
like.</english-text>
</hadith>
