<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14243</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4302</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Bequests - كتاب الوصية</chapter>
<chain-index>11015, 10602, 11280</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن أبي عمر المكي، حدثنا الثقفي، عن أيوب
السختياني، عن عمرو، بن سعيد عن حميد بن عبد الرحمن الحميري، عن
ثلاثة، من ولد سعد كلهم يحدثه عن أبيه، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
دخل على سعد يعوده بمكة فبكى قال ‏"‏ ما يبكيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال قد خشيت
أن أموت بالأرض التي هاجرت منها كما مات سعد ابن خولة ‏.‏ فقال النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اللهم اشف سعدا اللهم اشف سعدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث
مرار ‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله إن لي مالا كثيرا وإنما يرثني ابنتي أفأوصي
بمالي كله قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالثلثين قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فالنصف قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فالثلث قال ‏"‏ الثلث والثلث كثير إن
صدقتك من مالك صدقة وإن نفقتك على عيالك صدقة وإن ما تأكل امرأتك من
مالك صدقة وإنك أن تدع أهلك بخير - أو قال بعيش - خير من أن تدعهم
يتكففون الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال بيده ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Humaid b. 'Abd al-Rahman al-Himyari reported from
three of the sons of Sa'd all of whom reported from their father
that Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) visited Sa'd as he was
ill in Mecca. He (Sa'd) wept. He (the Holy Prophet) said: What
makes you weep? He said: I am afraid I may die in the land from
where I migrated as Sa'd b. Khaula had died. Thereupon Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: O Allah, grant health to
Sa'd. O Allah, grant health to Sad. He repeated it three times. He
(Sa'd) said: Allah's Messenger, I own a large property and I have
only one daughter as my inheritor. Should I not will away the whole
of my property? He (the Holy Prophet) said: No. He said: (Should I
not will away, ) two-thirds of the property? he (the Holy Prophet)
said: No. He (Sa'd) (again) said: (Should I not will away) half (of
my property)? He said: No. He (Sa'd) said: Then one-third?
Thereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said: (Yes), one-third, and
one-third is quite substanial. And what you spend as charity from
your property is Sadaqa and flour spending on your family is also
Sadaqa, and what your wife eats from your property is also Sadaqa,
and that you leave your heirs well off (or he said: prospreous) is
better than to leave them (poor and) begging from people. He (the
Holy Prophet) pointed this with his hands.</english-text>
</hadith>
