<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14346</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>28</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4403</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Oaths - كتاب الأيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20032, 11060, 11397</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا وكيع، حدثنا الأعمش،
عن المعرور بن سويد، قال مررنا بأبي ذر بالربذة وعليه برد وعلى غلامه
مثله فقلنا يا أبا ذر لو جمعت بينهما كانت حلة ‏.‏ فقال إنه كان بيني
وبين رجل من إخواني كلام وكانت أمه أعجمية فعيرته بأمه فشكاني إلى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلقيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ يا
أبا ذر إنك امرؤ فيك جاهلية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله من سب الرجال
سبوا أباه وأمه ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر إنك امرؤ فيك جاهلية هم إخوانكم
جعلهم الله تحت أيديكم فأطعموهم مما تأكلون وألبسوهم مما تلبسون ولا
تكلفوهم ما يغلبهم فإن كلفتموهم فأعينوهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Ma'rur b. Suwaid said: We went to Abu Dharr
(Ghifari) in Rabadha and he had a mantle over him, and his slave
had one like it. We said: Abu Dharr, had you joined them together,
it would have been a complete garment. Thereupon he said: There was
an altercation between me and one of the persons among my brothers.
His mother was a non-Arab. I reproached him for his mother. He
complained against me to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him).
As I met Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) he said: Abu
Dharr, you are a person who still has (in him the remnants) of the
days (of Ignorance). Thereupon I said: Allah's Messenger, he who
abuses (other) persons, they abuse (in return) his father and
mother. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Abu Dharr, you are a person who
still has (the remnants) of Ignorance in him They (your servants
and slaves) are your brothers. Allah has put them in your care, so
feed them with what you eat, clothe them with what you wear. and do
not burden them beyond their capacities; but if you burden them
(with an unbearable burden), then help them (by sharing their extra
burden).</english-text>
</hadith>
