<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14383</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4441</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Oath; for Establishing the
Responsibility of Murders; Fighting; Requital - كتاب القسامة
والمحاربين والقصاص والديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30313, 20211, 20001, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق بن منصور، أخبرنا بشر بن عمر، قال سمعت مالك
بن أنس، يقول حدثني أبو ليلى بن عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن سهل، عن
سهل بن أبي حثمة، أنه أخبره عن رجال، من كبراء قومه أن عبد، الله بن
سهل ومحيصة خرجا إلى خيبر من جهد أصابهم فأتى محيصة فأخبر أن عبد الله
بن سهل قد قتل وطرح في عين أو فقير فأتى يهود فقال أنتم والله قتلتموه
‏.‏ قالوا والله ما قتلناه ‏.‏ ثم أقبل حتى قدم على قومه فذكر لهم ذلك
ثم أقبل هو وأخوه حويصة وهو أكبر منه وعبد الرحمن بن سهل فذهب محيصة
ليتكلم وهو الذي كان بخيبر فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمحيصة
‏"‏ كبر كبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يريد السن فتكلم حويصة ثم تكلم محيصة ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إما أن يدوا صاحبكم وإما أن يؤذنوا
بحرب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكتب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إليهم في ذلك فكتبوا
إنا والله ما قتلناه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لحويصة
ومحيصة وعبد الرحمن ‏"‏ أتحلفون وتستحقون دم صاحبكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فتحلف لكم يهود ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ليسوا بمسلمين ‏.‏ فوداه
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من عنده فبعث إليهم رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم مائة ناقة حتى أدخلت عليهم الدار ‏.‏ فقال سهل فلقد ركضتني
منها ناقة حمراء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Laila 'Abdullah b. 'Abd al-Rahman b. Sahl
reported that the elderly persons of (the tribe) had informed Sahl
b. Abu Hathma that 'Abdullah b. Sahl and Muhayyisa went out to
Khaibar under some distress which had afflicted them. Muhayyisa
came and informed that Abdutlah b. Sahl had been killed, and (his
dead body) had been thrown in a well or in a ditch. He came to the
Jews and said: By Allah, it is you who have killed him. They said:
By Allah, we have not killed him. He then came to his people, and
made mention of that to them. Then came he and his brother
Huwayyisa, and he was older than he, and 'Abd al-Rahman b. Sahl.
Then Muhayyisa went to speak, and it was he who had accompanied
('Abdullah) to Khaibar, whereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) said to Muhayyisa: Observe greatness of the great (he
meant the seniority of age). Then Huwayyisa spoke and then
Muhayyisa also spoke. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) said: They should either pay blood-wit for your
companion, or be prepared for war. Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) wrote about it to them (to the Jews). They wrote: Verily,
by Allah, we have not killed him. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said to Huwayyisa and Muhayyisa and Abd
al-Rahman: Are you prepared to take oath in order to entitle
yourselves for the blood-wit of your companion? They said: No. He
(the Holy Prophet) said: Then the Jews will take oath (of their
innocence). They said: They are not Muslims. Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him), however, himself paid the blood-wit to them and
sent to them one hundred camels until they entered into their
houses, Sahl said: One red she-camel among them kicked
me.</english-text>
</hadith>
