<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14388</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4446</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Oath; for Establishing the
Responsibility of Murders; Fighting; Requital - كتاب القسامة
والمحاربين والقصاص والديات</chapter>
<chain-index>20208, 11277, 11047, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو جعفر، محمد بن الصباح وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة -
واللفظ لأبي بكر - قال حدثنا ابن علية، عن حجاج بن أبي عثمان، حدثني
أبو رجاء، مولى أبي قلابة عن أبي قلابة، حدثني أنس، أن نفرا، من عكل
ثمانية قدموا على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فبايعوه على الإسلام
فاستوخموا الأرض وسقمت أجسامهم فشكوا ذلك إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ألا تخرجون مع راعينا في إبله فتصيبون من أبوالها
وألبانها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا بلى ‏.‏ فخرجوا فشربوا من أبوالها وألبانها
فصحوا فقتلوا الراعي وطردوا الإبل فبلغ ذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فبعث في آثارهم فأدركوا فجيء بهم فأمر بهم فقطعت أيديهم وأرجلهم
وسمر أعينهم ثم نبذوا في الشمس حتى ماتوا ‏.‏ وقال ابن الصباح في
روايته واطردوا النعم ‏.‏ وقال وسمرت أعينهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas reported: Eight men of the tribe of 'Ukl came to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and swore allegiance to
him on Islam, but found the climate of that land uncogenial to
their health and thus they became sick, and they made complaint of
that to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), and he said: Why
don't you go to (the fold) of our camels along with our shepherd,
and make use of their milk and urine. They said: Yes. They set out
and drank their (camels') milk and urine and regained their health.
They killed the shepherd and drove away the camels. This (news)
reached Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and he sent them
on their track and they were caught and brought to him (the Holy
Prophet). He commanded about them, and (thus) their hands and feet
were cut off and their eyes were gouged and then they were thrown
in the sun, until they died. This hadith has been narrated on the
authority of Ibn al-Sabbah with a slight variation of
words.</english-text>
</hadith>
