<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14419</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4478</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Oath; for Establishing the
Responsibility of Murders; Fighting; Requital - كتاب القسامة
والمحاربين والقصاص والديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20304, 11071, 11035, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي الجهضمي، حدثنا يزيد بن زريع، حدثنا
عبد الله بن عون، عن محمد بن سيرين، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكرة، عن
أبيه، قال لما كان ذلك اليوم قعد على بعيره وأخذ إنسان بخطامه فقال
‏"‏ أتدرون أى يوم هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ حتى ظننا
أنه سيسميه سوى اسمه ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أليس بيوم النحر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا بلى
يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأى شهر هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس بذي الحجة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا بلى يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ فأى بلد هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم - قال - حتى ظننا أنه
سيسميه سوى اسمه ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس بالبلدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا بلى يا رسول
الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم وأعراضكم عليكم حرام كحرمة
يومكم هذا في شهركم هذا في بلدكم هذا فليبلغ الشاهد الغائب ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال ثم انكفأ إلى كبشين أملحين فذبحهما وإلى جزيعة من الغنم فقسمها
بيننا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Bakra reported that when it was that day (the
10th of Dhu'l-Hijja) he mounted his camel and a person caught its
nosestring, whereupon he said: Do you know which day is this? They
said: Allah and His Messenger know best. (The Holy Prophet [may
peace be upon him] kept silent) until we thought that he would give
that another name. He said: Is it not the day of Nahr (Sacrifice)
(10th of Dhu'l- Hijja)? We said: Allah's Messenger, yes. He (again)
said: Which month is it? We said: Allah and His Messenger knows
best. He said: Is it not Dhu'l-Hijja? We said: Allah's Messenger,
yes. He said: Which city is this? We said: Allah and His Messenger
know best. He (the narrator) said (that the Holy Prophet kept
silent until we thought that he would give it another name besides
its (original) name. He said: Is it not Balda (the city of Mecca)?
We said: Yes, Allah's Messenger. He (then) said: Verily your blood
(lives) and your property and your honour are as sacred unto you as
sacred is this day of yours, in this month of yours, in this city
of yours. Let him who is present convey it to one who is absent. He
then turned his attention towards two multicoloured (black and
white) rams and slaughtered them, and two goats, and distributed
them amongst us.</english-text>
</hadith>
