<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14456</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4515</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Punishments Prescribed by Islam -
كتاب الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>11207, 11013, 10567, 11002, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني عبد الملك بن شعيب بن الليث بن سعد، حدثني أبي،
عن جدي، قال حدثني عقيل، عن ابن شهاب، عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن بن
عوف، وسعيد بن المسيب، عن أبي هريرة، أنه قال أتى رجل من المسلمين
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو في المسجد فناداه فقال يا رسول الله
إني زنيت ‏.‏ فأعرض عنه فتنحى تلقاء وجهه فقال له يا رسول الله إني
زنيت ‏.‏ فأعرض عنه حتى ثنى ذلك عليه أربع مرات فلما شهد على نفسه
أربع شهادات دعاه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أبك جنون ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فهل أحصنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اذهبوا به فارجموه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported that a person from amongst the
Muslims came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) while he
was in the mosque. He called him saying: Allah's Messenger. I have
committed adultery. He (the Holy Prophet) turned away from him, He
(again) came round facing him and said to him: Allah's Messenger, I
have committed adultery. He (the Holy Prophet) turned away until he
did that four times, and as he testified four times against his own
self, Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) called him and
said: Are you mad? He said: No. He (again) said: Are you married?
He said: Yes. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said: Take him and stone him. Ibn Shihab (one of the narrators)
said: One who had heard Jabir b. 'Abdullah saying this informed me
thus: I was one of those who stoned him. We stoned him at the place
of prayer (either that of 'Id or a funeral). When the stones hurt
him, he ran away. We caught him in the Harra and stoned him (to
death). This hadith has been narrated through another chain of
transmitters.</english-text>
</hadith>
