<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14474</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4533</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Punishments Prescribed by Islam -
كتاب الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30502, 20239, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني الحكم بن موسى أبو صالح، حدثنا شعيب بن إسحاق،
أخبرنا عبيد الله، عن نافع، أن عبد الله بن عمر، أخبره أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أتي بيهودي ويهودية قد زنيا فانطلق رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم حتى جاء يهود فقال ‏"‏ ما تجدون في التوراة على من زنى
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نسود وجوههما ونحملهما ونخالف بين وجوههما ويطاف بهما
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأتوا بالتوراة إن كنتم صادقين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاءوا بها
فقرءوها حتى إذا مروا بآية الرجم وضع الفتى الذي يقرأ يده على آية
الرجم وقرأ ما بين يديها وما وراءها فقال له عبد الله بن سلام وهو مع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مره فليرفع يده فرفعها فإذا تحتها آية
الرجم فأمر بهما رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرجما ‏.‏ قال عبد الله
بن عمر كنت فيمن رجمهما فلقد رأيته يقيها من الحجارة بنفسه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. 'Umar reported that a Jew and a Jewess
were brought to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) who had
committed adultery. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) came
to the Jews and said: What do you find in Torah for one who commits
adultery? They said: We darken their faces and make them ride on
the donkey with their faces turned to the opposite direction (and
their backs touching each other), and then they are taken round
(the city). He said: Bring Torah if you are truthful. They brought
it and recited it until when they came to the verse pertaining to
stoning, the person who was reading placed his hand on the verse
pertaining to stoning, and read (only that which was) between his
hands and what was subsequent to that. Abdullah b. Salim who was at
that time with the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said:
Command him (the reciter) to lift his hand. He lifted it and there
was, underneath that, the verse pertaining to stoning. Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) pronounced judgment about both of
them and they were stoned. Abdullah b. 'Umar said: I was one of
those who stoned them, and I saw him (the Jew) protecting her (the
Jewess) with his body.</english-text>
</hadith>
