<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14469</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4528</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Punishments Prescribed by Islam -
كتاب الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20331, 10747, 11432, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، ح
وحدثنا محمد بن عبد، الله بن نمير - وتقاربا في لفظ الحديث - حدثنا
أبي، حدثنا بشير بن المهاجر، حدثنا عبد الله بن بريدة، عن أبيه، أن
ماعز بن مالك الأسلمي، أتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول
الله إني قد ظلمت نفسي وزنيت وإني أريد أن تطهرني ‏.‏ فرده فلما كان
من الغد أتاه فقال يا رسول الله إني قد زنيت ‏.‏ فرده الثانية فأرسل
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى قومه فقال ‏"‏ أتعلمون بعقله بأسا
تنكرون منه شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا ما نعلمه إلا وفي العقل من صالحينا
فيما نرى فأتاه الثالثة فأرسل إليهم أيضا فسأل عنه فأخبروه أنه لا بأس
به ولا بعقله فلما كان الرابعة حفر له حفرة ثم أمر به فرجم ‏.‏ قال
فجاءت الغامدية فقالت يا رسول الله إني قد زنيت فطهرني ‏.‏ وإنه ردها
فلما كان الغد قالت يا رسول الله لم تردني لعلك أن تردني كما رددت
ماعزا فوالله إني لحبلى ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إما لا فاذهبي حتى تلدي ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فلما ولدت أتته بالصبي في خرقة قالت هذا قد ولدته ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهبي
فأرضعيه حتى تفطميه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما فطمته أتته بالصبي في يده كسرة خبز
فقالت هذا يا نبي الله قد فطمته وقد أكل الطعام ‏.‏ فدفع الصبي إلى
رجل من المسلمين ثم أمر بها فحفر لها إلى صدرها وأمر الناس فرجموها
فيقبل خالد بن الوليد بحجر فرمى رأسها فتنضح الدم على وجه خالد فسبها
فسمع نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سبه إياها فقال ‏"‏ مهلا يا خالد
فوالذي نفسي بيده لقد تابت توبة لو تابها صاحب مكس لغفر له ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم
أمر بها فصلى عليها ودفنت ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abdullah b. Buraida reported on the authority of his
father that Ma'iz b. Malik al-Aslami came to Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) and said: Allah's Messenger, I have wronged
myself; I have committed adultery and I earnestly desire that you
should purify me. He turned him away. On the following day, he
(Ma'iz) again came to him and said: Allah's Messenger, I have
committed adultery. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
turned him away for the second time, and sent him to his people
saying: Do you know if there is anything wrong with his mind. They
denied of any such thing in him and said: We do not know him but as
a wise good man among us, so far as we can judge. He (Ma'iz) came
for the third time, and he (the Holy Prophet) sent him as he had
done before. He asked about him and they informed him that there
was nothing wrong with him or with his mind. When it was the fourth
time, a ditch was dug for him and he (the Holy Prophet) pronounced
judg- ment about him and he wis stoned. He (the narrator) said:
There came to him (the Holy Prophet) a woman from Ghamid and said:
Allah's Messenger, I have committed adultery, so purify me. He (the
Holy Prophet) turned her away. On the following day she said:
Allah's Messenger, Why do you turn me away? Perhaps, you turn me
away as you turned away Ma'iz. By Allah, I have become pregnant. He
said: Well, if you insist upon it, then go away until you give
birth to (the child). When she was delivered she came with the
child (wrapped) in a rag and said: Here is the child whom I have
given birth to. He said: Go away and suckle him until you wean him.
When she had weaned him, she came to him (the Holy Prophet) with
the child who was holding a piece of bread in his hand. She said:
Allah's Apostle, here is he as I have weaned him and he eats food.
He (the Holy Prophet) entrusted the child to one of the Muslims and
then pronounced punishment. And she was put in a ditch up to her
chest and he commanded people and they stoned her. Khalid b Walid
came forward with a stone which he flung at her head and there
spurted blood on the face of Khalid and so he abused her. Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) heard his (Khalid's) curse that he
had huried upon her. Thereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said: Khalid,
be gentle. By Him in Whose Hand is my life, she has made such a
repentance that even if a wrongful tax-collector were to repent, he
would have been forgiven. Then giving command regarding her, he
prayed over her and she was buried.</english-text>
</hadith>
