<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14472</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4531</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Punishments Prescribed by Islam -
كتاب الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 30490, 20023, 11013, 11004, 13,
3625</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا ليث، ح وحدثناه محمد بن رمح،
أخبرنا الليث، عن ابن شهاب، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن
مسعود، عن أبي هريرة، وزيد بن خالد، الجهني أنهما قالا إن رجلا من
الأعراب أتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله أنشدك
الله إلا قضيت لي بكتاب الله ‏.‏ فقال الخصم الآخر وهو أفقه منه نعم
فاقض بيننا بكتاب الله وائذن لي ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ قل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا فزنى بامرأته وإني
أخبرت أن على ابني الرجم فافتديت منه بمائة شاة ووليدة فسألت أهل
العلم فأخبروني أنما على ابني جلد مائة وتغريب عام وأن على امرأة هذا
الرجم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده
لأقضين بينكما بكتاب الله الوليدة والغنم رد وعلى ابنك جلد مائة
وتغريب عام واغد يا أنيس إلى امرأة هذا فإن اعترفت فارجمها ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال فغدا عليها فاعترفت فأمر بها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرجمت
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira and Zaid b Khalid al-Juhani reported that
one of the desert tribes came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) and said: Messenger of Allah, I beg of you in the name of
Allah that you pronounce judgment about me according to the Book of
Allah. The second claimant who was wiser than him said: Well,
decide amongst us according to the Book of Allah, but permit me (to
say something). Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon ham)
said: Say. He said: My son was a servant in the house of this
person and he committed adultery with his wife. I was informed that
my son deserved stoning to death (as punishment for this offence).
I gave one hundred goats and a slave girl as ransom for this. I
asked the scholars (if this could serve as an expiation for this
offence). They informed me that my son deserved one hundred lathes
and exile for one year. and this woman deserved stoning (as she was
married). Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace he upon him) said:
By Him in Whose Hand is my life. I will decide between you
according to the Book of Allah. The slave-girl and the goats should
be given back, and your son is to be punished with one hundred
lashes and exile for one year. And, O Unais (b. Zuhaq al-Aslami),
go to this woman in the morning, and if she makes a confession,
then stone her. He (the narrator) said: He went to her in the
morning and she made a confession. And Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) made pronouncement about her and she was stoned to
death.</english-text>
</hadith>
