<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14495</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4554</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Punishments Prescribed by Islam -
كتاب الحدود</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30022, 20387, 20208, 11073, 30123, 20574,
20252</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وزهير بن حرب، وعلي بن حجر،
قالوا حدثنا إسماعيل، - وهو ابن علية - عن ابن أبي عروبة، عن عبد الله
الداناج، ح وحدثنا إسحاق، بن إبراهيم الحنظلي - واللفظ له - أخبرنا
يحيى بن حماد، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن المختار، حدثنا عبد الله بن فيروز،
مولى ابن عامر الداناج حدثنا حضين بن المنذر أبو ساسان، قال شهدت
عثمان بن عفان وأتي بالوليد قد صلى الصبح ركعتين ثم قال أزيدكم فشهد
عليه رجلان أحدهما حمران أنه شرب الخمر وشهد آخر أنه رآه يتقيأ فقال
عثمان إنه لم يتقيأ حتى شربها فقال يا علي قم فاجلده ‏.‏ فقال علي قم
يا حسن فاجلده ‏.‏ فقال الحسن ول حارها من تولى قارها - فكأنه وجد
عليه - فقال يا عبد الله بن جعفر قم فاجلده ‏.‏ فجلده وعلي يعد حتى
بلغ أربعين فقال أمسك ‏.‏ ثم قال جلد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أربعين
وجلد أبو بكر أربعين وعمر ثمانين وكل سنة وهذا أحب إلى ‏.‏ زاد علي بن
حجر في روايته قال إسماعيل وقد سمعت حديث الداناج منه فلم أحفظه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hudain b. al-Mundhir Abu Sasan reported: I saw that
Walid was brought to Uthmin b. 'Affan as he had prayed two rak'ahs
of the dawn prayer, and then he said: I make an increase for you.
And two men bore witness against him. One of them was Humran who
said that he had drunk wine. The second one gave witness that he
had seen him vomiting. Uthman said: He would not have vomited
(wine) unless he had drunk it. He said: 'Ali, stand up and lash
him. 'Ali said: Hasan, stand up and lash him. Thereupon Hasan said:
Let him suffer the heat (of Caliphate) who has enjoyed its
coolness. ('Ali felt annoyed at this remark) and he said: 'Abdullah
b. Ja'far, stand up and flog him, and he began to flog him and 'Ali
counted the stripes until these were forty. He (Hadrat 'Ali) said:
Stop now, and then said: Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
gave forty stripes, and Abu Bakr also gave forty stripes, and Umar
gave eighty stripes, and all these fall under the category of the
Sunnab, but this one (forty stripes) is dearer to
me.</english-text>
</hadith>
