<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14591</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4653</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20025, 20115, 30375, 20121, 20115, 11447,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو كريب، محمد بن العلاء حدثنا ابن المبارك، عن
معمر، ح وحدثنا محمد، بن رافع - واللفظ له - حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا
معمر، عن همام بن منبه، قال هذا ما حدثنا أبو هريرة، عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فذكر أحاديث منها وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ غزا نبي من الأنبياء فقال لقومه لا يتبعني رجل قد ملك بضع امرأة
وهو يريد أن يبني بها ولما يبن ولا آخر قد بنى بنيانا ولما يرفع سقفها
ولا آخر قد اشترى غنما أو خلفات وهو منتظر ولادها ‏.‏ قال فغزا فأدنى
للقرية حين صلاة العصر أو قريبا من ذلك فقال للشمس أنت مأمورة وأنا
مأمور اللهم احبسها على شيئا ‏.‏ فحبست عليه حتى فتح الله عليه - قال
- فجمعوا ما غنموا فأقبلت النار لتأكله فأبت أن تطعمه فقال فيكم غلول
فليبايعني من كل قبيلة رجل ‏.‏ فبايعوه فلصقت يد رجل بيده فقال فيكم
الغلول فلتبايعني قبيلتك ‏.‏ فبايعته - قال - فلصقت بيد رجلين أو
ثلاثة فقال فيكم الغلول أنتم غللتم - قال - فأخرجوا له مثل رأس بقرة
من ذهب - قال - فوضعوه في المال وهو بالصعيد فأقبلت النار فأكلته ‏.‏
فلم تحل الغنائم لأحد من قبلنا ذلك بأن الله تبارك وتعالى رأى ضعفنا
وعجزنا فطيبها لنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated by Abu Huraira that the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: One of the
Prophets made a holy war. He said to his followers: One who has
married a woman and wants to consummate to his marriage but has not
yet done so; another who has built a house but has not yet erected
its roof; and another who has bought goats and pregnantshe-camels
and is waiting for their offspring-will not accommpany me. So he
marched on and approached a village at or about the time of the Asr
prayers. He said to the sun: Thou art subserviant (to Allah) and so
am I. O Allah, stop it for me a little. It was stopped for him
until Allah granted him victory. The people gathered the spoils of
war (at one place). A fire approached the spoils to devour them,
but it did not devour them. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Some of you
have been guilty of misappropriation. So one man from each tribe
should swear fealty to me. The did so (putting their hands into
his). The hand of one man stuck to his hand and the Prophet (may
peace be upon him) said: Your tribe is guilty of misappropriation.
Let all the members of your tribe swear fealty to me one by one.
They did so, when the hands of two or three persons got stuck with
his hand. He said: You have misappropriated. So they took out gold
equal in volume to the head of a cow. They-placed it among the
spoils on the earth. Then the fire approached the spoils and
devoured them. The spoils of war were not made lawful for any
people before us, This is because Allah saw our weakness and
humility and made them lawful for us.</english-text>
</hadith>
