<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14606</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4669</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20675, 10865, 10805</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني أبو الطاهر، أحمد بن عمرو بن سرح أخبرنا عبد الله
بن وهب، أخبرني معاوية بن صالح، عن عبد الرحمن بن جبير، عن أبيه، عن
عوف بن مالك، قال قتل رجل من حمير رجلا من العدو فأراد سلبه فمنعه
خالد بن الوليد وكان واليا عليهم فأتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
عوف بن مالك فأخبره فقال لخالد ‏"‏ ما منعك أن تعطيه سلبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
استكثرته يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ادفعه إليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فمر خالد بعوف
فجر بردائه ثم قال هل أنجزت لك ما ذكرت لك من رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فسمعه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فاستغضب فقال ‏"‏ لا تعطه يا
خالد لا تعطه يا خالد هل أنتم تاركون لي أمرائي إنما مثلكم ومثلهم
كمثل رجل استرعي إبلا أو غنما فرعاها ثم تحين سقيها فأوردها حوضا
فشرعت فيه فشربت صفوه وتركت كدره فصفوه لكم وكدره عليهم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Auf b. Malik has narrated that a man from the Himyar
tribe killed an enemy and wanted to take the booty. Khalid b.
Walid, who was the commander over them, forbade, him. 'Auf b Malik
(the narrator) came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) and informed him (to this effect). The latter asked Khalid:
What prevented you from giving the booty to him? Khalid said: I
thought it was too much. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Hand it over
to him. Now when Khalid by Auf, the latter pulled him by his cloak
and said (by way of chafing him): Hasn't the same thing happened
what I reported to you from the Messenger of Allah (may peace he
upon him)? When the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
heard it. he was angry (and said): Khalid, don't give him, Khalid,
don't give him. Are you going to desert the commanders appointed by
roe? Your similitude and theirs is like a person who took camels
and sheep for grazing. He grazed them and when it was time for them
to have a drink, he brought them to a pool. So they drank from it,
drinking away its clear water and leaving the turbid water below So
the clear water (i. e. the best reward) is for you and the turbid
water (i e. blame) is for them.</english-text>
</hadith>
