<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14609</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4672</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20450, 10704</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زهير بن حرب، حدثنا عمر بن يونس، حدثنا عكرمة بن
عمار، حدثني إياس بن سلمة، حدثني أبي قال، غزونا فزارة وعلينا أبو بكر
أمره رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم علينا فلما كان بيننا وبين الماء
ساعة أمرنا أبو بكر فعرسنا ثم شن الغارة فورد الماء فقتل من قتل عليه
وسبى وأنظر إلى عنق من الناس فيهم الذراري فخشيت أن يسبقوني إلى الجبل
فرميت بسهم بينهم وبين الجبل فلما رأوا السهم وقفوا فجئت بهم أسوقهم
وفيهم امرأة من بني فزارة عليها قشع من أدم - قال القشع النطع - معها
ابنة لها من أحسن العرب فسقتهم حتى أتيت بهم أبا بكر فنفلني أبو بكر
ابنتها فقدمنا المدينة وما كشفت لها ثوبا فلقيني رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في السوق فقال ‏"‏ يا سلمة هب لي المرأة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت يا
رسول الله والله لقد أعجبتني وما كشفت لها ثوبا ثم لقيني رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم من الغد في السوق فقال لي ‏"‏ يا سلمة هب لي
المرأة لله أبوك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت هي لك يا رسول الله فوالله ما كشفت لها
ثوبا فبعث بها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى أهل مكة ففدى بها
ناسا من المسلمين كانوا أسروا بمكة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Salama (b.
al-Akwa') who said: We fought against the Fazara and Abu Bakr was
the commander over us. He had been appointed by the Messenger oi
Allah (may peace be upon him). When we were onlv at an hour's
distance from the water of the enemy, Abu Bakr ordered us to
attack. We made a halt during the last part of the night tor rest
and then we attacked from all sides and reached their
watering-place where a battle was fought. Some of the enemies were
killed and some were taken prisoners. I saw a group of persons that
consisted of women and children. I was afraid lest they should
reach the mountain before me, so I shot an arrow between them and
the mountain. When they saw the arrow, they stopped. So I brought
them, driving them along. Among them was a woman from Banu Fazara.
She was wearing a leather coat. With her was her daughter who was
one of the prettiest girls in Arabia. I drove them along until I
brought them to Abu Bakr who bestowed that girl upon me as a prize.
So we arrived in Medina. I had not yet disrobed her when the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) met me in the street and
said: Give me that girl, O Salama. I said: Messenger of Allah, she
has fascinated me. I had not yet disrobed her. When on the next
day. the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) ag;tin met me
in the street, he said: O Salama, give me that girl, may God bless
your father. I said: She is for you. Messenger of Allah! By Allah.
I have not yet disrobed her. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) sent her to the people of Mecca, and surrendered her as
ransom for a number of Muslims who had been kept as prisoners at
Mecca.</english-text>
</hadith>
