<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14618</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4681</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20184, 20150, 30022, 30115, 20184, 20150,
11176, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا ابن نمير، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا أبي ح،
وحدثنا زهير بن حرب، والحسن بن علي الحلواني قالا حدثنا يعقوب، - وهو
ابن إبراهيم - حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، أخبرني عروة بن
الزبير، أن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرته أن فاطمة بنت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سألت أبا بكر بعد وفاة رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أن يقسم لها ميراثها مما ترك رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم مما أفاء الله عليه ‏.‏ فقال لها أبو بكر إن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ لا نورث ما تركنا صدقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وعاشت بعد رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ستة أشهر وكانت فاطمة تسأل أبا بكر نصيبها
مما ترك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من خيبر وفدك وصدقته بالمدينة
فأبى أبو بكر عليها ذلك وقال لست تاركا شيئا كان رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يعمل به إلا عملت به إني أخشى إن تركت شيئا من أمره أن أزيغ
فأما صدقته بالمدينة فدفعها عمر إلى علي وعباس فغلبه عليها علي وأما
خيبر وفدك فأمسكهما عمر وقال هما صدقة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
كانتا لحقوقه التي تعروه ونوائبه وأمرهما إلى من ولي الأمر قال فهما
على ذلك إلى اليوم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated by 'Urwa b Zubair on the
authority of 'A'isha, wife of the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon
him), that Fatima, daughter of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him), requested Abu Bakr, after the death of the Messenger of
Allah (may peace he upon him), that he should set apart her share
from what the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) had left
from the properties that God had bestowed upon him. Abu Bakr said
to her: The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said:" We do
not have any heirs; what we leave behind is Sadaqa (charity)." The
narrator said: She (Fatima) lived six months after the death of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) and she used to demand
from Abu Bakr her share from the legacy of the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) from Khaibar, Fadak and his charitable
endowments at Medina. Abu Bakr refused to give her this, and said:
I am not going to give up doing anything which the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) used to do. I am afraid that it I go
against his instructions in any matter I shall deviate from the
right course. So far as the charitable endowments at Medina were
concerned, 'Umar handed them over to 'Ali and Abbas, but 'Ali got
the better of him (and kept the property under his exclusive
possession). And as far as Khaibar and Fadak were concerned 'Umar
kept them with him, and said: These are the endowments of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) (to the Umma). Their
income was spent on the discharge of the responsibilities that
devolved upon him on the emergencies he had to meet. And their
management was to be in the hands of one who managed the affairs
(of the Islamic State). The narrator said: They have been managed
as such up to this day.</english-text>
</hadith>
