<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14639</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4702</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني أبو الطاهر، وحرملة، قالا أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني
يونس، عن ابن، شهاب عن أنس بن مالك، قال لما قدم المهاجرون من مكة
المدينة قدموا وليس بأيديهم شىء وكان الأنصار أهل الأرض والعقار
فقاسمهم الأنصار على أن أعطوهم أنصاف ثمار أموالهم كل عام ويكفونهم
العمل والمئونة وكانت أم أنس بن مالك وهى تدعى أم سليم - وكانت أم عبد
الله بن أبي طلحة كان أخا لأنس لأمه - وكانت أعطت أم أنس رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم عذاقا لها فأعطاها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
أم أيمن مولاته أم أسامة بن زيد ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب فأخبرني أنس بن مالك
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لما فرغ من قتال أهل خيبر وانصرف إلى
المدينة رد المهاجرون إلى الأنصار منائحهم التي كانوا منحوهم من
ثمارهم - قال - فرد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى أمي عذاقها
وأعطى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أم أيمن مكانهن من حائطه ‏.‏ قال
ابن شهاب وكان من شأن أم أيمن أم أسامة بن زيد أنها كانت وصيفة لعبد
الله بن عبد المطلب وكانت من الحبشة فلما ولدت آمنة رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم بعد ما توفي أبوه فكانت أم أيمن تحضنه حتى كبر رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأعتقها ثم أنكحها زيد بن حارثة ثم توفيت بعد
ما توفي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بخمسة أشهر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Anas b.
Malik who said: When the Muhajirs migrated from Mecca to Medina;
they came (in a state that) they had not anything (i. e. money) in
theirhands, while the Ansar possessed lands and date palms. They
divided their properties with the Muhajirs. The Ansar divided and
gave them on the condition that they would give half the fruit from
the orchards every year, and the Muhajirs would recompense them by
working with them and putting in labour. The mother of Anas b.
Malik was called Umm Sulaim and she was also the mother of
'Abdullah b. Talha who was a brother of Anas from his mother's
side. The mother of Anas had given the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) her date-palms. He bestowed them upon Umm Aiman,
the slave-girl who had been freed by him and was the mother of
Usama b. Zaid. When the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
had finished the war with the people of Khaibar and returned to
Medina, the Muhajirs returned to the Ansar all the gifts which they
had given them out of the fruits. (Anas b. Malik said: ) The
Messenger of. Allah (may peace be upon him) returned to my mother
her date-palms and gave to Umm Aiman instead of them date-palms
from his orchard. Ibn Shihab says that Umm Aiman was the mother of
Usama b. Zaid who was the slave-girl of 'Abdullah b.
'Abd-ul-Muttalib and hailed from Abyssinia. When Amina gave birth
to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) after the death
of his father, Umm Aiman used to nurse him until he grew up. He
(later on) freed her and married her to Zaid b. Haritha. She died
five months after the death of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him).</english-text>
</hadith>
