<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14657</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4721</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30106, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عفان، حدثنا حماد بن
سلمة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شاور حين
بلغه إقبال أبي سفيان قال فتكلم أبو بكر فأعرض عنه ثم تكلم عمر فأعرض
عنه فقام سعد بن عبادة فقال إيانا تريد يا رسول الله والذي نفسي بيده
لو أمرتنا أن نخيضها البحر لأخضناها ولو أمرتنا أن نضرب أكبادها إلى
برك الغماد لفعلنا - قال - فندب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الناس
فانطلقوا حتى نزلوا بدرا ووردت عليهم روايا قريش وفيهم غلام أسود لبني
الحجاج فأخذوه فكان أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يسألونه عن
أبي سفيان وأصحابه ‏.‏ فيقول ما لي علم بأبي سفيان ولكن هذا أبو جهل
وعتبة وشيبة وأمية بن خلف ‏.‏ فإذا قال ذلك ضربوه فقال نعم أنا أخبركم
هذا أبو سفيان ‏.‏ فإذا تركوه فسألوه فقال ما لي بأبي سفيان علم ولكن
هذا أبو جهل وعتبة وأمية بن خلف في الناس ‏.‏ فإذا قال هذا أيضا ضربوه
ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائم يصلي فلما رأى ذلك انصرف قال ‏"‏
والذي نفسي بيده لتضربوه إذا صدقكم وتتركوه إذا كذبكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا مصرع فلان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
ويضع يده على الأرض ها هنا وها هنا قال فما ماط أحدهم عن موضع يد رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Anas that
when (the news of) the advance of Abu Sufyan (at the head of a
force) reached him. the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
held consultations with his Companions. The narrator said: Abu Bakr
spoke (expressing his own views), but he (the Holy Prophet) did not
pay heed to him. Then spoke 'Umar (expressing his views), but he
(the Holy Prophet) did not pay heed to him (too). Then Sa'd b.
'Ubada stood up and said: Messenger of Allah, you want us (to
speak). By God in Whose control is my life, if you order us to
plunge our horses into the sea, we would do so. If you order us to
goad our horses to the most distant place like Bark al-Ghimad, we
would do so. The narrator said: Now the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) called upon the people (for the encounter). So
they set out and encamped at Badr. (Soon) the water-carriers of the
Quraish arrived. Among them was a black slave belonging to Banu
al-Hajjaj. The Companions of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) caught him and interrogated him about Abu Sufyan and his
companions. He said: I know nothing about Abu Sufyan, but Abu Jahl,
Utba, Shaiba and Umayya b. Khalaf are there. When he said this,
they beat him. Then he said: All right, I will tell you about Abu
Sufyan. They would stop beating him and then ask him (again) about
Abu Sufyan. He would again say', I know nothing about Abu Sufyan,
but Abu Jahl. 'Utba, Shaiba and Umayya b. Khalaf are there. When he
said this, they beat him likewise. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) was standing in prayer. When he saw this he
finished his prayer and said: By Allah in Whose control is my life,
you beat him when he is telling you the truth, and you let him go
when he tells you a lie. The narrator said: Then the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: This is the place where so and
so would be killed. He placed his hand on the earth (saying) here
and here; (and) none of them fell away from the place which the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) had indicated by placing
his hand on the earth.</english-text>
</hadith>
