<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14660</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4724</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 20300, 20021, 11269, 11865</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن الدارمي، حدثنا يحيى بن
حسان، حدثنا حماد، بن سلمة أخبرنا ثابت، عن عبد الله بن رباح، قال
وفدنا إلى معاوية بن أبي سفيان وفينا أبو هريرة فكان كل رجل منا يصنع
طعاما يوما لأصحابه فكانت نوبتي فقلت يا أبا هريرة اليوم نوبتي ‏.‏
فجاءوا إلى المنزل ولم يدرك طعامنا فقلت يا أبا هريرة لو حدثتنا عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى يدرك طعامنا فقال كنا مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم الفتح فجعل خالد بن الوليد على المجنبة اليمنى
وجعل الزبير على المجنبة اليسرى وجعل أبا عبيدة على البياذقة وبطن
الوادي فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا هريرة ادع لي الأنصار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فدعوتهم فجاءوا
يهرولون فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر الأنصار هل ترون أوباش قريش ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا
نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ انظروا إذا لقيتموهم غدا أن تحصدوهم حصدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وأخفى بيده ووضع يمينه على شماله وقال ‏"‏ موعدكم الصفا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فما أشرف يومئذ لهم أحد إلا أناموه - قال - وصعد رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم الصفا وجاءت الأنصار فأطافوا بالصفا فجاء أبو سفيان فقال يا
رسول الله أبيدت خضراء قريش لا قريش بعد اليوم ‏.‏ قال أبو سفيان قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من دخل دار أبي سفيان فهو آمن ومن
ألقى السلاح فهو آمن ومن أغلق بابه فهو آمن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت الأنصار أما
الرجل فقد أخذته رأفة بعشيرته ورغبة في قريته ‏.‏ ونزل الوحى على رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ قلتم أما الرجل فقد أخذته رأفة
بعشيرته ورغبة في قريته ‏.‏ ألا فما اسمي إذا - ثلاث مرات - أنا محمد
عبد الله ورسوله هاجرت إلى الله وإليكم فالمحيا محياكم والممات مماتكم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا والله ما قلنا إلا ضنا بالله ورسوله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن
الله ورسوله يصدقانكم ويعذرانكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Abdullah b.
Rabah who said: We came to Mu'awiya b. Abu Sufyan as a deputation
and Abu Huraira was among us. Each of us would prepare food for his
companions turn by turn for a day. (Accordingly) when it was my
turn I said: Abu Huraira, it is my turn today. So they came to my
place. The food was not yet ready, so I said to Abu Huraira: I wish
you could narrate to us a tradition from the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) until the food was ready. (Complying with
my request) Abu Huraira said: We were with the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) on the day of the Conquest of Mecca. He
appointed Khalid b. Walid as commander of the right flank, Zubair
as commander of the left flank, and Abu 'Ubaida as commander of the
foot-soldiers (who were to advance) to the interior of the valley.
He (then) said: Abu Huraira, call the Ansar to me. So I called out
to them and they came hurriedly. He said: O ye Assembly of the
Ansaar, do you see the ruffians of the Quraish? They said: Yes. He
said: See, when you meet them tomorrow, wipe them out. He hinted at
this with his hand, placing his right hand on his left and said:
You will meet us at as-Safa'. (Abu Huraira continued): Whoever was
seen by them that day was put to death. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) ascended the mount of as-Safa'. The Ansar also
came there and surrounded the mount. Then came Abu Sufyan and said:
Messenger ot Allah, the Quraish have perished. No member of the
Quraish tribe will survive this day. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) said: Who enters the house of Abu Safyin will be
safe, who lays down arms will be safe, who locks his door will be
safe. (some of) the Ansar said: (After all) the man has been swayed
by tenderness towards his family and love for his city. At this,
Divine inspiration descended upon the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him). He said: You were saying that the man has been swayed
by tenderness towards his family and love for his city. Do you know
what my name is? I am Muhammad, the bondman of God and His
Messenger. (He repeated this thrice.) I left my native place for
the take of Allah and joined you. So I will live with you and die
with you. Now the Ansar said: By God, we said (that) only out of
our greed for Allah and His Messenger. He said: Allah and His
Apostle testify to you and accept your apology.</english-text>
</hadith>
