<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14668</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4732</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30106, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عفان، حدثنا حماد بن
سلمة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، أن قريشا، صالحوا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فيهم سهيل بن عمرو فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لعلي ‏"‏ اكتب بسم
الله الرحمن الرحيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سهيل أما باسم الله فما ندري ما بسم
الله الرحمن الرحيم ولكن اكتب ما نعرف باسمك اللهم فقال ‏"‏ اكتب من
محمد رسول الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لو علمنا أنك رسول الله لاتبعناك ولكن
اكتب اسمك واسم أبيك ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اكتب من
محمد بن عبد الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاشترطوا على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن
من جاء منكم لم نرده عليكم ومن جاءكم منا رددتموه علينا فقالوا يا
رسول الله أنكتب هذا قال ‏"‏ نعم إنه من ذهب منا إليهم فأبعده الله
ومن جاءنا منهم سيجعل الله له فرجا ومخرجا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Anas that
the Quraish made peace with the Prophet (may peace be upon him).
Among them was Suhail b. Amr. The Prophet (may peace be upon him)
said to 'Ali: Write" In the name of Allah, most Gracious and most
Merciful." Suhail said: As for" Bismillah," we do not know what is
meant by" Bismillah-ir-Rahman-ir-Rahim" (In the name of Allah most
Gracious and most Merciful). But write what we understand, i. e. Bi
ismika allahumma (in thy name. O Allah). Then, the Prophet (may
peace be upon him) said: Write:" From Muhammad, the Messenger of
Allah." They said: If we knew that thou welt the Messenger of
Allah, we would follow you. Therefore, write your name and the name
of your father. So the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him) said:
Write" From Muhammad b. 'Abdullah." They laid the condition on the
Prophet (may peace be upon him) that anyone who joined them from
the Muslims, the Meccans would not return him, and anyone who
joined you (the Muslims) from them, you would send him back to
them. The Companions said: Messenger of Allah, should we write
this? He said: Yes. One who goes away from us to join them-may
Allah keep him away! and one who comes to join us from them (and is
sent back) Allah will provide him relief and a way of
escape.</english-text>
</hadith>
