<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14667</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4731</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 20347, 20347, 11338, 11049, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي، وأحمد بن جناب المصيصي،
جميعا عن عيسى بن يونس، - واللفظ لإسحاق - أخبرنا عيسى بن يونس،
أخبرنا زكرياء، عن أبي إسحاق، عن البراء، قال لما أحصر النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم عند البيت صالحه أهل مكة على أن يدخلها فيقيم بها ثلاثا ولا
يدخلها إلا بجلبان السلاح السيف وقرابه ‏.‏ ولا يخرج بأحد معه من
أهلها ولا يمنع أحدا يمكث بها ممن كان معه ‏.‏ قال لعلي ‏"‏ اكتب
الشرط بيننا بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم هذا ما قاضى عليه محمد رسول الله
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال له المشركون لو نعلم أنك رسول الله تابعناك ولكن اكتب
محمد بن عبد الله ‏.‏ فأمر عليا أن يمحاها فقال علي لا والله لا
أمحاها ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرني مكانها ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأراه مكانها فمحاها وكتب ‏"‏ ابن عبد الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأقام بها
ثلاثة أيام فلما أن كان يوم الثالث قالوا لعلي هذا آخر يوم من شرط
صاحبك فأمره فليخرج ‏.‏ فأخبره بذلك فقال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فخرج ‏.‏
وقال ابن جناب في روايته مكان تابعناك بايعناك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Bara' who
said: When the Prophet (may peace be upon him) was checked from
going to the Ka'ba, the people of Mecca made peace with him'on the
condition that he would (be allowed to) enter Mecca (next year) and
stay there for three days, that he would not enter (the city)
except with swords in their sheaths and arms encased in their
covers, that he would not take eway with him anyone from its
dwellers, nor would he prevent anyone from those with him to stay
on in Mecca (if he so desired). He said to 'Ali: Write down the
terms settled between us. (So 'Ali wrote): In the name of Allah,
most Gracious and most Merciful. This is what Muhammad, the
Messenger of Allah, has settled (with the Meccans), The polytheists
said to him: If we knew that thou art the Messenger of of Allah, we
would follow you. But write: Muhammad b. 'Abdullah. So he told 'Ali
to strike out these words. 'Ali said: No, by Allah, I will not
strike them out. The Messenger of Allah (may Peace be upon him)
said: Show me their place (on the parchment). So he ('Ali) showed
him their place and he (the Holy Prophet) struck them out; and 'Ali
wrote: Ibn 'Abdullah. (According to the terms of the treaty, next
year) the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him) stayed there for
three days When it was the third day, they said to 'Ali: This is
the last day according to the terms of your companion. So tell him
to leave. 'Ali informed the Prophet (may peace be upon him)
accordingly. He said: Yes, and left (the city). Ibn Janab in his
version of the tradition used:" we would swear allegiance to you"
instead of" we would follow you".</english-text>
</hadith>
