<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14676</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4741</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 30123, 20028, 20321, 4057, 11060, 11322,
11405</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زهير بن حرب، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، جميعا عن جرير،
قال زهير حدثنا جرير، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم التيمي، عن أبيه، قال كنا
عند حذيفة فقال رجل لو أدركت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قاتلت معه
وأبليت فقال حذيفة أنت كنت تفعل ذلك لقد رأيتنا مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ليلة الأحزاب وأخذتنا ريح شديدة وقر فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ألا رجل يأتيني بخبر القوم جعله الله معي يوم
القيامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فسكتنا فلم يجبه منا أحد ثم قال ‏"‏ ألا رجل يأتينا
بخبر القوم جعله الله معي يوم القيامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فسكتنا فلم يجبه منا
أحد ثم قال ‏"‏ ألا رجل يأتينا بخبر القوم جعله الله معي يوم القيامة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فسكتنا فلم يجبه منا أحد فقال ‏"‏ قم يا حذيفة فأتنا بخبر
القوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلم أجد بدا إذ دعاني باسمي أن أقوم قال ‏"‏ اذهب فأتني
بخبر القوم ولا تذعرهم على ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما وليت من عنده جعلت كأنما أمشي
في حمام حتى أتيتهم فرأيت أبا سفيان يصلي ظهره بالنار فوضعت سهما في
كبد القوس فأردت أن أرميه فذكرت قول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
ولا تذعرهم على ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولو رميته لأصبته فرجعت وأنا أمشي في مثل
الحمام فلما أتيته فأخبرته بخبر القوم وفرغت قررت فألبسني رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم من فضل عباءة كانت عليه يصلي فيها فلم أزل نائما
حتى أصبحت فلما أصبحت قال ‏"‏ قم يا نومان ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated by Ibrahim al-Taimi on the
authority of his father who said: We were sitting in the company of
Hudhaifa. A man said: If I were in the time of the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him), I would have fought by his side and
would have striven hard for his causes. Hudhaifa said: You might
have done that, (but you should not make a flourish of your
enthusiasm). I was with the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) on the night of the Battle of Abzib and we were gripped by a
violent wind and severe cold. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
him) said: Hark, the man who (goes reconnoitring and) brings me the
news of the enemy shall be ranked with me on the Day of Judgment by
Allah (the Glorious and Exalted). We all kept quiet and none of us
responed to him. (Again) he said: Hark, a man who (goes
reconnoitring and) brings me the news of the enemy shall be ranked
with me on the Day of Judgment by Allah (the Glorious and Exalted).
We kept quiet and none of us responded to him. He again said: Hark,
a man who (goes reconnoitring and) brings me the news of the enemy
shall be ranked with me on the Day of Judgtuent by Allah (the
Glorious and Exalted) Then he said: Get up Hudhaifa, bring me the
news of the enemy. When he called me by name I had no alternative
but to get up. He said: Go and bring me information about the
enemy, and do nothing that may provoke them against me. When I left
him, I felt warm as if I were walking in a heated bath untill I
reached them. I saw Abu Sufyan warming his back against fire I put
an arrow in the middle of the bow. intending to shoot at him, when
I recalled the words of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him)" Do not provoke them against me." Had I shot at him, I would
have hit him. But I returned and (felt warm as if) I were walking
in a heated bath (hammam). Presenting myself before him, I gave him
information about the enemy. When I had done so, I began to feel
cold, so the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) wrapped me
in a blanket that he had in excess to his own requirement and with
which he used to cover himself while saying his prayers. So I
continued to sleep until it was morning. When it was morning he
said: Get up, O heavy sleeper.</english-text>
</hadith>
