<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14724</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4791</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20298, 11272, 11046, 10627, 38487, 20214,
11272, 172, 10627</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، أخبرنا وهب بن جرير بن حازم،
حدثني أبي قال، سمعت قيسا، يحدث عن يزيد بن هرمز، ح وحدثني محمد بن
حاتم، - واللفظ له - قال حدثنا بهز، حدثنا جرير بن حازم، حدثني قيس بن
سعد، عن يزيد بن هرمز، قال كتب نجدة بن عامر إلى ابن عباس قال فشهدت
ابن عباس حين قرأ كتابه وحين كتب جوابه وقال ابن عباس والله لولا أن
أرده عن نتن يقع فيه ما كتبت إليه ولا نعمة عين قال فكتب إليه إنك
سألت عن سهم ذي القربى الذي ذكر الله من هم وإنا كنا نرى أن قرابة
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هم نحن فأبى ذلك علينا قومنا وسألت عن
اليتيم متى ينقضي يتمه وإنه إذا بلغ النكاح وأونس منه رشد ودفع إليه
ماله فقد انقضى يتمه وسألت هل كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقتل
من صبيان المشركين أحدا فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لم يكن يقتل
منهم أحدا وأنت فلا تقتل منهم أحدا إلا أن تكون تعلم منهم ما علم
الخضر من الغلام حين قتله وسألت عن المرأة والعبد هل كان لهما سهم
معلوم إذا حضروا البأس فإنهم لم يكن لهم سهم معلوم إلا أن يحذيا من
غنائم القوم.</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the anthority of Yazid b.
Hurmuz who said: Najda wrote to Ibn Abbas. I was sitting in the
company of Ibn 'Abbas when he read his letter and wrote its reply.
Ibn Abbas said: Were it not for preventing him from falling into
wickedness. I would not have replied to his letter, may he never be
joyful. He wrote in reply to him referring to the share of the
close relatives (of the Holy Prophet) (from the booty) whom God has
mentioned. (I have to tell you that) we thought we were the close
relatives of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him), but
our people have refused to recognise us as such. You have asked
about the orphan as to when his orphanhood comes to an end. (I have
to say that) when he reaches the age of marriage, attains maturity
of mind, and his property is returned to him, then he is no longer
an orphan. You have inquired whether the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upo him) used to kill anyone from the children of the
polytheists in the war. (You should know that) the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) used not to kill any one of their
children, and you (too) should not kill any one of them, except
when you knew about them what Khadir had known about the boy whom
he killed. And you have inquired whether there is a fixed share of
the booty for women and slaves when they participate in a battle.
(I have to tell you that) there is no fixed share for them except
that they will be given some reward from the spoils of
war.</english-text>
</hadith>
