<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14736</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4803</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jihad and Expedition - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20033, 20001, 20029, 20001, 10937,
10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن مهدي، عن مالك،
ح وحدثنيه أبو الطاهر - واللفظ له - حدثني عبد الله بن وهب، عن مالك
بن أنس، عن الفضيل بن أبي، عبد الله عن عبد الله بن نيار الأسلمي، عن
عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أنها قالت
خرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قبل بدر فلما كان بحرة الوبرة أدركه
رجل قد كان يذكر منه جرأة ونجدة ففرح أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حين رأوه فلما أدركه قال لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جئت
لأتبعك وأصيب معك قال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تؤمن بالله
ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا قال ‏"‏ فارجع فلن أستعين بمشرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت
ثم مضى حتى إذا كنا بالشجرة أدركه الرجل فقال له كما قال أول مرة فقال
له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كما قال أول مرة قال ‏"‏ فارجع فلن
أستعين بمشرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم رجع فأدركه بالبيداء فقال له كما قال أول
مرة ‏"‏ تؤمن بالله ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فانطلق ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of A'isha, wife
of the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him), who said: The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) set out for Badr. When
he reached Harrat-ul-Wabara (a place four miles from Medina) a man
met him who was known for his valour and courage. The Companions of
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) were pleased to see
him. He said: I have come so that I may follow you and get a share
from the booty. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said
to him: Do you believe in Allah and His Apostle? He said: No. The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Go back, I will
not seek help from a Mushrik (polytheist). He went on until we
reached Shajara, where the man met him again. He asked him the same
question again and the man gave him the same answer. He said: Go
back. Im will not seek help from a Mushrik. The man returned and
overtook him at Baida'? He asked him as he had asked previously: Do
you believe in Allah and His Apostle? The man said: Yes. The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said to him: Then come
along with us.</english-text>
</hadith>
