<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14748</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4815</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 30201, 20159, 10554</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة قالا حدثنا
حاتم، - وهو ابن إسماعيل - عن المهاجر بن مسمار، عن عامر بن سعد بن
أبي وقاص، قال كتبت إلى جابر بن سمرة مع غلامي نافع أن أخبرني بشىء،
سمعته من، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال فكتب إلى سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم جمعة عشية رجم الأسلمي يقول ‏"‏ لا يزال الدين
قائما حتى تقوم الساعة أو يكون عليكم اثنا عشر خليفة كلهم من قريش ‏"‏
‏.‏ وسمعته يقول ‏"‏ عصيبة من المسلمين يفتتحون البيت الأبيض بيت كسرى
أو آل كسرى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وسمعته يقول ‏"‏ إن بين يدى الساعة كذابين
فاحذروهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وسمعته يقول ‏"‏ إذا أعطى الله أحدكم خيرا فليبدأ
بنفسه وأهل بيته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وسمعته يقول ‏"‏ أنا الفرط على الحوض ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Amir b. Sa'd
b. Abu Waqqas who said: I wrote (a letter) to Jabir b. Samura and
sent it to him through my servant Nafi', asking him to inform me of
something he had heard from the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him). He wrote to me (in reply): I heard the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) say on Friday evening, the day on
which al-Aslami was stoned to death (for committing adultery): The
Islamic religion will continue until the Hour has been established,
or you have been ruled over by twelve Caliphs, all of them being
from the Quraish. also heard him say: A small force of the Muslims
will capture the white palace, the police of the Persian Emperor or
his descendants. I also heard him say: Before the Day of Judgment
there will appear (a number of) impostors. You are to guard against
them. I also heard him say: When God grants wealth to any one of
you, he should first spend it on himself and his family (and then
give it in charity to the poor). I heard him (also) say: I will be
your forerunner at the Cistern (expecting your
arrival).</english-text>
</hadith>
