<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14870</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4941</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو الطاهر، أحمد بن عمرو بن سرح أخبرنا ابن وهب،
أخبرني يونس، بن يزيد قال قال ابن شهاب أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أن
عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت كانت المؤمنات إذا هاجرن
إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يمتحن بقول الله عز وجل ‏{‏ يا أيها
النبي إذا جاءك المؤمنات يبايعنك على أن لا يشركن بالله شيئا ولا
يسرقن ولا يزنين‏}‏ إلى آخر الآية ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فمن أقر بهذا من
المؤمنات فقد أقر بالمحنة وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا
أقررن بذلك من قولهن قال لهن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ انطلقن
فقد بايعتكن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولا والله ما مست يد رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يد امرأة قط ‏.‏ غير أنه يبايعهن بالكلام - قالت عائشة - والله
ما أخذ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على النساء قط إلا بما أمره الله
تعالى وما مست كف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كف امرأة قط وكان يقول
لهن إذا أخذ عليهن ‏"‏ قد بايعتكن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ كلاما ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of 'A'isha, the
wife of the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him). She said: When
the believing women migrated (to Medina) and came to the Messenger
of Allah (may peace be upon him), they would be tested in
accordance with the following words of Allah. the Almighty and
Exalted:" O Prophet, when believing women come to thee to take the
oath of fealty to thee that they will not associate in worship
anything with God, that they will not steal. that, they will not
commit adultery..." to the end of the verse (lx. 62). Whoso from
the believing women accepted these conditions and agreed to abide
by them were considered to have offered themselves for swearing
fealty. When they had (formally) declared their resolve to do so,
the Messenger of Allah (may peace he upon him) would say to them:
You may go. I have confirmed your fealty. By God, the hand of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) never touched the hand
of a woman. He would take the oath of fealty from them by oral
declaration. By God, the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
never took any vow from women except that which God had ordered him
to take, and his palm never touched the palm of a woman. When he
had taken their vow, he would tell them that he had taken the oath
from them orally.</english-text>
</hadith>
