<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14896</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4967</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20028, 11379, 11406, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا جرير، عن عمارة، - وهو ابن
القعقاع - عن أبي زرعة، عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تضمن الله لمن خرج في سبيله لا يخرجه إلا جهادا في
سبيلي وإيمانا بي وتصديقا برسلي فهو على ضامن أن أدخله الجنة أو أرجعه
إلى مسكنه الذي خرج منه نائلا ما نال من أجر أو غنيمة ‏.‏ والذي نفس
محمد بيده ما من كلم يكلم في سبيل الله إلا جاء يوم القيامة كهيئته
حين كلم لونه لون دم وريحه مسك والذي نفس محمد بيده لولا أن يشق على
المسلمين ما قعدت خلاف سرية تغزو في سبيل الله أبدا ولكن لا أجد سعة
فأحملهم ولا يجدون سعة ويشق عليهم أن يتخلفوا عني والذي نفس محمد بيده
لوددت أني أغزو في سبيل الله فأقتل ثم أغزو فأقتل ثم أغزو فأقتل ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Abu Huraira
that the Messenger of Allah (may peace upon him) said: Allah has
undertaken to look after the affairs of one who goes out to fight
in His way believing in Him and affirming the truth of His
Apostles. He is committed to His care that Re will either admit him
to Paradise or bring him back to his home from where he set out
with a reward or (his share of) booty. By the Being in Whose Hand
is the life of Muhammad. If a person gets wounded in the way of
Allah, he will come on the Day of Judgment with his wound in the
same condition as it was when it was first inflicted; its colour
being the colour of blood but its smell will be the smell of musk.
By, the Being in Whose Hand is Muhammad's life, if it were not to
be too hard upon the Muslime. I would not lag behind any expedition
which is going to fight in the cause of Allah. But I do not have
abundant means to provide them (the Mujahids) with riding beasts,
nor have they (i. e. all of them) abundant means (to provide
themselves with all the means of Jihad) so that they could he left
behind. By the Being in Whose Hand is Mubammgls lac, I love to
fight in the way of Allah and be killed, to fight and again be
killed and to fight again and be killed.</english-text>
</hadith>
