<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14908</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4979</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30335, 20401, 10912, 274</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حسن بن علي الحلواني، حدثنا أبو توبة، حدثنا
معاوية بن سلام، عن زيد بن سلام، أنه سمع أبا سلام، قال حدثني النعمان
بن بشير، قال كنت عند منبر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رجل ما
أبالي أن لا أعمل عملا بعد الإسلام إلا أن أسقي الحاج ‏.‏ وقال آخر ما
أبالي أن لا أعمل عملا بعد الإسلام إلا أن أعمر المسجد الحرام ‏.‏
وقال آخر الجهاد في سبيل الله أفضل مما قلتم ‏.‏ فزجرهم عمر وقال لا
ترفعوا أصواتكم عند منبر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو يوم الجمعة
ولكن إذا صليت الجمعة دخلت فاستفتيته فيما اختلفتم فيه ‏.‏ فأنزل الله
عز وجل ‏{‏ أجعلتم سقاية الحاج وعمارة المسجد الحرام كمن آمن بالله
واليوم الآخر‏}‏ الآية إلى آخرها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Nu'man b.
Bashir who said: As I was (sitting) near the pulpit of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him), a man said: I do not
care if, after embracing Islam, I do not do any good deed (except)
distributing drinking water among the pilgrims. Another said: I do
not care if, after embracing Islam, I do not do any good deed
beyond maintenance service to the Sacred Mosque. Another said:
Jihad in the way of Allah is better than what you have said. 'Umar
reprimanded them and said: Don't raise your voices near the pulpit
of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) on Friday. When
prayer was over, I entered (the apartment of the Holy Prophet) and
asked his verdict about the matter in which they had differed. (It
was upon this that) Allah, the Almighty and Exalted, revealed the
Qur'anic verse:" Do you make the giving of drinking water to the
pilgrims and the maintenance of the Sacred Mosque equal to (the
service of those) who believe in Allah and the Last Day and strive
hard in the cause of Allah. They are not equal in the sight of God.
And Allah guides not the wrongdoing people" (ix. 20). This
tradition has been narrated on the authority of Nu'man b. Bashir
through another chain of transmitters.</english-text>
</hadith>
