<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14922</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4993</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20354, 30123, 4057, 20347, 11060, 20354, 11060,
11362, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة كلاهما عن أبي
معاوية، ح وحدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، أخبرنا جرير، وعيسى بن يونس،
جميعا عن الأعمش، ح وحدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، - واللفظ له -
حدثنا أسباط، وأبو معاوية قالا حدثنا الأعمش، عن عبد الله بن مرة، عن
مسروق، قال سألنا عبد الله عن هذه الآية، ‏{‏ ولا تحسبن الذين قتلوا
في سبيل الله أمواتا بل أحياء عند ربهم يرزقون‏}‏ قال أما إنا قد
سألنا عن ذلك فقال ‏"‏ أرواحهم في جوف طير خضر لها قناديل معلقة
بالعرش تسرح من الجنة حيث شاءت ثم تأوي إلى تلك القناديل فاطلع إليهم
ربهم اطلاعة فقال هل تشتهون شيئا قالوا أى شىء نشتهي ونحن نسرح من
الجنة حيث شئنا ففعل ذلك بهم ثلاث مرات فلما رأوا أنهم لن يتركوا من
أن يسألوا قالوا يا رب نريد أن ترد أرواحنا في أجسادنا حتى نقتل في
سبيلك مرة أخرى ‏.‏ فلما رأى أن ليس لهم حاجة تركوا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Masruq Who
said: We asked 'Abdullah about the Qur'anic verse:" Think not of
those who are slain in Allah's way as dead. Nay, they are alive,
finding their sustenance in the presence of their Lord.." (iii.
169). He said: We asked the meaning of the verse (from the Holy
Prophet) who said: The souls, of the martyrs live in the bodies of
green birds who have their nests in chandeliers hung from the
throne of the Almighty. They eat the fruits of Paradise from
wherever they like and then nestle in these chandeliers. Once their
Lord cast a glance at them and said: Do ye want anything? They
said: What more shall we desire? We eat the fruit of Paradise from
wherever we like. Their Lord asked them the same question thrice.
When they saw that they will continue to be asked and not left
(without answering the question). they said: O Lord, we wish that
Thou mayest return our souls to our bodies so that we may be slain
in Thy way once again. When He (Allah) saw that they had no need,
they were left (to their joy in heaven).</english-text>
</hadith>
