<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14917</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4988</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11168, 11804, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا ليث، عن سعيد بن أبي سعيد،
عن عبد الله بن أبي، قتادة عن أبي قتادة، أنه سمعه يحدث، عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه قام فيهم فذكر لهم ‏"‏ أن الجهاد في سبيل الله
والإيمان بالله أفضل الأعمال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقام رجل فقال يا رسول الله
أرأيت إن قتلت في سبيل الله تكفر عني خطاياى فقال له رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ نعم إن قتلت في سبيل الله وأنت صابر محتسب مقبل
غير مدبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كيف قلت
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أرأيت إن قتلت في سبيل الله أتكفر عني خطاياى فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ نعم وأنت صابر محتسب مقبل غير مدبر إلا
الدين فإن جبريل عليه السلام قال لي ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of Abu Qatada
that the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) stood up among
them (his Companions) to deliver his sermon in which he told them
that Jihad in the way of Allah and belief in Allah (with all His
Attributes) are the most meritorious of acts. A man stood up and
said: Messenger of Allah, do you think that if I am killed in the
way of Allah, my sins will be blotted out from me? The Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Yes, in case you are killed in
the way of Allah and you were patient and sincere and you always
fought facing the enemy, never turming your back upon him. Then he
added: What have you said (now)? (Wishing to have further assurance
from him for his satisfaction), he asked (again): Do you think if I
am killed in the way of Allah, all my sins will be obliterated from
me? The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Yes, it
you were patient and sincere and always fought facing the enemy and
never turning your back upon him, (all your lapses would be
forgiven) except debt. Gabriel has told me this.</english-text>
</hadith>
