<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14972</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5043</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي، طلحة عن أنس بن مالك، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
كان يدخل على أم حرام بنت ملحان فتطعمه وكانت أم حرام تحت عبادة بن
الصامت فدخل عليها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يوما فأطعمته ثم جلست
تفلي رأسه فنام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم استيقظ وهو يضحك قالت
فقلت ما يضحكك يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ ناس من أمتي عرضوا على غزاة في
سبيل الله يركبون ثبج هذا البحر ملوكا على الأسرة أو مثل الملوك على
الأسرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يشك أيهما قال قالت فقلت يا رسول الله ادع الله أن
يجعلني منهم فدعا لها ثم وضع رأسه فنام ثم استيقظ وهو يضحك قالت فقلت
ما يضحكك يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ ناس من أمتي عرضوا على غزاة في سبيل
الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ كما قال في الأولى قالت فقلت يا رسول الله ادع الله أن
يجعلني منهم قال ‏"‏ أنت من الأولين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فركبت أم حرام بنت ملحان
البحر في زمن معاوية فصرعت عن دابتها حين خرجت من البحر فهلكت
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been reported on the authority of Anas b.
Malik that the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) used to
visit Umm Haram daughter of Milhan (who was the sister of his
foster-mother or his father's aunt). She was the wife of 'Ubada b.
Samit, One day the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) paid
her a visit. She entertained him with food and then sat down to rub
his head. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) dozed off
and when he woke up (after a while), he was laughing. She asked:
What made you laugh. Messenger of Allah? He said: Some people from
my Umma were presented to me who were fighters in the way of Allah
and were sailing in this sea. (Gliding smoothly on the water), they
appeared to be kings or like kings (sitting) on thrones (the
narrator has a doubt about the actual expression used by the Holy
Prophet). She said: Messenger of Allah, pray to Allah that He may
include me among these warriors. He prayed for her. Then he placed
his head (down) and dozed off (again). He woke up laughing, as
before. (She said) I said: Messenger of Allah, what makes you
laugh? He replied: A people from my Umma were presented to me. They
were fighters in Allah's way. (He described them in the same words
as he had described the first warriors.) She said: Messenger of
Allah, pray to God that He may include me among these warriors. He
said: You are among the first ones. Umm Haram daughter of Milhan
sailed in the aea in the time of Mu'awiya. When she came out of the
sea and (was going to mount a riding animal) she fell down and
died.</english-text>
</hadith>
