<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>14995</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5066</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Government - كتاب الإمارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30484, 20377, 11411, 10867</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أحمد بن عبد الرحمن بن وهب، حدثنا عمي عبد الله بن
وهب، حدثنا عمرو بن الحارث، حدثني يزيد بن أبي حبيب، حدثني عبد الرحمن
بن شماسة المهري، قال كنت عند مسلمة بن مخلد وعنده عبد الله بن عمرو
بن العاص فقال عبد الله لا تقوم الساعة إلا على شرار الخلق هم شر من
أهل الجاهلية لا يدعون الله بشىء إلا رده عليهم ‏.‏ فبينما هم على ذلك
أقبل عقبة بن عامر فقال له مسلمة يا عقبة اسمع ما يقول عبد الله ‏.‏
فقال عقبة هو أعلم وأما أنا فسمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول
‏"‏ لا تزال عصابة من أمتي يقاتلون على أمر الله قاهرين لعدوهم لا
يضرهم من خالفهم حتى تأتيهم الساعة وهم على ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال عبد الله
أجل ‏.‏ ثم يبعث الله ريحا كريح المسك مسها مس الحرير فلا تترك نفسا
في قلبه مثقال حبة من الإيمان إلا قبضته ثم يبقى شرار الناس عليهم
تقوم الساعة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It has been narrated on the authority of 'Abd
al-Rahman b. Shamasa al- Mahri who said: I was in the company of
Maslama b. Mukhallad, and 'Abdullah b. 'Amr b. 'As was with him.
'Abdullah said: The Hour shall some oniy when the worst type of
people are left on the earth. They will be worse than the people of
pre-Islamic days. They will get whatever they ask of Allah. While
we were yet sitting when 'Uqba b. 'Amir came, and Maslama said to
him: 'Uqba, listen to what 'Abdullah says. 'Uqba said: He knows
better; so far as I am concerned, I heard the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) say: A group of people from my Umma will
continue to fight in obedience to the Command of Allah, remaining
dominant over their enemies. Those who will oppose them shall not
do them any harm. They will remain ill this condition until the
Hour overtakes them. (At this) 'Abdullah said: Yes. Then Allah will
raise a wild which will be fragrant like musk and whose touch will
be like the touch of silk; (but) it will cause the death of all
(faithful) persons, not leaving behind a single person with an iota
of faith in his heart. Then only the worst of men will remain to be
overwhelmed by the Hour.</english-text>
</hadith>
