<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15143</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5215</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Sacrifices - كتاب الأضاحى</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 20229, 20001, 11104</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي، أخبرنا روح، حدثنا
مالك، عن عبد الله بن، أبي بكر عن عبد الله بن واقد، قال نهى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن أكل لحوم الضحايا بعد ثلاث ‏.‏ قال عبد
الله بن أبي بكر فذكرت ذلك لعمرة فقالت صدق سمعت عائشة تقول دف أهل
أبيات من أهل البادية حضرة الأضحى زمن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ادخروا ثلاثا ثم تصدقوا بما
بقي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما كان بعد ذلك قالوا يا رسول الله إن الناس يتخذون
الأسقية من ضحاياهم ويحملون منها الودك فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ وما ذاك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نهيت أن تؤكل لحوم الضحايا بعد ثلاث
‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إنما نهيتكم من أجل الدافة التي دفت فكلوا وادخروا
وتصدقوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. Waqid reported: Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) forbade (people) to cat the flesh of sacrificed
animals beyond three days. Abdullah b. Abu Bakr said, I made a
mention of that to 'Amra, whereupon she said: He has told the
truth, for I heard 'A'isha say: The poor among the people of the
desert come (to the towns) on the occasion of Id al-Adha during the
lifetime of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). Upon this
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Retain with you
(the flesh) sufficing for three (days), and whatever is left out of
that give in charity. After this. they (the Muslims) said: Allah's
Messenger, the people make waterskins with the (hides) of their
sacrificed animals and they melt fat out of them. Thereupon he
said. What the then? They said: You forbade (us) to eat the flesh
of sacrificial animals beyond threoq (days), whereupon he said: I
forbade you for those (poor persons) who flocked (to the towns on
this occasion for getting meat) but now when (this situation has
improved) you may eat, preserve and give -in
charity.</english-text>
</hadith>
