<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15171</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5244</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>11108, 20029, 20475, 11013, 11045, 31, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني أبو بكر بن إسحاق، أخبرنا سعيد بن كثير بن عفير
أبو عثمان المصري، حدثنا عبد الله بن وهب، حدثني يونس بن يزيد، عن ابن
شهاب، أخبرني علي بن حسين، بن علي أن حسين بن علي، أخبره أن عليا قال
كانت لي شارف من نصيبي من المغنم يوم بدر وكان رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أعطاني شارفا من الخمس يومئذ فلما أردت أن أبتني بفاطمة بنت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم واعدت رجلا صواغا من بني قينقاع يرتحل
معي فنأتي بإذخر أردت أن أبيعه من الصواغين فأستعين به في وليمة عرسي
فبينا أنا أجمع لشارفى متاعا من الأقتاب والغرائر والحبال وشارفاى
مناخان إلى جنب حجرة رجل من الأنصار وجمعت حين جمعت ما جمعت فإذا
شارفاى قد اجتبت أسنمتهما وبقرت خواصرهما وأخذ من أكبادهما فلم أملك
عينى حين رأيت ذلك المنظر منهما قلت من فعل هذا قالوا فعله حمزة بن
عبد المطلب وهو في هذا البيت في شرب من الأنصار غنته قينة وأصحابه
فقالت في غنائها ألا يا حمز للشرف النواء فقام حمزة بالسيف فاجتب
أسنمتهما وبقر خواصرهما فأخذ من أكبادهما قال علي فانطلقت حتى أدخل
على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وعنده زيد بن حارثة - قال - فعرف
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في وجهي الذي لقيت ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما لك ‏"‏ قلت يا رسول الله والله ما رأيت
كاليوم قط عدا حمزة على ناقتى فاجتب أسنمتهما وبقر خواصرهما وها هو ذا
في بيت معه شرب - قال - فدعا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بردائه
فارتداه ثم انطلق يمشي واتبعته أنا وزيد بن حارثة حتى جاء الباب الذي
فيه حمزة فاستأذن فأذنوا له فإذا هم شرب فطفق رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يلوم حمزة فيما فعل فإذا حمزة محمرة عيناه فنظر حمزة إلى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم صعد النظر إلى ركبتيه ثم صعد النظر فنظر
إلى سرته ثم صعد النظر فنظر إلى وجهه فقال حمزة وهل أنتم إلا عبيد
لأبي فعرف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه ثمل فنكص رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم على عقبيه القهقرى وخرج وخرجنا معه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Husain b. 'Ali reported 'Ali having said: There fell
to my lot a she-camel out of the spoils of war on the Day of Badr,
and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) gave me (another)
she-camel on that day out of the Khums (one-fifth reserved for
Allah and His Messenger). When I made up my mind to consummate my
marriage with Fatima, the daughter of Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him), I prevailed upon a goldsmith of the tribe of Qainuqa'
to go along with me so that we might bring Idhkhir wishing to sell
that to the goldsmiths and thus I should be able to arrange my
wedding feast. While I was arranging the equipments. i. e. litters,
sacks and ropes, my two she-camels were sitting down at the side of
the apartment of a person of the Ansar. I collected (the different
articles of equipment) and found to my surprise that their humps
had been chopped off and their haunches had been cut off and their
livers had been taken out. I could not help weeping when I saw that
plight of theirs. I said: Who has done that? They said: Hamza b.
'Abd al-Muttalib has done this. and he is in this house dead drunk
in the company of some of the Ansair with asinging girl singing
before him and his companions. She said in her song: O Hamza. get
up and attack these falty she-camels. Thereupon Hamza stood up with
a sword (in his hand) and cut off their humps and ripped their
haunches and tore out their livers. 'Ali said: I went away until I
came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and there was
with him Zaid b. Haritha. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
recognised from my face what I had experienced, whereupon Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: What has happened to you? I
said: Messenger of Allah, by Allah, I have never seen (such an
unfortunate day) as this day. Hamza has committed aggression to my
she-camels, and has cut off their humps. and ripped their haunches,
and he is in a house in the company of some drunkards. (Hearing
this) Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) sent for his mantle
and, putting it on him, he proceeded, and I and Zaid b. Haritha
followed him, until he came to the door (of the house) in which
there was Hamza. He (the Holy Prophet) sought permission which they
granted him. and they were all drunk. Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) began to reprimand Hamza for what he had done. Hamza's
eyes were red. He cast a glance at Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) and then looked towards his knees. and then lifted his
eyes and cast a glance at his waist and then lifted his eyes and
saw his face. And then Hamza said: Are you anything but the slaves
of my father? Alah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) came to know
that he was intoxicated, and he thus turned upon his heels, and
came out, and we also came out along with him.</english-text>
</hadith>
