<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15169</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5242</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20381, 11070, 11013, 11045, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى التميمي، أخبرنا حجاج بن محمد، عن
ابن جريج، حدثني ابن شهاب، عن علي بن حسين بن علي، عن أبيه، حسين بن
علي عن علي بن أبي طالب، قال أصبت شارفا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في مغنم يوم بدر وأعطاني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شارفا
أخرى فأنختهما يوما عند باب رجل من الأنصار وأنا أريد أن أحمل عليهما
إذخرا لأبيعه ومعي صائغ من بني قينقاع فأستعين به على وليمة فاطمة
وحمزة بن عبد المطلب يشرب في ذلك البيت معه قينة تغنيه فقالت ألا يا
حمز للشرف النواء فثار إليهما حمزة بالسيف فجب أسنمتهما وبقر خواصرهما
ثم أخذ من أكبادهما ‏.‏ قلت لابن شهاب ومن السنام قال قد جب أسنمتهما
فذهب بها ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب قال علي فنظرت إلى منظر أفظعني فأتيت نبي
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وعنده زيد بن حارثة فأخبرته الخبر فخرج ومعه
زيد وانطلقت معه فدخل على حمزة فتغيظ عليه فرفع حمزة بصره فقال هل
أنتم إلا عبيد لآبائي فرجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقهقر حتى
خرج عنهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Ali b. Abu Talib reported; There fell to my lot
along with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) an old
she-camel from the spoils of Badr. Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) granted me another camel. I made them kneel down one day
at the door of an Ansari, and I wanted to carry on them Idhkhir (a
kind of grass) in order to sell that. There was with me a goldsmith
of the tribe of Qainuqa'. I saught to give a wedding feast (on the
occasion of marriage with) Fatima with the help of that (the price
accrued from the sale of this grass). And Hamza b. 'Abd al-Muttalib
was busy in drinking in that house in the company of a singing girl
who was singing to him. She said: Hamza, get up for slaughtering
the fat she-camels. Hamza attacked them with the sword and cut off
their humps and ripped their haunches, and then took out their
livers. I said to Ibn Shihab: Did he take out anything from the
hump? He said: He cut off the humps altogether. Ibn Shihab reported
'Ali having said: I saw this (horrible) sight and it shocked me,
and I came to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) and there was
Zaid b, Haritha with him and communicated to him this news. He came
in the company of Zaid and I also went along with him and he went
to Hamza and he expressed anger with him. Hamza raised his eyes and
said: Are you (not) but the servants of my father? Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) turned back on his heels (on
hearing this) until he went away from them.</english-text>
</hadith>
