<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15365</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5438</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20331, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، ح
وحدثنا ابن نمير، - واللفظ له - حدثنا أبي، حدثنا سعد بن سعيد، حدثني
أنس بن مالك، قال بعثني أبو طلحة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
لأدعوه وقد جعل طعاما - قال - فأقبلت ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
مع الناس فنظر إلى فاستحييت فقلت أجب أبا طلحة ‏.‏ فقال للناس ‏"‏
قوموا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أبو طلحة يا رسول الله إنما صنعت لك شيئا - قال -
فمسها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ودعا فيها بالبركة ثم قال ‏"‏
أدخل نفرا من أصحابي عشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏ كلوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأخرج لهم
شيئا من بين أصابعه فأكلوا حتى شبعوا فخرجوا فقال ‏"‏ أدخل عشرة ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ‏.‏ فما زال يدخل عشرة ويخرج عشرة حتى لم يبق
منهم أحد إلا دخل فأكل حتى شبع ثم هيأها فإذا هي مثلها حين أكلوا منها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported: Abu Talha sent me to Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) in order to invite him (for
meal). She had prepared a meal. So I came and found Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) along with some people. He looked
at me, and I felt shy and said: Accept the invitation of Abu Talha.
He (the Holy Prophet) asked the people to get up. Thereupon Abu
Talha said: Allah's Messenger, I have prepared something for you.
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) touched (the food) and
invoked blessings upon it, and then said: Let ten persons from my
Companions enter (the house). He then said: Eat, and (in the
meanwhile) brought out something from between his fingers for them.
They then began to eat until they had their fill and then went out.
He then asked ten more men (to have the meal) and they ate to their
fill, and the ten persons went on getting in (and eating the food)
and then getting out until none was left amongst them who had not
got in and eaten to his fill. He then collected (the remaining part
of the food) and it (the quantity of the food) was the same (as it
had been prior to the serving of guests).</english-text>
</hadith>
