<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15364</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5437</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك بن أنس عن إسحاق
بن عبد، الله بن أبي طلحة أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول قال أبو طلحة لأم
سليم قد سمعت صوت، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضعيفا أعرف فيه الجوع
فهل عندك من شىء فقالت نعم ‏.‏ فأخرجت أقراصا من شعير ثم أخذت خمارا
لها فلفت الخبز ببعضه ثم دسته تحت ثوبي وردتني ببعضه ثم أرسلتني إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال فذهبت به فوجدت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم جالسا في المسجد ومعه الناس فقمت عليهم فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرسلك أبو طلحة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقلت نعم ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
ألطعام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت نعم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمن
معه ‏"‏ قوموا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فانطلق وانطلقت بين أيديهم حتى جئت أبا
طلحة فأخبرته فقال أبو طلحة يا أم سليم قد جاء رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بالناس وليس عندنا ما نطعمهم فقالت الله ورسوله أعلم - قال
- فانطلق أبو طلحة حتى لقي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأقبل رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم معه حتى دخلا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ هلمي ما عندك يا أم سليم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتت بذلك الخبز فأمر به
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ففت وعصرت عليه أم سليم عكة لها فأدمته
ثم قال فيه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله أن يقول ثم قال
‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا ثم قال
‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا ثم قال
‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى أكل القوم كلهم وشبعوا والقوم سبعون رجلا
أو ثمانون ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported that Abu Talha said to Umm
Sulaim: I felt some feebleness in the voice of Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) and perceived that it was due to hunger; so
have you anything with you? She said: Yes. She brought out barley
loaves, then took out a head-covering of hers, in a part of which
she wrapped those loaves and then put them beneath my mantle and
covered me with a part of it. She then sent me to Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him). I set forth and found Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) sitting in the mosque in the company of
some persons. I stood near them, whereupon Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: Has Abu Talha sent you? I said, Yes. He
said: Is it for a feast? I said. Yes. Thereupon Allah's messenger
(may peace be upon him) said to'those who were with him to get up
He went forth and so I did before them, until I came to Abu Talha
and informed him. Abu Talba said: Umm Sulaim, here comes Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) along with people and we do not
have enough (food) to feed them. She said: Allah and His Messenger
know best. Abu Talha went out (to receive him) Until he met Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him) came forward along with him until they both (Allah's
Messenger, along with Abu Talha) came in. Then Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) said: Umm Sulaim. bring forth that which
you have with you. She brought the bread. Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) commanded that the bread be broken into small
pieces, and when Umm Sulaim had squeezed a small waterskin and put
seasoning on it, Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) recited
something regarding it what Allah wished him to say. He then said:
Allow ten (guests to come in and have their meals). He permitted
them; they ate until they had their fill. They then went out. He
(the Holy Prophet) again said: Permit ten (more) and he (the host
gave permission to them. They ate until they had enough. Then they
went out. he again said: Permit ten (more) until all the people had
eaten to their fill, and they were seventy or eighty
persons.</english-text>
</hadith>
