<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15363</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5436</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>38834, 11510, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حجاج بن الشاعر، حدثني الضحاك بن مخلد، من رقعة
عارض لي بها ثم قرأه على قال أخبرناه حنظلة بن أبي سفيان حدثنا سعيد
بن ميناء قال سمعت جابر بن عبد الله يقول لما حفر الخندق رأيت برسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خمصا فانكفأت إلى امرأتي فقلت لها هل عندك
شىء فإني رأيت برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خمصا شديدا ‏.‏ فأخرجت
لي جرابا فيه صاع من شعير ولنا بهيمة داجن - قال - فذبحتها وطحنت
ففرغت إلى فراغي فقطعتها في برمتها ثم وليت إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقالت لا تفضحني برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ومن معه -
قال - فجئته فساررته فقلت يا رسول الله إنا قد ذبحنا بهيمة لنا وطحنت
صاعا من شعير كان عندنا فتعال أنت في نفر معك ‏.‏ فصاح رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وقال ‏"‏ يا أهل الخندق إن جابرا قد صنع لكم سورا
فحيهلا بكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تنزلن
برمتكم ولا تخبزن عجينتكم حتى أجيء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجئت وجاء رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يقدم الناس حتى جئت امرأتي فقالت بك وبك ‏.‏ فقلت قد
فعلت الذي قلت لي ‏.‏ فأخرجت له عجينتنا فبصق فيها وبارك ثم عمد إلى
برمتنا فبصق فيها وبارك ثم قال ‏"‏ ادعي خابزة فلتخبز معك واقدحي من
برمتكم ولا تنزلوها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وهم ألف فأقسم بالله لأكلوا حتى تركوه
وانحرفوا وإن برمتنا لتغط كما هي وإن عجينتنا - أو كما قال الضحاك -
لتخبز كما هو ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir b. 'Abdullah reported: When the ditch was dug,
I saw Allah's Messenger (may peace he upon him) feeling very
hungry. I came to my wife and said to her: Is there anything with
you? I have seen Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) feeling
extremely hungry. She brought out a bag of provisions which
contained a sa', of barley. We had also with us a lamb. I
slaughtered it. She ground the flour. She finished (this work)
along with me. I cut it into pieces and put it in the earthen pot
and then returned to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) (for
inviting him). She said: Do not humiliate me in the presence of
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and those who are with
him. When I came to him I whispered to him saying: Allah's
Messenger, we have slaughtered a lamb for you and she has ground a
sa' of barley which we had with us. So you come along with a group
of people with you. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) said loudly: O people of the ditch, Jabir has arranged a feast
for you, so (come along). Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said: Do not remove your earthen pot from the hearth and do not
bake the bread from the kneaded flour until I come. So I came and
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) came and he was ahead of
the people; and I came to my wife and she said (to me): You will be
humbled. I said: I did what you had asked me to do. She (his wife)
said: I brought out the kneaded flour and Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) put some saliva of his in that and blessed It.
He then put saliva in the earthen pot and blessed it and then said.
Call another baker who can bake with you. and bring out the soup
from it, but do not remove it from the hearth, and the guests were
one thousand. (Jabir said): I take an oath by Allah that all of
them ate (the food to their fill) until they left it and went away
and our earthen pot was brimming over as before, and so was the
case with our flour, or as Dahhak (another narrator) said: It (the
flour) was in the same condition and loaves had been prepared from
that.</english-text>
</hadith>
