<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15361</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5434</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20584, 10845, 11172, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا خلف بن خليفة، عن يزيد
بن كيسان، عن أبي حازم، عن أبي هريرة، قال خرج رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ذات يوم أو ليلة فإذا هو بأبي بكر وعمر فقال ‏"‏ ما أخرجكما
من بيوتكما هذه الساعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالا الجوع يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
وأنا والذي نفسي بيده لأخرجني الذي أخرجكما قوموا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقاموا معه
فأتى رجلا من الأنصار فإذا هو ليس في بيته فلما رأته المرأة قالت
مرحبا وأهلا ‏.‏ فقال لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أين فلان
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ذهب يستعذب لنا من الماء ‏.‏ إذ جاء الأنصاري فنظر إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وصاحبيه ثم قال الحمد لله ما أحد اليوم
أكرم أضيافا مني - قال - فانطلق فجاءهم بعذق فيه بسر وتمر ورطب فقال
كلوا من هذه ‏.‏ وأخذ المدية فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إياك والحلوب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذبح لهم فأكلوا من الشاة ومن ذلك العذق
وشربوا فلما أن شبعوا ورووا قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأبي
بكر وعمر ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده لتسألن عن هذا النعيم يوم القيامة
أخرجكم من بيوتكم الجوع ثم لم ترجعوا حتى أصابكم هذا النعيم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) went out (of his house) one day or one night,
and there he found Abu Bakr and 'Umar also. He said: What has
brought you out of your houses at this hour? They said: Allah's
Messenger, it is hunger. Thereupon he said: By Him in Whose Hand is
my life, what has brought you out has brought me out too; get up.
They got up along with him. and (all of them) came to the house of
an Ansari, but he was not at home. When his wife saw him she said:
Most welcome, and Allah's Messenger (may peace be Upon him) said to
her: Where is so and so? She said: He has gone to get some fresh
water for us. When the Ansari came and he saw Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) and his two Companions, he said: Praise be
to Allah, no one has more honourable guests today than I (have). He
then went out and brought them a bunch of ripe dates, dry dates and
fresh dates, and said: Eat some of them. He then took hold of his
long knife (for slaughtering a goat or a sheep). Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) said to him: Beware of killing a milch
animal. He slaughtered a sheep for them and after they had eaten of
it and of the bunch and drank, and when they had taken their fill
and had been fully satisfied with the drink, Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said to Abu Bakr and Umar: By Him in Whose Hand
is my life, you will certainly be questioned about this bounty on
the Day of judgment. Hunger brought you out of your house, then you
did not return until this bounty came to you.</english-text>
</hadith>
