<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15410</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5483</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20426, 20236, 11269, 11196, 163</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا شبابة بن سوار، حدثنا
سليمان بن المغيرة، عن ثابت، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي ليلى، عن المقداد،
قال أقبلت أنا وصاحبان، لي وقد ذهبت أسماعنا وأبصارنا من الجهد فجعلنا
نعرض أنفسنا على أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فليس أحد منهم
يقبلنا فأتينا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فانطلق بنا إلى أهله فإذا
ثلاثة أعنز فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ احتلبوا هذا اللبن
بيننا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فكنا نحتلب فيشرب كل إنسان منا نصيبه ونرفع للنبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم نصيبه - قال - فيجيء من الليل فيسلم تسليما لا
يوقظ نائما ويسمع اليقظان - قال - ثم يأتي المسجد فيصلي ثم يأتي شرابه
فيشرب فأتاني الشيطان ذات ليلة وقد شربت نصيبي فقال محمد يأتي الأنصار
فيتحفونه ويصيب عندهم ما به حاجة إلى هذه الجرعة فأتيتها فشربتها فلما
أن وغلت في بطني وعلمت أنه ليس إليها سبيل - قال - ندمني الشيطان فقال
ويحك ما صنعت أشربت شراب محمد فيجيء فلا يجده فيدعو عليك فتهلك فتذهب
دنياك وآخرتك ‏.‏ وعلى شملة إذا وضعتها على قدمى خرج رأسي وإذا وضعتها
على رأسي خرج قدماى وجعل لا يجيئني النوم وأما صاحباى فناما ولم يصنعا
ما صنعت - قال - فجاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسلم كما كان يسلم ثم
أتى المسجد فصلى ثم أتى شرابه فكشف عنه فلم يجد فيه شيئا فرفع رأسه
إلى السماء فقلت الآن يدعو على فأهلك ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اللهم أطعم من
أطعمني وأسق من أسقاني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فعمدت إلى الشملة فشددتها على
وأخذت الشفرة فانطلقت إلى الأعنز أيها أسمن فأذبحها لرسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فإذا هي حافلة وإذا هن حفل كلهن فعمدت إلى إناء لآل
محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم ما كانوا يطمعون أن يحتلبوا فيه - قال -
فحلبت فيه حتى علته رغوة فجئت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
‏"‏ أشربتم شرابكم الليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله اشرب ‏.‏ فشرب
ثم ناولني فقلت يا رسول الله اشرب ‏.‏ فشرب ثم ناولني فلما عرفت أن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قد روي وأصبت دعوته ضحكت حتى ألقيت إلى
الأرض - قال - فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إحدى سوآتك يا مقداد
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت يا رسول الله كان من أمري كذا وكذا وفعلت كذا ‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما هذه إلا رحمة من الله أفلا كنت
آذنتني فنوقظ صاحبينا فيصيبان منها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقلت والذي بعثك بالحق
ما أبالي إذا أصبتها وأصبتها معك من أصابها من الناس
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Miqdad reported: I and two of my companions were so
much afflicted by hunger that we had lost our power of seeing and
hearing. We presented ourselves (as guests) to the Companions of
the Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him), but none amongst them
would entertain us. So we came to Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him), and he took us to his residence and there were three
goats. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: Milk these for
us. So we milked them and every person amongst us drank his share
and we set aside the share of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon
him). (It was his habit) to come during the night and greet (the
people present there) in a manner that would not wake up one in
sleep but make one who was awake hear it. He would then go to the
mosque and say prayer, then go to the milk and drink it. Miqdad
added: One night the Satan came to me when I had taken my share,
and he said: Muhammad has gone to the Ansar, who would offer him
hospitality and he would get what is with them, and he has no need
for this draught (of milk). So I took (that milk) and drank it, and
when it had penetrated deeply in my stomach and I was certain that
there was no way out (but to digest it), the Satan aroused (my
sense of) remorse and said: Woe be to thee! what have you done? You
have taken the drink reserved for Muhammad! When he would come and
he would not find it, he would curse you, and you would be ruined,
and thus there would go (waste) this world and the Hereafter (for)
you. There was a sheet over me; as I placed (pulled) it upon my
feet, my head was uncovered and as I placed it upon my head, my
feet were uncovered, and I could not sleep, but my two companions
had gone to sleep for they had not done what I had done. There came
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him), and he greeted as he used
to greet (by saying as-Salamu 'Alaikum). He then came to the mosque
and observed prayer and then came to his drink (milk) and uncovered
it, but did not find anything in it. He raised his head towards the
sky, and I said (to myself) that he (the Holy Prophet) was going to
invoke curse upon me and I would be thus ruined; but he (the Holy
Prophet) said: Allah, feed him who fed me and give drink to him who
provided me drink. I held tight the sheet upon myself (and when he
had supplicated), I took hold of the knife and went to the goats
(possessed by the Holy Prophet) so that I may slauhter one for
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) which was the fattest
amongst them, and in fact all of them were milch goats; then I took
hold of the vessel which belonged to the family of Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) in which they used to milk and
drink therefrom, and milked them in that until it swelled up with
foam. I came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and he
said: Have you taken your share of the milk during the night? I
said: Drink it. and he drank it; he then handed over (the vessel)
to me and I said: Allah's Messenger, drink it, and he drank it and
handed over (the vessel) to me again, I then perceived that Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) had been satiated and I had got his
blessings. I burst into laughter (so much) so that I fell upon the
ground, whereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said:
Miqdad, it must be one of your mischiefs. I said: Allah's
Messenger, this affair of mind is like this and this. and I have
done so. Thereupon. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) said:
This is nothing but a mercy from Allah. Why is it that you did not
give me an opportunity so that we should have awakened our two
friends and they would have got their share (of the milk)? I said:
By Him Who has sent you with Truth. I do not mind whatever you give
(to them), and whatever the (other) people happen to get, when I
had got it along with you from among the people.</english-text>
</hadith>
