<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15413</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5486</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 30128, 20288, 11289, 11113, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ العنبري، وحامد بن عمر
البكراوي، ومحمد بن عبد الأعلى، القيسي كلهم عن المعتمر، - واللفظ
لابن معاذ - حدثنا المعتمر بن سليمان، قال قال أبي حدثنا أبو عثمان،
أنه حدثه عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر، أن أصحاب الصفة، كانوا ناسا فقراء
وإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال مرة ‏"‏ من كان عنده طعام اثنين
فليذهب بثلاثة ومن كان عنده طعام أربعة فليذهب بخامس بسادس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو
كما قال ‏.‏ وإن أبا بكر جاء بثلاثة وانطلق نبي الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم بعشرة وأبو بكر بثلاثة - قال - فهو وأنا وأبي وأمي - ولا أدري هل
قال وامرأتي وخادم بين بيتنا وبيت أبي بكر - قال وإن أبا بكر تعشى عند
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ ثم لبث حتى صليت العشاء ثم رجع فلبث حتى
نعس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجاء بعد ما مضى من الليل ما شاء
الله قالت له امرأته ما حبسك عن أضيافك - أو قالت - ضيفك قال أوما
عشيتهم قالت أبوا حتى تجيء قد عرضوا عليهم فغلبوهم - قال - فذهبت أنا
فاختبأت وقال يا غنثر ‏.‏ فجدع وسب وقال كلوا لا هنيئا ‏.‏ وقال والله
لا أطعمه أبدا - قال - فايم الله ما كنا نأخذ من لقمة إلا ربا من
أسفلها أكثر منها - قال - حتى شبعنا وصارت أكثر مما كانت قبل ذلك فنظر
إليها أبو بكر فإذا هي كما هي أو أكثر ‏.‏ قال لامرأته يا أخت بني
فراس ما هذا قالت لا وقرة عيني لهي الآن أكثر منها قبل ذلك بثلاث مرار
- قال - فأكل منها أبو بكر وقال إنما كان ذلك من الشيطان - يعني يمينه
- ثم أكل منها لقمة ثم حملها إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأصبحت
عنده - قال - وكان بيننا وبين قوم عقد فمضى الأجل فعرفنا اثنا عشر
رجلا مع كل رجل منهم أناس الله أعلم كم مع كل رجل إلا أنه بعث معهم
فأكلوا منها أجمعون ‏.‏ أو كما قال ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abd al-Rabman b. Abu Bakr reported that the people
of Suffa were very poor. Once the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) said (to his Companions): He who amongst you has food for
two persons should take three (guests with him). and he who has
with him food for four persons should take five or six (guests with
him for entertaining them). It was (in accordance with these
instructions of the Holy Prophet) that Abu Bakr brought three
persons, and the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) brought
ten persons (as guests to their respective houses). Abu Bakr had
brought three persons (he himself, and myself), my father and my
mother (along with therm). He (the narrator) said: I do not know
whether he also said: My wife and one servant who was common
between our house and that of Abu Bakr. Abu Bakr had had his
evening meal with Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him). He
stayed here until night prayer had been offered. He then came back
(to the house of Allah's Apostle) and stayed there until Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) felt drowsy and (Abu Bakr) then
came (back to his own house) when (a considerable) part of the
night had been over, as Allah had desired. His wife said to him:
What held you back from your guests? He said: Oh! have you not
served them the evening meal (by this time)? She said: It was in
fact served to them. but they refused to eat until you came. He
('Abd al-Rahman) said: I slunk away and bid myself. He (Abu Bakr)
said: O, you stupid fellow, and he reprimanded me, and said to the
guests: Eat, though it may not be pleasant now. He said: By Allah.
I will never eat it He ('Abd al-Rahman) said: By Allah. we did not
take a morsel when from beneath that (there appeared) more until
they had eaten to their fill, and lo! it was more than what it was
before. Abu Bakr saw that and found that it was so or more than
that. He said to his wife: Sister of Band Firis, what is th-is? She
said: By the coolness of my eyes. it is in excess by three times
over the previous one. Then Abu Bakr ate saying: That was from the
Satan (viz. his vow for not eating the food). He then took a morsel
out of that and then took it (the rest) to the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him), and it was kept there until morning, and
during (those days) there was a covenant between us and some other
people, and the period of covenant was over, and we had appointed
twelve officials with every person amongst them. It is Allah only
Who knows as to how many people were there with each of them. He
sent (this food to them) and all of them ate out of
it.</english-text>
</hadith>
