<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15412</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5485</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 30128, 20288, 20288, 11289, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ العنبري، وحامد بن عمر
البكراوي، ومحمد بن عبد، الأعلى جميعا عن المعتمر بن سليمان، - واللفظ
لابن معاذ - حدثنا المعتمر، حدثنا أبي، عن أبي عثمان، - وحدث أيضا، -
عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر، قال كنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
ثلاثين ومائة فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل مع أحد منكم طعام
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا مع رجل صاع من طعام أو نحوه فعجن ثم جاء رجل مشرك مشعان
طويل بغنم يسوقها فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أبيع أم عطية -
أو قال - أم هبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال لا بل بيع ‏.‏ فاشترى منه شاة فصنعت
وأمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بسواد البطن أن يشوى ‏.‏ قال وايم
الله ما من الثلاثين ومائة إلا حز له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
حزة حزة من سواد بطنها إن كان شاهدا أعطاه وإن كان غائبا خبأ له - قال
- وجعل قصعتين فأكلنا منهما أجمعون وشبعنا وفضل في القصعتين فحملته
على البعير ‏.‏ أو كما قال ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abd al-Rahman b. Abu Bakr reported: We were one
hundred and thirty (persons) with Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him). Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: Does any
one of You possess food? There was a person with (us) who had a sa'
of flour or something about that, and it was kneaded. Then a tall
polytheist with dishevelled hair came driving his flock of sheep.
Thereupon Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: Would you
like to sell it (any one of these goats) or offer it as a gift or a
present? He said: No, (I am not prepared to offer as a gift), but I
would sell it. He (the Holy Prophet) bought a sheep from him, and
it was slaughtered and its meat was prepared, and Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) commanded that its liver should be roasted.
He (the narrator) said: By Allah, none among one hundred and thirty
persons was left whom Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had
not given a part out of her liver; if anyone was present he gave it
to him. but if he was absent it was set aside for him. And he (the
Holy Prophet) filled two bowls (one with soup and the other with
mutton) and we all ate out of them to our hearts' content, but
(still) some part was (left) in (those) two bowls, and I placed it
on the camel- (or words to the same effect).</english-text>
</hadith>
