<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15452</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5524</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Clothes and Decoration - كتاب
اللباس والزينة</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 11272, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا شيبان بن فروخ، حدثنا جرير بن حازم، حدثنا نافع،
عن ابن عمر، قال رأى عمر عطاردا التميمي يقيم بالسوق حلة سيراء - وكان
رجلا يغشى الملوك ويصيب منهم - فقال عمر يا رسول الله إني رأيت عطاردا
يقيم في السوق حلة سيراء فلو اشتريتها فلبستها لوفود العرب إذا قدموا
عليك - وأظنه قال ولبستها يوم الجمعة - فقال له رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنما يلبس الحرير في الدنيا من لا خلاق له في الآخرة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما كان بعد ذلك أتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بحلل
سيراء فبعث إلى عمر بحلة وبعث إلى أسامة بن زيد بحلة وأعطى علي بن أبي
طالب حلة وقال ‏"‏ شققها خمرا بين نسائك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فجاء عمر بحلته
يحملها فقال يا رسول الله بعثت إلى بهذه وقد قلت بالأمس في حلة عطارد
ما قلت فقال ‏"‏ إني لم أبعث بها إليك لتلبسها ولكني بعثت بها إليك
لتصيب بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأما أسامة فراح في حلته فنظر إليه رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم نظرا عرف أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد أنكر ما
صنع فقال يا رسول الله ما تنظر إلى فأنت بعثت إلى بها فقال ‏"‏ إني لم
أبعث إليك لتلبسها ولكني بعثت بها إليك لتشققها خمرا بين نسائك ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Umar reported that Umar saw Utarid al-Tamimi
standing in the market (and selling) the silk garments, and he was
the person who went to (courts of) kings and got (high prices) for
these garments from them. Umar said: Allah's Messenger I saw
'Utarid standing in the market with a silk garment; would that you
buy and wear it for (receiving) the delegations of Arabs when they
visit you? I (the narrator) said: I think he ('Umar) also said: You
may wear it on Friday (also). Thereupon, Allah's Messenger (may
peace he upon him) said: He who wears silk in this world has no
share in the Hereafter. Later on when these silk garments were
presented to Allah's Massenger (may peace be upon him) he presented
one silk garment to 'Umar and presented one also to Usama b. Zaid
and gave one to 'Ali b. Abu 'Talib. saying: Tear them and make head
coverings for your ladies. 'Umar came carrying his garment and
said: Allah's Messenger, you have sent it to me, whereas you had
said yesterday about the (silk) garment of Utarid what you had to
say. He (the Holy Prophet) said: I have not sent it to you that you
wear it, but I have sent It to you so that you may derive benefit
out of it; and Usama (donned) the garment (presented to him) and
appeared to be brisk, whereupon Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon
him) looked at him with a look by which he perceived that the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) did not like what he had
done. He said: Allah's Messenger. why is it that you look at me
like this. whereas you yourself presented it to me? He said: I
never sent it to you to wear it, but I sent It to you so that you
may tear it and make out head covering for your
ladies.</english-text>
</hadith>
