<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15568</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5641</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Clothes and Decoration - كتاب
اللباس والزينة</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20028, 11173, 3625</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، أخبرنا جرير، عن سهيل بن أبي
صالح، عن سعيد،بن يسار أبي الحباب مولى بني النجار عن زيد بن خالد
الجهني، عن أبي طلحة الأنصاري،قال سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يقول ‏"‏ لا تدخل الملائكة بيتا فيه كلب ولاتماثيل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأتيت
عائشة فقلت إن هذا يخبرني أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال‏"‏ لا تدخل
الملائكة بيتا فيه كلب ولا تماثيل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فهل سمعت رسول الله صلى
الله عليهوسلم ذكر ذلك فقالت لا ولكن سأحدثكم ما رأيته فعل رأيته خرج
في غزاته فأخذتنمطا فسترته على الباب فلما قدم فرأى النمط عرفت
الكراهية في وجهه فجذبه حتىهتكه أو قطعه وقال ‏"‏ إن الله لم يأمرنا
أن نكسو الحجارة والطين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فقطعنامنه وسادتين وحشوتهما ليفا
فلم يعب ذلك على ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Talha Ansari reported Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) as saying: Angels do not enter the house in
which there is a picture or portraits. I came to 'A'isha and said
to her: This is a news that I have received that Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him) had said: Angels do not enter the house in
which there is a picture or a dog, (and further added) whether she
had heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) making a
mention of it. She said: No (I did not hear this myself), but I
narrate to you what I saw him doing. I bear testimony to the fact
that he (the Holy Prophet) set out for an expedition. I took a
carpet and screened the door with it. When he (the Holy Prophet)
came back he saw that carpet and I perceived signs of disapproval
on his face. He pulled it until it was torn or it was cut (into
pieces) and he said: God has not commanded us to clothe stones and
clay. We cut it (the curtain) and prepared two pillowa out of it by
stuffing them with the fibre of date-palms and he (the Holy
Prophet) did not find fault with it.</english-text>
</hadith>
