<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15562</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5635</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Clothes and Decoration - كتاب
اللباس والزينة</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 11203, 17,
61</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حرملة بن يحيى، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس، عن
ابن شهاب، عن ابن السباق، أن عبد الله بن عباس، قال أخبرتني ميمونة،
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليهوسلم أصبح يوما واجما فقالت ميمونة يا رسول
الله لقد استنكرت هيئتك منذ اليوم ‏.‏قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إن جبريل كان وعدني أن يلقاني الليلة فلم يلقنيأم والله ما
أخلفني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فظل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يومه ذلك على
ذلكثم وقع في نفسه جرو كلب تحت فسطاط لنا فأمر به فأخرج ثم أخذ بيده
ماء فنضحمكانه فلما أمسى لقيه جبريل فقال له ‏"‏ قد كنت وعدتني أن
تلقاني البارحة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالأجل ولكنا لا ندخل بيتا فيه كلب ولا صورة
‏.‏ فأصبح رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلميومئذ فأمر بقتل الكلاب حتى
إنه يأمر بقتل كلب الحائط الصغير ويترك كلب الحائط
الكبير‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Maimuna reported that one morning Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) was silent with grief. Maimuna said:
Allah's Messenger, I find a change in your mood today. Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Gabriel had promised me
that he would meet me tonight, but he did not meet me. By Allah, he
never broke his promises, and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) spent the day in this sad (mood). Then it occurred to him that
there had been a puppy under their cot. He commanded and it was
turned out. He then took some water in his hand and sprinkled it at
that place. When it was evening Gabriel met him and he said to him:
you promised me that you would meet me the previous night. He said:
Yes, but we do not enter a house in which there is a dog or a
picture. Then on that very morning he commanded the killing of the
dogs until he announced that the dog kept for the orchards should
also be killed, but he spared the dog meant for the protection of
extensive fields (or big gardens).</english-text>
</hadith>
