<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15586</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5661</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Clothes and Decoration - كتاب
اللباس والزينة</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20251</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا نصر بن علي الجهضمي، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد
الصمد، حدثنا منصور،عن مسلم بن صبيح، قال كنت مع مسروق في بيت فيه
تماثيل مريم ‏.‏ فقال مسروق هذاتماثيل كسرى ‏.‏ فقلت لا هذا تماثيل
مريم ‏.‏ فقال مسروق أما إني سمعت عبد الله بنمسعود يقول قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أشد الناس عذابا يوم القيامة المصورون‏"‏
‏.‏ قال مسلم قرأت على نصر بن علي الجهضمي عن عبد الأعلى بن عبد
الأعلى،حدثنا يحيى بن أبي إسحاق، عن سعيد بن أبي الحسن، قال جاء رجل
إلى ابن عباس فقال إني رجل أصور هذه الصور فأفتني فيها ‏.‏ فقال له
ادن مني ‏.‏ فدنا منه ثم قال ادن مني ‏.‏ فدنا حتى وضع يده على رأسه
قال أنبئك بما سمعت من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ كل مصور في النار يجعل له بكل صورة صورها
نفسا فتعذبه في جهنم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال إن كنت لا بد فاعلا فاصنع الشجر وما
لا نفس له ‏.‏ فأقر به نصر بن علي ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Muslim b. Subaih reported: I was with Masriuq in the
house which had the portrayals of Mary (hadrat Maryan). Thereupon
Masriuq said: These are portraits of Kisra. I said: No, these are
of Mary. Masruq said: I heard Abdullah b, Mas'ud as saying Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) had said: The most grievously
tormented people on the Day of Resurrection would be the painters
of pictures. (Muslim said): I read this before Nasr b. 'Ali
at-Jahdami and he read it before other narrators, the last one
being Ibn Sa'id b Abl at Hasan that a person came to Ibn 'Abbas and
said: I am the person who paints pictures; give me a religious
verdict about them. He (Ibn 'Abbas) said to him: Come near me
(still further). He came near him so much so that he placed his
hand upon his head and said: I am going to narrate to yor what I
heard from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). I heard him
say: All the painters who make pictures would be in the fire of
Hell. The soul will be breathed in every picture prepared by him
and it shall punish him in the Hell, and he (Ibn 'Abbas) said: If
you have to do it at all, then paint the pictures of trees and
lifeless things; and Nasr b. 'Ali confirmed it.</english-text>
</hadith>
