<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15655</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>39</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5737</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on General Behaviour - كتاب الآداب</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20472, 11071, 11035, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، أخبرنا
ابن عون، عن ابن، سيرين عن أنس بن مالك، قال كان ابن لأبي طلحة يشتكي
فخرج أبو طلحة فقبض الصبي فلما رجع أبو طلحة قال ما فعل ابني قالت أم
سليم هو أسكن مما كان ‏.‏ فقربت إليه العشاء فتعشى ثم أصاب منها فلما
فرغ قالت واروا الصبي ‏.‏ فلما أصبح أبو طلحة أتى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأخبره فقال ‏"‏ أعرستم الليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم قال ‏"‏
اللهم بارك لهما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فولدت غلاما فقال لي أبو طلحة احمله حتى تأتي
به النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فأتى به النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وبعثت معه بتمرات فأخذه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أمعه شىء
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم تمرات ‏.‏ فأخذها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فمضغها
ثم أخذها من فيه فجعلها في في الصبي ثم حنكه وسماه عبد الله
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported that the son of Abu Talha had
been ailing. Abu Talha set out (on a journey) and his son breathed
his last (in his absence). When Abu Talha came back, he said (to
his wife): What about my child? Umm Sulaim (the wife of Abu Talha)
said: He is now in a more comfortable state than before. She served
him the evening meal and he took it. He then came to her (and had
sexual intercourse with her) and when it was all over she said:
Make arrangements for the burial of the child. When it was morning.
Abu Talha came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and
informed him, whereupon he said: Did you spend the night with her.
He said: Yes. He (the Holy Prophet) then said: O Allah, bless both
of them (and as a result of blessing) she gave birth to a child.
Abu Talha said to me (Anas b. Malik) to take the child, (so I took
him) and came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). She
(Umm Sulaim) also had sent some dates (along with the child).
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) took him (the child) (in
his lap) and said: Is there anything with you (for Tahnik). They
(the Companions) said: Yes. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
took hold of them (dates and chewed them). He then put them (the
chewed dates) in the mouth of the child and then rubbed his palate
and gave him the name of 'Abdullah.</english-text>
</hadith>
