<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15724</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5808</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salutations and Greetings - كتاب
السلام</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 30553, 20121, 20115, 11013, 11045</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، وعبد بن حميد، - وتقاربا في
اللفظ - قالا أخبرنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن الزهري، عن علي بن
حسين، عن صفية بنت حيى، قالت كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم معتكفا
فأتيته أزوره ليلا فحدثته ثم قمت لأنقلب فقام معي ليقلبني ‏.‏ وكان
مسكنها في دار أسامة بن زيد فمر رجلان من الأنصار فلما رأيا النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم أسرعا فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ على رسلكما
إنها صفية بنت حيى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالا سبحان الله يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
إن الشيطان يجري من الإنسان مجرى الدم وإني خشيت أن يقذف في قلوبكما
شرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Safiyya daughter of Huyyay (the wife of Allah's
Apostle) reported that while Allah's Messenger (may peace be. upon
him) had been observing I'tikaf, I came to visit him one night and
talked with him for some time. Then I stood up to go back and he
(Allah's Apostle) also stood up with me in order to bid me
good-bye. She was at that time residing in the house of Usama b.
Zaid. The two persons from the Ansar happened to pass by him. When
they saw Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him). they began to
walk swiftly, thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said to them: Walk calmy, she is Safiyya daughter of Huyyay... Both
of them said: Messenger, hallowed be Allah, (we cannot conceive of
ab., ug doubtful even in the remotest corners of our minds),
whereupon he said: Satan circulates in the body of man like the
circulation of blood and I was afraid lest it should instill any
evil in your heart or anything. This hadith has been reported on
the authority of Safiyya, the wife of Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him), through another chain of transmitters (and the words)
are:" She went to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) to visit
him as he was observing I'tikaf in the mosque during Ramadan. She
talked with him for some time and then stood up to go back and
Allikh's Apostle (may peace be upon him) stood up in order to bid
her good-bye." The rest of the hadith is the same except with the
variation of the words that Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
said:" Satan penetrates in man like the penetration of blood (in
every part of body)."</english-text>
</hadith>
