<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15738</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5822</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salutations and Greetings - كتاب
السلام</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20022, 11015, 11090, 70</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبيد الغبري، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن أيوب،
عن ابن أبي مليكة، أن أسماء، قالت كنت أخدم الزبير خدمة البيت وكان له
فرس وكنت أسوسه فلم يكن من الخدمة شىء أشد على من سياسة الفرس كنت
أحتش له وأقوم عليه وأسوسه ‏.‏ قال ثم إنها أصابت خادما جاء النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم سبى فأعطاها خادما ‏.‏ قالت كفتني سياسة الفرس فألقت
عني مئونته فجاءني رجل فقال يا أم عبد الله إني رجل فقير أردت أن أبيع
في ظل دارك ‏.‏ قالت إني إن رخصت لك أبى ذاك الزبير فتعال فاطلب إلى
والزبير شاهد فجاء فقال يا أم عبد الله إني رجل فقير أردت أن أبيع في
ظل دارك ‏.‏ فقالت ما لك بالمدينة إلا داري فقال لها الزبير ما لك أن
تمنعي رجلا فقيرا يبيع فكان يبيع إلى أن كسب فبعته الجارية فدخل على
الزبير وثمنها في حجري ‏.‏ فقال هبيها لي ‏.‏ قالت إني قد تصدقت بها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Asma' reported: I performed the household duties of
Zubair and he had a horse; I used to look after it. Nothing was
more burdensome for me than looking after the horse I used to bring
grass for it and looked after it, then I got a servant as Allah's
Apustle (may peace be upon him) had some prisoners of war in his
possession. He gave me a female servant. She (the female servant)
then began to look after the horse and thus relieved me of this
burden. A person came and he said: Mother of 'Abdullah, I am a
destitute person and I intend that I should start business under
the shadow of your house. I (Asma') said: If I grant you
permission, Zubair may not agree to that, so you come and make a
demand of it when Zubair is also present there. He came accordingly
find said: Mother of 'Abdullah. I am a destitute person. I intend
to start t mall business in the shadow of your house. I said: Is
there not in Medina (any place for starting the business) except my
house? Zubair said: Why is it that you prohibit the destitute man
to start business here? So he started business and he (earned so
much) that we sold our slave-girl to him There came Zubair to me
while the money was in my lap. He said: Give this to me. I said: (I
intend) to spend it as charity.</english-text>
</hadith>
