<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15826</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5910</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salutations and Greetings - كتاب
السلام</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20276, 20020, 11276, 11020</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا ابن أبي عدي، عن شعبة، عن
حبيب، قال كنا بالمدينة فبلغني أن الطاعون قد وقع بالكوفة فقال لي
عطاء بن يسار وغيره إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إذا كنت
بأرض فوقع بها فلا تخرج منها وإذا بلغك أنه بأرض فلا تدخلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال قلت عمن قالوا عن عامر بن سعد يحدث به ‏.‏ قال فأتيته فقالوا غائب
- قال - فلقيت أخاه إبراهيم بن سعد فسألته فقال شهدت أسامة يحدث سعدا
قال سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إن هذا الوجع رجز أو
عذاب أو بقية عذاب عذب به أناس من قبلكم فإذا كان بأرض وأنتم بها فلا
تخرجوا منها وإذا بلغكم أنه بأرض فلا تدخلوها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال حبيب فقلت
لإبراهيم آنت سمعت أسامة يحدث سعدا وهو لا ينكر قال نعم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Shu'ba reported from Habib: While we were in Medina
we heard of plague having broken out in Kufa. 'Ata b. Yasir and
others said to me that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
had said. If you are in a land where it (this scourge) has broken
out, don't get out of it, and if you were to know that it had
broken (in another land, then don't enter it. I said to him: From
whom (did you hear it)? They said: 'Amir b. Sa'd has narrated it.
So I came to him. They said that he was not present there. So I met
his brother Ibrahim b. Sa'd and asked him. He said: I bear
testimony to the fact that Usama narrated it to Sa'd saying: I
heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) as saying that it
is a God-sent punishment from the calamity or from the remnant of
the calamity with which people were afflicted before you. So when
it is in a land and you are there, don't get out of it, and if
(this news reaches you) that it has broken out in a land, then
don't enter therein. Habib said: I said to Ibrahim: Did you hear
Usama narrating it to Sa'd and he was not denying it. He said:
Yes.</english-text>
</hadith>
