<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15875</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5962</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salutations and Greetings - كتاب
السلام</chapter>
<chain-index>30373, 20459, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا حاجب بن الوليد، حدثنا محمد بن حرب، عن الزبيدي،
عن الزهري، أخبرني سالم بن عبد الله، عن ابن عمر، قال سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يأمر بقتل الكلاب يقول ‏"‏ اقتلوا الحيات والكلاب
واقتلوا ذا الطفيتين والأبتر فإنهما يلتمسان البصر ويستسقطان الحبالى
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الزهري ونرى ذلك من سميهما والله أعلم ‏.‏ قال سالم قال
عبد الله بن عمر فلبثت لا أترك حية أراها إلا قتلتها فبينا أنا أطارد
حية يوما من ذوات البيوت مر بي زيد بن الخطاب أو أبو لبابة وأنا
أطاردها فقال مهلا يا عبد الله ‏.‏ فقلت إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم أمر بقتلهن ‏.‏ قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد نهى عن
ذوات البيوت ‏.‏ وحدثنيه حرملة بن يحيى، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس،
ح وحدثنا عبد بن، حميد أخبرنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، ح وحدثنا حسن
الحلواني، حدثنا يعقوب، حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، كلهم عن الزهري، بهذا
الإسناد غير أن صالحا، قال حتى رآني أبو لبابة بن عبد المنذر وزيد بن
الخطاب فقالا إنه قد نهى عن ذوات البيوت ‏.‏ وفي حديث يونس ‏"‏ اقتلوا
الحيات ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولم يقل ‏"‏ ذا الطفيتين والأبتر ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Umar reported: I heard Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) commanding the killing of dogs and the killing
of the striped and the short-tailed snakes, for both of them affect
the eyesight adversely and cause miscarriage. Zuhri said: We
thought of their poison (the pernicious effects of these two).
Allah, however, knows best. 'Abdullah b. 'Umar said: I did not
spare any snake. I rather killed everyone that I saw. One day as I
was pursuing a snake from amongst the snakes of the house, Zaid b.
Khattab or Abu Lubaba happened to pass by me and found me pursuing
it. He said: 'Abdullah, wait. I said: Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) commanded (us) to kill them, whereupon he said that
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) forbade the killing of
the snakes of the houses. This hadith has been narrated on the
authority of Zuhri with the same chain of transmitters but with a
slight variation of wording.</english-text>
</hadith>
