<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>15997</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6086</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 20260, 20001, 11263, 3660, 32</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن الدارمي، حدثنا أبو علي
الحنفي، حدثنا مالك، - وهو ابن أنس - عن أبي الزبير المكي، أن أبا
الطفيل، عامر بن واثلة أخبره أن معاذ بن جبل أخبره قال خرجنا مع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عام غزوة تبوك فكان يجمع الصلاة فصلى الظهر
والعصر جميعا والمغرب والعشاء جميعا حتى إذا كان يوما أخر الصلاة ثم
خرج فصلى الظهر والعصر جميعا ثم دخل ثم خرج بعد ذلك فصلى المغرب
والعشاء جميعا ثم قال ‏"‏ إنكم ستأتون غدا إن شاء الله عين تبوك وإنكم
لن تأتوها حتى يضحي النهار فمن جاءها منكم فلا يمس من مائها شيئا حتى
آتي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجئناها وقد سبقنا إليها رجلان والعين مثل الشراك تبض
بشىء من ماء - قال - فسألهما رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل
مسستما من مائها شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالا نعم ‏.‏ فسبهما النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم وقال لهما ما شاء الله أن يقول - قال - ثم غرفوا بأيديهم من
العين قليلا قليلا حتى اجتمع في شىء - قال - وغسل رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فيه يديه ووجهه ثم أعاده فيها فجرت العين بماء منهمر أو قال
غزير - شك أبو علي أيهما قال - حتى استقى الناس ثم قال ‏"‏ يوشك يا
معاذ إن طالت بك حياة أن ترى ما ها هنا قد ملئ جنانا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mu'adh b. Jabal reported that he went along with
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) in the expedition of Tabuk
and he (the Holy Prophet) combined the prayers. He offered the noon
and afternoon prayers together and the sunset and night prayers
together and on the other day he deferred the prayers; he then came
out and offered the noon and afternoon prayers together. He then
went in and (later on) came out and then after that offered the
sunset and night prayers together and then said: God willing, you
would reach by tomorrow the fountain of Tabuk and you should not
come to that until it is dawn, and he who amongst you happens to go
there should not touch its water until I come. We came to that and
two persons (amongst) us reached that fountain ahead of us. It was
a thin flow of water like the shoelace. Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) asked them whether they had touched the water.
They said: Yes. Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) scolded
them, and he said to them what he had to say by the will of God.
The people then took water of the fountain in their palms until it
became somewhat significant and Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) washed his hands and his face too in it, and then, took
it again in that (fountain) and there gushed forth abundant water
from that fountain, until all the people drank to their fill. He
then said: Mu'adh, it is hoped that if you live long you would see
its water irrigating well the gardens.</english-text>
</hadith>
