<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16021</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6111</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30504, 20203, 11090, 29</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا داود بن عمرو الضبي، حدثنا نافع بن عمر الجمحي،
عن ابن أبي مليكة، قال قال عبد الله بن عمرو بن العاص قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ حوضي مسيرة شهر وزواياه سواء وماؤه أبيض من
الورق وريحه أطيب من المسك وكيزانه كنجوم السماء فمن شرب منه فلا يظمأ
بعده أبدا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقالت أسماء بنت أبي بكر قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني على الحوض حتى أنظر من يرد على منكم وسيؤخذ
أناس دوني فأقول يا رب مني ومن أمتي ‏.‏ فيقال أما شعرت ما عملوا بعدك
والله ما برحوا بعدك يرجعون على أعقابهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فكان ابن أبي
مليكة يقول اللهم إنا نعوذ بك أن نرجع على أعقابنا أو أن نفتن عن
ديننا</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. 'Amr al-'As, reported Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) as saying: My Cistern (is as wide and broad
that it requires) a motith's journey (to go round it) all, and its
sides are equal and its water is whiter than silver, and its odour
is more fragrant than the fragrance of musk, and its jugs (placed
round it) are like stars in the sky; and he who would drink from it
would never feel thirsty after that. Asma', daughter of Abu Bakr
said: Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: I would be on
the Cistern and so that I would be seeing those who would be coming
to me from you, but some people would be detained (before reaching
me). I would say: My Lord, they are my followers and belong to my
Umma, and it would be said to me: Do you know what they did after
you? By Allah, they did not do good after you, and they turned back
upon their heels. He (the narrator) said: lbn Abu Mulaika used to
say (in supplication): O Allah, I seek refuge with Thee that we
should turn back upon our heels or put to any trial about our
religion.</english-text>
</hadith>
