<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16073</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6167</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 20236, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هداب بن خالد، وشيبان بن فروخ، كلاهما عن سليمان،
- واللفظ لشيبان - حدثنا سليمان بن المغيرة، حدثنا ثابت البناني، عن
أنس بن مالك، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ولد لي الليلة
غلام فسميته باسم أبي إبراهيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم دفعه إلى أم سيف امرأة قين
يقال له أبو سيف فانطلق يأتيه واتبعته فانتهينا إلى أبي سيف وهو ينفخ
بكيره قد امتلأ البيت دخانا فأسرعت المشى بين يدى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقلت يا أبا سيف أمسك جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏
فأمسك فدعا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالصبي فضمه إليه وقال ما شاء
الله أن يقول ‏.‏ فقال أنس لقد رأيته وهو يكيد بنفسه بين يدى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فدمعت عينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال ‏"‏ تدمع العين ويحزن القلب ولا نقول إلا ما يرضى ربنا والله يا
إبراهيم إنا بك لمحزونون ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: A child was born into me this night and I
named him after the name of my father Ibrihim. He then sent him to
Umm Saif, the wife of a blacksmith who was called Abu Saif. He (the
Holy Prophet) went to him and I followed him until we reached Abu
Saif and he was blowing fire with the help of blacksmith's bellows
and the house was filled with smoke. I hastened my step and went
ahead of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and said: Abu
Saif, stop it, as there comes Allah's Messenger (may peace he upon
him). He stopped and Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) called
for the child. He embraced him and said what Allah had desired.
Anas said: I saw that the boy breathed his last in the presence of
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). The eyes of Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) shed tears and he said: Ibrahim,
our eyes shed tears and our hearts are filled with grief, but we do
not say anything except that by which Allah is pleased. O Ibrahim,
we are grieved for you.</english-text>
</hadith>
