<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16176</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6270</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني حرملة بن يحيى بن عبد الله بن حرملة بن عمران
التجيبي، أخبرنا ابن، وهب أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، أخبرني أنس بن
مالك، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خرج حين زاغت الشمس فصلى لهم
صلاة الظهر فلما سلم قام على المنبر فذكر الساعة وذكر أن قبلها أمورا
عظاما ثم قال ‏"‏ من أحب أن يسألني عن شىء فليسألني عنه فوالله لا
تسألونني عن شىء إلا أخبرتكم به ما دمت في مقامي هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أنس
بن مالك فأكثر الناس البكاء حين سمعوا ذلك من رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأكثر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يقول ‏"‏ سلوني ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقام عبد الله بن حذافة فقال من أبي يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ أبوك حذافة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما أكثر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من أن يقول ‏"‏ سلوني
‏"‏ ‏.‏ برك عمر فقال رضينا بالله ربا وبالإسلام دينا وبمحمد رسولا -
قال - فسكت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين قال عمر ذلك ثم قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أولى والذي نفس محمد بيده لقد عرضت على
الجنة والنار آنفا في عرض هذا الحائط فلم أر كاليوم في الخير والشر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة قال قالت
أم عبد الله بن حذافة لعبد الله بن حذافة ما سمعت بابن قط أعق منك
أأمنت أن تكون أمك قد قارفت بعض ما تقارف نساء أهل الجاهلية فتفضحها
على أعين الناس قال عبد الله بن حذافة والله لو ألحقني بعبد أسود
للحقته ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him stood when the sun had passed the meridian and he
led them noon prayer and after observing salutations (completing
the prayer) he stood upon the pulpit and talked about the Last Hour
and made a mention of the important facts prior to it and then
said: He who desires to ask anything from me let him ask me about
it. By Allah, I shall not move from this place so long as I do not
inform you about that which you ask. Anas b. Malik said: People
began to shed tears profusely when they heard this from Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) said it repeatedly: You ask me. Thereupon 'Abdullah b.
Hudhafa stood up and said: Allah's Messenger, who is my father? He
said: Your father is Hudhafa, and Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) said repeatedly: Ask me, and (it was at this juncture
that 'Umar knelt down and said): We are well pleased with Allah as
our Lord, with Islam as our code of life and with Muhammad as the
Messenger (of Allah). Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
kept quiet so long as 'Umar spoke. Then Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: (The Doom) is near; by Him, in Whose Hand
is the life of Muhammad, there was presented to me the Paradise and
Hell in the nook of this enclosure, and I did not see good and evil
like that of the present day. Ibn Shihab reported: Ubaidullah b.
'Abdullah b. 'Utba told me that the mother of 'Abdullah b. Hudhafa
told 'Abdullah b. Hudhafa: I have never heard of a son more
disobedient than you. Do you feel yourself immune from the fact
that your mother committed a sin which the women in the pre-Islamic
period committed and then you disgrace her in the eyes of the
people? 'Abdullah b. Hudhafa said: If my fatherhood were to be
attributed to a black slave I would have connected myself with
him.</english-text>
</hadith>
