<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16178</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6272</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30573, 20246, 11168, 11019, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يوسف بن حماد المعني، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، عن سعيد،
عن قتادة، عن أنس بن مالك، أن الناس، سألوا نبي الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حتى أحفوه بالمسألة فخرج ذات يوم فصعد المنبر فقال ‏"‏ سلوني لا
تسألوني عن شىء إلا بينته لكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما سمع ذلك القوم أرموا
ورهبوا أن يكون بين يدى أمر قد حضر ‏.‏ قال أنس فجعلت ألتفت يمينا
وشمالا فإذا كل رجل لاف رأسه في ثوبه يبكي فأنشأ رجل من المسجد كان
يلاحى فيدعى لغير أبيه فقال يا نبي الله من أبي قال ‏"‏ أبوك حذافة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم أنشأ عمر بن الخطاب رضى الله عنه فقال رضينا بالله ربا
وبالإسلام دينا وبمحمد رسولا عائذا بالله من سوء الفتن ‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لم أر كاليوم قط في الخير والشر إني صورت
لي الجنة والنار فرأيتهما دون هذا الحائط ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported that the people asked Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) until he was hard pressed. He went
out one day and he occupied the pulpit and said: Ask me and I shall
leave no question of yours unanswered for you, and when the people
heard about it they were overawed, as if (something tragic) was
going to happen. Anas said: I began to look towards the right and
the left and (found) that every person was weeping wrapping his
head with the cloth. Then a person in the mosque broke the ice and
they used to dispute with him by attributing his fatherhood to
another man than his own father. He said: Allah's Apostle, who is
my father? He said: Your father is Hudhafa. Then 'Umar b. Khattab
(Allah be pleased with him) dared say something and said: We are
well pleased with Allah as our Lord, with Islam as our code of life
and with Muhammad as our Messenger, seeking refuge with Allah from
the evil of Turmoil. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) said: Never did I see the good and evil as today. Paradise and
Hell were given a visible shape before me (in this worldly life)
and I saw both of them near this well.</english-text>
</hadith>
