<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16201</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6295</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20121, 20115, 11447, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن رافع، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن
همام بن منبه، قال هذا ما حدثنا أبو هريرة، عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فذكر أحاديث منها وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
كانت بنو إسرائيل يغتسلون عراة ينظر بعضهم إلى سوأة بعض وكان موسى
عليه السلام يغتسل وحده فقالوا والله ما يمنع موسى أن يغتسل معنا إلا
أنه آدر ‏.‏ قال فذهب مرة يغتسل فوضع ثوبه على حجر ففر الحجر بثوبه -
قال - فجمح موسى بأثره يقول ثوبي حجر ثوبي حجر ‏.‏ حتى نظرت بنو
إسرائيل إلى سوأة موسى فقالوا والله ما بموسى من بأس ‏.‏ فقام الحجر
بعد حتى نظر إليه - قال - فأخذ ثوبه فطفق بالحجر ضربا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو
هريرة والله إنه بالحجر ندب ستة أو سبعة ضرب موسى عليه السلام بالحجر
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hammam b. Munabbih reported that Abu Huraira reported
many ahadith from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and
one, of them speaks that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
is reported to have said: Banu Isra'il used to take bath (together)
naked and thus saw private parts of one another, but Moses (peace
be upon him) used to take bath alone (in privacy), and they said:
By Allah, nothing prevents Moses to take bath along with us; but
scrotal hernia. One day when he (Moses) was taking bath (alone) he
placed his clothes upon a stone, but the stone began to move along
with his clothes. Moses raced after it saying: My garment, stone;
until (some of the people) of Banu Isra'il looked at the private
parts of Moses, and they said: By Allah, there is no trouble with
Moses. The stone stopped after he (Moses) had been seen. He took
hold of his garments and struck the stone. Abu Huraira said: I
swear by Allah that there were six or seven scars on the stone
because of the striking of stone by Moses (peace be upon
him).</english-text>
</hadith>
