<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16206</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6300</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Excellent Qualities of the Holy
Prophet (may Peace be upon them) and His - كتاب الفضائل</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20382, 20026, 11187, 11197, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا حجين بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد
العزيز بن عبد الله، بن أبي سلمة عن عبد الله بن الفضل الهاشمي، عن
عبد الرحمن الأعرج، عن أبي هريرة، قال بينما يهودي يعرض سلعة له أعطي
بها شيئا كرهه أو لم يرضه - شك عبد العزيز - قال لا والذي اصطفى موسى
عليه السلام على البشر ‏.‏ قال فسمعه رجل من الأنصار فلطم وجهه - قال
- تقول والذي اصطفى موسى عليه السلام على البشر ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بين أظهرنا قال فذهب اليهودي إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال يا أبا القاسم إن لي ذمة وعهدا ‏.‏ وقال فلان لطم وجهي ‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لم لطمت وجهه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏.‏
قال يا رسول الله والذي اصطفى موسى عليه السلام على البشر وأنت بين
أظهرنا ‏.‏ قال فغضب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى عرف الغضب في
وجهه ثم قال ‏"‏ لا تفضلوا بين أنبياء الله فإنه ينفخ في الصور فيصعق
من في السموات ومن في الأرض إلا من شاء الله - قال - ثم ينفخ فيه أخرى
فأكون أول من بعث أو في أول من بعث فإذا موسى عليه السلام آخذ بالعرش
فلا أدري أحوسب بصعقته يوم الطور أو بعث قبلي ولا أقول إن أحدا أفضل
من يونس بن متى عليه السلام ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported: While a Jew was selling goods,
he was given something which he did not accept or he did not agree
(to accept) that 'Abdul 'Azlz (one of the narrators) is doubtful
about it. He (the Jew) said: By Allah, Who chose Moses (peace be
upon him) among mankind. A person from the Ansar heard it and gave
a blow at his face saying: (You have the audacity) to say: By Him
Who chose Moses amongst mankind, whereas Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) is living amongst us. The Jew went to Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and said: Abu'l-Qasim, I am a
Dhimmi and (thus need your protection) by a covenant, and added:
Such and such person has given a blow upon my face. Thereupon
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Why did you give a
blow on his face? He said: Allah's Messenger, this man said: By Him
Who chose Moses (peace be upon him) amongst mankind, whereas you
are living amongst us. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
became angry and signs of anger could be seen on his face, and then
said: Don't make distinction amongst the Prophets of Allah. When
the horn will be blown and whatever is in the heavens and the earth
would swoon but he whom Allah grants exception, then another horn
will be blown and I would be the first amongst those who would
recover and Moses (peace be upon him) would be catching hold of the
Throne and I do not know whether it is a compensation for that when
he swooned on the Day of Tur or he would be resurrected before me
and I do not say that anyone is more excellent than Yunus son of
Matta (peace he upon him). This hadith has been narrated on the
authority of Abu Salama with the same chain of
transmitters.</english-text>
</hadith>
