<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16243</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6338</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30465, 30137, 20025, 10652, 11090, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن عمرو الأشعثي، وأبو الربيع العتكي، وأبو
كريب محمد بن العلاء - واللفظ لأبي كريب - قال أبو الربيع حدثنا وقال
الآخران، أخبرنا ابن المبارك، عن عمر بن سعيد بن أبي حسين، عن ابن أبي
مليكة، قال سمعت ابن عباس، يقول وضع عمر بن الخطاب على سريره فتكنفه
الناس يدعون ويثنون ويصلون عليه قبل أن يرفع وأنا فيهم - قال - فلم
يرعني إلا برجل قد أخذ بمنكبي من ورائي فالتفت إليه فإذا هو علي فترحم
على عمر وقال ما خلفت أحدا أحب إلى أن ألقى الله بمثل عمله منك وايم
الله إن كنت لأظن أن يجعلك الله مع صاحبيك وذاك أني كنت أكثر أسمع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ جئت أنا وأبو بكر وعمر ودخلت
أنا وأبو بكر وعمر وخرجت أنا وأبو بكر وعمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإن كنت لأرجو أو
لأظن أن يجعلك الله معهما ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Abu Mulaika reported: I heard Ibn 'Abbas as
saying: Wlien 'Umar b. Khatab was placed in the coffin the people
gathered around him. They praised him and supplicated for him
before the bier was lifted up, and I was one amongst them. Nothing
attracted my attention but a person who gripped my shoulder from
behind. I saw towards him and found that he was 'All. He invoked
Allah's mercy upon 'Umar and said: You have left none behind you
(whose) deeds (are so enviable) that I love to meet Allah with
them. By Allah, I hoped that Allah would keep you and your two
associates together. I had often heard Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) as saying: I came and there came too Abu Bakr and
'Umar; I entered and there entered too Abu Bakr and 'Umar; I went
out and there went out too Abu Bakr and 'Umar, and I hope and think
that Allah will keep you along with them.</english-text>
</hadith>
