<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16258</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6355</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30523, 20150, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013,
10553</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا منصور بن أبي مزاحم، حدثنا إبراهيم يعني ابن سعد،
ح وحدثنا حسن، الحلواني وعبد بن حميد قال عبد أخبرني وقال، حسن حدثنا
يعقوب، - وهو ابن إبراهيم بن سعد - حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب،
أخبرني عبد الحميد بن عبد الرحمن، بن زيد أن محمد بن سعد بن أبي وقاص،
أخبره أن أباه سعدا قال استأذن عمر على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وعنده نساء من قريش يكلمنه ويستكثرنه عالية أصواتهن فلما استأذن عمر
قمن يبتدرن الحجاب فأذن له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يضحك فقال عمر أضحك الله سنك يا رسول الله ‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ عجبت من هؤلاء اللاتي كن عندي
فلما سمعن صوتك ابتدرن الحجاب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عمر فأنت يا رسول الله أحق
أن يهبن ‏.‏ ثم قال عمر أى عدوات أنفسهن أتهبنني ولا تهبن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قلن نعم أنت أغلظ وأفظ من رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده ما
لقيك الشيطان قط سالكا فجا إلا سلك فجا غير فجك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sa'd b. Waqqas reported that Umar sought permission
from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) to visit him when
some women of the Quraish were busy in talking with him and raising
their voices above his Voiee. When'Umar sought permission they
stood up and went hurriedly behind the curtain. Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) gave him permission smilingly. Thereupon
'Umar said: Allah's Messenger, may Allah keep you happy all your
life. Then Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: I wonder
at these women who were with me and no sooner did they hear your
voice, they immediately went behind the curtain. Thereupon 'Umar
said: Allah's Messenger, you have more right that they should fear
you. Then Umar (addressing the women) said: O ye enemies of
yourselves, do you fear me and fear not the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him)? They said: Yes, you are harsh and strict as
compared to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him).
Thereupon, Allah's Messenger (maypeace be upon him) said: By Him in
Whose Hand is my life, if satan would encounter you in the way he
would certainly take a different way from that of
yours.</english-text>
</hadith>
