<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16266</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6363</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>11207, 11013, 10979, 989</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الملك بن شعيب بن الليث بن سعد، حدثني أبي، عن
جدي، حدثني عقيل، بن خالد عن ابن شهاب، عن يحيى بن سعيد بن العاص، أن
سعيد بن العاص، أخبره أن عائشة زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وعثمان
حدثاه أن أبا بكر استأذن على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو مضطجع
على فراشه لابس مرط عائشة فأذن لأبي بكر وهو كذلك فقضى إليه حاجته ثم
انصرف ثم استأذن عمر فأذن له وهو على تلك الحال فقضى إليه حاجته ثم
انصرف ‏.‏ قال عثمان ثم استأذنت عليه فجلس وقال لعائشة ‏"‏ اجمعي عليك
ثيابك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقضيت إليه حاجتي ثم انصرفت فقالت عائشة يا رسول الله
ما لي لم أرك فزعت لأبي بكر وعمر رضي الله عنهما كما فزعت لعثمان قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن عثمان رجل حيي وإني خشيت إن أذنت
له على تلك الحال أن لا يبلغ إلى في حاجته ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A'isha, the wife of Allah's Apostle (mav peace be
upon him), and Uthman both reported that Abu Bakr sought permission
from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) for entrance (in his
apartment) as he had been lying on his bed covered with the
bed-sheet of A'isha, and he gave permission to Abu Bakr in that
very state and he, having his need fulfilled, went back. Then Umar
sought permission and it was given to him in that very state and,
after having his need fulfilled, he went back. And 'Uthman
reported: Then I sought permission from him and he got up and raid
to A'isha: Wrap yourself well with your cloth, then I got my need
fulfilled and came back. And A'isha said: Allah's Messenger, why is
it that I did not see you feeling any anxiety in case of dressing
properly in the presence of Abu Bakr and 'Umar (Allah be pleased
with them) as you showed in case of 'Uthman. Thereupon Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Verily Uthman is a person
who is very modest and I was afraid that if I permitted him to
enter in this very state he would not inform me of his
need.</english-text>
</hadith>
