<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16265</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6362</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20379, 30367, 30399, 11535, 11029, 11005,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، ويحيى بن أيوب، وقتيبة، وابن، حجر
قال يحيى بن يحيى أخبرنا وقال الآخرون، حدثنا إسماعيل، - يعنون ابن
جعفر - عن محمد بن أبي حرملة، عن عطاء، وسليمان، ابنى يسار وأبي سلمة
بن عبد الرحمن أن عائشة، قالت كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
مضطجعا في بيتي كاشفا عن فخذيه أو ساقيه فاستأذن أبو بكر فأذن له وهو
على تلك الحال فتحدث ثم استأذن عمر فأذن له وهو كذلك فتحدث ثم استأذن
عثمان فجلس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسوى ثيابه - قال محمد ولا
أقول ذلك في يوم واحد - فدخل فتحدث فلما خرج قالت عائشة دخل أبو بكر
فلم تهتش له ولم تباله ثم دخل عمر فلم تهتش له ولم تباله ثم دخل عثمان
فجلست وسويت ثيابك فقال ‏"‏ ألا أستحي من رجل تستحي منه الملائكة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A'isha reported: Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) was lying in the bed in my apartment with his thigh or his
shank uncovered that Abu Bakr sought permission to get in. It was
given to him and he conversed in the same very state (the Prophet's
thigh or shank uncovered). Then 'Umar sought permission for getting
in and it was given to him and he conversed in that very state.
Then 'Uthman sought permission for getting in; Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) sat down and he set right his clothes.
Mubammad (one of the narrators) said: I do not say that it happened
on the same day. He ('Uthman) then entered and conversed and as he
went out, A'isha said: Abu Bakr entered aind you did not stir and
did not observe much care (in arranging your clothes), then 'Umar
entered and you did not stir and did not arrange your clothes, then
'Uthman entered and you got up and set your clothes right,
thereupon he said: Should I not show modesty to one whom even the
Angels show modesty.</english-text>
</hadith>
