<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16263</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6360</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20318, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا عبيد
الله، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر، قال لما توفي عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول
جاء ابنه عبد الله بن عبد الله إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فسأله أن يعطيه قميصه أن يكفن فيه أباه فأعطاه ثم سأله أن يصلي عليه
فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليصلي عليه فقام عمر فأخذ بثوب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله أتصلي عليه وقد نهاك
الله أن تصلي عليه فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنما خيرني
الله فقال ‏{‏ استغفر لهم أو لا تستغفر لهم إن تستغفر لهم سبعين
مرة‏}‏ وسأزيد على سبعين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال إنه منافق ‏.‏ فصلى عليه رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ ولا تصل على أحد منهم
مات أبدا ولا تقم على قبره‏}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Umar reported that when 'Abdullah b. Ubayy b.
Salul (the hypocrite) died, his son Abdullah b. Abdullah came to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon -him) and asked him to give
his shirt which should be used for the coffin of his father. He
gave that to him. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) stood
up to say prayer over him Thereupon I Umar caught hold of the
clothe of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and said:
Allah's Messenger, are you going to offer prayer, whereas Allah has
forbidden to offer prayer for him, whereupon Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: Allah has given me a choice saying: Ask
forgiveness for them or you may not ask for them; even if you ask
for them seventy times, I will make an addition to the seventy. He
was a hypocrite and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said
prayer over him that Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, revealed the
verse:" And never pray over any one of them that has died and never
should you stand by his grave" (ix. 84).</english-text>
</hadith>
