<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16270</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6367</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30275, 20300, 20160, 11858, 11002, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن مسكين اليمامي، حدثنا يحيى بن حسان، حدثنا
سليمان، - وهو ابن بلال - عن شريك بن أبي نمر، عن سعيد بن المسيب،
أخبرني أبو موسى الأشعري، أنه توضأ في بيته ثم خرج فقال لألزمن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ولأكونن معه يومي هذا ‏.‏ قال فجاء المسجد
فسأل عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا خرج ‏.‏ وجه ها هنا - قال -
فخرجت على أثره أسأل عنه حتى دخل بئر أريس - قال - فجلست عند الباب
وبابها من جريد حتى قضى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حاجته وتوضأ
فقمت إليه فإذا هو قد جلس على بئر أريس وتوسط قفها وكشف عن ساقيه
ودلاهما في البئر - قال - فسلمت عليه ثم انصرفت فجلست عند الباب فقلت
لأكونن بواب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اليوم ‏.‏ فجاء أبو بكر
فدفع الباب فقلت من هذا فقال أبو بكر ‏.‏ فقلت على رسلك - قال - ثم
ذهبت فقلت يا رسول الله هذا أبو بكر يستأذن فقال ‏"‏ ائذن له وبشره
بالجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأقبلت حتى قلت لأبي بكر ادخل ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يبشرك بالجنة - قال - فدخل أبو بكر فجلس عن يمين رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم معه في القف ودلى رجليه في البئر كما صنع النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم وكشف عن ساقيه ثم رجعت فجلست وقد تركت أخي يتوضأ
ويلحقني فقلت إن يرد الله بفلان - يريد أخاه - خيرا يأت به ‏.‏ فإذا
إنسان يحرك الباب فقلت من هذا فقال عمر بن الخطاب ‏.‏ فقلت على رسلك
‏.‏ ثم جئت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسلمت عليه وقلت هذا عمر
يستأذن فقال ‏"‏ ائذن له وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجئت عمر فقلت أذن
ويبشرك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالجنة - قال - فدخل فجلس مع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في القف عن يساره ودلى رجليه في البئر
ثم رجعت فجلست فقلت إن يرد الله بفلان خيرا - يعني أخاه - يأت به فجاء
إنسان فحرك الباب فقلت من هذا فقال عثمان بن عفان ‏.‏ فقلت على رسلك -
قال - وجئت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته فقال ‏"‏ ائذن له وبشره
بالجنة مع بلوى تصيبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فجئت فقلت ادخل ويبشرك رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بالجنة مع بلوى تصيبك - قال - فدخل فوجد القف قد
ملئ فجلس وجاههم من الشق الآخر ‏.‏ قال شريك فقال سعيد بن المسيب
فأولتها قبورهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa Ash'ari reported that he performed ablution
in his house and then came out saying: I would remain with Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) the whole day long. He came to
the mosque, and asked about Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon
him). They (his Companions) said: He has gone in this direction. He
(Abu Musa Ash'ari) said: I followed his steps asking about him
until I came to Bi'r Aris (it is a well in the suburb of Medina). I
sat by its wooden door until Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) had relieved himself and then performed ablution. I went to
him and he was sitting with his shanks uncovered hp to the knees
and his legs dangl- ing in that well. I offered him salutations. I
then came back and sat at the door as if I had been a chamberlain
at the door of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) that day.
There came Abu Bakr and knocked the door and I said: Who is it? He
said: This is Abu Bakr. I said: Wait, please. I went and said:
Allah's Messenger, here is Abu Bakr seeking permission. Thereupon
he said: Admit him and give him glad tidings of Paradise. I came
and I said to Abu Bakr to get in (and also told him) that Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) was giving him the glad tidings
of Paradise. Abu Bakr got in and sat on the right side of Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and dangled his feet in the well
as Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had done, and he
uncovered his shanks. I then returned and sat there and I had left
my brother as he had been performing ablution and he was to meet me
and I said: If Allah would intend goodness for such and such he
would intend goodness for his brother and He would bring him. I was
thinking this that a person stirred the door. I said: Who is it. He
said: This is Umar b., Khattab. I said: Wait. Then I came to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), greeted him and said:
Here is 'Umar seeking your. permission to get in. Thereupon he
said: Let him come in and give him glad tid- ings of Paradise. I
came to Umar and said: There is permission for you and glad tidings
for you from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) for
Paradise. He got in and sat on the left side of Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) with his feet dangling in the well. I then
returned and sat and said: If Allah would intend goodness for such
and such (that is for his brother), He would bring him. And I was
contemplat- ing over it that a man stirred the door and I said: Who
is it? He said: This is Uthman b. Affan. I said: Wait, please. I
then came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and informed
him. and he said: Admit him and give him glad tidings (and inform)
him of the turmoil which he shall have to face. I came and said:
Get in, Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) gives you the
glad tidings of Paradise along with the trial which you shall have
to face. He got in and saw the elevated plan round the well fully
occupied. He sat on the other side. Sharik said that Sa'id b.
al-Musayyib reported: I drew a conclusion from it that their groves
would be (in this very state, the graves of Hadrat Abu Bakr, 'Umar
Faruq by the tide of the Holy Prophet [may peace be upon him] and
the grave of Hadrat 'Uthman away from their graves). Abu Musa.
reported: I set out with the intention (of meeting) Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and came to know that he had gone
to the gardens (in the suburb of Medina). I followed him and found
him in a garden sitting upon an elevated place round the well with
his shanks uncovered which had been dangling in the well. The rest
of the hadith is the same but with this variation that there is no
mention of the words of Sa'id: all drew a conclusion from it
pertaining to their graves."</english-text>
</hadith>
