<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16279</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6376</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20165, 11172, 399, 30367, 20185, 11172,
399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا عبد العزيز، - يعني ابن أبي
حازم - عن أبي، حازم عن سهل، ح وحدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، - واللفظ هذا -
حدثنا يعقوب، - يعني ابن عبد الرحمن - عن أبي حازم، أخبرني سهل بن
سعد، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال يوم خيبر ‏"‏ لأعطين هذه
الراية رجلا يفتح الله على يديه يحب الله ورسوله ويحبه الله ورسوله
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبات الناس يدوكون ليلتهم أيهم يعطاها - قال - فلما أصبح
الناس غدوا على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كلهم يرجون أن يعطاها
فقال ‏"‏ أين علي بن أبي طالب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا هو يا رسول الله يشتكي
عينيه - قال - فأرسلوا إليه فأتي به فبصق رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في عينيه ودعا له فبرأ حتى كأن لم يكن به وجع فأعطاه الراية فقال
علي يا رسول الله أقاتلهم حتى يكونوا مثلنا ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ انفذ على
رسلك حتى تنزل بساحتهم ثم ادعهم إلى الإسلام وأخبرهم بما يجب عليهم من
حق الله فيه فوالله لأن يهدي الله بك رجلا واحدا خير لك من أن يكون لك
حمر النعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl b. Sa'd reported that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said on the Day of Khaibar: I would certainly
give this standard to a person at whose hand Allah would grant
victory and who loves Allah and His Messenger and Allah and His
Messenger love him also. The people spent the night thinking as to
whom it would be given. When it was morning the people hastened to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) all of them hoping that
that would be given to him. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Where is
'Ali b. Abu Talib? They said: Allah's Messenger, his eyes are sore.
He then sent for him and he was brought and Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) applied saliva to his eyes and invoked blessings
and he was all right, as if he had no ailment at all, and
coraferred upon him the standard. 'Ali said: Allah's Messenger, I
will fight them until they are like us. Thereupon he (the Holy
Prophet) said: Advance cautiously until you reach their open
places, thereafter invite them to Islam and inform them what is
obligatory for them from the rights of Allah, for, by Allah, if
Allah guides aright even one person through you that is better for
you than to possess the most valuable of the camels.</english-text>
</hadith>
