<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16281</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6378</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 30506, 20208, 20321, 20208, 11404,
28642</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، وشجاع بن مخلد، جميعا عن ابن علية،
قال زهير حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، حدثني أبو حيان، حدثني يزيد بن
حيان، قال انطلقت أنا وحصين، بن سبرة وعمر بن مسلم إلى زيد بن أرقم
فلما جلسنا إليه قال له حصين لقد لقيت يا زيد خيرا كثيرا رأيت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسمعت حديثه وغزوت معه وصليت خلفه لقد لقيت
يا زيد خيرا كثيرا حدثنا يا زيد ما سمعت من رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم - قال - يا ابن أخي والله لقد كبرت سني وقدم عهدي ونسيت بعض الذي
كنت أعي من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فما حدثتكم فاقبلوا وما لا
فلا تكلفونيه ‏.‏ ثم قال قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يوما فينا
خطيبا بماء يدعى خما بين مكة والمدينة فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ووعظ وذكر
ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد ألا أيها الناس فإنما أنا بشر يوشك أن يأتي رسول
ربي فأجيب وأنا تارك فيكم ثقلين أولهما كتاب الله فيه الهدى والنور
فخذوا بكتاب الله واستمسكوا به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فحث على كتاب الله ورغب فيه ثم
قال ‏"‏ وأهل بيتي أذكركم الله في أهل بيتي أذكركم الله في أهل بيتي
أذكركم الله في أهل بيتي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال له حصين ومن أهل بيته يا زيد
أليس نساؤه من أهل بيته قال نساؤه من أهل بيته ولكن أهل بيته من حرم
الصدقة بعده ‏.‏ قال ومن هم قال هم آل علي وآل عقيل وآل جعفر وآل عباس
‏.‏ قال كل هؤلاء حرم الصدقة قال نعم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Yazid b. Hayyan reported, I went along with Husain b.
Sabra and 'Umar b. Muslim to Zaid b. Arqam and, as we sat by his
side, Husain said to him: Zaid. you have been able to acquire a
great virtue that you saw Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
listened to his talk, fought by his side in (different) battles,
offered prayer behind me. Zaid, you have in fact earned a great
virtue. Zaid, narrate to us what you heard from Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him). He said: I have grown old and have almost
spent my age and I have forgotten some of the things which I
remembered in connection with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him), so accept whatever I narrate to you, and which I do not
narrate do not compel me to do that. He then said: One day Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) stood up to deliver sermon at a
watering place known as Khumm situated between Mecca and Medina. He
praised Allah, extolled Him and delivered the sermon and. exhorted
(us) and said: Now to our purpose. O people, I am a human being. I
am about to receive a messenger (the angel of death) from my Lord
and I, in response to Allah's call, (would bid good-bye to you),
but I am leaving among you two weighty things: the one being the
Book of Allah in which there is right guidance and light, so hold
fast to the Book of Allah and adhere to it. He exhorted (us) (to
hold fast) to the Book of Allah and then said: The second are the
members of my household I remind you (of your duties) to the
members of my family. He (Husain) said to Zaid: Who are the members
of his household? Aren't his wives the members of his family?
Thereupon he said: His wives are the members of his family (but
here) the members of his family are those for whom acceptance of
Zakat is forbidden. And he said: Who are they? Thereupon he said:
'Ali and the offspring of 'Ali, 'Aqil and the offspring of 'Aqil
and the offspring of Ja'far and the offspring of 'Abbas. Husain
said: These are those for whom the acceptance of Zakat is
forbidden. Zaid said: Yes.</english-text>
</hadith>
