<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16346</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6443</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني الحسن بن علي الحلواني، وأبو بكر بن النضر وعبد بن
حميد قال عبد حدثني وقال الآخران، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم بن سعد،
حدثني أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن، شهاب أخبرني محمد بن عبد الرحمن بن
الحارث بن هشام، أن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت أرسل
أزواج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فاطمة بنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فاستأذنت عليه وهو مضطجع معي
في مرطي فأذن لها فقالت يا رسول الله إن أزواجك أرسلنني إليك يسألنك
العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة وأنا ساكتة - قالت - فقال لها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أى بنية ألست تحبين ما أحب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت بلى ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فأحبي هذه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فقامت فاطمة حين سمعت ذلك من رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرجعت إلى أزواج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فأخبرتهن بالذي قالت وبالذي قال لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقلن لها ما نراك أغنيت عنا من شىء فارجعي إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقولي له إن أزواجك ينشدنك العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة ‏.‏
فقالت فاطمة والله لا أكلمه فيها أبدا ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فأرسل أزواج
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زينب بنت جحش زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وهي التي كانت تساميني منهن في المنزلة عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ولم أر امرأة قط خيرا في الدين من زينب وأتقى لله وأصدق حديثا
وأوصل للرحم وأعظم صدقة وأشد ابتذالا لنفسها في العمل الذي تصدق به
وتقرب به إلى الله تعالى ما عدا سورة من حد كانت فيها تسرع منها
الفيئة قالت فاستأذنت على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم مع عائشة في مرطها على الحالة التي دخلت فاطمة
عليها وهو بها فأذن لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت يا رسول
الله إن أزواجك أرسلنني إليك يسألنك العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة ‏.‏ قالت
ثم وقعت بي فاستطالت على وأنا أرقب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وأرقب طرفه هل يأذن لي فيها - قالت - فلم تبرح زينب حتى عرفت أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا يكره أن أنتصر - قالت - فلما وقعت بها لم
أنشبها حين أنحيت عليها - قالت - فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وتبسم ‏"‏ إنها ابنة أبي بكر ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha, the wife of Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him), said: The wives of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon
him) sent Fatima, the daughter of Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him), to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him). She ouaht
permission to get in as he had been lying with me in my mantle. He
gave her permission and she said: Allah's Messenger, verily, your
wives have sent me to you in order to ask you to observe equity in
case of the daughter of Abu Quhafa. She ('A'isha) said: I kept
quiet. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said to
her (Fatima): 0 daughter, don't you love whom I love? She said:
Yes, (I do). Thereupon he said: I love this one. Fatima then stood
up as she heard this from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
and went to the wives of Allatt's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
and informed them of what she had said to him and what Allah's
messenger (may peace be upon him) had said to her. Thereupon they
said to her: We think that you have been of no avail to us. You may
again go to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and tell him
that his wives seek equity in case of the daughter of Abu Quhafa.
Fitima said: By Allah, I will never talk to him about this matter.
'A'isha (further) reported: The wives of Allah's Apostle (may peace
be upon him) then sent Zainab b. jahsh, the wife of Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him), and she was one who was somewhat equal in
rank with me in the eyes of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) and I have never seen a woman more advanced in religious piety
than Zainab, more God-conscious, more truthful, more alive to the
ties of blood, more generous and having more. sense of
self-sacrifice in practical life and having more charitable
disposition and thus more close to God, the Exalted, than her. She,
however, lost temper very soon but was soon calm. Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) permitted her to enter as she ('A'isha) was
along with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) in her mantle,
in the same very state when Fatima had entered. She said: Allah's
Messenger, your wives have sent me to you seeking equity in case of
the daughter of Abu Quhafa. She then came to me and showed
harshness to me and I was seeing the eyes of Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) whether he would permit me. Zainab went on until
I came to know that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) would
not disapprove if I retorted. Then I exchanged hot words until I
made her quiet. Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
smiled and said: She is the daughter of Abu Bakr. This hadith has
been narrated on the authority of Zuhri with the same chain of
transmitters, but with a slight variation of
wording.</english-text>
</hadith>
