<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16354</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6451</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 30553, 20348, 20348, 11560, 11090, 10535,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي، وحدثنا عبد بن حميد،
كلاهما عن أبي نعيم، قال عبد حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا عبد الواحد بن
أيمن، حدثني ابن أبي مليكة، عن القاسم، بن محمد عن عائشة، قالت كان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا خرج أقرع بين نسائه فطارت القرعة
على عائشة وحفصة فخرجتا معه جميعا وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
إذا كان بالليل سار مع عائشة يتحدث معها فقالت حفصة لعائشة ألا تركبين
الليلة بعيري وأركب بعيرك فتنظرين وأنظر قالت بلى ‏.‏ فركبت عائشة على
بعير حفصة وركبت حفصة على بعير عائشة فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إلى جمل عائشة وعليه حفصة فسلم ثم صار معها حتى نزلوا فافتقدته
عائشة فغارت فلما نزلوا جعلت تجعل رجلها بين الإذخر وتقول يا رب سلط
على عقربا أو حية تلدغني رسولك ولا أستطيع أن أقول له شيئا
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported that when Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) set ont on a journey, he used to cast lots
amongst his wives. Once this lot came out in my favour and that of
Hafsa. They (Hafsi, and 'A'isha) both went along with him and
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) used to travel (on camel)
when it was night along with 'A'isha and talked with her. Hafsa
said to 'A'isha: Would you like to ride upon my camel tonight and
allow me to ride upon your camel and you would see (what you do not
generally see) and I would see (what I do not see) generally? She
said: Yes. So 'A'isha rode upon the camel of Hafsa and Hafsa rode
upon the camel of 'A'isha and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) came near the camel of 'A'isha. (whereas) Hafsa had been
riding over that. He greeted her and then rode with her until they
came down. She ('A'isha) thus missed (the company of the Holy
Prophet) and when they sat down, 'A'isha felt jealous. She put her
foot in the grass and said: O Allah, let the scorpion sting me or
the serpent bite me. And so far as thy Messenger is concerned, I
cannot say anything about him.</english-text>
</hadith>
