<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16366</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6463</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 30330, 20428, 11013, 11045, 2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن الدارمي، أخبرنا أبو
اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، أخبرني علي بن حسين، أن المسور بن
مخرمة، أخبره أن علي بن أبي طالب خطب بنت أبي جهل وعنده فاطمة بنت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما سمعت بذلك فاطمة أتت النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقالت له إن قومك يتحدثون أنك لا تغضب لبناتك وهذا علي
ناكحا ابنة أبي جهل ‏.‏ قال المسور فقام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فسمعته حين تشهد ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد فإني أنكحت أبا العاص بن الربيع
فحدثني فصدقني وإن فاطمة بنت محمد مضغة مني وإنما أكره أن يفتنوها
وإنها والله لا تجتمع بنت رسول الله وبنت عدو الله عند رجل واحد أبدا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فترك علي الخطبة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Ali b. Husain reported that Miswar b. Makhramah
informed him that 'Ali b. Abi Talib sent the proposal of marriage
to the daughter of Abu Jahl as he had Fatima, the daughter of
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), (as his wife). When
Fatima heard about it, she came to Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him) and said: The people say that you never feel angry on
account of your daughters and now 'Ali is going to marry the
daughter of Abu Jahl. Makhramah said: Thereupon Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) rose up and I heard him reciting Tashahhud
and say: Now to the point. I gave a daughter of mine (Zainab) to
Abu'l-'As b. Rabi, and he spoke to me and spoke the truth. Verily
Fatima, the daughter of Muhammad, is a part of me and I do not
approve that she may be put to any trial and by Allah, the daughter
of Allah's Messenger cannot be combined with the daughter of God's
enemy (as the co-wives) of one person. Thereupon 'Ali gave up (the
idea of his intended) marriage. This hadith has been narrated on
the authority of Zuhri with the same chain of
transmitters.</english-text>
</hadith>
