<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16365</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6462</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30007, 20184, 20150, 11230, 11220, 11013,
11045</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أحمد بن حنبل، أخبرنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا
أبي، عن الوليد بن كثير، حدثني محمد بن عمرو بن حلحلة الدؤلي، أن ابن
شهاب، حدثه أن علي بن الحسين حدثه أنهم، حين قدموا المدينة من عند
يزيد بن معاوية مقتل الحسين بن علي رضى الله عنهما لقيه المسور بن
مخرمة فقال له هل لك إلى من حاجة تأمرني بها قال فقلت له لا ‏.‏ قال
له هل أنت معطي سيف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فإني أخاف أن يغلبك
القوم عليه وايم الله لئن أعطيتنيه لا يخلص إليه أبدا حتى تبلغ نفسي
إن علي بن أبي طالب خطب بنت أبي جهل على فاطمة فسمعت رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وهو يخطب الناس في ذلك على منبره هذا وأنا يومئذ محتلم
فقال ‏"‏ إن فاطمة مني وإني أتخوف أن تفتن في دينها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم
ذكر صهرا له من بني عبد شمس فأثنى عليه في مصاهرته إياه فأحسن قال ‏"‏
حدثني فصدقني ووعدني فأوفى لي وإني لست أحرم حلالا ولا أحل حراما ولكن
والله لا تجتمع بنت رسول الله وبنت عدو الله مكانا واحدا أبدا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>(Imam Zain-ul-'Abidin) 'Ali b. Husain reported that
when they came to Medina from Yazid b. Mu'awiya after the martyrdom
of Husain b. 'Ali (Allah be pleased with him) Miswar b. Makhramah
met him and said to him: Is there any work for me which you ask me
to do? I said to him: No. He again said to me: Would you not give
me the sword of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) for I
fear that the people may snatch it from you? By Allah, if you give
that to me, no one would be able to take it away, so long as there
is life in me. Verily 'Ali b. Abi Talib sent a proposal of marriage
to the daughter of Abu Jahl in spite of (the fact that his wife)
Fatima (had been living in his house). Thereupon I heard Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) say while addressing the people
on the pulpit. I was adolescing in those days. He said: Fatima is a
part of me and I fear that she may be put to trial in regard to
religion. He then made a mention of his son-in law who had been
from the tribe of 'Abd Shams and praised his behaviour as a
son-in-law and said: Whatever he said to me he told the truth and
whatever he promised he fulfilled it for me. I am not going to
declare forbidden what is lawful and make lawful what is forbidden,
but, by Allah, the daaghter of Allah's Messenger and the daughter
of the enemy of Allah can never be combined at one
place.</english-text>
</hadith>
