<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16371</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6468</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20331, 11338, 30212, 20331, 11338, 11385,
11052, 11018, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وحدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، عن
زكرياء، ح وحدثنا ابن نمير، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا زكرياء، عن فراس، عن
عامر، عن مسروق، عن عائشة، قالت اجتمع نساء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فلم يغادر منهن امرأة فجاءت فاطمة تمشي كأن مشيتها مشية رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ مرحبا بابنتي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأجلسها عن يمينه أو عن
شماله ثم إنه أسر إليها حديثا فبكت فاطمة ثم إنه سارها فضحكت أيضا
فقلت لها ما يبكيك فقالت ما كنت لأفشي سر رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ فقلت ما رأيت كاليوم فرحا أقرب من حزن ‏.‏ فقلت لها حين بكت
أخصك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بحديثه دوننا ثم تبكين وسألتها عما
قال فقالت ما كنت لأفشي سر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ حتى إذا
قبض سألتها فقالت إنه كان حدثني ‏"‏ أن جبريل كان يعارضه بالقرآن كل
عام مرة وإنه عارضه به في العام مرتين ولا أراني إلا قد حضر أجلي وإنك
أول أهلي لحوقا بي ونعم السلف أنا لك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فبكيت لذلك ثم إنه سارني
فقال ‏"‏ ألا ترضين أن تكوني سيدة نساء المؤمنين أو سيدة نساء هذه
الأمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فضحكت لذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported that all the wives of Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) had gathered (in her apartment)
during the days of his (Prophet's) last illness and no woman was
left behind that Fatima, who walked after the style of Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him), came there. He welcomed her by
saying: You are welcome, my daughter, and made her sit on his right
side or on his left side, and then talked something secretly to her
and Fitima wept. Then he talked something secretly to her and she
laughed. I said to her: What makes you weep? She said; I am not
going to divulge the secret of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him). I ('A'isha) said: I have not seen (anything happening) like
today, the happiness being more close to grief (as I see today)
when she wept. I said to her: Has Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) singled you out for saying something leaving us aside?
She then wept and I asked her what he said, and she said: I am not
going to divulge the secrets of Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him). And when he died I again asked her and she said that he
(the Holy Prophet) told her: Gabriel used to recite the Qur'an to
me once a year and for this year it was twice and so I perceived
that my death had drawn near, and that I ('A'isha) would be the
first amongst the members of his family who would meet him (in the
Hereafter). He shall be my good forerunner and it made me weep. He
again talked to me secretly (saying): Arn't you pleased that you
should be the sovereign amongst the believing women or the head of
women of this Umma? And this made me laugh.</english-text>
</hadith>
