<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16415</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6512</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30427, 20021, 11269, 10713, 227</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن عمر بن سليط، حدثنا حماد بن سلمة، عن
ثابت، عن كنانة، بن نعيم عن أبي برزة، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
كان في مغزى له فأفاء الله عليه فقال لأصحابه ‏"‏ هل تفقدون من أحد
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم فلانا وفلانا وفلانا ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ هل تفقدون من
أحد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم فلانا وفلانا وفلانا ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ هل تفقدون
من أحد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لكني أفقد جليبيبا فاطلبوه ‏"‏
‏.‏ فطلب في القتلى فوجدوه إلى جنب سبعة قد قتلهم ثم قتلوه فأتى النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فوقف عليه فقال ‏"‏ قتل سبعة ثم قتلوه هذا مني
وأنا منه هذا مني وأنا منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فوضعه على ساعديه ليس له إلا
ساعدا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال فحفر له ووضع في قبره ‏.‏ ولم
يذكر غسلا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Barza reported that Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him) was there in a battlefield that Allah conferred upon him
the spoils of war. He said to his Companions: Is anyone missing
amongst you? They said: So and so and so. He again said: Is there
anyone missing amongst you? They said: So and so and so. He then
said: Is there anyone missing amongst you? They said: No. Thereupon
he (the Holy Prophet) said: But I am missing Julaibib. They (his
Companions) searched him amongst those who had been killed and they
found him by the side of seven (dead bodies) whom he had killed and
he had been killed (by the oppoments). Allah's Apostle (may peace
be upon him) came there and stood (by his side) and said: He killed
seven (persons). Then (his opponents) killed him. He is mine and I
am his. He then placed him upon his hands and there was none else
to lift but Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him). Then the grave
was dug for him and he was placed in the grave and no mention is
made of a bath.</english-text>
</hadith>
