<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16424</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6521</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20028, 11418, 11046, 4057</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، أخبرنا جرير، عن إسماعيل بن أبي
خالد، عن قيس، بن أبي حازم عن جرير بن عبد الله البجلي، قال قال لي
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا جرير ألا تريحني من ذي الخلصة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ بيت لخثعم كان يدعى كعبة اليمانية ‏.‏ قال فنفرت في خمسين
ومائة فارس وكنت لا أثبت على الخيل فذكرت ذلك لرسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فضرب يده في صدري فقال ‏"‏ اللهم ثبته واجعله هاديا مهديا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فانطلق فحرقها بالنار ثم بعث جرير إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم رجلا يبشره يكنى أبا أرطاة منا فأتى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال له ما جئتك حتى تركناها كأنها جمل أجرب ‏.‏ فبرك رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على خيل أحمس ورجالها خمس مرات
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jarir b. 'Abdullah al-Bajali said: Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) said to me: Can't on rid me of
Dhu'I-Khalasah, the idol-house of Khath'am, and this idol-house was
called the Yamanite Ka'ba. So I went along with 150 horsemen and I
could not sit with steadfastness upon the horse. I made the mention
of it to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and he struck
his hand on my chest and said: O Allah, grant him steadfastness and
make him the guide of righteousness and the rightly-guided one. So
he went away and he set fire to it. Then Jarir sent some person to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) whose Kunya was Abu Arta
to give him the happy news about that. He came to Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) and said: I have not come to you (but with
the news) that we have left Dhu'l-Khalasah as a scabed camel.
Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) blessed the
horses of Ahmas and the men of their tribe five
times.</english-text>
</hadith>
