<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16460</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6557</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30263, 30022, 30123, 30312, 20005, 11081,
30245, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وعمرو الناقد، وزهير بن حرب،
وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، وابن أبي عمر - واللفظ لعمرو - قال إسحاق أخبرنا
وقال الآخرون، حدثنا سفيان بن، عيينة عن عمرو، عن الحسن بن محمد،
أخبرني عبيد الله بن أبي رافع، - وهو كاتب علي قال سمعت عليا، رضى
الله عنه وهو يقول بعثنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنا والزبير
والمقداد فقال ‏"‏ ائتوا روضة خاخ فإن بها ظعينة معها كتاب فخذوه منها
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانطلقنا تعادى بنا خيلنا فإذا نحن بالمرأة فقلنا أخرجي
الكتاب ‏.‏ فقالت ما معي كتاب ‏.‏ فقلنا لتخرجن الكتاب أو لتلقين
الثياب ‏.‏ فأخرجته من عقاصها فأتينا به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فإذا فيه من حاطب بن أبي بلتعة إلى ناس من المشركين من أهل مكة يخبرهم
ببعض أمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ يا حاطب ما هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا تعجل على يا رسول الله إني
كنت امرأ ملصقا في قريش - قال سفيان كان حليفا لهم ولم يكن من أنفسها
- وكان ممن كان معك من المهاجرين لهم قرابات يحمون بها أهليهم فأحببت
إذ فاتني ذلك من النسب فيهم أن أتخذ فيهم يدا يحمون بها قرابتي ولم
أفعله كفرا ولا ارتدادا عن ديني ولا رضا بالكفر بعد الإسلام ‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ صدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال عمر دعني يا رسول الله
أضرب عنق هذا المنافق ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إنه قد شهد بدرا وما يدريك لعل
الله اطلع على أهل بدر فقال اعملوا ما شئتم فقد غفرت لكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ يا أيها الذين آمنوا لا تتخذوا عدوي وعدوكم
أولياء‏}‏ وليس في حديث أبي بكر وزهير ذكر الآية وجعلها إسحاق في
روايته من تلاوة سفيان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ubaidullah b. Rafi', who was the scribe of 'All,
reported: I heard 'Ali (Allah be pleased with him) as saying:
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) sent me and Zubair and
Miqdad saying: Go to the garden of, Khakh [it is a place between
Medina and Mecca at a distance of twelve miles from Medina] and
there you will find a woman riding a camel. She would be in
possession of a letter, which you must get from her. So we rushed
on horses and when we met that woman, we asked her to deliver that
letter to us. She said: There is no letter with me. We said: Either
bring out that letter or we would take off your clothes. She
brought out that letter from (the plaited hair of) her head. We
delivered that letter to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
in which Hatib b. Abu Balta'a had informed some people amongst the
polytheists of Mecca about the affairs of Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him). Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said:
Hatib, what is this? He said: Allah's messenger, do not be hasty in
judging my intention. I was a person attached to the Quraish.
Sufyan said: He was their ally but had no relationship with them.
(Hatib further said): Those who are with you amongst the emigrants
have blood-relationship with them (the Quraish) and thus they would
protect their families. I wished that when I had no
blood-relationship with them I should find some supporters from
(amongst them) who would help my family. I have not done this
because of any unbelief or apostasy and I have no liking for the
unbelief after I have (accepted) Islam. Thereupon Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him) said: You have told the truth. 'Umar said:
Allah's Messenger, permit me to strike the neck of this hypocrite.
But he (the Holy Prophet) said: He was a participant in Badr and
you little know that Allah revealed about the people of Badr: Do
what you like for there is forgiveness for you. And Allah, the
Exalted and Glorious, said:" O you who believe, do not take My
enemy and your enemy for friends" (lx. 1). And there is no mention
of this verse in the hadith transmitted on the authority of Abu
Bakr and Zubair and Ishaq has in his narration made a mention of
the recitation of this verse by Sufyan.</english-text>
</hadith>
