<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16464</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6561</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>20318, 20443, 20318, 11325, 11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عامر الأشعري، وأبو كريب جميعا عن أبي أسامة،
قال أبو عامر حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا بريد، عن جده أبي بردة، عن أبي
موسى، قال كنت عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو نازل بالجعرانة بين
مكة والمدينة ومعه بلال فأتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رجل أعرابي
فقال ألا تنجز لي يا محمد ما وعدتني فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أبشر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال له الأعرابي أكثرت على من ‏"‏ أبشر ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأقبل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على أبي موسى وبلال كهيئة
الغضبان فقال ‏"‏ إن هذا قد رد البشرى فاقبلا أنتما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالا
قبلنا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ ثم دعا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بقدح فيه
ماء فغسل يديه ووجهه فيه ومج فيه ثم قال ‏"‏ اشربا منه وأفرغا على
وجوهكما ونحوركما وأبشرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأخذا القدح ففعلا ما أمرهما به رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فنادتهما أم سلمة من وراء الستر أفضلا لأمكما
مما في إنائكما ‏.‏ فأفضلا لها منه طائفة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa reported: I was in the company of Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) as he had been sitting in Ji'rana
(a place) between Mecca and Medina and Bilal was also there, that
there came to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) a desert
Arab, and he said: Muhammad, fulfill your promise that you made
with me. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said to him:
Accept glad tidings. Thereupon the desert Arab said: You shower
glad tidings upon me very much; then Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) turned towards Abu Musa and Bilal seemingly in a state
of annoyance and said: Verily he has rejected glad tidings but you
two should accept them. We said: Allah's Messenger, we have readily
accepted them. Then Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
called for a cup of water and washed his hands in that and face too
and put the saliva in it and then said: Drink out of it and pour it
over your faces and over your chest and gladden yourselves. They
took hold of the cup and did as Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) had commanded them to do. Thereupon Umm Salama called
from behind the veil: Spare some water in your vessel for your
mother also, and they also gave some water which had been spared
for her.</english-text>
</hadith>
