<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16469</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6566</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30549, 30216, 20318, 11325, 11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن براد الأشعري، ومحمد بن العلاء
الهمداني، قالا حدثنا أبو أسامة حدثني بريد، عن أبي بردة، عن أبي
موسى، قال بلغنا مخرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ونحن باليمن
فخرجنا مهاجرين إليه أنا وأخوان لي أنا أصغرهما أحدهما أبو بردة
والآخر أبو رهم - إما قال بضعا وإما قال ثلاثة وخمسين أو اثنين وخمسين
رجلا من قومي - قال فركبنا سفينة فألقتنا سفينتنا إلى النجاشي بالحبشة
فوافقنا جعفر بن أبي طالب وأصحابه عنده فقال جعفر إن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم بعثنا ها هنا وأمرنا بالإقامة فأقيموا معنا ‏.‏ فأقمنا
معه حتى قدمنا جميعا - قال - فوافقنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
حين افتتح خيبر فأسهم لنا - أو قال أعطانا منها - وما قسم لأحد غاب عن
فتح خيبر منها شيئا إلا لمن شهد معه إلا لأصحاب سفينتنا مع جعفر
وأصحابه قسم لهم معهم - قال - فكان ناس من الناس يقولون لنا - يعني
لأهل السفينة - نحن سبقناكم بالهجرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa reported: We were in Yemen when we heard of
the migration of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). We also
set out as immigrants to him. And I was accompanied by two brothers
of mine, I being the youngest of them; one of them was Abu Burda
and the other one was Abu Ruhm, and there were some other persons
with them. Some say they were fifty-three or fifty-two persons of
my tribe. We embarked upon a boat, and the boat sailed away to the
Negus of Abyssinia. There we met Ja'far b. Abu Talib and his
companions. Ja'far said: Allall's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
has sent us here and has commanded us to stay here and you should
also stay with us. So we stayed with him and we came back (to
Medina) and met Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) when
Khaibar had been conquered. He (the Holy Prophet) allocated a share
to us and in the ordinary course he did not allocate the share to
one who had been absent on the occasion of the conquest of Khaibar
but conferred (a share) upon him only who had been present there
with him. He, however, made an exception for the people of the
boat, viz. for Ja'far and his companions. He allocated a share to
them, and some persons from amongst the people said to us, viz. the
people of the boat: We have preceded you in migration. Asma' bint
'Umais who had migrated to Abyssinia and had come back along with
them (along with immigrants) visited Hafsa, the wife of Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him). (Accordingly), Umar had been
sitting with her (Hafsa). As 'Umar saw Asma, he said: Who is she?
She (Hafsa) said: She is Asma, daughter of 'Umais. He said: She is
an Abyssinian and a sea-woman. Asma said: Yes, it is so. Thereupon
'Umar said: We preceded you in migration and so we have more right
to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) as compared with you.
At this she felt annoyed and said: 'Umar, you are not stating the
fact; by Allah, you had the privilege of being in the company of
the Messenger (may peace be upon him) who fed the hungry among you
and instructed the ignorant amongst you, whereas we had been far
(from here) in the land of Abyssinia amongst the enemies and that
was all for Allah and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
and, by Allah, I would never take food nor take water unless I make
a mention to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) of what you
have said. We remained in that country in constant trouble and
dread and I shall talk about it to Allah's Messenger (way peace be
upon him) and ask him (about it). By Allah, I shall not tell a lie
and deviate (from the truth) and add anything to that. So, when
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) came, she said: Allah's
Apostle, 'Umar says so and so. Upon this Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) said: His right is not more than yours, for him
and his companions there is one migration, but for you, i. e. for
the people of the boat, there are two migrations. She said: I saw
Abu Musa and the people of the boat coming to me in groups and
asking me about this hadith, because there was nothing more
pleasing and more significant for them than this. Abu Burda
reported that Asma said: I saw Abu Musa, asking me to repeat this
hadith to him again and again.</english-text>
</hadith>
