<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16483</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6581</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20182, 11061</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى التميمي، أخبرنا المغيرة بن عبد
الرحمن، عن أبي الزناد، قال شهد أبو سلمة لسمع أبا أسيد الأنصاري يشهد
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ خير دور الأنصار بنو النجار
ثم بنو عبد الأشهل ثم بنو الحارث بن الخزرج ثم بنو ساعدة وفي كل دور
الأنصار خير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو سلمة قال أبو أسيد أتهم أنا على رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لو كنت كاذبا لبدأت بقومي بني ساعدة ‏.‏ وبلغ
ذلك سعد بن عبادة فوجد في نفسه وقال خلفنا فكنا آخر الأربع أسرجوا لي
حماري آتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وكلمه ابن أخيه سهل فقال
أتذهب لترد على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أعلم أوليس حسبك أن تكون رابع أربع ‏.‏ فرجع وقال الله
ورسوله أعلم وأمر بحماره فحل عنه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Usaid Ansar reported: I bear witness to the fact
that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: The best
settlements of the Ansar are of those of Banu Najjar, then of Banu
'Abu al-Aslihal and then of Banu Harith b. Khazraj, then of Banu
Sa'ida and there is in every settlement of the Ansar good. Abu
Salama reported that Abu Usaid said: Can I tell a Iie about Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him)? And if I were a liar, I would
have started with my tribe Banu Sa'ida. This was conveyed to Sa'd
b. 'Ubida and he found (rankling) in his mind and said: We have
been left behind (in the sense) that we have been (mentioned) last
of the four. He (Sa'd) sid: Saddle my pony so that I should go to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). His nephew saw him and
said: Are you going to contradict (the order of) precedence set by
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), whereas Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) has the best knowledge of it? Is
it not sufficient for you that you are the fourth amongst the four
(best tribes of the Ansar)? So he returned and said: Allah and His
Messenger know best, and he commanded that his pony should be
unsaddled.</english-text>
</hadith>
