<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16485</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6583</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30263, 30553, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني عمرو الناقد، وعبد بن حميد، قالا حدثنا يعقوب، -
وهو ابن إبراهيم بن سعد - حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال قال
أبو سلمة وعبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن مسعود سمعا أبا هريرة،
يقول قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو في مجلس عظيم من المسلمين
‏"‏ أحدثكم بخير دور الأنصار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بنو عبد الأشهل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ثم من
يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ ثم بنو النجار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ثم من يا رسول الله
قال ‏"‏ ثم بنو الحارث بن الخزرج ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ثم من يا رسول الله
قال ‏"‏ ثم بنو ساعدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ثم من يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ ثم في
كل دور الأنصار خير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقام سعد بن عبادة مغضبا فقال أنحن آخر
الأربع حين سمى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دارهم فأراد كلام رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال له رجال من قومه اجلس ألا ترضى أن سمى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم داركم في الأربع الدور التي سمى فمن ترك
فلم يسم أكثر ممن سمى ‏.‏ فانتهى سعد بن عبادة عن كلام رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying in a large gathering of the Muslims: Should I
not tell you of the best clans of the Ansar? They said: Allah's
Messenger, (kindly) do this. Thereupon Allah's Messenger said: That
is Banu Abd al-Ashhal. They said: Allah's Messenger, then next? He
said: Banu Najjar. They again said: Allah's Messenger, then next?
He said: Then of Banu Harith b. Khazraj. They then said: Allah's
Messenger, then next? He said. Then of Banu Sa'ida. They said:
Allah's Messenger, then next? He said: There is good in all the
clans of the Ansar. It was upon this that Sa'd b. Ubida stood up in
annoyance and said: Are we the last of the four as Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) has determined (the order of
precedence) of their clans? He decided to talk with Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) on this issue, but the people Of
his tribe said to him: Be seated, are you not happy with this that
Allah's Messenger' (may peace be upon him) has mentioned your clan
as one of the four (best) clans and those whom he left and did not
mention (the order of their precedence) are more than those whom he
mentioned? And Sa'd b. 'Ubada dropped the idea of talking to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) (on this
issue).</english-text>
</hadith>
