<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16531</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6629</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30123, 11278, 20436, 20315, 10821, 11345,
11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، وعبد
الله بن عمر بن أبان، كلهم عن حسين، - قال أبو بكر حدثنا حسين بن علي
الجعفي، - عن مجمع بن يحيى، عن سعيد بن أبي بردة، عن أبي بردة، عن
أبيه، قال صلينا المغرب مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم قلنا لو
جلسنا حتى نصلي معه العشاء - قال - فجلسنا فخرج علينا فقال ‏"‏ ما
زلتم ها هنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا يا رسول الله صلينا معك المغرب ثم قلنا نجلس
حتى نصلي معك العشاء قال ‏"‏ أحسنتم أو أصبتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فرفع رأسه
إلى السماء وكان كثيرا مما يرفع رأسه إلى السماء فقال ‏"‏ النجوم أمنة
للسماء فإذا ذهبت النجوم أتى السماء ما توعد وأنا أمنة لأصحابي فإذا
ذهبت أتى أصحابي ما يوعدون وأصحابي أمنة لأمتي فإذا ذهب أصحابي أتى
أمتي ما يوعدون ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Burda reported on the authority of his father: We
offered the sunset prayer along with Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him). We then said: If we sit (along with Allah's Messenger)
and observe night prayer with him it would be very good, so we sat
down and he came to us and said: You are still sitting here. I
said: Allah's Messenger, we observed evening prayer with you, then
we said: Let us sit down and observe night prayer along with you,
whereupon he said: You have done well or you have done right. He
then lifted his head towards the sky and it often happened that as
he lifted his head towards the sky, he said: The stars are a source
of security for the sky and when the stars disappear there comes to
the sky, i. e. (it meets the same fate) as it has been promised (it
would plunge into darkness). And I am a source of safety and
security to my Companions and when I would go away there would fall
to the lot (of my Companions) as they have been promised with and
my Companions are a source of security for the Umma and as they
would go there would fall to the lot of my Umma as (its people)
have been promised.</english-text>
</hadith>
