<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16533</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6631</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30254, 20367, 11070, 11263, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني سعيد بن يحيى بن سعيد الأموي، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
ابن جريج، عن أبي، الزبير عن جابر، قال زعم أبو سعيد الخدري قال قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يأتي على الناس زمان يبعث منهم
البعث فيقولون انظروا هل تجدون فيكم أحدا من أصحاب النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فيوجد الرجل فيفتح لهم به ثم يبعث البعث الثاني فيقولون هل
فيهم من رأى أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فيفتح لهم به ثم يبعث
البعث الثالث فيقال انظروا هل ترون فيهم من رأى من رأى أصحاب النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم يكون البعث الرابع فيقال انظروا هل ترون فيهم
أحدا رأى من رأى أحدا رأى أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فيوجد الرجل
فيفتح لهم به ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Sa'id Khudri reported Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) as saying: There would come to the people a time
when a detachment would be sent for fighting in the cause of Allah
and they would say: See, if you can find amongst them someone from
amongst the Companions of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him).
They would find a person and they would be granted victory because
of him. Then a second detachment would be sent to them and they
would say: Do you find amongst them one who had had the privilege
of seeing the Companions of the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon
him)? -and the victory would be granted to them because of him.
Then the third detachment would be sent and it would be said to
them: See, if you find amongst them (who had had the honour of
seeing one) who saw those who saw the Companions of Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him). Then the fourth detachment would be sent
and it would be said to them: See it you find amongst them one who
had the privilege (of seeing) one who saw those who saw those who
saw the Companions of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him), and
a person would be found and they would be granted victory because
of him.</english-text>
</hadith>
