<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16558</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6656</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Merits of the Companions (Allah
Be Pleased With Them) of the Holy Prophet - كتاب فضائل الصحابة رضى
الله تعالى عنهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 30170, 30160, 30312, 20287, 20295, 11019,
11284</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي، ومحمد بن المثنى، ومحمد
بن بشار، - قال إسحاق أخبرنا وقال الآخران، حدثنا - واللفظ، لابن
المثنى - حدثنا معاذ بن هشام، حدثني أبي، عن قتادة، عن زرارة بن أوفى،
عن أسير بن جابر، قال كان عمر بن الخطاب إذا أتى عليه أمداد أهل اليمن
سألهم أفيكم أويس بن عامر حتى أتى على أويس فقال أنت أويس بن عامر قال
نعم ‏.‏ قال من مراد ثم من قرن قال نعم ‏.‏ قال فكان بك برص فبرأت منه
إلا موضع درهم قال نعم ‏.‏ قال لك والدة قال نعم ‏.‏ قال سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ يأتي عليكم أويس بن عامر مع أمداد
أهل اليمن من مراد ثم من قرن كان به برص فبرأ منه إلا موضع درهم له
والدة هو بها بر لو أقسم على الله لأبره فإن استطعت أن يستغفر لك
فافعل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاستغفر لي ‏.‏ فاستغفر له ‏.‏ فقال له عمر أين تريد
قال الكوفة ‏.‏ قال ألا أكتب لك إلى عاملها قال أكون في غبراء الناس
أحب إلى ‏.‏ قال فلما كان من العام المقبل حج رجل من أشرافهم فوافق
عمر فسأله عن أويس قال تركته رث البيت قليل المتاع ‏.‏ قال سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ يأتي عليكم أويس بن عامر مع أمداد
أهل اليمن من مراد ثم من قرن كان به برص فبرأ منه إلا موضع درهم له
والدة هو بها بر لو أقسم على الله لأبره فإن استطعت أن يستغفر لك
فافعل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتى أويسا فقال استغفر لي ‏.‏ قال أنت أحدث عهدا بسفر
صالح فاستغفر لي ‏.‏ قال استغفر لي ‏.‏ قال أنت أحدث عهدا بسفر صالح
فاستغفر لي ‏.‏ قال لقيت عمر قال نعم ‏.‏ فاستغفر له ‏.‏ ففطن له
الناس فانطلق على وجهه ‏.‏ قال أسير وكسوته بردة فكان كلما رآه إنسان
قال من أين لأويس هذه البردة</arabic-text>
<english-text>Usair b. Jabir reported that when people from Yemen
came to help (the Muslim army at the time of jihad) he asked them:
Is there amongst you Uwais b. 'Amir? (He continued finding him out)
until he met Uwais. He said: Are you Uwais b., Amir? He said: Yes.
He said: Are you from the tribe of Qaran? He said: Yes. He (Hadrat)
'Umar (again) said: Did you suffer from leprosy and then you were
cured from it but for the space of a dirham? He said: Yes. He
('Umar) said: Is your mother (living)? He said: Yes. He ('Umar)
said: I heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) say: There
would come to you Uwais b. Amir with the reinforcement from the
people of Yemen. (He would be) from Qaran, (the branch) of Murid.
He had been suffering from leprosy from which he was cured but for
a spot of a dirham. His treatment with his mother would have been
excellent. If he were to take an oath in the name of Allah, He
would honour that. And if it is possible for you, then do ask him
to beg forgiveness for you (from your Lord). So he (Uwais) begged
forgiveness for him. Umar said: Where do you intend to go? He said:
To Kufa. He ('Umar) said: Let me write a letter for you to its
governor, whereupon he (Uwais) said: I love to live amongst the
poor people. When it was the next year, a person from among the
elite (of Kufa) performed Hajj and he met Umar. He asked him about
Uwais. He said: I left him in a state with meagre means of
sustenance. (Thereupon) Umar said: I heard Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) as saying: There would come to you Uwais b.
'Amir, of Qaran, a branch (of the tribe) of Murid, along with the
reinforcement of the people of Yemen. He had been suffering from
leprosy which would have been cured but for the space of a dirham.
His treatment with his mother would have been very kind. If he
would take an oath in the name of Allah (for something) He would
honour it. Ask him to beg forgiveness for you (from Allah) in case
it is possible for you. So he came to Uwais and said.: Beg
forgiveness (from Allah) for me. He (Uwais) said: You have just
come from a sacred journey (Hajj) ; you, therefore, ask forgiveness
for me. He (the person who had performed Hajj) said: Ask
forgiveness for me (from Allah). He (Uwais again) said: You have
just come from the sacred journey, so you ask forgiveness for me.
(Uwais further) said: Did you meet Umar? He said: Yes. He (Uwais)
then begged forgiveness for him (from Allah). So the people came to
know about (the status of religious piety) of Uwais. He went away
(from that place). Usair said: His clothing consisted of a mantle,
and whosoever saw him said: From where did Uwais get this
mantle?</english-text>
</hadith>
