<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16621</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>46</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6721</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Virtue; Good Manners and Joining of the Ties
of Relationship - كتاب البر والصلة والآداب</chapter>
<chain-index>30514, 20214, 20021, 11269, 479, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن حاتم بن ميمون، حدثنا بهز، حدثنا حماد بن
سلمة، عن ثابت، عن أبي رافع، عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الله عز وجل يقول يوم القيامة يا ابن آدم مرضت
فلم تعدني ‏.‏ قال يا رب كيف أعودك وأنت رب العالمين ‏.‏ قال أما علمت
أن عبدي فلانا مرض فلم تعده أما علمت أنك لو عدته لوجدتني عنده يا ابن
آدم استطعمتك فلم تطعمني ‏.‏ قال يا رب وكيف أطعمك وأنت رب العالمين
‏.‏ قال أما علمت أنه استطعمك عبدي فلان فلم تطعمه أما علمت أنك لو
أطعمته لوجدت ذلك عندي يا ابن آدم استسقيتك فلم تسقني ‏.‏ قال يا رب
كيف أسقيك وأنت رب العالمين قال استسقاك عبدي فلان فلم تسقه أما إنك
لو سقيته وجدت ذلك عندي ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: Verily, Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, would
say on the Day of Resurrection: O son of Adam, I was sick but you
did not visit Me. He would say: O my Lord; how could I visit Thee
whereas Thou art the Lord of the worlds? Thereupon He would say:
Didn't you know that such and such servant of Mine was sick but you
did not visit him and were you not aware of this that if you had
visited him, you would have found Me by him? O son of Adam, I asked
food from you but you did not feed Me. He would say: My Lord, how
could I feed Thee whereas Thou art the Lord of the worlds? He said:
Didn't you know that such and such servant of Mine asked food from
you but you did not feed him, and were you not aware that if you
had fed him you would have found him by My side? (The Lord would
again say: ) O son of Adam, I asked drink from you but you did not
provide Me. He would say: My Lord, how could I provide Thee whereas
Thou art the Lord of the worlds? Thereupon He would say: Such and
such of servant of Mine asked you for a drink but you did not
provide him, and had you provided him drink you would have found
him near Me.</english-text>
</hadith>
