<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16791</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6893</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Destiny - كتاب القدر</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20354, 20032, 11060, 11341, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو معاوية، ووكيع، ح
وحدثنا محمد بن عبد، الله بن نمير الهمداني - واللفظ له - حدثنا أبي
وأبو معاوية ووكيع قالوا حدثنا الأعمش، عن زيد بن وهب، عن عبد الله،
قال حدثنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو الصادق المصدوق ‏"‏ إن
أحدكم يجمع خلقه في بطن أمه أربعين يوما ثم يكون في ذلك علقة مثل ذلك
ثم يكون في ذلك مضغة مثل ذلك ثم يرسل الملك فينفخ فيه الروح ويؤمر
بأربع كلمات بكتب رزقه وأجله وعمله وشقي أو سعيد فوالذي لا إله غيره
إن أحدكم ليعمل بعمل أهل الجنة حتى ما يكون بينه وبينها إلا ذراع
فيسبق عليه الكتاب فيعمل بعمل أهل النار فيدخلها وإن أحدكم ليعمل بعمل
أهل النار حتى ما يكون بينه وبينها إلا ذراع فيسبق عليه الكتاب فيعمل
بعمل أهل الجنة فيدخلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah (b. Mas'ud) reported that Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) who is the most truthful (of the human
beings) and his being truthful (is a fact) said: Verily your
creation is on this wise. The constituents of one of you are
collected for forty days in his mother's womb in the form of blood,
after which it becomes a clot of blood in another period of forty
days. Then it becomes a lump of flesh and forty days later Allah
sends His angel to it with instructions concerning four things, so
the angel writes down his livelihood, his death, his deeds, his
fortune and misfortune. By Him, besides Whom there is no god, that
one amongst you acts like the people deserving Paradise until
between him and Paradise there remains but the distance of a cubit,
when suddenly the writing of destiny overcomes him and he begins to
act like the denizens of Hell and thus enters Hell, and another one
acts in the way of the denizens of Hell, until there remains
between him and Hell a distance of a cubit that the writing of
destiny overcomes him and then he begins to act like the people of
Paradise and enters Paradise.</english-text>
</hadith>
