<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16799</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6901</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Destiny - كتاب القدر</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 30022, 30123, 30312, 4057, 11067, 11344, 11359,
5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، وزهير بن حرب، وإسحاق بن
إبراهيم، - واللفظ لزهير - قال إسحاق أخبرنا وقال الآخران، حدثنا
جرير، عن منصور، عن سعد بن عبيدة، عن أبي عبد الرحمن، عن علي، قال كنا
في جنازة في بقيع الغرقد فأتانا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقعد
وقعدنا حوله ومعه مخصرة فنكس فجعل ينكت بمخصرته ثم قال ‏"‏ ما منكم من
أحد ما من نفس منفوسة إلا وقد كتب الله مكانها من الجنة والنار وإلا
وقد كتبت شقية أو سعيدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال رجل يا رسول الله أفلا نمكث
على كتابنا وندع العمل فقال ‏"‏ من كان من أهل السعادة فسيصير إلى عمل
أهل السعادة ومن كان من أهل الشقاوة فسيصير إلى عمل أهل الشقاوة ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اعملوا فكل ميسر أما أهل السعادة فييسرون لعمل أهل
السعادة وأما أهل الشقاوة فييسرون لعمل أهل الشقاوة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قرأ
‏{‏ فأما من أعطى واتقى * وصدق بالحسنى * فسنيسره لليسرى * وأما من
بخل واستغنى * وكذب بالحسنى * فسنيسره للعسرى‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ali reported: We were in a funeral in the graveyard
of Gharqad that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) came to
us and we sat around him. He had a stick with him. He lowered his
head and began to scratch the earth with his stick, and then said:
There is not one amongst you whom a scat in Paradise or Hell has
not been allotted and about whom it has not been written down
whether he would be an evil person or a blessed person. A person
said: Allah's Messenger, should we not then depend upon our destiny
and abandon our deeds? Thereupon he said: Acts of everyone will be
facilitated in, that which has been created for him so that whoever
belongs to the company of the blessed will have good works made
easier for him and whoever belongs to the unfortunate ones will
have evil acts made easier for him. He then recited this verse
(from the Qur'an):" Then, who gives to the needy and guards against
evil and accepts the excellent (the truth of Islam and the path of
righteousness it prescribes), We shall make easy for him the easy
end and who is miserly and considers himself above need, We shall
make easy for him the dificult end". (XCii. 5-10).</english-text>
</hadith>
