<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16871</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6974</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 5355, 11114, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حرملة بن يحيى التجيبي، أخبرنا عبد الله بن وهب،
حدثني أبو شريح، أن أبا الأسود، حدثه عن عروة بن الزبير، قال قالت لي
عائشة يا ابن أختي بلغني أنحمل عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم علما
كثيرا - قال - فلقيته فساءلته عن أشياء يذكرها عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال عروة فكان فيما ذكر أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ إن الله لا ينتزع العلم من الناس انتزاعا ولكن يقبض العلماء
فيرفع العلم معهم ويبقي في الناس رءوسا جهالا يفتونهم بغير علم فيضلون
ويضلون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عروة فلما حدثت عائشة بذلك أعظمت ذلك وأنكرته قالت
أحدثك أنه سمع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول هذا قال عروة حتى إذا
كان قابل قالت له إن ابن عمرو قد قدم فالقه ثم فاتحه حتى تسأله عن
الحديث الذي ذكره لك في العلم - قال - فلقيته فساءلته فذكره لي نحو ما
حدثني به في مرته الأولى ‏.‏ قال عروة فلما أخبرتها بذلك قالت ما
أحسبه إلا قد صدق أراه لم يزد فيه شيئا ولم ينقص ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Urwa b. Zubair reported that 'A'isha said to him:
This news has reached me that 'Abdullah b. 'Amr al-'As would pass
by us during the Hajj season, so you meet him and ask him (about
religious matters) as he has acquired great knowledge from Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him). I thus met him and asked him
about things which he narrated from Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him). And amongst these the one he mentioned was that Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) said: Verily, Allah does not take
away knowledge from people directly but he takes away the scholars
and consequently takes away (knowledge) along with them and leaves
amongst persons the ignorant as their leaders who deliver religious
verdicts without (adequate) knowledge and themselves go astray and
lead others astray. 'Urwa said: When I narrated this to 'A'isha,
she deemed it too much (to believe) and thus showed reluctance to
accept that (as perfectly true) and said to, 'Urwa: Did he
('Abdullah b. 'Amr) say to you that he had heard Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him) as saying: ('Urwa had forgotten to ask this
from 'Abdullah b. 'Amr). So when it was the next year, she
('A'isha) said to him ('Urwa): Ibn Amr has come (for Hajj), so meet
him. talk to him and ask him about this hadith that he narrated to
You (last year on the occasion of the Hajj) pertaining to
knowledge. He ('Urwa), said: So I met him, and asked about it and
he narrated to me exactly like one that he had narrated (to me) for
the first time. So when I informed her ('A'isha) about that, she
said: I do not think but this that he has certainly told the truth
and I find that be has neither made any addition to it, nor missed
anything from it.</english-text>
</hadith>
