<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16899</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7002</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Remembrance of Allah;
Supplication; Repentance and Seeking Forgiveness - كتاب الذكر
والدعاء والتوبة والاستغفار</chapter>
<chain-index>30465, 11395, 11052, 10774, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن عمرو الأشعثي، أخبرنا عبثر، عن مطرف، عن
عامر، عن شريح، بن هانئ عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أحب لقاء الله أحب الله لقاءه ومن كره لقاء الله كره
الله لقاءه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأتيت عائشة فقلت يا أم المؤمنين سمعت أبا
هريرة يذكر عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حديثا إن كان كذلك فقد
هلكنا ‏.‏ فقالت إن الهالك من هلك بقول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وما ذاك قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أحب لقاء الله
أحب الله لقاءه ومن كره لقاء الله كره الله لقاءه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وليس منا
أحد إلا وهو يكره الموت ‏.‏ فقالت قد قاله رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وليس بالذي تذهب إليه ولكن إذا شخص البصر وحشرج الصدر واقشعر
الجلد وتشنجت الأصابع فعند ذلك من أحب لقاء الله أحب الله لقاءه ومن
كره لقاء الله كره الله لقاءه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: He who loves meeting Allah, Allah loves to
meet him, and he who dislikes to meet Allah, Allah abhors to meet
him. I (Shuraih b. Hani, one of the narrators) came to A'isha and
said to her: Mother of the faithful, I heard Abu Huraira narrate
from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) which, if it is
actually so, is a destruction to us. Thereupon she said: Those are
in fact ruined who are ruined at the words of Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him). What are (the words which in your opinion
would cause your destruction)? He said that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) had stated: He who loves to meet Allah, Allah
too loves to meet him, and he who dislikes to meet Allah, Allah too
abhors to meet him, and there is none amongst us who dons not hate
death. Thereupon she said: Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) has in fact stated this, but it does not mean what you
construe, but it implies (the time) when one loses the lustre of
the eye, and there is rattling in the throat, shudder in the body
and convulsion in fingers (at the time of death). (It is about this
time) that it has been said: He who loves to meet Allah, Allah
would love to meet him, and he who dislikes to meet Allah, Allah
would abhor to meet him</english-text>
</hadith>
