<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16912</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7015</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Remembrance of Allah;
Supplication; Repentance and Seeking Forgiveness - كتاب الذكر
والدعاء والتوبة والاستغفار</chapter>
<chain-index>30514, 20214, 20299, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن حاتم بن ميمون، حدثنا بهز، حدثنا وهيب،
حدثنا سهيل، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ إن لله تبارك وتعالى ملائكة سيارة فضلا يتبعون مجالس الذكر فإذا
وجدوا مجلسا فيه ذكر قعدوا معهم وحف بعضهم بعضا بأجنحتهم حتى يملئوا
ما بينهم وبين السماء الدنيا فإذا تفرقوا عرجوا وصعدوا إلى السماء -
قال - فيسألهم الله عز وجل وهو أعلم بهم من أين جئتم فيقولون جئنا من
عند عباد لك في الأرض يسبحونك ويكبرونك ويهللونك ويحمدونك ويسألونك
‏.‏ قال وماذا يسألوني قالوا يسألونك جنتك ‏.‏ قال وهل رأوا جنتي
قالوا لا أى رب ‏.‏ قال فكيف لو رأوا جنتي قالوا ويستجيرونك ‏.‏ قال
ومم يستجيرونني قالوا من نارك يا رب ‏.‏ قال وهل رأوا ناري قالوا لا
‏.‏ قال فكيف لو رأوا ناري قالوا ويستغفرونك - قال - فيقول قد غفرت
لهم فأعطيتهم ما سألوا وأجرتهم مما استجاروا - قال - فيقولون رب فيهم
فلان عبد خطاء إنما مر فجلس معهم قال فيقول وله غفرت هم القوم لا يشقى
بهم جليسهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Apostle (may peace be
upon him) as saying Allah has mobile (squads) of angels, who have
no other work (to attend to but) to follow the assemblies of Dhikr
and when they find such assemblies in which there is Dhikr (of
Allah) they sit in them and some of them surround the others with
their wings till the space between them and the sky of the world is
fully covered, and when they disperse (after the assembly of Dhikr
is adjourned) they go upward to the heaven and Allah, the Exalted
and Glorious, asks them although He is best informed about them:
Where have you come from? They say: We come from Thine servants
upon the earth who had been glorifying Thee (reciting Subhan
Allah), uttering Thine Greatness (saying Allah o-Akbar) and
uttering Thine Oneness (La ilaha ill Allah) and praising Thee
(uttering al-Hamdu Lillah) and begging of Thee. Be would say: What
do they beg of Me? They would say: They beg of Thee the Paradise of
Thine. He (God) would say: Have they seen My Paradise? They said:
No, our Lord. He would say: (What it would be then) if they were to
see Mine Paradise? They (the angels) said: They seek Thine
protection. He (the Lord) would say: Against what do they seek
protection of Mine? They (the angels) would say: Our Lord, from the
Hell-Fire. He (the Lord) would say: Have they seen My Fire? They
would say: No. He (the Lord) would say: What it would be if they
were to see My Fire? They would say: They beg of Thee forgiveness.
He would say: I grant pardon to them, and confer upon them what
they ask for and grant them protection against which they seek
protection. They (the angels) would again say: Our Lord, there is
one amongst them such and such simple servant who happened to pass
by (that assembly) and sat there along with them (who had been
participating in that assembly). He (the Lord) would say: I also
grant him pardon, for they are a people the seat-fellows of whom
are in no way unfortunate.</english-text>
</hadith>
