<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>16985</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7090</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Remembrance of Allah;
Supplication; Repentance and Seeking Forgiveness - كتاب الذكر
والدعاء والتوبة والاستغفار</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 30160, 20173, 20020, 11069, 11196,
5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، ومحمد بن بشار، - واللفظ لابن
المثنى - قالا حدثنا محمد بن جعفر، حدثنا شعبة، عن الحكم، قال سمعت
ابن أبي ليلى، حدثنا علي، أن فاطمة، اشتكت ما تلقى من الرحى في يدها
وأتى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم سبى فانطلقت فلم تجده ولقيت عائشة
فأخبرتها فلما جاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرته عائشة بمجيء فاطمة
إليها فجاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلينا وقد أخذنا مضاجعنا فذهبنا
نقوم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ على مكانكما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقعد
بيننا حتى وجدت برد قدمه على صدري ثم قال ‏"‏ ألا أعلمكما خيرا مما
سألتما إذا أخذتما مضاجعكما أن تكبرا الله أربعا وثلاثين وتسبحاه
ثلاثا وثلاثين وتحمداه ثلاثا وثلاثين فهو خير لكما من خادم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is reported on the authority of Ali that Fatima
had corns in her hand because of working at the hand-mill. There
had fallen to the lot of Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him)
some prisoners of war. She (Fatima) came to the Holy Prophet (may
peace be upon him) but she did not find him (in the house). She met
A'isha and informed her (about her hardship). When Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him) came, she ( A'isha) informed him about the
visit of Fatima. ABah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) came to
them (Fitima and her family). They had gone to their beds. 'Ali
further (reported): We tried to stand up (as a mark of respect) but
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Keep to your beds,
and he sat amongst us and I felt coldness of his feet upon my
chest. He then said: May I not direct you to something better than
what you have asked for? When you go to your bed, you should recite
Takbir (Allah-o-Akbar) thirty-four times and Tasbih (Subhdn Allah)
thirty-three times and Tahmid (al-Hamdu li-Allah) thirty-three
times, and that is better than the servant for you.</english-text>
</hadith>
