<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17048</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>51</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7157</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Repentance and Exhortation to
Repentance - كتاب التوبة</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 30553, 20121, 20115, 11013, 10561,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن رافع، وعبد بن حميد، قال عبد أخبرنا وقال
ابن رافع، - واللفظ له - حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، قال قال لي
الزهري ألا أحدثك بحديثين عجيبين قال الزهري أخبرني حميد بن عبد
الرحمن عن أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أسرف رجل
على نفسه فلما حضره الموت أوصى بنيه فقال إذا أنا مت فأحرقوني ثم
اسحقوني ثم اذروني في الريح في البحر فوالله لئن قدر على ربي ليعذبني
عذابا ما عذبه به أحدا ‏.‏ قال ففعلوا ذلك به فقال للأرض أدي ما أخذت
‏.‏ فإذا هو قائم فقال له ما حملك على ما صنعت فقال خشيتك يا رب - أو
قال - مخافتك ‏.‏ فغفر له بذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الزهري وحدثني حميد، عن
أبي هريرة، عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ دخلت امرأة النار
في هرة ربطتها فلا هي أطعمتها ولا هي أرسلتها تأكل من خشاش الأرض حتى
ماتت هزلا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الزهري ذلك لئلا يتكل رجل ولا ييأس رجل
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying that a person committed sin beyond measure and
when he was going to die, he left this will: (When I die), bum my
dead body and then cast them (the ashes) to the wind and in the
ocean. By Allah, if my Lord takes hold of me, He would torment me
as He has not tormented anyone else. They did as he had asked them
to do. He (the Lord) said to the earth: Return what you have taken.
And he was thus restored to his (original form). He (Allah) said to
him: What prompted you to do this? He said: My Lord, it was Thine
fear or Thine awe, and Allah pardoned him because of this. Abu
Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) as
saying that a woman was thrown into Hell-Fire because of a cat whom
she had tied and did not provide it with food. nor did she set it
free to cat insects of the euth until it died inch by inch. Zuhri
said: (These two ahidith) show that a person rhould neither feel
confident (of getting into Paradise) because of his deeds, nor
should he lose (all hopes) of getting into Paradise.</english-text>
</hadith>
