<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17072</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>51</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7183</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Repentance and Exhortation to
Repentance - كتاب التوبة</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 30022, 20450, 10704, 4048</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي الجهضمي، وزهير بن حرب، - واللفظ لزهير
- قالا حدثنا عمر بن يونس، حدثنا عكرمة بن عمار، حدثنا شداد، حدثنا
أبو أمامة، قال بينما رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في المسجد ونحن
قعود معه إذ جاء رجل فقال يا رسول الله إني أصبت حدا فأقمه على ‏.‏
فسكت عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم أعاد فقال يا رسول الله إني
أصبت حدا فأقمه على ‏.‏ فسكت عنه وأقيمت الصلاة فلما انصرف نبي الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال أبو أمامة فاتبع الرجل رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم حين انصرف واتبعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنظر ما يرد
على الرجل فلحق الرجل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله
إني أصبت حدا فأقمه على - قال أبو أمامة - فقال له رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرأيت حين خرجت من بيتك أليس قد توضأت فأحسنت الوضوء
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال بلى يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ثم شهدت الصلاة معنا ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقال نعم يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ فإن الله قد غفر لك حدك - أو قال - ذنبك ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Umama reported: We were sitting in the mosque in
the company of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). A person
came there and said: Allah's Messenger, I have committed an offence
which deserves the imposition of hadd upon me, so impose it upon
me. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) kept silent. He
repeated it and said: Allah's Messenger, I have committed an
offence which deserves the imposition of hadd upon me, so impose it
upon me. He (the Holy Prophet) kept silent, and it was at this time
that Iqama was pronounced for prayer (and the prayer was observed).
And when Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) had concluded the
payer that person followed Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him). Abu Umama said: I too followed Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) after he had concluded the prayer, so that I should
know what answer he would give to that person. That person remained
attached to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and said:
Allah's Messenger, I have committed an offence which deserves
imposition of hadd upon me, so impose it upon me. Abu Umama
reported that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said to
him: Didn't you see that as you got out of the house, you performed
ablution perfectly well. He said: Allah's Messenger, of course. I
did it. He again said to him: Then you observed prayer along with
us. He said: Allah's Messenger, yes, it is so. Thereupon Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said to him: Verily, Allah has
exempted you from the imposition of hadd, or he said. From your
sin.</english-text>
</hadith>
