<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17088</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>52</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7200</hadith-number>
<chapter>Pertaining To The Charateristics Of The Hypocrites And
Command Concerning Them - كتاب صفات المنافقين وأحكامهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20383, 20321, 11049, 384</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا الحسن بن موسى، حدثنا
زهير بن معاوية، حدثنا أبو إسحاق، أنه سمع زيد بن أرقم، يقول خرجنا مع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في سفر أصاب الناس فيه شدة فقال عبد
الله بن أبى لأصحابه لا تنفقوا على من عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حتى ينفضوا من حوله ‏.‏ قال زهير وهي قراءة من خفض حوله ‏.‏ وقال
لئن رجعنا إلى المدينة ليخرجن الأعز منها الأذل - قال - فأتيت النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته بذلك فأرسل إلى عبد الله بن أبى فسأله
فاجتهد يمينه ما فعل فقال كذب زيد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - قال
- فوقع في نفسي مما قالوه شدة حتى أنزل الله تصديقي ‏{‏ إذا جاءك
المنافقون‏}‏ قال ثم دعاهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ليستغفر لهم -
قال - فلووا رءوسهم ‏.‏ وقوله ‏{‏ كأنهم خشب مسندة‏}‏ وقال كانوا
رجالا أجمل شىء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Zaid b. Arqam reported: We set out on a journey along
with Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) in which we faced
many hardships. 'Abdullah b. Ubayy said to his friends: Do not give
what you have in your possession to those who are with Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) until they desert him. Zubair
said: That is the reciting of that person who recited as min
haulahu (from around him) and the other reciting is man haulahia
(who are around him). And in this case when we would return to
Medina the honourable would drive out the meaner therefrom (lxiv.
8). I came to Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) and informed
him about that and he sent someone to 'Abdullah b. Ubayy and he
asked him whether he had said that or not. He took an oath to the
fact that he had not done that and told that it was Zaid who had
stated a lie to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). Zaid
said: I was much perturbed because of this until this verse was
revealed attesting my truth:" When the hypocrites come" (lxiii. 1).
Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) then called them in order
to seek forgiveness for them, but they turned away their heads as
if they were hooks of wood fixed in the wall (lxiii. 4), and they
were in fact apparently good-looking persons.</english-text>
</hadith>
