<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17081</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>51</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7192</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Repentance and Exhortation to
Repentance - كتاب التوبة</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو الطاهر، أحمد بن عمرو بن عبد الله بن عمرو بن
سرح مولى بني أمية أخبرني ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، قال ثم
غزا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غزوة تبوك وهو يريد الروم ونصارى
العرب بالشام ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب فأخبرني عبد الرحمن بن عبد الله بن كعب
بن مالك أن عبد الله بن كعب كان قائد كعب من بنيه حين عمي قال سمعت
كعب بن مالك يحدث حديثه حين تخلف عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
غزوة تبوك قال كعب بن مالك لم أتخلف عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في غزوة غزاها قط إلا في غزوة تبوك غير أني قد تخلفت في غزوة بدر ولم
يعاتب أحدا تخلف عنه إنما خرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والمسلمون
يريدون عير قريش حتى جمع الله بينهم وبين عدوهم على غير ميعاد ولقد
شهدت مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليلة العقبة حين تواثقنا على
الإسلام وما أحب أن لي بها مشهد بدر وإن كانت بدر أذكر في الناس منها
وكان من خبري حين تخلفت عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في غزوة تبوك
أني لم أكن قط أقوى ولا أيسر مني حين تخلفت عنه في تلك الغزوة والله
ما جمعت قبلها راحلتين قط حتى جمعتهما في تلك الغزوة فغزاها رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في حر شديد واستقبل سفرا بعيدا ومفازا واستقبل
عدوا كثيرا فجلا للمسلمين أمرهم ليتأهبوا أهبة غزوهم فأخبرهم بوجههم
الذي يريد والمسلمون مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كثير ولا يجمعهم
كتاب حافظ - يريد بذلك الديوان - قال كعب فقل رجل يريد أن يتغيب يظن
أن ذلك سيخفى له ما لم ينزل فيه وحى من الله عز وجل وغزا رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم تلك الغزوة حين طابت الثمار والظلال فأنا إليها
أصعر فتجهز رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والمسلمون معه وطفقت أغدو
لكى أتجهز معهم فأرجع ولم أقض شيئا ‏.‏ وأقول في نفسي أنا قادر على
ذلك إذا أردت ‏.‏ فلم يزل ذلك يتمادى بي حتى استمر بالناس الجد فأصبح
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غاديا والمسلمون معه ولم أقض من جهازي
شيئا ثم غدوت فرجعت ولم أقض شيئا فلم يزل ذلك يتمادى بي حتى أسرعوا
وتفارط الغزو فهممت أن أرتحل فأدركهم فيا ليتني فعلت ثم لم يقدر ذلك
لي فطفقت إذا خرجت في الناس بعد خروج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يحزنني أني لا أرى لي أسوة إلا رجلا مغموصا عليه في النفاق أو رجلا
ممن عذر الله من الضعفاء ولم يذكرني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى
بلغ تبوكا فقال وهو جالس في القوم بتبوك ‏"‏ ما فعل كعب بن مالك ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال رجل من بني سلمة يا رسول الله حبسه برداه والنظر في عطفيه ‏.‏
فقال له معاذ بن جبل بئس ما قلت والله يا رسول الله ما علمنا عليه إلا
خيرا ‏.‏ فسكت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فبينما هو على ذلك رأى
رجلا مبيضا يزول به السراب فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كن
أبا خيثمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا هو أبو خيثمة الأنصاري وهو الذي تصدق بصاع
التمر حين لمزه المنافقون ‏.‏ فقال كعب بن مالك فلما بلغني أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد توجه قافلا من تبوك حضرني بثي فطفقت أتذكر
الكذب وأقول بم أخرج من سخطه غدا وأستعين على ذلك كل ذي رأى من أهلي
فلما قيل لي إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد أظل قادما زاح عني
الباطل حتى عرفت أني لن أنجو منه بشىء أبدا فأجمعت صدقه وصبح رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قادما وكان إذا قدم من سفر بدأ بالمسجد فركع
فيه ركعتين ثم جلس للناس فلما فعل ذلك جاءه المخلفون فطفقوا يعتذرون
إليه ويحلفون له وكانوا بضعة وثمانين رجلا فقبل منهم رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم علانيتهم وبايعهم واستغفر لهم ووكل سرائرهم إلى الله
حتى جئت فلما سلمت تبسم تبسم المغضب ثم قال ‏"‏ تعال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجئت
أمشي حتى جلست بين يديه فقال لي ‏"‏ ما خلفك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ألم تكن قد ابتعت
ظهرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله إني والله لو جلست عند غيرك من أهل
الدنيا لرأيت أني سأخرج من سخطه بعذر ولقد أعطيت جدلا ولكني والله لقد
علمت لئن حدثتك اليوم حديث كذب ترضى به عني ليوشكن الله أن يسخطك على
ولئن حدثتك حديث صدق تجد على فيه إني لأرجو فيه عقبى الله والله ما
كان لي عذر والله ما كنت قط أقوى ولا أيسر مني حين تخلفت عنك ‏.‏ قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما هذا فقد صدق فقم حتى يقضي الله
فيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقمت وثار رجال من بني سلمة فاتبعوني فقالوا لي والله ما
علمناك أذنبت ذنبا قبل هذا لقد عجزت في أن لا تكون اعتذرت إلى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بما اعتذر به إليه المخلفون فقد كان كافيك
ذنبك استغفار رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لك ‏.‏ قال فوالله ما
زالوا يؤنبونني حتى أردت أن أرجع إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فأكذب نفسي - قال - ثم قلت لهم هل لقي هذا معي من أحد قالوا نعم لقيه
معك رجلان قالا مثل ما قلت فقيل لهما مثل ما قيل لك - قال - قلت من
هما قالوا مرارة بن ربيعة العامري وهلال بن أمية الواقفي - قال -
فذكروا لي رجلين صالحين قد شهدا بدرا فيهما أسوة - قال - فمضيت حين
ذكروهما لي ‏.‏ قال ونهى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المسلمين عن
كلامنا أيها الثلاثة من بين من تخلف عنه - قال - فاجتنبنا الناس -
وقال - تغيروا لنا حتى تنكرت لي في نفسي الأرض فما هي بالأرض التي
أعرف فلبثنا على ذلك خمسين ليلة فأما صاحباى فاستكانا وقعدا في
بيوتهما يبكيان وأما أنا فكنت أشب القوم وأجلدهم فكنت أخرج فأشهد
الصلاة وأطوف في الأسواق ولا يكلمني أحد وآتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فأسلم عليه وهو في مجلسه بعد الصلاة فأقول في نفسي هل حرك شفتيه
برد السلام أم لا ثم أصلي قريبا منه وأسارقه النظر فإذا أقبلت على
صلاتي نظر إلى وإذا التفت نحوه أعرض عني حتى إذا طال ذلك على من جفوة
المسلمين مشيت حتى تسورت جدار حائط أبي قتادة وهو ابن عمي وأحب الناس
إلى فسلمت عليه فوالله ما رد على السلام فقلت له يا أبا قتادة أنشدك
بالله هل تعلمن أني أحب الله ورسوله قال فسكت فعدت فناشدته فسكت فعدت
فناشدته فقال الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ ففاضت عيناى وتوليت حتى تسورت
الجدار فبينا أنا أمشي في سوق المدينة إذا نبطي من نبط أهل الشام ممن
قدم بالطعام يبيعه بالمدينة يقول من يدل على كعب بن مالك - قال - فطفق
الناس يشيرون له إلى حتى جاءني فدفع إلى كتابا من ملك غسان وكنت كاتبا
فقرأته فإذا فيه أما بعد فإنه قد بلغنا أن صاحبك قد جفاك ولم يجعلك
الله بدار هوان ولا مضيعة فالحق بنا نواسك ‏.‏ قال فقلت حين قرأتها
وهذه أيضا من البلاء ‏.‏ فتياممت بها التنور فسجرتها بها حتى إذا مضت
أربعون من الخمسين واستلبث الوحى إذا رسول رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يأتيني فقال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يأمرك أن تعتزل
امرأتك ‏.‏ قال فقلت أطلقها أم ماذا أفعل قال لا بل اعتزلها فلا
تقربنها - قال - فأرسل إلى صاحبى بمثل ذلك - قال - فقلت لامرأتي الحقي
بأهلك فكوني عندهم حتى يقضي الله في هذا الأمر - قال - فجاءت امرأة
هلال بن أمية رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت له يا رسول الله إن
هلال بن أمية شيخ ضائع ليس له خادم فهل تكره أن أخدمه قال ‏"‏ لا ولكن
لا يقربنك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت إنه والله ما به حركة إلى شىء ووالله ما زال
يبكي منذ كان من أمره ما كان إلى يومه هذا ‏.‏ قال فقال لي بعض أهلي
لو استأذنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في امرأتك فقد أذن لامرأة
هلال بن أمية أن تخدمه - قال - فقلت لا أستأذن فيها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وما يدريني ماذا يقول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
إذا استأذنته فيها وأنا رجل شاب - قال - فلبثت بذلك عشر ليال فكمل لنا
خمسون ليلة من حين نهي عن كلامنا - قال - ثم صليت صلاة الفجر صباح
خمسين ليلة على ظهر بيت من بيوتنا فبينا أنا جالس على الحال التي ذكر
الله عز وجل منا قد ضاقت على نفسي وضاقت على الأرض بما رحبت سمعت صوت
صارخ أوفى على سلع يقول بأعلى صوته يا كعب بن مالك أبشر - قال - فخررت
ساجدا وعرفت أن قد جاء فرج ‏.‏ - قال - فآذن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم الناس بتوبة الله علينا حين صلى صلاة الفجر فذهب الناس يبشروننا
فذهب قبل صاحبى مبشرون وركض رجل إلى فرسا وسعى ساع من أسلم قبلي وأوفى
الجبل فكان الصوت أسرع من الفرس فلما جاءني الذي سمعت صوته يبشرني
فنزعت له ثوبى فكسوتهما إياه ببشارته والله ما أملك غيرهما يومئذ
واستعرت ثوبين ‏.‏ فلبستهما فانطلقت أتأمم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يتلقاني الناس فوجا فوجا يهنئوني بالتوبة ويقولون لتهنئك توبة
الله عليك ‏.‏ حتى دخلت المسجد فإذا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
جالس في المسجد وحوله الناس فقام طلحة بن عبيد الله يهرول حتى صافحني
وهنأني والله ما قام رجل من المهاجرين غيره ‏.‏ قال فكان كعب لا
ينساها لطلحة ‏.‏ قال كعب فلما سلمت على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال وهو يبرق وجهه من السرور ويقول ‏"‏ أبشر بخير يوم مر عليك منذ
ولدتك أمك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقلت أمن عندك يا رسول الله أم من عند الله
فقال ‏"‏ لا بل من عند الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إذا سر استنار وجهه كأن وجهه قطعة قمر - قال - وكنا نعرف ذلك -
قال - فلما جلست بين يديه قلت يا رسول الله إن من توبتي أن أنخلع من
مالي صدقة إلى الله وإلى رسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أمسك بعض مالك فهو خير لك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقلت
فإني أمسك سهمي الذي بخيبر - قال - وقلت يا رسول الله إن الله إنما
أنجاني بالصدق وإن من توبتي أن لا أحدث إلا صدقا ما بقيت - قال -
فوالله ما علمت أن أحدا من المسلمين أبلاه الله في صدق الحديث منذ
ذكرت ذلك لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى يومي هذا أحسن مما أبلاني
الله به والله ما تعمدت كذبة منذ قلت ذلك لرسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إلى يومي هذا وإني لأرجو أن يحفظني الله فيما بقي ‏.‏ قال فأنزل
الله عز وجل ‏{‏ لقد تاب الله على النبي والمهاجرين والأنصار الذين
اتبعوه في ساعة العسرة من بعد ما كاد يزيغ قلوب فريق منهم ثم تاب
عليهم إنه بهم رءوف رحيم * وعلى الثلاثة الذين خلفوا حتى إذا ضاقت
عليهم الأرض بما رحبت وضاقت عليهم أنفسهم‏}‏ حتى بلغ ‏{‏ يا أيها
الذين آمنوا اتقوا الله وكونوا مع الصادقين‏}‏ قال كعب والله ما أنعم
الله على من نعمة قط بعد إذ هداني الله للإسلام أعظم في نفسي من صدقي
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن لا أكون كذبته فأهلك كما هلك الذين
كذبوا إن الله قال للذين كذبوا حين أنزل الوحى شر ما قال لأحد وقال
الله ‏{‏ سيحلفون بالله لكم إذا انقلبتم إليهم لتعرضوا عنهم فأعرضوا
عنهم إنهم رجس ومأواهم جهنم جزاء بما كانوا يكسبون * يحلفون لكم
لترضوا عنهم فإن ترضوا عنهم فإن الله لا يرضى عن القوم الفاسقين‏}‏
قال كعب كنا خلفنا أيها الثلاثة عن أمر أولئك الذين قبل منهم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين حلفوا له فبايعهم واستغفر لهم وأرجأ رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أمرنا حتى قضى الله فيه فبذلك قال الله عز
وجل ‏{‏ وعلى الثلاثة الذين خلفوا‏}‏ وليس الذي ذكر الله مما خلفنا
تخلفنا عن الغزو وإنما هو تخليفه إيانا وإرجاؤه أمرنا عمن حلف له
واعتذر إليه فقبل منه ‏.‏ وحدثنيه محمد بن رافع، حدثنا حجين بن
المثنى، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب، بإسناد يونس عن الزهري،
سواء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Shihab reported that Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) made an expedition to Tabuk and he (the Holy Prophet)
had in his mind (the idea of threatening the) Christians of Arabia
in Syria and those of Rome. Ibn Shihab (further) reported that 'Abd
al-Rahman b. 'Abdullah b. Ka'b informed him that Abdullah b. Ka'b
who served as the guide of Ka'b b. 'Malik as he became blind that
he heard Ka'b b. Malik narrate the story of his remaining behind
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) from the Battle of Tabuk.
Ka'b b. Malik said: I never remained behind Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) from any expedition which he undertook except
the Battle of Tabuk and that of the Battle of Badr. So far as the
Battle of Badr is concerned, nobody was blamed for remaining behind
as Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and the Muslims (did
not set out for attack but for waylaying) the caravan of the
Quraish, but it was Allah Who made them confront their enemies
without their intention (to do so). I had the honour to be with
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) on the night of 'Aqaba
when we pledged our allegiance to Islam and it was more dear to me
than my participation in the Battle of Badr, although Badr was more
popular amongst people as compared with that (Tabuk). And this is
my story of remaining back from Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) on the occasion of the Battle of Tabuk. Never did I
possess means enough and (my circumstances) more favourable than at
the occasion of this expedition. And, by Allah, I had never before
this expedition simultaneously in my possession two rides. Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) set out for this expedition in
extremely hot season; the journey was long and the land (which he
and his army had to cover) was waterless and he had to confront a
large army, so he informed the Muslims about the actual situation
(they had to face), so that they should adequately equip themselves
for this expedition, and he also told them the destination where he
intended to go. And the Muslims who accompanied Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) at that time were large in numbers but
there was no proper record of them. Ka'b (further) said: Few were
the persons who wanted to absent themselves, and were under the
impression that they could easily conceal themselves (and thus
remain undetected) until revelations from Allah, the Exalted and
Glorious (descended in connection with them). And Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) set out on an expedition when the fruits
were ripe and their shadows had been lengthened. I had weakness for
them and it was during this season that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) made preparations and the Muslims too along with
them. I also set out in the morning so that I should make
preparations along with them but I came back and did nothing and
said to myself: I have means enough (to make preparations) as soon
as I like. And I went on doing this (postponing my preparations)
until people were about to depart and it was in the morning that
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) set out and the Muslims
too along with him, but I made no preparations. I went early in the
morning and came back, but I made no decision. I continued to do so
until they (the Muslims) hastened and covered a good deal of
distance. I also made up my mind to march on and to meet them.
Would that I had done that but perhaps it was not destined for me.
After the departure of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) as
I went out amongst people, I was shocked to find that I did not
find anyone like me but people who were labelled as hypocrites or
the people whom Allah granted exemption because of their incapacity
and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) took no notice of me
until he had reached Tabuk. (One day as he was sitting amongst the
people in Tabuk) he said: What has happened to Ka'b b. Malik? A
person from Banu' Salama said: Allah's Messenger, the (beauty) of
his cloak and his appreciation of his sides have allured him and he
was thus detained. Mua'dh b. Jabal said: Woe be upon that what you
contend. Allah's Messenger, by Allah, we know nothing about him but
good. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), however, kept
quiet. It was during that time that he (the Holy Prophet) saw a
person (dressed in all white (garment) shattering the illusion of
eye (mirage). Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said: May he be Abu Khaithama and, lo, it was Abu Khaithama
al-Ansari and he was that person who contributed a sa' of dates and
was scoffed at by the hypocrites. Ka'b b. Malik farther said: When
this news reached me that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
was on his way back from Tabuk I was greatly perturbed. I thought
of fabricating false stories and asked myself how I would save
myself from his anger on the following day. In this connection, I
sought the help of every prudent man from amongst the members of my
family and when it was said to me that Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) was about to arrive, all the false ideas banished
(from my mind) and I came to the conclusion that nothing could save
me but the telling of truth, so I decided to speak the truth and it
was in the morning that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
arrived (in Medina). And it was his habit that as he came back from
a journey he first went to the mosque and observed two Rak'ahs of
nafl prayer (as a mark of gratitude) and then sat amongst people.
And as he did that, those who had remained behind him began to put
forward their excuses and take an oath before him and they were
more than eighty persons. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
accepted their excuses on the very face of them and accepted their
allegiance and sought forgiveness for them and left their secret
(intentions) to Allah, until I presented myself to him. I greeted
him and he smiled and there was a tinge of anger in that. He (the
Holy Prophet) then said to me: Come forward. I went forward until I
sat in front of him. He said to me: What kept you back? Could you
not afford to go in for a ride? I said: Allah's Messenger, by
Allah, if I were to sit in the presence of anybody else from
amongst the worldly people I would have definitely saved myself
from his anger on one pretext (or the other) and I have also the
knack to fall into argumentation, but, by Allah, I am fully aware
of the fact that if I were to put forward before you a false excuse
to please you Allah would definitely provoke your wrath upon me,
and if I speak the truth you may be annoyed with me, but I hope
that Allah would make its end well and, by Allah, there is no valid
excuse for me. By Allah, I never possessed so good means, and I
never had such favourable conditions for me as I had when I stayed
behind you (failed to join the expedition). Thereupon, Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: This man told the truth, so
get up until Allah gives a decision in your case. I stood up and
some people of Banu' Salama followed me in hot haste, and they said
to me: By Allah, we do not know about you that you committed a sin
prior to this. You, however, showed inability to put forward an
excuse before Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) as those
who stayed behind him have put forward excuses. It would have been
enough for the forgiveness of your sin that Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) would have sought forgiveness for you. By Allah,
they continued to incite me until I thought of going back to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and contradict myself.
Then I said to them: Has anyone else also met the same fate? They
said: Yes, two persons have met the same fate as has fallen to you
and they have made the sane statement as you have made, and the
same verdict has been delivered in their case as it has been
delivered in your case. I said: Who are they? They said: Murara b.
ar-Rabi'a 'Amiri and Hilal b. Umayya al-Waqafi. They made a mention
of these two pious persons to me who had participated in the Battle
of Badr and there was an example for me in them. I went away when
they named these two persons. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) forbade the Nluslims to talk with three of us from amongst
those (persons) who had stayed behind him. The people began to
avoid us and their attitude towards us underwent a change and it
seemed as if the whole atmosphere had turned (hostile) against us
and it was in fact the same atmosphere ot which I was fully aware
and in which I had lived (for a fairly long time). We spent fifty
nights in this very state and my two friends confined themselves
withen their houses and spent (most of the) time in weeping, but as
I was young and strong amongst them I got (out of my house),
participated in congregational prayers, moved about in the bazar;
but none spoke to me. I came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as he sat amongst (people) after the prayer, greeted him
and asked myself whether his lips stirred in response to my
greetings (or not). Then I observed prayer beside him and looked at
him with stealing glances and when I attended to my prayer, he
looked at me and when I cast a glance at him he turned away his
eyes from me. And when the harsh treatment of the Muslims towards
me extended to a (considerable) length of time, I walked until I
climbed upon the wall of the garden of Abu Qatada, and he was my
cousin, and I had the greatest love for him. I greeted him but, by
Allah, he did not respond to my greetings. I said to him: Abu
Qatada, I adjure you by Allah, arn't you well aware of the fact
that I love Allah and His Messenger (may peace be upon him) the
most. He kept quiet. I again repeated saying: I adjure you by
Allah. arn't you well aware of the fact that I love Allah and His
Messenger (may peace be upon him) the most. He kept quiet. I again
adjured him, whereupon he said: Allah and the Messenger (may peace
be upon him) are best aware of it. My eyes began to shed tears and
I came back climbing down from the wall and as I was walking in the
bazar of Medina a Nabatean from amongst the Nabateans of Syria, who
had come to sell foodgrains in Medina, asked people to direct him
to Ka'b b. Malik. People gave him the indication by pointing
towards me. He came to me and delivered to me a letter of the King
of Ghassan and as I was a scribe I read that letter and it was
written like this:" Coming to my point, it has been conveyed to us
that your friend (the Holy Prophet) is subjecting you to cruelty
and Allah has not created you for a place where you are to be
degraded and where you cannot find your right place, so you come to
us that we should accord you honour. As I read that letter I said:
This is also a calamity, so I burnt it in the oven. When out of the
fifty days, forty days had passed and Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) received no revelation, there came the messenger of
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) to me and said: Verily,
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) has commanded you to
remain separate from your wife. I said: Should I divorce her or
what (else) should I do? He said: No, but only remain separate from
her and don't have sexual contact with her. The same message was
sent to my companions. So I said to my wife: You better go to your
parents and stay there with them until Allah gives the decision in
my case. The wife of Hilal b. Umayya came to Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) and said: Allah's Messenger, Hilal b. Umayya is
a senile person, he has no servant. Do you disapprove of my serving
him? He said: No, but don't go near him. She said: By Allah, he has
no such instinct in him. By Allah, he spends his time in weeping
from that day to this day. Some of the members of my family said to
me: Were you to seek permission from Allah's Messenger (may peace
be upon him) in regard to your wife as he has granted permission to
the wife of Hilal b. Umayya to serve him. I said: I would not seek
permission from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), for I
cannot say what Allah's Apostle may say in response to seeking my
permission. Moreover, I am a young man. It was in this state that I
spent ten more nights and thus fifty nights had passed that
(people) had observed boycott with us. It was on the morning of the
fiftieth night that I observed my dawn prayer and was sitting on
one of the roofs of our houses. And I was in fact sitting in that
very state which Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, has described
about us in these words:" Life had become hard for myself and the
earth had compressed despite its vastness," that I heard the noise
of an announcer from the peak of the hill of Sal' saying at the top
of his voice: Ka'b b. Malik, there is glad tidings for you. I fell
down in prostration and came to realise that there was (a message
of) relief for me. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had
informed the people of the acceptance of our repentance by Allah as
he offered the dawn prayer. So the people went on to give us glad
tidings and some of them went to my friends in order to give them
the glad tidings and a person galloped his horse and came from the
tribe of Aslam and his horse reached me more quickly than his
voice. And when he came to me whose sound I heard, he gave me the
glad tidings. I took off my clothes and clothed him with them
because of his bringing good news to me and, by Allah, I possessed
nothing else (in the form of clothes) than these two on that
occasion, and I asked one to lend me two clothes and dressed myself
in them. I came to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and on
my way I met groups of people who greeted me because of (the
acceptance of) repentance and they said: Here is a greeting for you
for your repentance being accepted by Allah. (I moved on) until I
came to the mosque and Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
had been sitting there amongst persons. So Talha b. 'Ubaidullah got
up and rushed towards me and he shook hands with me and greeted me
and, by Allah, no person stood up (to greet me) from amongst the
emigrants except he. Ka'b said that he never forgot (this good
gesture of) Talha. Ka'b further said: I greeted Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) with Assalam-o-'Alaikam and his face was
glistening because of delight, and he said: Let there be glad
tidings and blessings for you, the like of which (you have neither
found nor you will find, as you find today) since your mother gave
your birth. I said: Allah's Messenger. is this acceptance of
repentance from you or from Allah? He said: No, (it is not from
ma), it is from Allah, and it was common with Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) that as he was happy his face brightened up
and it looked like a part of the moon and it was from this that we
recognised it (his delight). As I sat before him, I said: Allah's
Messenger, am I allowed to give in charity my wealth for Allah's
sake and for the sake of His Messenger (may peace be upon him)?
Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: Keep some
property with you as it is better for you. I said: I shall keep
with me that part (of my property) which fell to my lot (on the
occasion of the expedition of) Khaibar. I said: Allah's Messenger,
verily, Allah has granted me salvation because of truth and,
therefore, (I think) that repentance implies that I should not
speak anything but truth as long as I live. He said: By Allah, I do
not know whether anyone amongst the Muslims was put to more severe
trial than I by Allah because of telling the truth. And since I
made a mention of this to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
up to this day I have not told any lie and, by Allah, I have
decided not to tell a lie and I hope that Allah would save me (from
trials) for the rest of my life and Allah, the Exalted and
Glorious, revealed these verses:" Certainly, Allah has turned in
Mercy to the Prophet and the emigrants and the helpers who followed
him in the hour of hardship after the hearts of a part of them were
about to deviate; then He turned to them in mercy. Surely, to them
He is Compassionate, Merciful and (He turned in Mercy) to the three
who were left behind until the earth despite its vastness became
strait for them and their souls were also straitened to them." And
this revelation reached up to the (words):" O you who believe,
develop God consciousness, and be with the truthful" (ix. 117-118).
Ka'b said: By Allah, since Allah directed me to Islam there has
been no blessing more significant for me than this truth of mine
which I spoke to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and if I
were to tell a lie I would have been ruined as were ruined those
who told lies, for in regard to those who told lies Allah used
harshest words used for anyone as He descended revelation (and the
words of Allah are):" They will swear by Allah to you when you
return to them so that you may leave them alone. So leave them
alone. Surely, they are unclean and their resort is Hell,
recompense for what they earned. They will swear to you that you
may be pleased with them but if you are pleased with them, yet
surely Allah is not pleased with the transgressing people" (ix.
95-96). K'ab said that the matter of us three persons was deferred
as compared with those who took an oath in the presence of Allahs
Messenger (may peace be upon him) and he accepted their allegiance
and sought forgiveness for them and Allah did not give any decision
in regard to us. It was Allah, the Exalted and Glorious, Who gave
decisions in our case, three who remained behind. (The words of the
Qur'an)" the three who were left behind" do not mean that we
remained back from Jihad but these imply that He kept our matter
behind them who took oath and presented excuse before Him. This
hadith has been narrated on the authority of Zuhri with the same
chain of transmitters.</english-text>
</hadith>
