<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17091</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>52</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7203</hadith-number>
<chapter>Pertaining To The Charateristics Of The Hypocrites And
Command Concerning Them - كتاب صفات المنافقين وأحكامهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20318, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا عبيد
الله بن عمر، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر، قال لما توفي عبد الله بن أبى ابن
سلول جاء ابنه عبد الله بن عبد الله إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فسأله أن يعطيه قميصه يكفن فيه أباه فأعطاه ثم سأله أن يصلي عليه فقام
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليصلي عليه فقام عمر فأخذ بثوب رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله أتصلي عليه وقد نهاك الله
أن تصلي عليه فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنما خيرني الله
فقال استغفر لهم أو لا تستغفر لهم إن تستغفر لهم سبعين مرة وسأزيده
على سبعين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال إنه منافق ‏.‏ فصلى عليه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ ولا تصل على أحد منهم مات أبدا ولا
تقم على قبره‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Umar reported that when 'Abdullah b. Ubayy b.
Salul died. His son 'Abdullah b. 'Abdullah (b. Ubayy) came to
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and begged him that he
should give him his shirt which he would use as a coffin for his
father, he gave him that. He then begged that he should conduct
funeral prayer for him. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
had hardly got up to observe the prayer for him that 'Umar stood up
and caught hold of the garment of Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) and said: Allah's Messenger, are you going to conduct
prayer for this man, whereas Allah has forbidden you to offer
prayer for him? Thereupon Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
said: Allah has given me an option as He has said:" You may beg
pardon for them or you may not beg pardon for them, and even if you
beg pardon for them, seventy times" (ix. 80), and I am going to
make an addition to the seventy. He was a hypocrite and Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) offered prayer for him and Allah,
the Exalted and Glorious, revealed this verse:" Do not offer prayer
for any one of them at all and do not stand upon their graves for
(offering prayer over them)" (ix. 84).</english-text>
</hadith>
