<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17099</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>52</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7211</hadith-number>
<chapter>Pertaining To The Charateristics Of The Hypocrites And
Command Concerning Them - كتاب صفات المنافقين وأحكامهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20381, 11070, 11090, 10561, 20201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زهير بن حرب، وهارون بن عبد الله، - واللفظ لزهير
- قالا حدثنا حجاج، بن محمد عن ابن جريج، أخبرني ابن أبي مليكة، أن
حميد بن عبد الرحمن بن عوف، أخبره أن مروان قال اذهب يا رافع - لبوابه
- إلى ابن عباس فقل لئن كان كل امرئ منا فرح بما أتى وأحب أن يحمد بما
لم يفعل معذبا لنعذبن أجمعون ‏.‏ فقال ابن عباس ما لكم ولهذه الآية
إنما أنزلت هذه الآية في أهل الكتاب ‏.‏ ثم تلا ابن عباس ‏{‏ وإذ أخذ
الله ميثاق الذين أوتوا الكتاب لتبيننه للناس ولا تكتمونه‏}‏ هذه
الآية وتلا ابن عباس ‏{‏ لا تحسبن الذين يفرحون بما أتوا ويحبون أن
يحمدوا بما لم يفعلوا‏}‏ وقال ابن عباس سألهم النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم عن شىء فكتموه إياه وأخبروه بغيره فخرجوا قد أروه أن قد أخبروه
بما سألهم عنه واستحمدوا بذلك إليه وفرحوا بما أتوا من كتمانهم إياه
ما سألهم عنه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Humaid b. 'Abd al-Rahman b. 'Auf reported that Marwan
said to Rafi', his chamberlain, that he should go to Ibn 'Abbas and
ask him: If every one of us be punished for his being happy upon
his deed and for his being praised for what he has not done, nobody
would be saved from the torment. Ibn 'Abbas said: What you have to
do with this verse? It has been in fact revealed in connection with
the people of the Book." Then Ibn Abbas recited this verse:" When
Allah took a covenant from those who had been given the Book: You
shall explain it to people and shall not conceal this" (iii. 186),
and then Ibn 'Abbas recited this verse:" Think not that those who
exult in what they have done and love to be praised for what they
have not done" (iii. 186). Ibn 'Abbas (further) said: Allah's
Apostle (may peace be upon him) asked them about something and then
they concealed that and they told him something else and they went
out and they thought that they had informed him as lie had asked
them and they felt happy of what they had concealed.</english-text>
</hadith>
