<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17123</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>53</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7235</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Giving Description of the Day of Judgement;
Paradise and Hell - كتاب صفة القيامة والجنة والنار</chapter>
<chain-index>30489, 36033, 11408, 11169, 11163, 11020,
38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الملك بن شعيب بن الليث، حدثني أبي، عن جدي،
حدثني خالد بن يزيد، عن سعيد بن أبي هلال، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن عطاء بن
يسار، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
تكون الأرض يوم القيامة خبزة واحدة يكفؤها الجبار بيده كما يكفأ أحدكم
خبزته في السفر نزلا لأهل الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأتى رجل من اليهود فقال
بارك الرحمن عليك أبا القاسم ألا أخبرك بنزل أهل الجنة يوم القيامة
قال ‏"‏ بلى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال تكون الأرض خبزة واحدة - كما قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم - قال فنظر إلينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم
ضحك حتى بدت نواجذه قال ألا أخبرك بإدامهم قال ‏"‏ بلى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
إدامهم بالام ونون ‏.‏ قالوا وما هذا قال ثور ونون يأكل من زائدة
كبدهما سبعون ألفا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu al-Sa'id Khudri reported Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) as saying that the earth would turn to be one
single bread on the Day of Resurrection and the Almighty would turn
it in His hand as one of you turns a loaf while on a journey. It
would be a feast arranged in the honour of the people of Paradise.
He (the narrator) further narrated that a person from among the
Jews came and he said: Abu al-Qasim, may the Compassionate Lord be
pleased with you! May I inform you about the feast arranged in
honour of the people of Paradise on the Day of Resurrection? He
said: Do it, of course. He said: The earth would become one single
bread. Then Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) looked
towards us and laughed until his molar teeth became visible. He
then again said: May I inform you about that with which they would
season it? He said: Do it, of course. He said: Their seasoning
would be balim and fish. The Companions of the Holy Prophet (may
peace be upon him) said: What is this balam? He said: Ox and fish
from whose excessive livers seventy thousand people would be able
to eat.</english-text>
</hadith>
