<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17237</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7354</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Paradise; Its Description; Its
Bounties and Its Intimates - كتاب الجنة وصفة نعيمها
وأهلها</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20121, 20115, 11447, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن رافع، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، حدثنا معمر، عن
همام بن منبه، قال هذا ما حدثنا أبو هريرة، عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فذكر أحاديث منها وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ تحاجت الجنة والنار فقالت النار أوثرت بالمتكبرين والمتجبرين ‏.‏
وقالت الجنة فما لي لا يدخلني إلا ضعفاء الناس وسقطهم وغرتهم قال الله
للجنة إنما أنت رحمتي أرحم بك من أشاء من عبادي ‏.‏ وقال للنار إنما
أنت عذابي أعذب بك من أشاء من عبادي ‏.‏ ولكل واحدة منكما ملؤها فأما
النار فلا تمتلئ حتى يضع الله تبارك وتعالى رجله تقول قط قط قط ‏.‏
فهنالك تمتلئ ويزوى بعضها إلى بعض ولا يظلم الله من خلقه أحدا وأما
الجنة فإن الله ينشئ لها خلقا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hammam b. Munabbih reported that Abu Huraira narrated
to them some ahadith of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
and one of them is this that Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him) said: The Paradise and the Hell fell into dispute and the Hell
said: 1 have been distinguished for accommodating (the haughty and
proud in me), and the Paradise said: What is the matter that the
meek and the humble and the downtrodden and simple would find an
abode in me? Thereupon Allah said to Paradise: You are a (means) of
My Mercy. 1 shall show mercy through you to one whom I will from
amongst My servants. And lie said to the Hell: You are a (sign) of
My chastisement and I shall chastise through you anyone whom I will
from amongst My servants and both of you, would be full. And as
regards the Hell it would not be full until Allah, the Exalted and
Glorious, places His foot therein, and it would say: Enough,
enough, enough, and it would be then full and the one part would
draw very close to the other one and Allah would not treat unjustly
anyone amongst His creation and He would create another creation
for the Paradise (to accommodate it).</english-text>
</hadith>
