<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17263</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7380</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Paradise; Its Description; Its
Bounties and Its Intimates - كتاب الجنة وصفة نعيمها
وأهلها</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20032, 30150, 20020, 30170, 30160, 20173,
20020, 11655, 11050, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا وكيع، ح وحدثنا عبيد
الله بن معاذ، حدثنا أبي كلاهما، عن شعبة، ح وحدثنا محمد بن المثنى،
ومحمد بن بشار، - واللفظ لابن المثنى - قالا حدثنا محمد بن جعفر،
حدثنا شعبة، عن المغيرة بن النعمان، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس،
قال قام فينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خطيبا بموعظة فقال ‏"‏ يا
أيها الناس إنكم تحشرون إلى الله حفاة عراة غرلا ‏{‏ كما بدأنا أول
خلق نعيده وعدا علينا إنا كنا فاعلين‏}‏ ألا وإن أول الخلائق يكسى يوم
القيامة إبراهيم عليه السلام ألا وإنه سيجاء برجال من أمتي فيؤخذ بهم
ذات الشمال فأقول يا رب أصحابي ‏.‏ فيقال إنك لا تدري ما أحدثوا بعدك
‏.‏ فأقول كما قال العبد الصالح ‏{‏ وكنت عليهم شهيدا ما دمت فيهم
فلما توفيتني كنت أنت الرقيب عليهم وأنت على كل شىء شهيد * إن تعذبهم
فإنهم عبادك وإن تغفر لهم فإنك أنت العزيز الحكيم‏}‏ قال فيقال لي
إنهم لم يزالوا مرتدين على أعقابهم منذ فارقتهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وفي حديث وكيع
ومعاذ ‏"‏ فيقال إنك لا تدري ما أحدثوا بعدك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>This hadith has been narrated through other chains of
transmitters on the authority of Ibn Abbas, (and) the words are:
While Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) stood up to deliver
a sermon, he said: 0 people, Allah would make you assemble
barefooted, naked and uncircumcised (and then recited the words of
the Qur'an):" As We created you for the first time, We shall repeat
it. (It is) a promise (binding) upon us. Lo! We are to perform it,
and the first person who would be clothed on the Day of
Resurrection would be (Hadrat) Ibrahim (peace be upon him)" and,
behold! some persons of my Ummah would be brought and taken to the
left and I would say: My Lord, they are my companions, and it would
be said: You do not know what they did after you, and I would say
just as the pious servant (Hadrat 'Isa) said:, I was a witness
regarding them as I remained among them and Thou art a witness over
everything, so if Thou chastisest them, they are Thy servants and
if Thou for- givest them, Thou art Mighty, Wise" (v. 117-118). And
it would be said to him: They constantly turned to their heels
since you left them. This hadith has been transmitted on the
authority of Waki' and Mu'adh (and the words are):" What new things
they fabricated."</english-text>
</hadith>
