<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17275</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7392</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Paradise; Its Description; Its
Bounties and Its Intimates - كتاب الجنة وصفة نعيمها
وأهلها</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 20208, 20208, 10721, 38, 49</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة جميعا عن ابن
علية، قال ابن أيوب حدثنا ابن علية، قال وأخبرنا سعيد الجريري، عن أبي
نضرة، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، عن زيد بن ثابت، قال أبو سعيد ولم أشهده من
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ولكن حدثنيه زيد بن ثابت قال بينما النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم في حائط لبني النجار على بغلة له ونحن معه إذ حادت
به فكادت تلقيه وإذا أقبر ستة أو خمسة أو أربعة - قال كذا كان يقول
الجريري - فقال ‏"‏ من يعرف أصحاب هذه الأقبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال رجل أنا
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فمتى مات هؤلاء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ماتوا في الإشراك ‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ إن هذه الأمة تبتلى في قبورها فلولا أن لا تدافنوا لدعوت الله أن
يسمعكم من عذاب القبر الذي أسمع منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم أقبل علينا بوجهه فقال
‏"‏ تعوذوا بالله من عذاب النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعوذ بالله من عذاب
النار فقال ‏"‏ تعوذوا بالله من عذاب القبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعوذ بالله
من عذاب القبر ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تعوذوا بالله من الفتن ما ظهر منها وما بطن
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعوذ بالله من الفتن ما ظهر منها وما بطن قال ‏"‏
تعوذوا بالله من فتنة الدجال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعوذ بالله من فتنة الدجال
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Sa'id al-Khudri reported: I did not hear this
hadith from Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) directly but it
was Zaid b. Thabit who narrated it from him. As Allah's Apostle
(may peace be upon him) was going along with us towards the
dwellings of Bani an-Najjar, riding upon his pony, it shied and he
was about to fall. He found four, five or six graves there. He
said: Who amongst you knows about those lying in the graves? A
person said: It is I. Thereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said: In what
state did they die? He said: They died as polytheists. He said:
These people are passing through the ordeal in the graves. If it
were not the reason that you would stop burying (your dead) in the
graves on listening to the torment in the grave which I am
listening to, I would have certainly made you hear that. Then
turning his face towards us, he said: Seek refuge with Allah from
the torment of Hell. They said: We seek refuge with Allah from the
torment of Hell. He said: Seek refuge with Allah from the torment
of the grave. They said: We seek refuge with Allah from the torment
of the grave. He said: Seek refuge with Allah from turmoil, its
visible and invisible (aspects), and they said: We seek refuge with
Allah from turmoil and its visible and invisible aspects and he
said: Seek refuge with Allah from the turmoil of the Dajjal, and
they said We seek refuge with Allah from the turmoil of the
Dajjal.</english-text>
</hadith>
