<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17285</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7402</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Paradise; Its Description; Its
Bounties and Its Intimates - كتاب الجنة وصفة نعيمها
وأهلها</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 20236, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا شيبان بن فروخ، - واللفظ له - حدثنا سليمان بن
المغيرة، عن ثابت، عن أنس بن مالك، قال كنا مع عمر بين مكة والمدينة
فتراءينا الهلال وكنت رجلا حديد البصر فرأيته وليس أحد يزعم أنه رآه
غيري - قال - فجعلت أقول لعمر أما تراه فجعل لا يراه - قال - يقول عمر
سأراه وأنا مستلق على فراشي ‏.‏ ثم أنشأ يحدثنا عن أهل بدر فقال إن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يرينا مصارع أهل بدر بالأمس يقول
‏"‏ هذا مصرع فلان غدا إن شاء الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال عمر فوالذي بعثه
بالحق ما أخطئوا الحدود التي حد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - قال -
فجعلوا في بئر بعضهم على بعض فانطلق رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى
انتهى إليهم فقال ‏"‏ يا فلان بن فلان ويا فلان بن فلان هل وجدتم ما
وعدكم الله ورسوله حقا فإني قد وجدت ما وعدني الله حقا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
عمر يا رسول الله كيف تكلم أجسادا لا أرواح فيها قال ‏"‏ ما أنتم
بأسمع لما أقول منهم غير أنهم لا يستطيعون أن يردوا على شيئا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported: We were along with Umar
between Mecca and Medina that we began to look for the new moon.
And I was a man with sharp eye- sight, so I could see it, but none
except me saw it. I began to say to 'Umar: Don't you see it? But he
would not see it. Thereupon Umar said: I would soon be able to see
it (when it will shine more brightly). I lay upon bed. He then made
a mention of the people of Badr to us and said: Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) showed us one day before (the actual
battle) the place of death of the people (participating) in (the
Battle) of Badr and he was saying: This would be the place of death
of so and so tomorrow, if Allah wills. Umar said: By Him Who sent
him with truth, they did not miss the places (of their death) which
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) had pointed for them.
Then they were all thrown in a well one after another. Allah's
Messenger (may peace be upon him) then went to them and said: O, so
and so, the son of so and so; O so and so, the son of so and so,
have you found correct what Allah and His Messenger had promised
you? I have, however, found absolutely true what Allah had promised
with me. Umar said: Allah's Messenger, how are you talking with the
bodies without soul in them. Thereupon he said: You cannot hear
more distinctly than (their hearing) of what I say, but with this
exception that they have not power to make any
reply.</english-text>
</hadith>
