<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17314</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7432</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30559, 20022, 10703, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو كامل الجحدري، فضيل بن حسين حدثنا حماد بن
زيد، حدثنا عثمان، الشحام قال انطلقت أنا وفرقد السبخي، إلى مسلم بن
أبي بكرة وهو في أرضه فدخلنا عليه فقلنا هل سمعت أباك يحدث في الفتن
حديثا قال نعم سمعت أبا بكرة يحدث قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إنها ستكون فتن ألا ثم تكون فتنة القاعد فيها خير من الماشي
فيها والماشي فيها خير من الساعي إليها ألا فإذا نزلت أو وقعت فمن كان
له إبل فليلحق بإبله ومن كانت له غنم فليلحق بغنمه ومن كانت له أرض
فليلحق بأرضه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال رجل يا رسول الله أرأيت من لم يكن له
إبل ولا غنم ولا أرض قال ‏"‏ يعمد إلى سيفه فيدق على حده بحجر ثم لينج
إن استطاع النجاء اللهم هل بلغت اللهم هل بلغت اللهم هل بلغت ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال فقال رجل يا رسول الله أرأيت إن أكرهت حتى ينطلق بي إلى أحد
الصفين أو إحدى الفئتين فضربني رجل بسيفه أو يجيء سهم فيقتلني قال ‏"‏
يبوء بإثمه وإثمك ويكون من أصحاب النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Bakra reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: There would soon be turmoil. Behold! there
would be turmoil in which the one who would be seated would be
better than one who would stand and the one who would stand would
be better than one who would run. Behold! when the turmoil comes or
it appears, the one who has camel should stick to his camel and he
who has sheep or goat should stick to his sheep and goat and he who
has land should stick to the land. A person said: 'Allah's
Messenger, what is your opinion about one who has neither camel nor
sheep nor land? Thereupon, he said: He should take hold of his
sword and beat its edge with the help of stone and then try to find
a way of escape. O Allah, I have conveyed (Thy Message) ; O Allah,
I have conveyed (Thy Message) ; O Allah, I have conveyed (Thy
Message). A person said: Allah's Messenger, what is your opinion it
I am drawn to a rank in spite of myself, or in one of the groups
and made to march and a man strikes with his sword or there comes
an arrow and kills me? Thereupon he said: He will bear the
punishment of his sin and that of yours and he would be one amongst
the denizens of Hell.</english-text>
</hadith>
