<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17322</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7440</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20022, 20022, 11015, 11047, 130</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو الربيع العتكي، وقتيبة بن سعيد، كلاهما عن
حماد بن زيد، - واللفظ لقتيبة - حدثنا حماد، عن أيوب، عن أبي قلابة،
عن أبي أسماء، عن ثوبان، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن
الله زوى لي الأرض فرأيت مشارقها ومغاربها وإن أمتي سيبلغ ملكها ما
زوي لي منها وأعطيت الكنزين الأحمر والأبيض وإني سألت ربي لأمتي أن لا
يهلكها بسنة بعامة وأن لا يسلط عليهم عدوا من سوى أنفسهم فيستبيح
بيضتهم وإن ربي قال يا محمد إني إذا قضيت قضاء فإنه لا يرد وإني
أعطيتك لأمتك أن لا أهلكهم بسنة بعامة وأن لا أسلط عليهم عدوا من سوى
أنفسهم يستبيح بيضتهم ولو اجتمع عليهم من بأقطارها - أو قال من بين
أقطارها - حتى يكون بعضهم يهلك بعضا ويسبي بعضهم بعضا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Thauban reported that Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) said: Allah drew the ends of the world near one another
for my sake. And I have seen its eastern and western ends. And the
dominion of my Unimah would reach those ends which have been drawn
near me and I have been granted the red and the white trea- sure
and I begged my Lord for my Ummah that it should not be destroyed
because of famine, nor be dominated by an enemy who is not amongst
them to take their lives and destroy them root and branch, and my
Lord said: Muhammad, whenever I make a decision, there is none to
change it. Well, I grant you for your Ummah that it would not be
destroyed by famine and it would not be dominated by an enemy who
would not be amongst it and would take their lives and destroy them
root and branch even if all the people from the different parts of
the world join hands together (for this purpose), but it would be
from amongst them, viz. your Ummah, that some people would kill the
others or imprison the others.</english-text>
</hadith>
