<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17332</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7450</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 30216, 20354, 20354, 11060, 11353,
145</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، ومحمد بن العلاء أبو
كريب، جميعا عن أبي، معاوية قال ابن العلاء حدثنا أبو معاوية، حدثنا
الأعمش، عن شقيق، عن حذيفة، قال كنا عند عمر فقال أيكم يحفظ حديث رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في الفتنة كما قال قال فقلت أنا ‏.‏ قال إنك
لجريء وكيف قال قال قلت سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏
فتنة الرجل في أهله وماله ونفسه وولده وجاره يكفرها الصيام والصلاة
والصدقة والأمر بالمعروف والنهى عن المنكر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال عمر ليس هذا
أريد إنما أريد التي تموج كموج البحر - قال - فقلت ما لك ولها يا أمير
المؤمنين إن بينك وبينها بابا مغلقا قال أفيكسر الباب أم يفتح قال قلت
لا بل يكسر ‏.‏ قال ذلك أحرى أن لا يغلق أبدا ‏.‏ قال فقلنا لحذيفة هل
كان عمر يعلم من الباب قال نعم كما يعلم أن دون غد الليلة إني حدثته
حديثا ليس بالأغاليط ‏.‏ قال فهبنا أن نسأل حذيفة من الباب فقلنا
لمسروق سله فسأله فقال عمر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hudhaifa repotted: We were one day in the company of
'Umar that he said: Who amongst you has preserved in his mind most
perfectly the hadith of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
in regard to the turmoil as he told about it? I said: It is I.
Thereupon he said: You are bold (enough to make this claim). And he
further said: How? I said: I heard Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: There would (first) be turmoil for a person in
regard to his family, his property, his own self, his children, his
neighbours (and the sins comnaitted in their connection) would be
expiated by fasting, prayer, charity, enjoining good and
prohibiting evil. Thereupon 'Umar said: I do not mean (that turmoil
on a small scale) but that one which would eme-ge like the mounting
waves of the ocean. I said: Commander of the Faithful, you have
nothing to do with it, for the door is closed between you and that.
He said: Would that door be broken or opened? I said: No, it would
be broken. Thereupon he said: Then it would not be closed despite
best efforts. We said to Hudhaifa: Did Umar know the door?
Thereupon he said: Yes, he knew it (for certain) just as one knows
that night precede the next day. And I narrated to him something in
which there was nothing fabricated. Shaqiq (one of the narrators)
said: We dared not ask Hudhaifa about that door. So we requested
Masrdq to ask him. So he asked him and he said: (By that door, he
meant) 'Umar.</english-text>
</hadith>
