<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17345</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7463</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20387, 20208, 11015, 11281</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وعلي بن حجر، كلاهما عن ابن
علية، - واللفظ لابن حجر - حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، عن أيوب، عن
حميد بن هلال، عن أبي قتادة، العدوي عن يسير بن جابر، قال هاجت ريح
حمراء بالكوفة فجاء رجل ليس له هجيرى إلا يا عبد الله بن مسعود جاءت
الساعة ‏.‏ قال فقعد وكان متكئا فقال إن الساعة لا تقوم حتى لا يقسم
ميراث ولا يفرح بغنيمة ‏.‏ ثم قال بيده هكذا - ونحاها نحو الشأم -
فقال عدو يجمعون لأهل الإسلام ويجمع لهم أهل الإسلام ‏.‏ قلت الروم
تعني قال نعم وتكون عند ذاكم القتال ردة شديدة فيشترط المسلمون شرطة
للموت لا ترجع إلا غالبة فيقتتلون حتى يحجز بينهم الليل فيفيء هؤلاء
وهؤلاء كل غير غالب وتفنى الشرطة ثم يشترط المسلمون شرطة للموت لا
ترجع إلا غالبة فيقتتلون حتى يحجز بينهم الليل فيفيء هؤلاء وهؤلاء كل
غير غالب وتفنى الشرطة ثم يشترط المسلمون شرطة للموت لا ترجع إلا
غالبة فيقتتلون حتى يمسوا فيفيء هؤلاء وهؤلاء كل غير غالب وتفنى
الشرطة فإذا كان يوم الرابع نهد إليهم بقية أهل الإسلام فيجعل الله
الدبرة عليهم فيقتلون مقتلة - إما قال لا يرى مثلها وإما قال لم ير
مثلها - حتى إن الطائر ليمر بجنباتهم فما يخلفهم حتى يخر ميتا فيتعاد
بنو الأب كانوا مائة فلا يجدونه بقي منهم إلا الرجل الواحد فبأى غنيمة
يفرح أو أى ميراث يقاسم فبينما هم كذلك إذ سمعوا ببأس هو أكبر من ذلك
فجاءهم الصريخ إن الدجال قد خلفهم في ذراريهم فيرفضون ما في أيديهم
ويقبلون فيبعثون عشرة فوارس طليعة ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إني لأعرف أسماءهم وأسماء آبائهم وألوان خيولهم هم خير فوارس
على ظهر الأرض يومئذ أو من خير فوارس على ظهر الأرض يومئذ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
ابن أبي شيبة في روايته عن أسير بن جابر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Yusair b. Jabir reported: Once there blew a red storm
in Kufah that there came a person who had nothing to say but (these
words): Abdullah b. Mas'ud, the Last Hour has come. He ('Abdullah
b. Mas'ud) was sitting reclining against something, and he said:
The Last Hour would not come until the people divide in- heritance
and rejoice over booty, and then said pointing towards Syria, with
the gesture of his hand like this: The enemy shall muster strength
against Muslims and the Muslims will muster strength against them
(Syrians). I said: You mean Rome? And he said: Yes, and there would
be a terrible fight and the Muslims would prepare a detachment (for
fighting unto death) which would not return but victorious. They
will fight until night will intervene them; both the sides will
return without being victorious and both will be wiped out. The
Muslims will again prepare a detachment for fighting unto death so
that they may not return but victorious. When it would be the
fourth day, a new detachment out of the remnant of the Muslims
would be prepared and Allah will decree that the enemy should be
routed. And they would fight such a fight the like of which would
not be seen, so much so that even if a bird were to pass their
flanks, it would fall down dead before reaching the end of them.
(There would be such a largescale massacre) that when counting
would be done, (only) one out of a hundred men related to one
another would be found alive. So what can be the joy at the spoils
of such war and what inheritance would be divided! They would be in
this very state that they would hear of a calamity more horrible
than this. And a cry would reach them: The Dajjil has taken your
place among your off- spring. They will, therefore, throw away what
would be in their hands and go forward sending ten horsemen, as a
scouting party. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) said: I
know their names and the names of their forefathers and the colour
of their horses. They will be best horsemen on the surface of the
earth on that day or amongst the best horsemen on the surface of
the earth on that day.</english-text>
</hadith>
