<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17350</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7468</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 20286, 20020, 11384, 3660</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ العنبري، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
شعبة، عن فرات القزاز، عن أبي الطفيل، عن أبي سريحة، حذيفة بن أسيد
قال كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في غرفة ونحن أسفل منه فاطلع إلينا
فقال ‏"‏ ما تذكرون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا الساعة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إن الساعة لا
تكون حتى تكون عشر آيات خسف بالمشرق وخسف بالمغرب وخسف في جزيرة العرب
والدخان والدجال ودابة الأرض ويأجوج ومأجوج وطلوع الشمس من مغربها
ونار تخرج من قعرة عدن ترحل الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال شعبة وحدثني عبد العزيز
بن رفيع عن أبي الطفيل عن أبي سريحة ‏.‏ مثل ذلك لا يذكر النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم وقال أحدهما في العاشرة نزول عيسى ابن مريم صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وقال الآخر وريح تلقي الناس في البحر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hudhaifa b. Usaid reported: Allah's Apostle (may
peace be upon him) was in an apartment and we were beneath that
that he peeped in and said to us: What are you discussing about? We
said: (We are discussing about the Last) Hour. Thereupon he said:
The Last Hour would not come until the ten signs dppear:
land-sliding in the east, and land-sliding in the west, and
land-sliding in the peninsula of Arabia, the smoke, the Dajjal, the
beast of the earth, Gog and Magog, the rising of the sun from the
west and the fire which would emit from the lower part of 'Adan.
Shu'ba said that 'Abd al-'Aziz b. Rufai' reported on the authority
of Abu Tufail who reported on the authority of Abu Sariha a hadith
like this that Allah's Apostle (may peace be upon him) did not make
a mention of (the tenth sign) but he said that out of the ten one
was the descent of Jesus Christ, son of Mary (peace be upon him),
and in another version it is theb lowing of the violent gale which
would drive the people to the ocean.</english-text>
</hadith>
