<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17398</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7517</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20167, 11155, 11165, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا عبد العزيز، - يعني ابن محمد
- عن ثور، - وهو ابن زيد الديلي - عن أبي الغيث، عن أبي هريرة، أن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ سمعتم بمدينة جانب منها في البر
وجانب منها في البحر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لا
تقوم الساعة حتى يغزوها سبعون ألفا من بني إسحاق فإذا جاءوها نزلوا
فلم يقاتلوا بسلاح ولم يرموا بسهم قالوا لا إله إلا الله والله أكبر
‏.‏ فيسقط أحد جانبيها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثور لا أعلمه إلا قال ‏"‏ الذي في
البحر ثم يقولوا الثانية لا إله إلا الله والله أكبر ‏.‏ فيسقط جانبها
الآخر ثم يقولوا الثالثة لا إله إلا الله والله أكبر ‏.‏ فيفرج لهم
فيدخلوها فيغنموا فبينما هم يقتسمون المغانم إذ جاءهم الصريخ فقال إن
الدجال قد خرج ‏.‏ فيتركون كل شىء ويرجعون ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Apostle (may peace he
upon him) saying: You have heard about a city the one side of which
is in the land and the other is in the sea (Constantinople). They
said: Allall's Messenger, yes. Thererupon he said: The Last Hour
would not cmoe unlesss seventy thousand persons from Bani lsra'il
would attack it. When they would land there, they will neither
fight with weapons nor would shower arrows but would only say:"
There is no god but Allah and Allah is the Greatest," that one side
of it would fall. Thaur (one of the narrators) said: I think that
he said: The part by the side of the ocean. Then they would say for
the second time:" There is no god but Allah and Allah is the
Greatest" that the second side would also fall, and they would
say:" There is no god but Allah and Allah is the Greatest," that
the gates would be opened for them and they would enter therein
and, they would be collecting spoils of war and distributing them
amongst themselves that a noise would be heard and It would be
said: Verily, Dajjal has come. And thus they would leave everything
there and would turn to him.</english-text>
</hadith>
