<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17448</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7573</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to the Turmoil and Portents of the
Last Hour - كتاب الفتن وأشراط الساعة</chapter>
<chain-index>38834, 11432</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الوارث بن عبد الصمد بن عبد الوارث، وحجاج بن
الشاعر، كلاهما عن عبد الصمد، - واللفظ لعبد الوارث بن عبد الصمد -
حدثنا أبي، عن جدي، عن الحسين، بن ذكوان حدثنا ابن بريدة، حدثني عامر
بن شراحيل الشعبي، شعب همدان أنه سأل فاطمة بنت قيس أخت الضحاك بن قيس
وكانت من المهاجرات الأول فقال حدثيني حديثا سمعتيه من رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم لا تسنديه إلى أحد غيره فقالت لئن شئت لأفعلن فقال لها
أجل حدثيني ‏.‏ فقالت نكحت ابن المغيرة وهو من خيار شباب قريش يومئذ
فأصيب في أول الجهاد مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما تأيمت
خطبني عبد الرحمن بن عوف في نفر من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وخطبني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على مولاه أسامة بن زيد
وكنت قد حدثت أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من أحبني فليحب
أسامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما كلمني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قلت أمري بيدك
فأنكحني من شئت فقال ‏"‏ انتقلي إلى أم شريك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأم شريك امرأة
غنية من الأنصار عظيمة النفقة في سبيل الله ينزل عليها الضيفان فقلت
سأفعل فقال ‏"‏ لا تفعلي إن أم شريك امرأة كثيرة الضيفان فإني أكره أن
يسقط عنك خمارك أو ينكشف الثوب عن ساقيك فيرى القوم منك بعض ما تكرهين
ولكن انتقلي إلى ابن عمك عبد الله بن عمرو ابن أم مكتوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ - وهو
رجل من بني فهر فهر قريش وهو من البطن الذي هي منه - فانتقلت إليه
فلما انقضت عدتي سمعت نداء المنادي منادي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ينادي الصلاة جامعة ‏.‏ فخرجت إلى المسجد فصليت مع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فكنت في صف النساء التي تلي ظهور القوم فلما قضى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاته جلس على المنبر وهو يضحك فقال ‏"‏
ليلزم كل إنسان مصلاه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ أتدرون لم جمعتكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالوا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إني والله ما جمعتكم لرغبة ولا
لرهبة ولكن جمعتكم لأن تميما الداري كان رجلا نصرانيا فجاء فبايع
وأسلم وحدثني حديثا وافق الذي كنت أحدثكم عن مسيح الدجال حدثني أنه
ركب في سفينة بحرية مع ثلاثين رجلا من لخم وجذام فلعب بهم الموج شهرا
في البحر ثم أرفئوا إلى جزيرة في البحر حتى مغرب الشمس فجلسوا في أقرب
السفينة فدخلوا الجزيرة فلقيتهم دابة أهلب كثير الشعر لا يدرون ما
قبله من دبره من كثرة الشعر فقالوا ويلك ما أنت فقالت أنا الجساسة ‏.‏
قالوا وما الجساسة قالت أيها القوم انطلقوا إلى هذا الرجل في الدير
فإنه إلى خبركم بالأشواق ‏.‏ قال لما سمت لنا رجلا فرقنا منها أن تكون
شيطانة - قال - فانطلقنا سراعا حتى دخلنا الدير فإذا فيه أعظم إنسان
رأيناه قط خلقا وأشده وثاقا مجموعة يداه إلى عنقه ما بين ركبتيه إلى
كعبيه بالحديد قلنا ويلك ما أنت قال قد قدرتم على خبري فأخبروني ما
أنتم قالوا نحن أناس من العرب ركبنا في سفينة بحرية فصادفنا البحر حين
اغتلم فلعب بنا الموج شهرا ثم أرفأنا إلى جزيرتك هذه فجلسنا في أقربها
فدخلنا الجزيرة فلقيتنا دابة أهلب كثير الشعر لا يدرى ما قبله من دبره
من كثرة الشعر فقلنا ويلك ما أنت فقالت أنا الجساسة ‏.‏ قلنا وما
الجساسة قالت اعمدوا إلى هذا الرجل في الدير فإنه إلى خبركم بالأشواق
فأقبلنا إليك سراعا وفزعنا منها ولم نأمن أن تكون شيطانة فقال أخبروني
عن نخل بيسان قلنا عن أى شأنها تستخبر قال أسألكم عن نخلها هل يثمر
قلنا له نعم ‏.‏ قال أما إنه يوشك أن لا تثمر قال أخبروني عن بحيرة
الطبرية ‏.‏ قلنا عن أى شأنها تستخبر قال هل فيها ماء قالوا هي كثيرة
الماء ‏.‏ قال أما إن ماءها يوشك أن يذهب ‏.‏ قال أخبروني عن عين زغر
‏.‏ قالوا عن أى شأنها تستخبر قال هل في العين ماء وهل يزرع أهلها
بماء العين قلنا له نعم هي كثيرة الماء وأهلها يزرعون من مائها ‏.‏
قال أخبروني عن نبي الأميين ما فعل قالوا قد خرج من مكة ونزل يثرب ‏.‏
قال أقاتله العرب قلنا نعم ‏.‏ قال كيف صنع بهم فأخبرناه أنه قد ظهر
على من يليه من العرب وأطاعوه قال لهم قد كان ذلك قلنا نعم ‏.‏ قال
أما إن ذاك خير لهم أن يطيعوه وإني مخبركم عني إني أنا المسيح وإني
أوشك أن يؤذن لي في الخروج فأخرج فأسير في الأرض فلا أدع قرية إلا
هبطتها في أربعين ليلة غير مكة وطيبة فهما محرمتان على كلتاهما كلما
أردت أن أدخل واحدة أو واحدا منهما استقبلني ملك بيده السيف صلتا
يصدني عنها وإن على كل نقب منها ملائكة يحرسونها قالت قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم وطعن بمخصرته في المنبر ‏"‏ هذه طيبة هذه طيبة هذه
طيبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يعني المدينة ‏"‏ ألا هل كنت حدثتكم ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
الناس نعم ‏"‏ فإنه أعجبني حديث تميم أنه وافق الذي كنت أحدثكم عنه
وعن المدينة ومكة ألا إنه في بحر الشام أو بحر اليمن لا بل من قبل
المشرق ما هو من قبل المشرق ما هو من قبل المشرق ما هو ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأومأ
بيده إلى المشرق ‏.‏ قالت فحفظت هذا من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Amir b. Sharahil Sha'bi Sha'b Hamdan reported that he
asked Fatima, daughter of Qais and sister of ad-Dahhak b. Qais and
she was the first amongst the emigrant women: Narrate to me a
hadith which you had heard directly from Allah's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) and there is no extra link in between them. She
said: Very well, if you like, I am prepared to do that, and he said
to her: Well, do It and narrate that to me. She said: I married the
son of Mughira and he was a chosen young man of Quraish at that
time, but he fell as a martyr in the first Jihad (fighting) on the
side of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him). When I became a
widow, 'Abd al-Rahman b. Auf, one amongst the group of the
Companions of Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him), sent me
the proposal of marriage. Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
also sent me such a message for his freed slave Usama b. Zaid. And
it had been conveyed to me that Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) had said (about Usama): He who loves me should also love
Usama. When Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) talked to me
(about this matter), I said: My affairs are in your hand. You may
marry me to anyone whom you like. He said: You better shift now to
the house of Umm Sharik, and Umm Sharik was a rich lady from
amongst the Ansar. She spent generously for the cause of Allah and
entertained guests very hospitably. I said: Well, I will do as you
like. He said: Do not do that for Umm Sharik is a woman who is very
frequently visited by guests and I do not like that your head may
be uncovered or the cloth may be removed from your shank and the
strangers may catch sight of them which you abhor. You better shift
to the house of your cousin 'Abdullah b. 'Amr b. Umm Maktum and he
is a person of the Bani Fihr branch of the Quraish, and he belonged
to that tribe (to which Fatima) belonged. So I shifted to that
house, and when my period of waiting was over, I heard the voice of
an announcer making an announcement that the prayer would be
observed in the mosque (where) congregational prayer (is observed).
So I set out towards that mosque and observed prayer along with
Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) and I was in the row of
the women which was near the row of men. When Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) had finished his prayer, he sat on the
pulpit smiling and said: Every worshipper should keep sitting at
his place. He then said: Do you know why I had asked you to
assemble? They said: Allah and His Messenger know best. He said: By
Allah. I have not made you assemble for exhortation or for a
warning, but I have detained you here, for Tamim Dari, a Christian,
who came and accepted Islam, told me something, which agrees with
what I was telling, you about the Dajjal. He narrated to me that he
had sailed in a ship along with thirty men of Bani Lakhm and Bani
Judham and had been tossed by waves in the ocean for a month. Then
these (waves) took them (near) the land within the ocean (island)
at the time of sunset. They sat in a small side-boat and entered
that island. There was a beast with long thick hair (and because of
these) they could not distinguish his face from his back. They
said: Woe to you, who can you be? Thereupon it said: I am
al-Jassasa. They said: What is al-Jassasa? And it said: O people,
go to this person in the monastery as he is very much eager to know
about you. He (the narrator) said: When it named a person for us we
were afraid of it lest it should be a devil. Then we hurriedly went
on till we came to that monastery and found a well-built person
there with his hands tied to his neck and having iron shackles
between his two legs up to the ankles. We said: Woe be upon thee,
who are you? And he said: You would soon come to know about me. but
tell me who are you. We said: We are people from Arabia and we
embarked upon a boat but the sea-waves had been driving us for one
month and they brought as near this island. We got Into the
side-boats and entered this island and here a beast met us with
profusely thick hair and because of the thickness of his hair his
face could not be distinguished from his back. We said: Woe be to
thee, who are you? It said: I am al- Jassasa. We said: What is
al-Jassasa? And it said: You go to this very person in the
monastery for he is eagerly waiting for you to know about you. So
we came to you in hot haste fearing that that might be the Devil.
He (that chained person) said: Tell me about the date-palm trees of
Baisan. We said: About what aspect of theirs do you seek
information? He said: I ask you whether these trees bear fruit or
not. We said: yes. Thereupon he said: I think these would not bear
fruits. He said: Inform me about the lake of Tabariyya? We said:
Which aspect of it do you want to know? He said: Is there water in
it? They said: There is abundance of water in it. Thereupon he
said: I think it would soon become dry. He again said: Inform me
about the spring of Zughar. They said: Which aspect of it you want
to know? He (the chained person) said: Is there water in it and
does it irrigate (the land)? We said to him: Yes, there is
abundance of water in it and the inhabitants (of Medina) irrigate
(land) with the help of it, He said: Inform me about the unlettered
Prophet; what has he done? We said: He has come out from Mecca and
has settled In Yathrib (Medina). He said: Do the Arabs fight
against him? We said: Yes. He said: How did he deal with them? We
informed him that he had overcome those in his neighbourhood and
they had submitted themselves before him. Thereupon he said to us:
Has it actually happened? We said: Yes. Thereupon he said: If it is
so that is better for them that they should show obedience to him.
I am going to tell you about myself and I am Dajjal and would be
soon permitted to get out and so I shall get out and travel in the
land, and will not spare any town where I would not stay for forty
nights except Mecca and Medina as these two (places) are prohibited
(areas) for me and I would not make an attempt to enter any one of
these two. An angel with a sword in his hand would confront me and
would bar my way and there would be angels to guard every passage
leading to it; then Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him)
striking the pulpit with the help of the end of his staff said:
This implies Taiba meaning Medina. Have I not, told you an account
(of the Dajjal) like this? 'The people said: Yes, and this account
narrated by Tamim Dari was liked by me for it corroborates the
account which I gave to you in regard to him (Dajjal) at Medina and
Mecca. Behold he (Dajjal) is in the Syrian sea (Mediterranean) or
the Yemen sea (Arabian sea). Nay, on the contrary, he is in the
east, he is in the east, he is in the east, and he pointed with his
hand towards the east. I (Fatima bint Qais) said: I preserved it in
my mind (this narration from Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him).</english-text>
</hadith>
