<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17494</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7620</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Piety and Softening of Hearts -
كتاب الزهد والرقائق</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 20297, 11151, 1238, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا شيبان بن فروخ، حدثنا همام، حدثنا إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي طلحة، حدثني عبد الرحمن بن أبي عمرة، أن أبا هريرة، حدثه
أنه، سمع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إن ثلاثة في بني إسرائيل
أبرص وأقرع وأعمى فأراد الله أن يبتليهم فبعث إليهم ملكا فأتى الأبرص
فقال أى شىء أحب إليك قال لون حسن وجلد حسن ويذهب عني الذي قد قذرني
الناس ‏.‏ قال فمسحه فذهب عنه قذره وأعطي لونا حسنا وجلدا حسنا قال
فأى المال أحب إليك قال الإبل - أو قال البقر شك إسحاق - إلا أن
الأبرص أو الأقرع قال أحدهما الإبل وقال الآخر البقر - قال فأعطي ناقة
عشراء فقال بارك الله لك فيها - قال - فأتى الأقرع فقال أى شىء أحب
إليك قال شعر حسن ويذهب عني هذا الذي قذرني الناس ‏.‏ قال فمسحه فذهب
عنه وأعطي شعرا حسنا - قال - فأى المال أحب إليك قال البقر ‏.‏ فأعطي
بقرة حاملا فقال بارك الله لك فيها - قال - فأتى الأعمى فقال أى شىء
أحب إليك قال أن يرد الله إلى بصري فأبصر به الناس - قال - فمسحه فرد
الله إليه بصره ‏.‏ قال فأى المال أحب إليك قال الغنم ‏.‏ فأعطي شاة
والدا فأنتج هذان وولد هذا - قال - فكان لهذا واد من الإبل ولهذا واد
من البقر ولهذا واد من الغنم ‏.‏ قال ثم إنه أتى الأبرص في صورته
وهيئته فقال رجل مسكين قد انقطعت بي الحبال في سفري فلا بلاغ لي اليوم
إلا بالله ثم بك أسألك بالذي أعطاك اللون الحسن والجلد الحسن والمال
بعيرا أتبلغ عليه في سفري ‏.‏ فقال الحقوق كثيرة ‏.‏ فقال له كأني
أعرفك ألم تكن أبرص يقذرك الناس فقيرا فأعطاك الله فقال إنما ورثت هذا
المال كابرا عن كابر ‏.‏ فقال إن كنت كاذبا فصيرك الله إلى ما كنت ‏.‏
قال وأتى الأقرع في صورته فقال له مثل ما قال لهذا ورد عليه مثل ما رد
على هذا فقال إن كنت كاذبا فصيرك الله إلى ما كنت ‏.‏ قال وأتى الأعمى
في صورته وهيئته فقال رجل مسكين وابن سبيل انقطعت بي الحبال في سفري
فلا بلاغ لي اليوم إلا بالله ثم بك أسألك بالذي رد عليك بصرك شاة
أتبلغ بها في سفري فقال قد كنت أعمى فرد الله إلى بصري فخذ ما شئت ودع
ما شئت فوالله لا أجهدك اليوم شيئا أخذته لله فقال أمسك مالك فإنما
ابتليتم فقد رضي عنك وسخط على صاحبيك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira, narrated that he beard Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) as saying: There were three persons in Bani
Isra'il, one suffering from leprosy, the other bald-headed and the
third one blind. Allah decided to test them. So He sent an angel
who came to one who was suffering from leprosy and said: Which
thing do you like most? He said: Beautiful colour and fine skin and
removal of that which makes me detestable in the eye of people. He
wiped him and his illness was no more and he was conferred upon
beautiful colour and beautiful skin. He (the angel) again said:
Which property do you like most? He said: Camels, or he said: The
cow the narrator is, however, doubtful about it, but (out of the
persons) suffering from leprosy or baldness one of them definitely
said: The came]. And the other one said: Cow. And he (one who
demanded came]) was bestowed upon a she-camel, in an advanced stage
of pregnancy, and while giving he said: May Allah bless you in this
I Then he came to the bald-headed person and said: Which thing do
you like most? He said: Beautiful hair and that (this baldness) may
be removed from me because of which people hate me He wiped his
body and his illness was removed and he was bestowed upon beautiful
hair, and the angel said: Which wealth do you like most? He said:
The cow. And he was given a pregnant cow and while handing it over
to him he (the angel) said: May Allah bless you in this I Then he
came to the blind man and he said: Which thing do you like most? He
said: Allah should restore my eyesight so that I should be able to
see people with the help of that. He wiped his body and Allah
restored to him his eyesight, and he (the angel) also said: Which
wealth do you like most? He said. The flock of sheep. And he was
given a pregnant goat and that gave birth to young ones and it so
happened that one valley abounded in camels and the other one in
goats and the third one in sheep. He then came to one suffering
from leprosy in his (old) form and shape and he said: I am a poor
person and my provision has run short in my journey and there is
none to take me to my destination except with the help of Allah and
your favour. I beg of you in His name Who gave you fine colour and
fine skin, and the camel in the shape of wealth (to confer upon me)
a camel which should carry me in my journey. He said: I have many
responsibilities to discharge. Thereupon he said: I perceive as if
I recognise you. Were you not suffering from leprosy whom people
hated and you were a destitude and Allah conferred upon you
(wealth) He said: I have inherited this property from my
forefathers. Thereupon he said: If you are a liar may Allah change
you to that very position in which you had been. He then came to
the one who was bald-headed in his (old) form and said to him the
same what he had said to him (one suffering from leprosy) and he
gave him the same reply as he had given him and he said: If you
'are a liar, may Allah turn you to your previous position in which
you had been. And then he came to the blind man in his (old) form
and shape and he said: I am a destitute person and a wayfarer. My
provision have ran short and today there is no way to reach the
destination but with the help of Allah and then with your help and
I beg of you in the (name) of One Who restored your eyesight and
gave you the flock of sheep to give me a sheep by which I should be
able to make my provisions for the journey. He said: I was blind
and Allah restored to me my eyesight; you take whatever you like
and leave whatever you like. By Allah. I shall not stand in your
way today for what you take in the name of God. Thereupon, he said:
You keep with you what you have (in your possession). The fact is
that you three were put to test and Allah is well pleased with you
and He is annoyed with your companions.</english-text>
</hadith>
