<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17527</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7653</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Piety and Softening of Hearts -
كتاب الزهد والرقائق</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 10938, 29</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو الطاهر، أحمد بن عمرو بن سرح أخبرنا ابن وهب،
أخبرني أبو هانئ سمع أبا عبد الرحمن الحبلي، يقول سمعت عبد الله بن
عمرو بن العاص، وسأله، رجل فقال ألسنا من فقراء المهاجرين فقال له عبد
الله ألك امرأة تأوي إليها قال نعم ‏.‏ قال ألك مسكن تسكنه قال نعم
قال فأنت من الأغنياء قال فإن لي خادما قال فأنت من الملوك ‏.‏ قال
أبو عبد الرحمن وجاء ثلاثة نفر إلى عبد الله بن عمرو بن العاص وأنا
عنده فقالوا يا أبا محمد إنا والله ما نقدر على شىء لا نفقة ولا دابة
ولا متاع ‏.‏ فقال لهم ما شئتم إن شئتم رجعتم إلينا فأعطيناكم ما يسر
الله لكم وإن شئتم ذكرنا أمركم للسلطان وإن شئتم صبرتم فإني سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إن فقراء المهاجرين يسبقون الأغنياء
يوم القيامة إلى الجنة بأربعين خريفا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا فإنا نصبر لا نسأل
شيئا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abd al-Rahman al-Hubuli reported: I heard that a
person asked 'Abdullah b. 'Amr b. 'Asas saying: Are we not amongst
the destitute of the emigrants? Abdullah said to him: Have you a
spouse with whom you live? He said: Yes. He again said: Then you
are amongst the rich. He said: I have a servant also. Thereupon he
(Abdullah b. 'Amr b. 'As) said: Then you are amongst the kings. Abu
'Abdal-Rahman reported that three persons came to 'Abdullah b. Amr
b. 'As while I was sitting with him and they said: By Allah, we
have nothing with us either in the form of provision, riding
animals or wealth. Thereupon he said to them: I am prepared to do
whatever you like. If you come to us, we would give you what Allah
would make available for you. and if you like I would make a
mention of your case to the ruler, and if you like you can show
patience also. for I have beard Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: Destitute amongst the emigrants would precede
the rich emigrants by forty years in getting into Paradise on the
Day of Resurrection. Thereupon they said: We then, show patience
and do not ask for anything.</english-text>
</hadith>
