<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17537</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7664</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Piety and Softening of Hearts -
كتاب الزهد والرقائق</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30022, 20472, 32017, 11231, 11236,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وزهير بن حرب، - واللفظ لأبي
بكر - قالا حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي سلمة، عن
وهب بن كيسان، عن عبيد بن عمير، الليثي عن أبي هريرة، عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ بينا رجل بفلاة من الأرض فسمع صوتا في سحابة
اسق حديقة فلان ‏.‏ فتنحى ذلك السحاب فأفرغ ماءه في حرة فإذا شرجة من
تلك الشراج قد استوعبت ذلك الماء كله فتتبع الماء فإذا رجل قائم في
حديقته يحول الماء بمسحاته فقال له يا عبد الله ما اسمك قال فلان ‏.‏
للاسم الذي سمع في السحابة فقال له يا عبد الله لم تسألني عن اسمي
فقال إني سمعت صوتا في السحاب الذي هذا ماؤه يقول اسق حديقة فلان
لاسمك فما تصنع فيها قال أما إذا قلت هذا فإني أنظر إلى ما يخرج منها
فأتصدق بثلثه وآكل أنا وعيالي ثلثا وأرد فيها ثلثه ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported: While a person was in the
wilderness he heard a voice from the cloud (commanding it thus):
Irrigate the garden of so and so. (After that the clouds slinked
aside and poured water on a stony ground. It filled a channel
amongst the channels of that land and that person followed that
water and he found a person standing in the garden busy in changing
the course of water with the help of a hatchet. He said to him:
Servant of Allah, what is your name? he said: So and so. And it was
that very name which he had heard from the clouds. and he said to
him: Servant of Allah, why do you ask me my name? He said: I beard
a voice from the clouds of which It is the downpour, saying: Water
the garden of so and to. like your name. What do you do (for the
favour) shown to you by Allah in this matter? He said: Now as you
state so. I look what yield I get from it. and I give one-third as
charity out of it and I and my children eat one-third of it and
one-third I return to it as investment.</english-text>
</hadith>
