<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>17574</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7703</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book Pertaining to Piety and Softening of Hearts -
كتاب الزهد والرقائق</chapter>
<chain-index>20021, 11269, 11196, 182</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هداب بن خالد، حدثنا حماد بن سلمة، حدثنا ثابت، عن
عبد الرحمن بن، أبي ليلى عن صهيب، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ كان ملك فيمن كان قبلكم وكان له ساحر فلما كبر قال للملك إني
قد كبرت فابعث إلى غلاما أعلمه السحر ‏.‏ فبعث إليه غلاما يعلمه فكان
في طريقه إذا سلك راهب فقعد إليه وسمع كلامه فأعجبه فكان إذا أتى
الساحر مر بالراهب وقعد إليه فإذا أتى الساحر ضربه فشكا ذلك إلى
الراهب فقال إذا خشيت الساحر فقل حبسني أهلي ‏.‏ وإذا خشيت أهلك فقل
حبسني الساحر ‏.‏ فبينما هو كذلك إذ أتى على دابة عظيمة قد حبست الناس
فقال اليوم أعلم آلساحر أفضل أم الراهب أفضل فأخذ حجرا فقال اللهم إن
كان أمر الراهب أحب إليك من أمر الساحر فاقتل هذه الدابة حتى يمضي
الناس ‏.‏ فرماها فقتلها ومضى الناس فأتى الراهب فأخبره فقال له
الراهب أى بنى أنت اليوم أفضل مني ‏.‏ قد بلغ من أمرك ما أرى وإنك
ستبتلى فإن ابتليت فلا تدل على ‏.‏ وكان الغلام يبرئ الأكمه والأبرص
ويداوي الناس من سائر الأدواء فسمع جليس للملك كان قد عمي فأتاه
بهدايا كثيرة فقال ما ها هنا لك أجمع إن أنت شفيتني فقال إني لا أشفي
أحدا إنما يشفي الله فإن أنت آمنت بالله دعوت الله فشفاك ‏.‏ فآمن
بالله فشفاه الله فأتى الملك فجلس إليه كما كان يجلس فقال له الملك من
رد عليك بصرك قال ربي ‏.‏ قال ولك رب غيري قال ربي وربك الله ‏.‏
فأخذه فلم يزل يعذبه حتى دل على الغلام فجيء بالغلام فقال له الملك أى
بنى قد بلغ من سحرك ما تبرئ الأكمه والأبرص وتفعل وتفعل ‏.‏ فقال إني
لا أشفي أحدا إنما يشفي الله ‏.‏ فأخذه فلم يزل يعذبه حتى دل على
الراهب فجيء بالراهب فقيل له ارجع عن دينك ‏.‏ فأبى فدعا بالمئشار
فوضع المئشار في مفرق رأسه فشقه حتى وقع شقاه ثم جيء بجليس الملك فقيل
له ارجع عن دينك ‏.‏ فأبى فوضع المئشار في مفرق رأسه فشقه به حتى وقع
شقاه ثم جيء بالغلام فقيل له ارجع عن دينك ‏.‏ فأبى فدفعه إلى نفر من
أصحابه فقال اذهبوا به إلى جبل كذا وكذا فاصعدوا به الجبل فإذا بلغتم
ذروته فإن رجع عن دينه وإلا فاطرحوه فذهبوا به فصعدوا به الجبل فقال
اللهم اكفنيهم بما شئت ‏.‏ فرجف بهم الجبل فسقطوا وجاء يمشي إلى الملك
فقال له الملك ما فعل أصحابك قال كفانيهم الله ‏.‏ فدفعه إلى نفر من
أصحابه فقال اذهبوا به فاحملوه في قرقور فتوسطوا به البحر فإن رجع عن
دينه وإلا فاقذفوه ‏.‏ فذهبوا به فقال اللهم اكفنيهم بما شئت ‏.‏
فانكفأت بهم السفينة فغرقوا وجاء يمشي إلى الملك فقال له الملك ما فعل
أصحابك قال كفانيهم الله ‏.‏ فقال للملك إنك لست بقاتلي حتى تفعل ما
آمرك به ‏.‏ قال وما هو قال تجمع الناس في صعيد واحد وتصلبني على جذع
ثم خذ سهما من كنانتي ثم ضع السهم في كبد القوس ثم قل باسم الله رب
الغلام ‏.‏ ثم ارمني فإنك إذا فعلت ذلك قتلتني ‏.‏ فجمع الناس في صعيد
واحد وصلبه على جذع ثم أخذ سهما من كنانته ثم وضع السهم في كبد القوس
ثم قال باسم الله رب الغلام ‏.‏ ثم رماه فوقع السهم في صدغه فوضع يده
في صدغه في موضع السهم فمات فقال الناس آمنا برب الغلام آمنا برب
الغلام آمنا برب الغلام ‏.‏ فأتي الملك فقيل له أرأيت ما كنت تحذر قد
والله نزل بك حذرك قد آمن الناس ‏.‏ فأمر بالأخدود في أفواه السكك
فخدت وأضرم النيران وقال من لم يرجع عن دينه فأحموه فيها ‏.‏ أو قيل
له اقتحم ‏.‏ ففعلوا حتى جاءت امرأة ومعها صبي لها فتقاعست أن تقع
فيها فقال لها الغلام يا أمه اصبري فإنك على الحق ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Suhaib reported that Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) thus said: There lived a king before you and he had a
(court) magician. As he (the magician) grew old, he said to the
king: I have grown old, send some young boy to me so that I should
teach him magic. He (the king) sent to him a young man so that he
should train him (in magic). And on his way (to the magician) he
(the young man) found a monk sitting there. He (the young man)
listened to his (the monk's) talk and was impressed by it. It
became his habit that on his way to the magician he met the monk
and set there and he came to the magician (late). He (the magician)
beat him because of delay. He made a complaint of that to the monk
and he said to him: When you feel afraid of the magician, say:
Members of my family had detained me. And when you feel afraid of
your family you should say: The magician had detained me. It so
happened that there came a huge beast (of prey) and it blocked the
way of the people, and he (the young boy) said: I will come to know
today whether the magician is superior or the monk is superior. He
picked up a stone and said: O Allah, if the affair of the monk is
dearer to Thee than the affair of the magician, cause death to this
animal so that the people should be able to move about freely. He
threw that stone towards it and killed it and the people began to
move about (on the path freely). He (the young man) then came to
that monk and Informed him and the monk said: Sonny, today you are
superior to me. Your affair has come to a stage where I find that
you would be soon put to a trial, and in case you are put to a
trial don't give my clue. That young man began to treat the blind
and those suffering from leprosy and he in fact began to cure
people from (all kinds) of illness. When a companion of the king
who had gone blind heard about him, he came to him with numerous
gifts and said: If you cure me all these things collected together
here would be yours. Be said: I myself do not cure anyone. It is
Allah Who cures and if you affirm faith in Allah, I shall also
supplicate Allah to cure you. He affirmed his faith in Allah and
Allah cured him and he came to the king and sat by his side as he
used to sit before. The king said to him: Who restored your
eyesight? He said: My Lord. Thereupon he said: It means that your
Lord is One besides me. He said: My Lord and your Lord is Allah, so
he (the king) took hold of him and tormented him till he gave a
clue of that boy. The young man was thus summoned and the king said
to him: O boy, it has been conveyed to me that you have become so
much proficient in your magic that you cure the blind and those
suffering from leprosy and you do such and such things. Thereupon
he said: I do not cure anyone; it is Allah Who cures, and he (the
king) took hold of him and began to torment him. So he gave a clue
of the monk. The monk was thus summoned and it was said to him: You
should turn back from your religion. He, however, refused to do so.
He (ordered) for a saw to be brought (and when it was done) he (the
king) placed it in the middle of his head and tore it into parts
till a part fell down. Then the courtier of the king was brought
and it was said to him: Turn back from your religion. Arid he
refused to do so, and the saw was placed in the midst of his head
and it was torn till a part fell down. Then that young boy was
brought and it was said to him: Turn back from your religion. He
refused to do so and he was handed over to a group of his
courtiers. And he 'said to them: Take him to such and such
mountain; make him climb up that mountain and when you reach its
top (ask him to renounce his faith) but if he refuses to do so,
then throw him (down the mountain). So they took him and made him
climb up the mountain and he said: O Allah, save me from them (in
any way) Thou likest and the mountain began to quake and they all
fell down and that person came walking to the king. The king said
to him: What has happened to your companions? He said: Allah has
saved me from them. He again handed him to some of his courtiers
and said: Take him and carry him in a small boat and when you reach
the middle of the ocean (ask him to renounce) his religion, but if
he does not renounce his religion throw him (into the water). So
they took him and he said: O Allah, save me from them and what they
want to do. It was quite soon that the boat turned over and they
were drowned and he came walking to the king, and the king said to
him: What has happened to your companions? He said: Allah has saved
me from them, and he said to the king: You cannot kill me until you
do what I ask you to do. And he said: What is that? He said: You
should gather people in a plain and hang me by the trunk (of a
tree). Then take hold of an arrow from the quiver and say: In the
name of Allah, the Lord of the worlds; then shoot an arrow and if
you do that then you would be able to kill me. So he (the king)
called the people in an open plain and tied him (the boy) to the
trunk of a tree, then he took hold of an arrow from his quiver and
then placed the arrow in the bow and then said: In the name of
Allah, the Lord of the young boy; he then shot an arrow and it bit
his temple. He (the boy) placed his hands upon the temple where the
arrow had bit him and he died and the people said: We affirm our
faith in the Lord of this young man, we affirm our faith in the
Lord of this young man, we affirm our faith in the Lord of this
young man. The courtiers came to the king and it was said to him:
Do you see that Allah has actually done what you aimed at averting.
They (the people) have affirmed their faith in the Lord. He (the
king) commanded ditches to be dug at important points in the path.
When these ditches were dug, and the fire was lit in them it was
said (to the people): He who would not turn back from his (boy's)
religion would be thrown in the fire or it would be said to them to
jump in that. (The people courted death but did not renounce
religion) till a woman came with her child and she felt hesitant in
jumping into the fire and the child said to her: 0 mother, endure
(this ordeal) for it is the Truth.</english-text>
</hadith>
