<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10109</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>109</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20001, 11445, 11443, 6</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد بن جميل بن طريف بن عبد الله
الثقفي، عن مالك بن أنس، - فيما قرئ عليه - عن أبي سهيل، عن أبيه، أنه
سمع طلحة بن عبيد الله، يقول جاء رجل إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم من أهل نجد ثائر الرأس نسمع دوي صوته ولا نفقه ما يقول حتى دنا
من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فإذا هو يسأل عن الإسلام فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خمس صلوات في اليوم والليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
هل على غيرهن قال ‏"‏ لا ‏.‏ إلا أن تطوع وصيام شهر رمضان ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقال هل على غيره فقال ‏"‏ لا ‏.‏ إلا أن تطوع ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذكر له رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الزكاة فقال هل على غيرها قال ‏"‏ لا ‏.‏ إلا
أن تطوع ‏"‏ قال فأدبر الرجل وهو يقول والله لا أزيد على هذا ولا أنقص
منه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أفلح إن صدق ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is reported on the authority of Talha b.
'Ubaidullah that a person with dishevelled hair, one of the people
of Nejd, came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him). We
heard the humming of his voice but could not fully discern what he
had been saying, till he came nigh to the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him). It was then (disclosed to us) that he was
asking questions pertaining to Islam. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) said: Five prayers during the day and the night.
(Upon this he said: Am I obliged to say any other (prayer) besides
these? He (the Holy Prophet, ) said: No, but whatever you observe
voluntarily, out of your own free will, and the fasts of Ramadan.
The inquirer said: Am I obliged to do anything else besides this?
He (the Holy Prophet) said: No, but whatever you do out of your own
free will. And the Messenger of Allah told him about the Zakat
(poor-rate). The inquirer said: Am I obliged to pay anything else
besides this? He (the Holy Prophet) said: No, but whatever you pay
voluntarily out of your own free will. The man turned back and was
saying: I would neither make any addition to this, nor will
decrease anything out of it. The Prophet remarked: He is
successful, if he is true to what he affirms.</english-text>
</hadith>
