<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10124</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>124</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30503, 20022, 11309, 17, 30399, 20243, 11309,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا خلف بن هشام، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن أبي جمرة، قال
سمعت ابن عباس، ح وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، - واللفظ له - أخبرنا عباد بن
عباد، عن أبي جمرة، عن ابن عباس، قال قدم وفد عبد القيس على رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا يا رسول الله إنا هذا الحى من ربيعة وقد
حالت بيننا وبينك كفار مضر فلا نخلص إليك إلا في شهر الحرام فمرنا
بأمر نعمل به وندعو إليه من وراءنا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ آمركم بأربع وأنهاكم
عن أربع الإيمان بالله - ثم فسرها لهم فقال - شهادة أن لا إله إلا
الله وأن محمدا رسول الله وإقام الصلاة وإيتاء الزكاة وأن تؤدوا خمس
ما غنمتم وأنهاكم عن الدباء والحنتم والنقير والمقير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ زاد خلف
في روايته ‏"‏ شهادة أن لا إله إلا الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وعقد واحدة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Ibn 'Abbas that a
delegation of Abdul Qais came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) and said: Messenger of Allah, verily ours is a tribe
of Rabi'a and there stand between you and us the unbelievers of
Mudar and we find no freedom to come to you except in the sacred
month. Direct us to an act which we should ourselves perform and
invite those who live beside us. Upon this the Prophet remarked: I
command you to do four things and prohibit you against four acts.
(The four deeds which you are commanded to do are): Faith in Allah,
and then he explained it for them and said: Testifying the fact.
that there is no god but Allah, that Muhammad is the messenger of
Allah, performance of prayer, payment of Zakat, that you pay Khums
(one-fifth) of the booty fallen to your lot, and I prohibit you to
use round gourd, wine jars, wooden pots or skins for wine. Khalaf
b. Hisham has made this addition in his narration: Testifying the
fact that there is no god but Allah, and then he with his finger
pointed out the oneness of the Lord.</english-text>
</hadith>
