<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10127</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>127</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 20208, 11073, 11019</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، حدثنا ابن علية، حدثنا سعيد بن أبي
عروبة، عن قتادة، قال حدثنا من، لقي الوفد الذين قدموا على رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم من عبد القيس ‏.‏ قال سعيد وذكر قتادة أبا نضرة عن
أبي سعيد الخدري في حديثه هذا ‏.‏ أن أناسا من عبد القيس قدموا على
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا يا نبي الله إنا حى من ربيعة
وبيننا وبينك كفار مضر ولا نقدر عليك إلا في أشهر الحرم فمرنا بأمر
نأمر به من وراءنا وندخل به الجنة إذا نحن أخذنا به ‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ آمركم بأربع وأنهاكم عن أربع اعبدوا الله
ولا تشركوا به شيئا وأقيموا الصلاة وآتوا الزكاة وصوموا رمضان وأعطوا
الخمس من الغنائم وأنهاكم عن أربع عن الدباء والحنتم والمزفت والنقير
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا يا نبي الله ما علمك بالنقير قال ‏"‏ بلى جذع تنقرونه
فتقذفون فيه من القطيعاء - قال سعيد أو قال من التمر - ثم تصبون فيه
من الماء حتى إذا سكن غليانه شربتموه حتى إن أحدكم - أو إن أحدهم -
ليضرب ابن عمه بالسيف ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وفي القوم رجل أصابته جراحة كذلك
‏.‏ قال وكنت أخبأها حياء من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت ففيم
نشرب يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ في أسقية الأدم التي يلاث على أفواهها ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله إن أرضنا كثيرة الجرذان ولا تبقى بها أسقية
الأدم ‏.‏ فقال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وإن أكلتها الجرذان
وإن أكلتها الجرذان وإن أكلتها الجرذان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقال نبي الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم لأشج عبد القيس ‏"‏ إن فيك لخصلتين يحبهما الله الحلم
والأناة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is reported on the authority of Qatada that one
among the delegates of the 'Abdul-Qais tribe narrated this
tradition to him. Sa'id said that Qatada had mentioned the name of
Abu Nadra on the authority of Abu Sa'id Khudri who narrated this
tradition: That people from the- tribe of 'Abdul-Qais came to the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) and said: Messenger of
Allah, we belong to the tribe of Rabi'a and there live between you
and us the unbelievers of the Mudar tribe and we find it impossible
to come to you except in the sacred months; direct us to a deed
which we must communicate to those who have been left behind us and
by doing which we may enter heaven. Upon this the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: I enjoin upon you four (things)
and forbid you to do four (things): worship Allah and associate
none with Him, establish prayer, pay Zakat, and observe the fast of
Ramadan, and pay the fifth part out of the booty. And I prohibit
you from four (things): dry gourds, green-coloured jars, hollowed
stumps of palm-trees, and receptacles. They (the members of the
delegation) said: Do you know what al-naqir is? He replied: Yes, it
is a stump which you hollow out and in which you throw small dates.
Sa'id said: He (the Holy Prophet) used the word tamar (dates). (The
Holy Prophet then added): Then you sprinkle water over it and when
its ebullition subsides, you drink it (and you are so intoxicated)
that one amongst you, or one amongst them (the other members of
your tribe, who were not present there) strikes his cousin with the
sword. He (the narrator) said: There was a man amongst us who had
sustained injury on this very account due to (intoxication), and he
told that he tried to conceal it out of shame from the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him). I, however, inquired from the
Messenger of Allah (it we discard those utensils which you have
forbidden us to use), then what type of vessels should be used for
drink? He (the Holy Prophet) replied: In the waterskin the mouths
of which are tied (with a string). They (again) said: Prophet of
Allah, our land abounds in rats and water-skins cannot remain
preserved. The holy Prophet of Allah (may peace be upon him) said:
(Drink in water-skins) even if these arenibbled by rats. And then
(addressing) al-Ashajj of 'Abdul-Qais he said: Verily, you possess
two such qualities which Allah loves: insight and
deliberateness.</english-text>
</hadith>
