<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10152</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>152</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20297, 11019, 19, 32</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هداب بن خالد الأزدي، حدثنا همام، حدثنا قتادة،
حدثنا أنس بن مالك، عن معاذ بن جبل، قال كنت ردف النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ليس بيني وبينه إلا مؤخرة الرحل فقال ‏"‏ يا معاذ بن جبل ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قلت لبيك رسول الله وسعديك ‏.‏ ثم سار ساعة ثم قال ‏"‏ يا معاذ بن جبل
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لبيك رسول الله وسعديك ‏.‏ ثم سار ساعة ثم قال ‏"‏ يا
معاذ بن جبل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لبيك رسول الله وسعديك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل تدري
ما حق الله على العباد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فإن حق الله على العباد أن يعبدوه ولا يشركوا به شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم سار
ساعة ثم قال ‏"‏ يا معاذ بن جبل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لبيك رسول الله وسعديك
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل تدري ما حق العباد على الله إذا فعلوا ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
قلت الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أن لا يعذبهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Mu'adh b. Jabal: I
was riding behind the Prophet (may peace be upon him) and there was
nothing between him and me but the rear part of the saddle, when he
said: Mu'adh b. Jabal: To which I replied: At your beck and call,
and at your pleasure, Messenger of Allah! He moved along for a few
minutes, when again he said: Mu'adh b. Jabal: To which I replied:
At your beck and call, and at your pleasure, Messenger of Allah! He
then again moved along for a few minutes and said: Mu'adh b. Jabal:
To which I replied. At your beck and call, and at your pleasure.
Messenger of Allah He, (the Holy Prophet) said: Do you know what
right has Allah upon His servants? I said: Allah and His Messenger
know best. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Verily the right of Allah
over His servants is that they should worship Him, not associating
anything with Him. He (the Holy Prophet) with Mu'adh behind him,
moved along for a few minutes and said: Mu'adh b. Jabal: To which I
replied: At your beck and call, and at your pleasure, Messenger of
Allah! He (the Holy Prophet) said: Do you know what rights have
servants upon Allah in case they do it (i. e. they worship Allah
without associating anything with Him)? I (Mu'adh b. Jabal)
replied: Allah and His Messenger know best. (Upon this) he (the
Holy Prophet) remarked: That He would not torment them (with the
fire of Hell).</english-text>
</hadith>
