<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10287</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>287</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20326, 30216, 30123, 11060, 19301,
50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو خالد الأحمر، ح
وحدثنا أبو كريب، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، عن أبي معاوية، كلاهما عن
الأعمش، عن أبي ظبيان، عن أسامة بن زيد، وهذا، حديث ابن أبي شيبة قال
بعثنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في سرية فصبحنا الحرقات من جهينة
فأدركت رجلا فقال لا إله إلا الله ‏.‏ فطعنته فوقع في نفسي من ذلك
فذكرته للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ أقال لا إله إلا الله وقتلته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله إنما
قالها خوفا من السلاح ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أفلا شققت عن قلبه حتى تعلم أقالها
أم لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فمازال يكررها على حتى تمنيت أني أسلمت يومئذ ‏.‏ قال
فقال سعد وأنا والله لا أقتل مسلما حتى يقتله ذو البطين ‏.‏ يعني
أسامة قال قال رجل ألم يقل الله ‏{‏ وقاتلوهم حتى لا تكون فتنة ويكون
الدين كله لله‏}‏ فقال سعد قد قاتلنا حتى لا تكون فتنة وأنت وأصحابك
تريدون أن تقاتلوا حتى تكون فتنة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Usama b. Zaid that
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) sent us in a raiding
party. We raided Huraqat of Juhaina in the morning. I caught hold
of a man and he said: There is no god but Allah, I attacked him
with a spear. It once occurred to me and I talked about it to the
Apostle (may peace be upon him). The Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) said: Did he profess" There is no god but Allah," and
even then you killed him? I said: Messenger of Allah, he made a
profession of it out of the fear of the weapon. He (the Holy
Prophet) observed: Did you tear his heart in order to find out
whether it had professed or not? And he went on repeating it to me
till I wished I had embraced Islam that day. Sa'd said: By Allah, I
would never kill any Muslim so long as a person with a heavy belly,
i. e., Usama, would not kill. Upon this a person remarked: Did
Allah not say this: And fight them until there is no more mischief
and religion is wholly for Allah? Sa'd said: We fought so that
there should be no mischief, but you and your companions wish to
fight so that there should be mischief.</english-text>
</hadith>
