<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10326</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>326</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30123, 20160, 20436, 20193, 20022, 11263,
34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، جميعا عن
سليمان، - قال أبو بكر حدثنا سليمان بن حرب، - حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن
حجاج الصواف، عن أبي الزبير، عن جابر، أن الطفيل بن عمرو الدوسي، أتى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله هل لك في حصن حصين ومنعة
- قال حصن كان لدوس في الجاهلية - فأبى ذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
للذي ذخر الله للأنصار فلما هاجر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى
المدينة هاجر إليه الطفيل بن عمرو وهاجر معه رجل من قومه فاجتووا
المدينة فمرض فجزع فأخذ مشاقص له فقطع بها براجمه فشخبت يداه حتى مات
فرآه الطفيل بن عمرو في منامه فرآه وهيئته حسنة ورآه مغطيا يديه فقال
له ما صنع بك ربك فقال غفر لي بهجرتي إلى نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال ما لي أراك مغطيا يديك قال قيل لي لن نصلح منك ما أفسدت ‏.‏
فقصها الطفيل على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اللهم وليديه فاغفر ‏"‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Jabir that Tufail
son of Amr al-Dausi came to the Apostle (may peace be upon him) and
said: Do you need strong, fortified protection? The tribe of Daus
had a fort in the pre-Islamic days. The Apostle (may peace be upon
him) declined this offer, since it (the privilege of protecting the
Holy Prophet) had already been reserved for the Ansar. When the
Apostle (may peace be upon him) migrated to Medina, Tufail son of
Amr also migrated to that place, and there also migrated along with
him a man of his tribe. But the climate of Medina did not suit him,
and he fell sick. He felt very uneasy. So he took hold of an iron
head of an arrow and cut his finger-joints. The blood streamed
forth from his hands, till he died. Tufail son of Amr saw him in a
dream. His state was good and he saw him with his hands wrapped. He
(Tufail) said to him: What treatment did your Allah accord to you?
He replied. Allah granted me pardon for my migration to the Apostle
(may peace be upon him): He (Tufail) again said: What is this that
I see you wrapping up your hands? He replied: I was told (by
Allah): We would not set right anything of yours which you damaged
yourself. Tufail narrated this (dream) to the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him). Upon this he prayed: O Allah I grant
pardon even to his hands.</english-text>
</hadith>
