<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10329</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>329</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20383, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا الحسن بن موسى، حدثنا
حماد بن سلمة، عن ثابت البناني، عن أنس بن مالك، أنه قال لما نزلت هذه
الآية ‏{‏ يا أيها الذين آمنوا لا ترفعوا أصواتكم فوق صوت النبي‏}‏
إلى آخر الآية جلس ثابت بن قيس في بيته وقال أنا من أهل النار ‏.‏
واحتبس عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسأل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
سعد بن معاذ فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا عمرو ما شأن ثابت أشتكى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سعد
إنه لجاري وما علمت له بشكوى ‏.‏ قال فأتاه سعد فذكر له قول رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ثابت أنزلت هذه الآية ولقد علمتم أني من
أرفعكم صوتا على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأنا من أهل النار ‏.‏
فذكر ذلك سعد للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ بل هو من أهل الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Anas b. Malik that
when this verse: " O ye who believe I raise not your voices above
the voice of the Prophet, nor shout loud unto him in discourse, as
ye shout loud unto one another, lest your deeds should become null
and void, while you perceive not" (xlix. 2-5), was revealed. Thabit
b. Qais confined himself in his house and said: I am one of the
denizens of Fire, and he deliberately avoided coming to the Apostle
(may peace be upon him). The Apostle (may peace be upon him) asked
Sa'd b, Mu'adh about him and said, Abu Amr, how is Thabit? Has he
fallen sick? Sa'd said: He is my neighbour, but I do not know of
his illness. Sa'd came to him (Thabit), and conveyed to him the
message of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him). Upon
this Thabit said: This verse was revealed, and you are well aware
of the fact that, amongst all of you, mine is the voice louder than
that of the Messenger of Allah, and so I am one amongst the
denizens of Fire, Sa'd Informed the Holy Prophet about it. Upon
this the Messenger of Allah observed: (Nay, not so) but he (Thabit)
is one of the dwellers of Paradise.</english-text>
</hadith>
