<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10370</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>372</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20032, 30212, 20354, 20032, 30123, 20032,
11060, 11353, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا وكيع، ح وحدثنا ابن
نمير، حدثنا أبو معاوية، ووكيع، ح وحدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي، -
واللفظ له - أخبرنا وكيع، حدثنا الأعمش، عن أبي وائل، عن عبد الله، عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من حلف على يمين صبر يقتطع بها
مال امرئ مسلم هو فيها فاجر لقي الله وهو عليه غضبان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فدخل
الأشعث بن قيس فقال ما يحدثكم أبو عبد الرحمن قالوا كذا وكذا ‏.‏ قال
صدق أبو عبد الرحمن في نزلت كان بيني وبين رجل أرض باليمن فخاصمته إلى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ هل لك بينة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت لا ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فيمينه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت إذا يحلف ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم عند ذلك ‏"‏ من حلف على يمين صبر يقتطع بها مال امرئ مسلم
هو فيها فاجر لقي الله وهو عليه غضبان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فنزلت ‏{‏ إن الذين
يشترون بعهد الله وأيمانهم ثمنا قليلا‏}‏ إلى آخر الآية
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Abdullah (b. Umar)
that the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) observed: He
who perjured with a view to appropriating the property of a Muslim,
and he is in fact a liar and would meet Allah in a state that He
would be angry with him. He (the narrator) said: There came Ash'ath
b. Qais and said (to the people): What does Abu Abdur-Rahman (the
Kunya of Abdullah b. Umar) narrate to you? They replied: So and so.
Upon this he remarked: Abu Abdur-Rahman told the truth. This
(command) has been revealed in my case. There was a piece of land
in Yemen over which I and another person had a claim. I brought the
dispute with him to the Apostle of Allah (to decide) He (the Holy
Prophet) said: Can you produce an evidence (in your support)? I
said: No. He (the Holy Prophet) observed: (Then the decision would
be made) on his oath. I said: He would readily take an oath. Upon
this the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) remarked: He
who perjured for appropriating the wealth of a Muslim, whereas he
is a liar, would meet Allah while He would be angry with him. This
verse was then revealed:" Verily those who barter Allah's covenant
and their oaths at a small price..." (iii 77).</english-text>
</hadith>
