<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10394</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>396</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20184, 20176, 10554</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا ابن
أخي ابن شهاب، عن عمه، قال أخبرني عامر بن سعد بن أبي وقاص، عن أبيه،
سعد أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أعطى رهطا وسعد جالس فيهم قال
سعد فترك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منهم من لم يعطه وهو أعجبهم
إلى فقلت يا رسول الله ما لك عن فلان فوالله إني لأراه مؤمنا ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أو مسلما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فسكت قليلا ثم
غلبني ما أعلم منه فقلت يا رسول الله ما لك عن فلان فوالله إني لأراه
مؤمنا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أو مسلما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فسكت قليلا ثم غلبني ما علمت منه فقلت يا رسول الله ما لك عن فلان
فوالله إني لأراه مؤمنا ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أو
مسلما ‏.‏ إني لأعطي الرجل وغيره أحب إلى منه خشية أن يكب في النار
على وجهه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Sa'd that the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) bestowed upon a group of
persons (things), and Sa'd was sitting amongst them. Sa'd said: The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) ignored some of them.
And he who was ignored seemed to be more deserving in my eyes (as
compared with others). I (Sa'd) said: Messenger of Allah I why is
it that you did not give to such and such (man)? Verily I see him a
believer. Upon this the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
observed: Or a Muslim? I kept quiet for some time but I was again
impelled (to express) what I knew about him. I said: Messenger of
Allah why is it that you did not give it to such and such? Verily,
by Allah, see him a believer. Upon this the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) remarked: (Nay, not a believer) but a Muslim. He
(Sa'd) said: I again kept quite for some time but what I knew about
him again impelled me (to express my opinion) and I said: Why is it
that you did not give (the share) to so and so: By Allah, verily I
see him a believer. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
remarked; (Nay, not so) but a Muslim. Verily (at times) I give (a
share) to a certain man apprehending that he may not be thrown
prostrate in the Fire, whereas the other man (who is not given) is
dearer to me (as compared with him).</english-text>
</hadith>
