<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10402</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>404</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20468, 11052, 11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، أخبرنا هشيم، عن صالح بن صالح
الهمداني، عن الشعبي، قال رأيت رجلا من أهل خراسان سأل الشعبي فقال يا
أبا عمرو إن من قبلنا من أهل خراسان يقولون في الرجل إذا أعتق أمته ثم
تزوجها فهو كالراكب بدنته ‏.‏ فقال الشعبي حدثني أبو بردة بن أبي موسى
عن أبيه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ ثلاثة يؤتون أجرهم
مرتين رجل من أهل الكتاب آمن بنبيه وأدرك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فآمن به واتبعه وصدقه فله أجران وعبد مملوك أدى حق الله تعالى وحق
سيده فله أجران ورجل كانت له أمة فغذاها فأحسن غذاءها ثم أدبها فأحسن
أدبها ثم أعتقها وتزوجها فله أجران ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال الشعبي للخراساني
خذ هذا الحديث بغير شىء ‏.‏ فقد كان الرجل يرحل فيما دون هذا إلى
المدينة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Sha'bi that one
among the citizens of Khurasan asked him: 0 Abu! some of the people
amongst us who belong to Khurasan say that a person who freed his
bondswoman and then married her is like one who rode over a
sacrificial animal. Sha'bi said: Abu Burda b. Abi Musa narrated it
to me on the authority of his father that verily the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: There are three (classes of
persons) who would be given a double reward. One who is amongst the
People of the Book and believed in his apostle and (lived) to see
the time of Apostle Muhammad (may peace be upon him) and affirmed
his faith in him and followed him and attested his truth, for him
is the double reward; and the slave of the master who discharges
all those obligations that he owes to Allah and discharges his
duties that he owes to his master, for him there is a double
reward. And a man who had a bondswoman and fed her and fed her
well, then taught her good manners, and did that well and later on
granted her freedom and married her, for him is the double reward.
Then Sha'bi said: Accept this hadith without (giving) anything.
Formerly a man was (obliged) to travel to Medina even for a smaller
hadith than this.</english-text>
</hadith>
