<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10416</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>418</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 30123, 20208, 20208, 20475, 11322, 11405,
23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم، جميعا عن ابن
علية، - قال ابن أيوب حدثنا ابن علية، - حدثنا يونس، عن إبراهيم بن
يزيد التيمي، - سمعه فيما، أعلم - عن أبيه، عن أبي ذر، أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال يوما ‏"‏ أتدرون أين تذهب هذه الشمس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا
الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إن هذه تجري حتى تنتهي إلى مستقرها تحت
العرش فتخر ساجدة ولا تزال كذلك حتى يقال لها ارتفعي ارجعي من حيث جئت
فترجع فتصبح طالعة من مطلعها ثم تجري حتى تنتهي إلى مستقرها تحت العرش
فتخر ساجدة ولا تزال كذلك حتى يقال لها ارتفعي ارجعي من حيث جئت فترجع
فتصبح طالعة من مطلعها ثم تجري لا يستنكر الناس منها شيئا حتى تنتهي
إلى مستقرها ذاك تحت العرش فيقال لها ارتفعي أصبحي طالعة من مغربك
فتصبح طالعة من مغربها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
أتدرون متى ذاكم ذاك حين لا ينفع نفسا إيمانها لم تكن آمنت من قبل أو
كسبت في إيمانها خيرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Abu Dharr that the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) one day said: Do you
know where the sun goes? They replied: Allah and His Apostle know
best. He (the Holy Prophet) observed: Verily it (the sun) glides
till it reaches its resting place under the Throne. Then it falls
prostrate and remains there until it is asked: Rise up and go to
the place whence you came, and it goes back and continues emerging
out from its rising place and then glides till it reaches its place
of rest under the Throne and falls prostrate and remains in that
state until it is asked: Rise up and return to the place whence you
came, and it returns and emerges out from it rising place and the
it glides (in such a normal way) that the people do not discern
anything ( unusual in it) till it reaches its resting place under
the Throne. Then it would be said to it: Rise up and emerge out
from the place of your setting, and it will rise from the place of
its setting. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said.
Do you know when it would happen? It would happen at the time when
faith will not benefit one who has not previously believed or has
derived no good from the faith.</english-text>
</hadith>
