<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10420</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>422</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو الطاهر، أحمد بن عمرو بن عبد الله بن عمرو بن
سرح أخبرنا ابن وهب، قال أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، قال حدثني عروة بن
الزبير، أن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرته أنها قالت كان
أول ما بدئ به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من الوحى الرؤيا الصادقة
في النوم فكان لا يرى رؤيا إلا جاءت مثل فلق الصبح ثم حبب إليه الخلاء
فكان يخلو بغار حراء يتحنث فيه - وهو التعبد - الليالي أولات العدد
قبل أن يرجع إلى أهله ويتزود لذلك ثم يرجع إلى خديجة فيتزود لمثلها
حتى فجئه الحق وهو في غار حراء فجاءه الملك فقال اقرأ ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما
أنا بقارئ - قال - فأخذني فغطني حتى بلغ مني الجهد ثم أرسلني فقال
اقرأ ‏.‏ قال قلت ما أنا بقارئ - قال - فأخذني فغطني الثانية حتى بلغ
مني الجهد ثم أرسلني فقال اقرأ ‏.‏ فقلت ما أنا بقارئ فأخذني فغطني
الثالثة حتى بلغ مني الجهد ثم أرسلني ‏.‏ فقال ‏{‏ اقرأ باسم ربك الذي
خلق * خلق الإنسان من علق * اقرأ وربك الأكرم * الذي علم بالقلم * علم
الإنسان ما لم يعلم‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجع بها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
ترجف بوادره حتى دخل على خديجة فقال ‏"‏ زملوني زملوني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فزملوه
حتى ذهب عنه الروع ثم قال لخديجة ‏"‏ أى خديجة ما لي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأخبرها
الخبر قال ‏"‏ لقد خشيت على نفسي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت له خديجة كلا أبشر
فوالله لا يخزيك الله أبدا والله إنك لتصل الرحم وتصدق الحديث وتحمل
الكل وتكسب المعدوم وتقري الضيف وتعين على نوائب الحق ‏.‏ فانطلقت به
خديجة حتى أتت به ورقة بن نوفل بن أسد بن عبد العزى وهو ابن عم خديجة
أخي أبيها وكان امرأ تنصر في الجاهلية وكان يكتب الكتاب العربي ويكتب
من الإنجيل بالعربية ما شاء الله أن يكتب وكان شيخا كبيرا قد عمي ‏.‏
فقالت له خديجة أى عم اسمع من ابن أخيك ‏.‏ قال ورقة بن نوفل يا ابن
أخي ماذا ترى فأخبره رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خبر ما رآه فقال له
ورقة هذا الناموس الذي أنزل على موسى صلى الله عليه وسلم يا ليتني
فيها جذعا يا ليتني أكون حيا حين يخرجك قومك ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أومخرجي هم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ورقة نعم لم يأت رجل قط
بما جئت به إلا عودي وإن يدركني يومك أنصرك نصرا مؤزرا ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>A'isha, the wife of the Apostle of Allah (may peace
be upon him), reported: The first (form) with which was started the
revelation to the Messenger of Allah was the true vision in sleep.
And he did not see any vision but it came like the bright gleam of
dawn. Thenceforth solitude became dear to him and he used to
seclude himself in the cave of Hira', where he would engage in
tahannuth (and that is a worship for a number of nights) before
returning to his family and getting provisions again for this
purpose. He would then return to Khadija and take provisions for a
like period, till Truth came upon him while he was in the cave of
Hira'. There came to him the angel and said: Recite, to which he
replied: I am not lettered. He took hold of me [the Apostle said]
and pressed me, till I was hard pressed; thereafter he let me off
and said: Recite. I said: I am not lettered. He then again took
hold of me and pressed me for the second time till I was hard
pressed and then let me off and said: Recite, to which I replied: I
am not lettered. He took hold of me and pressed me for the third
time, till I was hard pressed and then let me go and said: Recite
in the name of your Lord Who created, created man from a clot of
blood. Recite. And your most bountiful Lord is He Who taught the
use of pen, taught man what he knew not (al-Qur'an, xcvi. 1-4).
Then the Prophet returned therewith, his heart was trembling, and
he went to Khadija and said: Wrap me up, wrap me up! So they
wrapped him till the fear had left him. He then said to Khadija: O
Khadija! what has happened to me? and he informed her of the
happening, saying: I fear for myself. She replied: It can't be. Be
happy. I swear by Allah that He shall never humiliate you. By
Allah, you join ties of relationship, you speak the truth, you bear
people's burden, you help the destitute, you entertain guests, and
you help against the vicissitudes which affect people. Khadija then
took him to Waraqa b. Naufal b. Asad b. 'Abd al-'Uzza, and he was
the son of Khadija's uncle, i. e., the brother of her father. And
he was the man who had embraced Christianity in the Days of
Ignorance (i. e. before Islam) and he used to write books in Arabic
and, therefore, wrote Injil in Arabic as God willed that he should
write. He was very old and had become blind Khadija said to him: O
uncle! listen to the son of your brother. Waraqa b. Naufal said: O
my nephew! what did you see? The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him), then, informed him what he had seen, and Waraqa said to
him: It is namus that God sent down to Musa. Would that I were then
(during your prophetic career) a young man. Would that I might be
alive when your people would expel you! The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) said: Will they drive me out? Waraqa said: Yes.
Never came a man with a like of what you have brought but met
hostilities. If I see your day I shall help you
wholeheartedly.</english-text>
</hadith>
