<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10428</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>429</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا شيبان بن فروخ، حدثنا حماد بن سلمة، حدثنا ثابت
البناني، عن أنس بن مالك، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
أتيت بالبراق - وهو دابة أبيض طويل فوق الحمار ودون البغل يضع حافره
عند منتهى طرفه - قال فركبته حتى أتيت بيت المقدس - قال - فربطته
بالحلقة التي يربط به الأنبياء - قال - ثم دخلت المسجد فصليت فيه
ركعتين ثم خرجت فجاءني جبريل - عليه السلام - بإناء من خمر وإناء من
لبن فاخترت اللبن فقال جبريل صلى الله عليه وسلم اخترت الفطرة ‏.‏ ثم
عرج بنا إلى السماء فاستفتح جبريل فقيل من أنت قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن
معك قال محمد ‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا
أنا بآدم فرحب بي ودعا لي بخير ‏.‏ ثم عرج بنا إلى السماء الثانية
فاستفتح جبريل عليه السلام ‏.‏ فقيل من أنت قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك
قال محمد ‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا أنا
بابنى الخالة عيسى ابن مريم ويحيى بن زكرياء صلوات الله عليهما فرحبا
ودعوا لي بخير ‏.‏ ثم عرج بي إلى السماء الثالثة فاستفتح جبريل ‏.‏
فقيل من أنت قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا أنا بيوسف
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا هو قد أعطي شطر الحسن فرحب ودعا لي بخير ‏.‏
ثم عرج بنا إلى السماء الرابعة فاستفتح جبريل - عليه السلام - قيل من
هذا قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد ‏.‏ قال وقد بعث إليه قال قد
بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا أنا بإدريس فرحب ودعا لي بخير قال الله عز
وجل ‏{‏ ورفعناه مكانا عليا‏}‏ ثم عرج بنا إلى السماء الخامسة فاستفتح
جبريل ‏.‏ قيل من هذا قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد ‏.‏ قيل وقد
بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا أنا بهارون صلى الله عليه
وسلم فرحب ودعا لي بخير ‏.‏ ثم عرج بنا إلى السماء السادسة فاستفتح
جبريل عليه السلام ‏.‏ قيل من هذا قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد
‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏ ففتح لنا فإذا أنا بموسى
صلى الله عليه وسلم فرحب ودعا لي بخير ‏.‏ ثم عرج بنا إلى السماء
السابعة فاستفتح جبريل فقيل من هذا قال جبريل ‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال
محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه قال قد بعث إليه ‏.‏
ففتح لنا فإذا أنا بإبراهيم صلى الله عليه وسلم مسندا ظهره إلى البيت
المعمور وإذا هو يدخله كل يوم سبعون ألف ملك لا يعودون إليه ثم ذهب بي
إلى السدرة المنتهى وإذا ورقها كآذان الفيلة وإذا ثمرها كالقلال - قال
- فلما غشيها من أمر الله ما غشي تغيرت فما أحد من خلق الله يستطيع أن
ينعتها من حسنها ‏.‏ فأوحى الله إلى ما أوحى ففرض على خمسين صلاة في
كل يوم وليلة فنزلت إلى موسى صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ما فرض ربك على
أمتك قلت خمسين صلاة ‏.‏ قال ارجع إلى ربك فاسأله التخفيف فإن أمتك لا
يطيقون ذلك فإني قد بلوت بني إسرائيل وخبرتهم ‏.‏ قال فرجعت إلى ربي
فقلت يا رب خفف على أمتي ‏.‏ فحط عني خمسا فرجعت إلى موسى فقلت حط عني
خمسا ‏.‏ قال إن أمتك لا يطيقون ذلك فارجع إلى ربك فاسأله التخفيف ‏.‏
- قال - فلم أزل أرجع بين ربي تبارك وتعالى وبين موسى - عليه السلام -
حتى قال يا محمد إنهن خمس صلوات كل يوم وليلة لكل صلاة عشر فذلك خمسون
صلاة ‏.‏ ومن هم بحسنة فلم يعملها كتبت له حسنة فإن عملها كتبت له
عشرا ومن هم بسيئة فلم يعملها لم تكتب شيئا فإن عملها كتبت سيئة واحدة
- قال - فنزلت حتى انتهيت إلى موسى صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته فقال
ارجع إلى ربك فاسأله التخفيف ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقلت قد رجعت إلى ربي حتى استحييت منه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Anas b. Malik that
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: I was brought
al-Buraq Who is an animal white and long, larger than a donkey but
smaller than a mule, who would place his hoof a distance equal to
the range of version. I mounted it and came to the Temple (Bait
Maqdis in Jerusalem), then tethered it to the ring used by the
prophets. I entered the mosque and prayed two rak'ahs in it, and
then came out and Gabriel brought me a vessel of wine and a vessel
of milk. I chose the milk, and Gabriel said: You have chosen the
natural thing. Then he took me to heaven. Gabriel then asked the
(gate of heaven) to be opened and he was asked who he was. He
replied: Gabriel. He was again asked: Who is with you? He (Gabriel)
said: Muhammad. It was said: Has he been sent for? Gabriel replied:
He has indeed been sent for. And (the door of the heaven) was
opened for us and lo! we saw Adam. He welcomed me and prayed for my
good. Then we ascended to the second heaven. Gabriel (peace be upon
him) (asked the door of heaven to be opened), and he was asked who
he was. He answered: Gabriel; and was again asked: Who is with you?
He replied: Muhammad. It was said: Has he been sent for? He
replied: He has indeed been sent for. The gate was opened. When I
entered 'Isa b. Maryam and Yahya b. Zakariya (peace be upon both of
them), cousins from the maternal side. welcomed me and prayed for
my good Then I was taken to the third heaven and Gabriel asked for
the opening (of the door). He was asked: Who are you? He replied:
Gabriel. He was (again) asked: Who is with you? He replied Muhammad
(may peace be upon him). It was said: Has he been sent for? He
replied He has indeed been sent for. (The gate) was opened for us
and I saw Yusuf (peace of Allah be upon him) who had been given
half of (world) beauty. He welcomed me prayed for my well-being.
Then he ascended with us to the fourth heaven. Gabriel (peace be
upon him) asked for the (gate) to be opened, and it was said: Who
is he? He replied: Gabriel. It was (again) said: Who is with you?
He said: Muhammad. It was said: Has he been sent for? He replied:
He has indeed been sent for. The (gate) was opened for us, and lo!
Idris was there. He welcomed me and prayed for my well-being (About
him) Allah, the Exalted and the Glorious, has said:" We elevated
him (Idris) to the exalted position" (Qur'an xix. 57). Then he
ascended with us to the fifth heaven and Gabriel asked for the
(gate) to be opened. It was said: Who is he? He replied Gabriel. It
was (again) said: Who is with thee? He replied: Muhammad. It was
said Has he been sent for? He replied: He has indeed been sent for.
(The gate) was opened for us and then I was with Harun (Aaron-peace
of Allah be upon him). He welcomed me prayed for my well-being.
Then I was taken to the sixth heaven. Gabriel (peace be upon him)
asked for the door to be opened. It was said: Who is he? He
replied: Gabriel. It was said: Who is with thee? He replied:
Muhammad. It was said: Has he been sent for? He replied: He has
indeed been sent for. (The gate) was opened for us and there I was
with Musa (Moses peace be upon him) He welcomed me and prayed for
my well-being. Then I was taken up to the seventh heaven. Gabriel
asked the (gate) to be opened. It was said: Who is he? He said:
Gabriel It was said. Who is with thee? He replied: Muhammad (may
peace be upon him.) It was said: Has he been sent for? He replied:
He has indeed been sent for. (The gate) was opened for us and there
I found Ibrahim (Abraham peace be upon him) reclining against the
Bait-ul-Ma'mur and there enter into it seventy thousand angels
every day, never to visit (this place) again. Then I was taken to
Sidrat-ul-Muntaha whose leaves were like elephant ears and its
fruit like big earthenware vessels. And when it was covered by the
Command of Allah, it underwent such a change that none amongst the
creation has the power to praise its beauty. Then Allah revealed to
me a revelation and He made obligatory for me fifty prayers every
day and night. Then I went down to Moses (peace be upon him) and he
said: What has your Lord enjoined upon your Ummah? I said: Fifty
prayers. He said: Return to thy Lord and beg for reduction (in the
number of prayers), for your community shallnot be able to bear
this burden. as I have put to test the children of Isra'il and
tried them (and found them too weak to bear such a heavy burden).
He (the Holy Prophet) said: I went back to my Lord and said: My
Lord, make things lighter for my Ummah. (The Lord) reduced five
prayers for me. I went down to Moses and said. (The Lord) reduced
five (prayers) for me, He said: Verily thy Ummah shall not be able
to bear this burden; return to thy Lord and ask Him to make things
lighter. I then kept going back and forth between my Lord Blessed
and Exalted and Moses, till He said: There are five prayers every
day and night. O Muhammad, each being credited as ten, so that
makes fifty prayers. He who intends to do a good deed and does not
do it will have a good deed recorded for him; and if he does it, it
will be recorded for him as ten; whereas he who intends to do an
evil deed and does not do, it will not be recorded for him; and if
he does it, only one evil deed will be recorded. I then came down
and when I came to Moses and informed him, he said: Go back to thy
Lord and ask Him to make things lighter. Upon this the Messenger of
Allah remarked: I returned to my Lord until I felt ashamed before
Him.</english-text>
</hadith>
