<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10455</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>457</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20208, 11052, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، عن داود،
عن الشعبي، عن مسروق، قال كنت متكئا عند عائشة فقالت يا أبا عائشة
ثلاث من تكلم بواحدة منهن فقد أعظم على الله الفرية ‏.‏ قلت ما هن
قالت من زعم أن محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم رأى ربه فقد أعظم على الله
الفرية ‏.‏ قال وكنت متكئا فجلست فقلت يا أم المؤمنين أنظريني ولا
تعجليني ألم يقل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ ولقد رآه بالأفق المبين‏}‏ ‏{‏ ولقد
رآه نزلة أخرى‏}‏ ‏.‏ فقالت أنا أول هذه الأمة سأل عن ذلك رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ إنما هو جبريل لم أره على صورته التي خلق
عليها غير هاتين المرتين رأيته منهبطا من السماء سادا عظم خلقه ما بين
السماء إلى الأرض ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت أولم تسمع أن الله يقول ‏{‏ لا تدركه
الأبصار وهو يدرك الأبصار وهو اللطيف الخبير‏}‏ أولم تسمع أن الله
يقول ‏{‏ وما كان لبشر أن يكلمه الله إلا وحيا أو من وراء حجاب أو
يرسل رسولا فيوحي بإذنه ما يشاء إنه علي حكيم‏}‏ قالت ومن زعم أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كتم شيئا من كتاب الله فقد أعظم على الله
الفرية والله يقول ‏{‏ يا أيها الرسول بلغ ما أنزل إليك من ربك وإن لم
تفعل فما بلغت رسالته‏}‏ ‏.‏ قالت ومن زعم أنه يخبر بما يكون في غد
فقد أعظم على الله الفرية والله يقول ‏{‏ قل لا يعلم من في السموات
والأرض الغيب إلا الله‏}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is narrated on the authority of Masruq that he
said: I was resting at (the house of) 'A'isha that she said: O Abu
'A'isha (kunya of Masruq), there are three things, and he who
affirmed even one of them fabricated the greatest lie against
Allah. I asked that they were. She said: He who presumed that
Muhammad (may peace be upon him) saw his Lord (with his ocular
vision) fabricated the greatest lie against Allah. I was reclining
but then sat up and said: Mother of the Faithful, wait a bit and do
not be in a haste. Has not Allah (Mighty and Majestic) said:" And
truly he saw him on the clear horizon" (al-Qur'an, lxxxi. 23) and"
he saw Him in another descent" (al-Qur'an, iiii. 13)? She said: I
am the first of this Ummah who asked the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) about it, and he said: Verily he is Gabriel. I
have never seen him in his original form in which he was created
except on those two occasions (to which these verses refer) ; I saw
him descending from the heaven and filling (the space) from the sky
to the earth with the greatness of his bodily structure. She said:
Have you not heard Allah saying." Eyes comprehend Him not, but He
comprehends (all) vision. and He is Subtle, and All-Aware"
(al-Qur'an, v. 104)? (She, i. e. 'A'isha, further said): Have you
not heard that, verily, Allah says:" And it is not vouchsafed to a
human being that Allah should speak unto him otherwise than by
revelation, or from behind a veil, or that He sendeth a messenger
(angel), so that he revealth whatsoever He wills. Verily He is
Exalted. Wise" (al. Qur'an, xii. 51) She said: He who presumes that
the Messengerof Allah (may peace be upon him) concealed anything,
from the Book, of Allah fabricates the greatest lie against Allah.
Allah says:" O Messenger! deliver that which has been revealed to
thee from thy Lord, and if thou do (it) not, thou hast not
delivered His message" (al-Qur'an, v. 67). She said: He who
presumes that he would inform about what was going to happen
tomorrow fabricates the greatest lie against Allah. And Allah says"
Say thou (Muhammad): None in the heavens and the earth knoweth the
unseen save Allah" (al-Qur'an, xxvii 65).</english-text>
</hadith>
