<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10467</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>469</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20184, 20150, 11013, 11206, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا أبي،
عن ابن شهاب، عن عطاء بن يزيد الليثي، أن أبا هريرة، أخبره أن ناسا
قالوا لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يا رسول الله هل نرى ربنا يوم
القيامة فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل تضارون في رؤية
القمر ليلة البدر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل
تضارون في الشمس ليس دونها سحاب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا يا رسول الله ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإنكم ترونه كذلك يجمع الله الناس يوم القيامة فيقول من كان
يعبد شيئا فليتبعه ‏.‏ فيتبع من كان يعبد الشمس الشمس ويتبع من كان
يعبد القمر القمر ويتبع من كان يعبد الطواغيت الطواغيت وتبقى هذه
الأمة فيها منافقوها فيأتيهم الله - تبارك وتعالى - في صورة غير صورته
التي يعرفون فيقول أنا ربكم ‏.‏ فيقولون نعوذ بالله منك هذا مكاننا
حتى يأتينا ربنا فإذا جاء ربنا عرفناه ‏.‏ فيأتيهم الله تعالى في
صورته التي يعرفون فيقول أنا ربكم ‏.‏ فيقولون أنت ربنا ‏.‏ فيتبعونه
ويضرب الصراط بين ظهرى جهنم فأكون أنا وأمتي أول من يجيز ولا يتكلم
يومئذ إلا الرسل ودعوى الرسل يومئذ اللهم سلم سلم ‏.‏ وفي جهنم كلاليب
مثل شوك السعدان هل رأيتم السعدان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم يا رسول الله ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإنها مثل شوك السعدان غير أنه لا يعلم ما قدر عظمها إلا الله
تخطف الناس بأعمالهم فمنهم المؤمن بقي بعمله ومنهم المجازى حتى ينجى
حتى إذا فرغ الله من القضاء بين العباد وأراد أن يخرج برحمته من أراد
من أهل النار أمر الملائكة أن يخرجوا من النار من كان لا يشرك بالله
شيئا ممن أراد الله تعالى أن يرحمه ممن يقول لا إله إلا الله ‏.‏
فيعرفونهم في النار يعرفونهم بأثر السجود تأكل النار من ابن آدم إلا
أثر السجود حرم الله على النار أن تأكل أثر السجود ‏.‏ فيخرجون من
النار وقد امتحشوا فيصب عليهم ماء الحياة فينبتون منه كما تنبت الحبة
في حميل السيل ثم يفرغ الله تعالى من القضاء بين العباد ويبقى رجل
مقبل بوجهه على النار وهو آخر أهل الجنة دخولا الجنة فيقول أى رب اصرف
وجهي عن النار فإنه قد قشبني ريحها وأحرقني ذكاؤها فيدعو الله ما شاء
الله أن يدعوه ثم يقول الله تبارك وتعالى هل عسيت إن فعلت ذلك بك أن
تسأل غيره ‏.‏ فيقول لا أسألك غيره ‏.‏ ويعطي ربه من عهود ومواثيق ما
شاء الله فيصرف الله وجهه عن النار فإذا أقبل على الجنة ورآها سكت ما
شاء الله أن يسكت ثم يقول أى رب قدمني إلى باب الجنة ‏.‏ فيقول الله
له أليس قد أعطيت عهودك ومواثيقك لا تسألني غير الذي أعطيتك ويلك يا
ابن آدم ما أغدرك ‏.‏ فيقول أى رب ويدعو الله حتى يقول له فهل عسيت إن
أعطيتك ذلك أن تسأل غيره ‏.‏ فيقول لا وعزتك ‏.‏ فيعطي ربه ما شاء
الله من عهود ومواثيق فيقدمه إلى باب الجنة فإذا قام على باب الجنة
انفهقت له الجنة فرأى ما فيها من الخير والسرور فيسكت ما شاء الله أن
يسكت ثم يقول أى رب أدخلني الجنة ‏.‏ فيقول الله تبارك وتعالى له أليس
قد أعطيت عهودك ومواثيقك أن لا تسأل غير ما أعطيت ويلك يا ابن آدم ما
أغدرك ‏.‏ فيقول أى رب لا أكون أشقى خلقك ‏.‏ فلا يزال يدعو الله حتى
يضحك الله تبارك وتعالى منه فإذا ضحك الله منه قال ادخل الجنة ‏.‏
فإذا دخلها قال الله له تمنه ‏.‏ فيسأل ربه ويتمنى حتى إن الله ليذكره
من كذا وكذا حتى إذا انقطعت به الأماني قال الله تعالى ذلك لك ومثله
معه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عطاء بن يزيد وأبو سعيد الخدري مع أبي هريرة لا يرد
عليه من حديثه شيئا ‏.‏ حتى إذا حدث أبو هريرة أن الله قال لذلك الرجل
ومثله معه ‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد وعشرة أمثاله معه يا أبا هريرة ‏.‏ قال
أبو هريرة ما حفظت إلا قوله ذلك لك ومثله معه ‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد أشهد
أني حفظت من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قوله ذلك لك وعشرة أمثاله
‏.‏ قال أبو هريرة وذلك الرجل آخر أهل الجنة دخولا الجنة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Haraira reported: The people said to the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him): Messenger of Allah,
shall we see our Lord on the Day of Resurrection? The Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Do you feel any trouble in
seeing the moon on the night when it is full? They said: Messenger
of Allah, no. He (the Messenger) further said: Do you feel any
trouble in seeing the sun, when there is no cloud over it? They
said: Messenger of Allah. no. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Verily
you would see Him like this (as you see the sun and the moon). God
will gather people on the Day of Resurrection and say: Let every
people follow what they worshipped. Those who worshipped the sun
would follow the sun, and those who worshipped the moon would
follow the moon, and those who worshipped the devils would follow
the devils. This Ummah (of Islam) alone would be left behind and
there would be hypocrites too amongst it. Allah would then come to
them in a form other than His own Form, recognisable to them, and
would say: I am your Lord. They would say: We take refuge with
Allah from thee. We will stay here till our Lord comes to us. and
when our Lord would come we would recognise Him. Subsequently Allah
would come to them in His own Form, recognisable to them, and say:
I am your Lord. They would say: Thou art our Lord. And they would
follow Him, and a bridge would be set over the Hell; and I (the
Holy Prophet) and my Ummah would be the first to pass over it; and
none but the messengers would speak on that day, and the prayer of
the messengers on that day would be: O Allah! grant safety, grant
safety. In Hell, there would be long spits like the thorns of
Sa'dan He (the Holy Prophet) said: Have you seen Sa'dan? They
replied: Yes, Messenger of Allah. He said: Verily those (hooks)
would be like the thorns of Sa'dan, but no one knows their size
except Allah. These would seize people for their misdeeds. Some of
them would escape for their (good) deeds, and some would be
rewarded for their deeds till they get salvation. When Allah would
finish judging His bondsmen and because of His mercy decide to take
out of Hell such people as He pleases. He would command the angels
to bring out those who had not associated anything with Allah; to
whom Allah decided to show mercy. those who would say: There is no
god but Allah. They (the angels) would recognise them in the Fire
by the marks of prostration, for Hell-fire will devour everything
(limb) of the sons of Adam except the marks of prostration. Allah
has forbidden the fire to consume the marks of prostration. They
will be taken out of the Fire having been burnt, and the water of
life would be poured over them, and they will sprout as seed does
In the silt carried by flood. Then Allah would finish judging
amongst His bondsmen; but a man who will be the last to enter
Paradise will remain facing Hell and will say: O my Lord I turn my
face away from Hell, for its air has poisoned me ard its blaze has
burnt me. He will then call to Allah as long as Allah would wish
that he should call to Him. Then Allah, Blessed and Exalted, would
say: If I did that, perhaps you would ask for more than that. He
would say: I would not ask You more than this, and he would give
his Lord covenants and agreements as Allah wished, and so He would
turn his face away from the Fire When he turns towards the Paradise
and sees it, he will remain silent as long as Allah wishes him to
remain so. He will then say: O my Lord I bring me forward to the
gate of the Paradise. Allah would say to him: Did you not give
covenants and agreements that you would not ask for anything
besides what I had given you. Woe to thee! O son of Adam, how
treacherous you are! He would say: O my Lord! and would continue
calling to Allah till He would say to him: If I grant you that,
perhaps you will ask for more. He will reply: No, by Thy greatness,
and he will give His Lord promises and covenants as Allah had
wished. He would then bring him to the gate of the Paradise, and
when he would stand at the gate of the Paradise, it would lay open
before him. and he would see the bounty and the joy that there is
in it. He would remain quiet as long as Allah would desire him to
remain silent. He would then say: O my Lord, admit me to Paradise.
Allah. Blessed and Exalted, would say: Did you not give covenants
and agreements that you would not ask for anything more than what I
had granted you? Woe to you! son of Adam, how treacherous you are!
And he would say: O my Lord, I do not wish to be the most miserable
of Thy creatures. He would continue calling upon Allah till Allah,
Blessed and Exalted, would laugh. When Allah would laugh at him, He
would say: Enter the Paradise. When he would enter, Allah would
say: State your wish. He would express his wishes till Allah would
remind him (the desire of) such and such (things). When his desires
would be exhausted Allah would say: That is for thee and, besides
it, the like of it also. 'Ata' b. Yazid said: Abu Sa'id al-Khudri
was with Abu Huraira and be did not reject anything from the hadith
narrated by him, but when Abu Huraira narrated:" Allah said to that
man; ind its like along with it," Abu Sa'id said:" Ten like it
along with it," O Abu Huraira. Abu Huraira said: I do not remember
except the words:" That is for you and a similar one along with
it." Abu Sa'id said: I bear witness to the fact that I remembered
from the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) his words:"
That is for thee and ten like it." Abu Huraira said: That man was
the last of those deserving of Paradise to enter
Paradise.</english-text>
</hadith>
