<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10477</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>479</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 30123, 20028, 30203, 20028, 11067, 11051,
11370, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، وإسحاق بن إبراهيم الحنظلي،
كلاهما عن جرير، قال عثمان حدثنا جرير، عن منصور، عن إبراهيم، عن
عبيدة، عن عبد الله بن مسعود، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إني لأعلم آخر أهل النار خروجا منها وآخر أهل الجنة دخولا الجنة
رجل يخرج من النار حبوا فيقول الله تبارك وتعالى له اذهب فادخل الجنة
فيأتيها فيخيل إليه أنها ملأى فيرجع فيقول يا رب وجدتها ملأى ‏.‏
فيقول الله تبارك وتعالى له اذهب فادخل الجنة - قال - فيأتيها فيخيل
إليه أنها ملأى فيرجع فيقول يا رب وجدتها ملأى فيقول الله له اذهب
فادخل الجنة فإن لك مثل الدنيا وعشرة أمثالها أو إن لك عشرة أمثال
الدنيا - قال - فيقول أتسخر بي - أو أتضحك بي - وأنت الملك ‏"‏ قال
لقد رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضحك حتى بدت نواجذه ‏.‏ قال
فكان يقال ذاك أدنى أهل الجنة منزلة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. Mas'ud reported that the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: I know the last of the
inhabitants of Fire to be taken out therefrom, and the last of the
inhabitants of Paradise to enter it. A man will come out of the
Fire crawling. Then Allah, the Blessed and Exalted will say to him:
Go and enter Paradise. So he would come to it and it would appear
to him as if it were full. He would go back and say: O my Lord! I
found it full. Allah, the Blessed and Exalted, would say to him: Go
and enter Paradise. He would come and perceive as if it were full.
He would return and say: O my Lord! I found it full. Allah would
say to him: Go and enter Paradise, for there is for you the like of
the world and ten times like it, or for you is ten times the like
of this world. He (the narrator) said. He (that man) would say: Art
Thou making a fun of me? or Art Thou laughing at me. though Thou
art the King? He (the narrator) said: I saw the Messenger of Allah
laugh till his front teeth were visible. And it was said: That
would be the lowest rank among the inhabitants of
Paradise.</english-text>
</hadith>
