<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10480</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>482</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20365, 20394, 11173, 11542, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا يحيى بن أبي بكير،
حدثنا زهير بن محمد، عن سهيل بن أبي صالح، عن النعمان بن أبي عياش، عن
أبي سعيد الخدري، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن أدنى
أهل الجنة منزلة رجل صرف الله وجهه عن النار قبل الجنة ومثل له شجرة
ذات ظل فقال أى رب قدمني إلى هذه الشجرة أكون في ظلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وساق
الحديث بنحو حديث ابن مسعود ولم يذكر ‏"‏ فيقول يا ابن آدم ما يصريني
منك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ إلى آخر الحديث وزاد فيه ‏"‏ ويذكره الله سل كذا وكذا
فإذا انقطعت به الأماني قال الله هو لك وعشرة أمثاله - قال - ثم يدخل
بيته فتدخل عليه زوجتاه من الحور العين فتقولان الحمد لله الذي أحياك
لنا وأحيانا لك - قال - فيقول ما أعطي أحد مثل ما أعطيت ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is transmitted from Abu Sa'id al-Khudri that,
verily, the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said:
Amongst the inhabitants of Paradise the lowest in rank will be the
person whose face Allah would turn away from the Fire towards the
Paradise, and make a shady tree appear before him. He would say: O
my Lord! direct my steps to this tree so that I (should enjoy) its
shade; and the rest of the hadith is like that narrated by Ibn
Mas'ud, but he did not mention:" He (Allah) would say: O son of
Adam! what will bring an end to your making requests to Me" to the
end of the tradition. In it, he added: Allah will remind him: Ask
such and such, and when his expectations would be realised, Allah
would say: That is for you, and ten times as much. He said that he
would then enter his house and his two wives with large and dark
eyes would enter after him. They will say: Praise be to Allah, Who
has created you for us and us for you. He will say: No one has been
given the like of what I have been given.</english-text>
</hadith>
