<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10491</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>493</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>38834, 20348, 11665</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا حجاج بن الشاعر، حدثنا الفضل بن دكين، حدثنا أبو
عاصم، - يعني محمد بن أبي أيوب - قال حدثني يزيد الفقير، قال كنت قد
شغفني رأى من رأى الخوارج فخرجنا في عصابة ذوي عدد نريد أن نحج ثم
نخرج على الناس - قال - فمررنا على المدينة فإذا جابر بن عبد الله
يحدث القوم - جالس إلى سارية - عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
فإذا هو قد ذكر الجهنميين - قال - فقلت له يا صاحب رسول الله ما هذا
الذي تحدثون والله يقول ‏{‏ إنك من تدخل النار فقد أخزيته‏}‏ و ‏{‏
كلما أرادوا أن يخرجوا منها أعيدوا فيها‏}‏ فما هذا الذي تقولون قال
فقال أتقرأ القرآن قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال فهل سمعت بمقام محمد - عليه السلام
- يعني الذي يبعثه الله فيه قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال فإنه مقام محمد صلى الله
عليه وسلم المحمود الذي يخرج الله به من يخرج ‏.‏ - قال - ثم نعت وضع
الصراط ومر الناس عليه - قال - وأخاف أن لا أكون أحفظ ذاك - قال - غير
أنه قد زعم أن قوما يخرجون من النار بعد أن يكونوا فيها - قال - يعني
فيخرجون كأنهم عيدان السماسم ‏.‏ قال فيدخلون نهرا من أنهار الجنة
فيغتسلون فيه فيخرجون كأنهم القراطيس ‏.‏ فرجعنا قلنا ويحكم أترون
الشيخ يكذب على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرجعنا فلا والله ما خرج
منا غير رجل واحد أو كما قال أبو نعيم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Yazid al-Faqir said: This view of the Khwarij (i. e.
those who commit major sins and would be eternally doomed to Hell)
had obsessed me, and we set out in a large group intending to
perform the hajj and then going to the people (for the propagation
of the views of the Khwarij). He (the narrator) said: We happened
to past by Medina and found there Jabir b. 'Abdullah sitting near a
column narrating to the people (the ahadith of) the Holy Prophet
(may peace be upon him). When he mentioned the inhabitants of Hell,
I said: O companion of the Messenger of Allah what is this that
thou narrateth, whereas Allah sayeth:" Verily whomsoever Thou shall
commit to the Fire, Thou indeed humillateth him" (al-Qur'an, iii.
192) ; and All those who endeavoured to get out of that would be
thrown back into it" (al-Qur'an, xxxi i. 20)? So what is it that
you say? He said: Have you read the Qur'an? I said: Yes. He said:
Have you heard about' the (exalted) position of Muhammad (may peace
be upon him), i. e. to which Allah would raise, him? I said: Yes.
He said: Verily the position of Muhammad (may peace be upon him) is
that of great glory and that is by which Allah would bring out
whornsoever He would wish to bring out. He then described the Path
(the Bridge) and the passing of the people over it, and said: I am
afraid I may not have remembered (other things) but this much is
still in my memory that people would come out of the Hell after
having gone into it, and he said: They would come out of it as if
they were the wood of the ebony tree. He (the narrator said: They
would enter a river, one or the rivers of Paradise, and would bathe
in it, and then come out as if they were (white like) paper. We
then turned back and said: Woe be upon you! How can this old man
tell a lie against the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)?
We turned back (from the views of the Khwarij), and by God every
one of us abandoned this (band of Khwarij) except one man. A
similar statement has been made by Abu Nu'aim.</english-text>
</hadith>
