<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10527</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>529</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Faith - كتاب الإيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20318, 11060, 11381, 11050, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا أبو كريب، محمد بن العلاء حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن
الأعمش، عن عمرو بن مرة، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس، قال لما نزلت
هذه الآية ‏{‏ وأنذر عشيرتك الأقربين‏}‏ ورهطك منهم المخلصين ‏.‏ خرج
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى صعد الصفا فهتف ‏"‏ يا صباحاه ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقالوا من هذا الذي يهتف قالوا محمد ‏.‏ فاجتمعوا إليه فقال ‏"‏
يا بني فلان يا بني فلان يا بني فلان يا بني عبد مناف يا بني عبد
المطلب ‏"‏ فاجتمعوا إليه فقال ‏"‏ أرأيتكم لو أخبرتكم أن خيلا تخرج
بسفح هذا الجبل أكنتم مصدقي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ما جربنا عليك كذبا ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ فإني نذير لكم بين يدى عذاب شديد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال أبو لهب تبا لك
أما جمعتنا إلا لهذا ثم قام فنزلت هذه السورة تبت يدا أبي لهب وقد تب
‏.‏ كذا قرأ الأعمش إلى آخر السورة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It is reported on the authority of Ibn 'Abbas that
when this verse was revealed: " And warn thy nearest kindred" (and
thy group of selected people among them) the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) set off till he climbed Safa' and called
loudly: Be on your guard! They said: Who is it calling aloud? They
said: Muhammad. They gathered round him, and he said: O sons of so
and so, O sons of so and so, O sons of 'Abd Manaf, O sons of 'Abd
al-Muttalib, and they gathered around him. He (the Apostle) said:
If I were to inform you that there were horsemen emerging out of
the foot of this mountain, would you believe me? They said: We have
not experienced any lie from you. He said: Well, I am a warner to
you before a severe torment. He (the narrator) said that Abu Lahab
then said: Destruction to you! Is it for this you have gathered us?
He (the Holy Prophet) then stood up, and this verse was revealed:"
Perish the hands of Abu Lahab, and he indeed perished" (cxi. 1).
A'mash recited this to the end of the Sura.</english-text>
</hadith>
