<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10603</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>249</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Purification - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 30251, 30367, 20387, 20155, 11418, 10606,
11884, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وسريج بن يونس، وقتيبة بن سعيد،
وعلي بن حجر، جميعا عن إسماعيل بن جعفر، - قال ابن أيوب حدثنا
إسماعيل، - أخبرني العلاء، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أتى المقبرة فقال ‏"‏ السلام عليكم دار قوم مؤمنين
وإنا إن شاء الله بكم لاحقون وددت أنا قد رأينا إخواننا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا
أولسنا إخوانك يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ أنتم أصحابي وإخواننا الذين لم
يأتوا بعد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا كيف تعرف من لم يأت بعد من أمتك يا رسول
الله فقال ‏"‏ أرأيت لو أن رجلا له خيل غر محجلة بين ظهرى خيل دهم بهم
ألا يعرف خيله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا بلى يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنهم
يأتون غرا محجلين من الوضوء وأنا فرطهم على الحوض ألا ليذادن رجال عن
حوضي كما يذاد البعير الضال أناديهم ألا هلم ‏.‏ فيقال إنهم قد بدلوا
بعدك ‏.‏ فأقول سحقا سحقا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported: The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) came to the graveyard and said: Peace be upon
you! the abode of the believing people and we, if God so wills, are
about to join you. I love to see my brothers. They (the hearers)
said: Arn't we your brothers-Messenger of Allah? He said: You are
my companions, and our brothers are those who have, so far, not
come into the world. They said: Messenger of Allah, how would you
recognise those persons of your Ummah who have not yet been born?
He said: Supposing a man had horses with white blazes on fore-
heads and legs among horses which were all black, tell me, would he
not recognise his own horses? They said: Certainly. Messenger of
Allah. He said: They would come with white faces and arms and legs
owing to ablution, and I would arrive at the Cistern before them.
Some people would be driven away from my Cistern as the stray camel
is driven away. I would call out. Come. come. Then it would be said
(to me): These people changed themselves after you, and I would
say: Be off, be off.</english-text>
</hadith>
