<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10803</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>349</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Menstruation - كتاب الحيض</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20280, 11311, 11281, 11901, 41, 30170, 20246,
20295, 11281, 11901</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله
الأنصاري، حدثنا هشام بن حسان، حدثنا حميد بن هلال، عن أبي بردة، عن
أبي موسى الأشعري، ح وحدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، - وهذا
حديثه - حدثنا هشام، عن حميد بن هلال، قال - ولا أعلمه إلا عن أبي
بردة، - عن أبي موسى، قال اختلف في ذلك رهط من المهاجرين والأنصار
فقال الأنصاريون لا يجب الغسل إلا من الدفق أو من الماء ‏.‏ وقال
المهاجرون بل إذا خالط فقد وجب الغسل ‏.‏ قال قال أبو موسى فأنا
أشفيكم من ذلك ‏.‏ فقمت فاستأذنت على عائشة فأذن لي فقلت لها يا أماه
- أو يا أم المؤمنين - إني أريد أن أسألك عن شىء وإني أستحييك ‏.‏
فقالت لا تستحيي أن تسألني عما كنت سائلا عنه أمك التي ولدتك فإنما
أنا أمك ‏.‏ قلت فما يوجب الغسل قالت على الخبير سقطت قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إذا جلس بين شعبها الأربع ومس الختان الختان
فقد وجب الغسل ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa reported: There cropped up a difference of
opinion between a group of Muhajirs (Emigrants and a group of Ansar
(Helpers) (and the point of dispute was) that the Ansar said: The
bath (because of sexual intercourse) becomes obligatory only-when
the semen spurts out or ejaculates. But the Muhajirs said: When a
man has sexual intercourse (with the woman), a bath becomes
obligatory (no matter whether or not there is seminal emission or
ejaculation). Abu Musa said: Well, I satisfy you on this (issue).
He (Abu Musa, the narrator) said: I got up (and went) to 'A'isha
and sought her permission and it was granted, and I said to her: 0
Mother, or Mother of the Faithful, I want to ask you about a matter
on which I feel shy. She said: Don't feel shy of asking me about a
thing which you can ask your mother, who gave you birth, for I am
too your mother. Upon this I said: What makes a bath obligatory for
a person? She replied: You have come across one well informed! The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: When anyone sits
amidst four parts (of the woman) and the circumcised parts touch
each other a bath becomes obligatory.</english-text>
</hadith>
