<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10900</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>397</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20031, 11201, 11168, 11212, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، عن عبيد
الله، قال حدثني سعيد بن أبي سعيد، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دخل المسجد فدخل رجل فصلى ثم جاء فسلم على
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
السلام قال ‏"‏ ارجع فصل فإنك لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجع الرجل فصلى كما كان
صلى ثم جاء إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسلم عليه فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعليك السلام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ارجع فصل
فإنك لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى فعل ذلك ثلاث مرات فقال الرجل والذي بعثك
بالحق ما أحسن غير هذا علمني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إذا قمت إلى الصلاة فكبر ثم
اقرأ ما تيسر معك من القرآن ثم اركع حتى تطمئن راكعا ثم ارفع حتى
تعتدل قائما ثم اسجد حتى تطمئن ساجدا ثم ارفع حتى تطمئن جالسا ثم افعل
ذلك في صلاتك كلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported: The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) entered the mosque and a person also entered
therein and offered prayer, and then came and paid salutation to
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him). The Mes- senger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) returned his salutation and said: Go
back and pray, for you have not offered the prayer. He again prayed
as he had prayed before, and came to the Apostle of Allah (may
peace be upon. him) and saluted him. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) returned the salutation and said: Go back and
say prayer, for you have not offered the prayer. This (act of
repeating the prayer) was done three times. Upon this the person
said: By Him Who hast sent you with Truth, whatever better I can do
than this, please teach me. He (the Holy Prophet) said: When you
get up to pray, recite takbir, and then recite whatever you
conveniently can from the Qur'an, then bow down and remain quietly
in that position, then raise your- self and stand erect; then
prostrate yourself and remain quietly in that attitude; then raise
yourself and sit quietly; and do that throughout all your
prayers.</english-text>
</hadith>
