<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10909</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>400</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20387, 20345, 10962, 19, 20436, 20345,
19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن حجر السعدي، حدثنا علي بن مسهر، أخبرنا
المختار بن فلفل، عن أنس بن مالك، ح وحدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، -
واللفظ له - حدثنا علي بن مسهر، عن المختار، عن أنس، قال بينا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات يوم بين أظهرنا إذ أغفى إغفاءة ثم رفع
رأسه متبسما فقلنا ما أضحكك يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ أنزلت على آنفا سورة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقرأ ‏"‏ بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم ‏{‏ إنا أعطيناك الكوثر *
فصل لربك وانحر * إن شانئك هو الأبتر‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ أتدرون ما
الكوثر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلنا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنه نهر وعدنيه
ربي عز وجل عليه خير كثير هو حوض ترد عليه أمتي يوم القيامة آنيته عدد
النجوم فيختلج العبد منهم فأقول رب إنه من أمتي ‏.‏ فيقول ما تدري ما
أحدثت بعدك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ زاد ابن حجر في حديثه بين أظهرنا في المسجد ‏.‏
وقال ‏"‏ ما أحدث بعدك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas reported: One day the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) was sitting amongst us that he dozed off. He
then raised his head smilingly. We said: What makes you smile.
Messenger of Allah? He said: A Sura has just been revealed to me,
and then recited: In the name of Allah, the Compassionate, the
Merciful. Verily We have given thee Kauthar (fount of abundance).
Therefore turn to thy Lord for prayer and offer sacrifice, and
surely thy enemy is cut off (from the good). Then he (the Holy
Prophet) said: Do you know what Kauthar is? We said: Allah and His
Messenger know best. The Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him) said:
It (Kauthar) is a canal which my Lord, the Exalted and Glorious has
promised me, and there is an abundance of good in it. It is a
cistern and my people would come to it on the Day of Resurrection,
and tumblers there would be equal to the number of stars. A servant
would be turned away from (among the people gathered there). Upon
this I would say: My Lord, he is one of my people, and He (the
Lord) would say: You do not know that he innovated new things (in
Islam) after you. Ibn Hujr made this addition in the hadith:" He
(the Holy Prophet) was sitting amongst us in the mosque, and He
(Allah) said: (You don't know) what he innovated after
you"</english-text>
</hadith>
