<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10951</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>418</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 20320, 11399, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عبد الله بن يونس، حدثنا زائدة، حدثنا
موسى بن أبي عائشة، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، قال دخلت على عائشة
فقلت لها ألا تحدثيني عن مرض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت بلى
ثقل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا لا
وهم ينتظرونك يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي ماء في المخضب ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ففعلنا فاغتسل ثم ذهب لينوء فأغمي عليه ثم أفاق فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا لا وهم ينتظرونك يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي ماء
في المخضب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلنا فاغتسل ثم ذهب لينوء فأغمي عليه ثم أفاق
فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا لا وهم ينتظرونك يا رسول الله ‏.‏
فقال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي ماء في المخضب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلنا فاغتسل ثم ذهب لينوء
فأغمي عليه ثم أفاق فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلنا لا وهم
ينتظرونك يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قالت والناس عكوف في المسجد ينتظرون رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لصلاة العشاء الآخرة - قالت - فأرسل رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى أبي بكر أن يصلي بالناس فأتاه الرسول
فقال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يأمرك أن تصلي بالناس ‏.‏ فقال
أبو بكر وكان رجلا رقيقا يا عمر صل بالناس ‏.‏ قال فقال عمر أنت أحق
بذلك ‏.‏ قالت فصلى بهم أبو بكر تلك الأيام ثم إن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وجد من نفسه خفة فخرج بين رجلين أحدهما العباس لصلاة الظهر
وأبو بكر يصلي بالناس فلما رآه أبو بكر ذهب ليتأخر فأومأ إليه النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن لا يتأخر وقال لهما ‏"‏ أجلساني إلى جنبه ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأجلساه إلى جنب أبي بكر وكان أبو بكر يصلي وهو قائم بصلاة النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس يصلون بصلاة أبي بكر والنبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قاعد ‏.‏ قال عبيد الله فدخلت على عبد الله بن عباس فقلت له ألا
أعرض عليك ما حدثتني عائشة عن مرض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
هات ‏.‏ فعرضت حديثها عليه فما أنكر منه شيئا غير أنه قال أسمت لك
الرجل الذي كان مع العباس قلت لا ‏.‏ قال هو علي ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ubaidullah b. Abdullah reported: I visited 'A'isha
and asked her to tell about the illness of the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him). She agreed and said: The Apostle (may
peace be upon him) was seriously ill and he asked whether the
people had prayed. We said: No, they are waiting for you, Messenger
of Allah. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Put some water in the tub for
me. We did accordingly and he (the Holy Prophet) took a bath;and,
when he was about to move with difficulty, he fainted. When he came
round, he again said: Have the people said prayer? We said: No,
they are waiting for you, Messenger of Allah. He (the Holy Prophet)
again said: Put some water for me in the tub. We did accordingly
and he took a bag, but when he was about to move with difficultyhe
fainted. When he came round, he asked whether the people had
prayed. We said: No, they are waiting for you, Messenger of Allah.
He said: Put some water for me in the tub. We did accordingly and
he took a bath and he was about to move with difficulty when he
fainted. When he came roundhe said: Have the people saidprayer? We
said: No, they are waiting for you, Messenger of Allah. She
('A'isha) said: The people were staying in the mosque and waiting
for the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) to lead the last
(night) prayer. She ('A'isha) said: The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) sent (instructions) to Abu Bakr to lead the
people in prayer. When the messenger came, he told him (Abd Bakr):
The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) has ordered you to
lead the people in prayer. Abu Bakr who was a man of very tenderly
feelings asked Umar to lead the prayer. 'Umar said: You are more
entitled to that. Abu Bakr led the prayers during those days.
Afterwards the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) felt some
relief and he went out supported by two men, one of them was
al-'Abbas, to the noon prayer. Abu Bakr was leading the people in
prayer. When Abu Bakr saw him. he began to withdraw, but the
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) told him not to withdraw.
He told his two (companions) to seat him down beside him (Abu
Bakr). They seated him by the side of Abu Bakr. Abu Bakr said the
prayer standing while following the prayer of the Apostle (way
peace be upon him) and the people Bald prayer (standing) while
following the prayer of Abu Bakr. The Apostle (may peace be upon
him) was seated. Ubaidullah said: I visited 'Abdullah b. 'Abbas,
and said: Should I submit to you what 'A'isha had told about the
illness of the Apostle (may peace be upon him)? He said: Go ahead.
I submitted to him what had been transmitted by her ('A'isha). He
objected to none of it, only asking whether she had named to him
the man who accompanied al-'Abbas. I said: No. He said: It was
'Ali.</english-text>
</hadith>
