<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10956</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>418</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20354, 20032, 30399, 20354, 11060, 11051,
11054, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو معاوية، ووكيع، ح
وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، - واللفظ له - قال أخبرنا أبو معاوية، عن
الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، عن الأسود، عن عائشة، قالت لما ثقل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم جاء بلال يؤذنه بالصلاة فقال ‏"‏ مروا أبا بكر فليصل
بالناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فقلت يا رسول الله إن أبا بكر رجل أسيف إنه متى
يقم مقامك لا يسمع الناس فلو أمرت عمر ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ مروا أبا بكر
فليصل بالناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فقلت لحفصة قولي له إن أبا بكر رجل أسيف
وإنه متى يقم مقامك لا يسمع الناس فلو أمرت عمر ‏.‏ فقالت له ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنكن لأنتن صواحب يوسف ‏.‏ مروا أبا
بكر فليصل بالناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فأمروا أبا بكر يصلي بالناس - قالت -
فلما دخل في الصلاة وجد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من نفسه خفة
فقام يهادى بين رجلين ورجلاه تخطان في الأرض - قالت - فلما دخل المسجد
سمع أبو بكر حسه ذهب يتأخر فأومأ إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قم مكانك ‏.‏ فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى جلس عن يسار أبي
بكر - قالت - فكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي بالناس جالسا
وأبو بكر قائما يقتدي أبو بكر بصلاة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ويقتدي
الناس بصلاة أبي بكر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported: When the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) was confined to bed, Bilal came to him to summon
him to prayer. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Ask Abu Bakr to lead the
people in prayer. She ('A'isha) reported: I said: Messenger of
Allah, Abu! Bakr is a tenderhearted man, go when ]be would stand at
your place (he would be so overwhelmed by feelings) that he would
not be able to make the people hear anything (his recitation would
not be audible to the followers in prayer). You should better order
Umar (to lead the prayer). He (the Holy Prophet) said: Ask Abu Bakr
to lead people in- prayer. She ('A'isha) said: I asked Hafsa to
(convey) my impression to him (the Holy Prophet) that Abu Bakr was
a tenderhearted man, so when he would stand at his place, he would
not be able to make the people bear anything. He better order Umar.
Hafsa conveyed this (message of Hadrat 'A'isha) to him (the Holy
Prophet). The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: (You
are behaving) as if you are the females who had gathered around
Yusuf. Order Abd Bakr to lead the people in prayer. She ('A'isha)
reported: So Abu Bakr was ordered to lead the people in prayer. As
the prayer began, the Messenger of Allah (may peace he upon him)
felt some relief; he got up and moved supported by two persons and
his feet dragged on earth (due to excessive weakness). 'A'isha
reported: As he (the Holy Prophet) entered the mosque. Abu Bakr
perceived his (arrival). He was about to with. draw, but the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) by the gesture (of This
hand) told him to keep standing at his place. The Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) came and seated himself on the left
side of Abu Bakr. She ('A'isha) reported: The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) was leading people in prayer sitting. Abu
Bakr was following the prayer of the Apostle (may peace be upon
him) in a standing posture and the people were following the prayer
of Abu Bakr.</english-text>
</hadith>
