<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10959</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>419</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30263, 130115, 30553, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 19,
20436</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عمرو الناقد، وحسن الحلواني، وعبد بن حميد، - قال
عبد أخبرني وقال الآخران، حدثنا يعقوب، - وهو ابن إبراهيم بن سعد -
وحدثني أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني أنس بن مالك، أن أبا
بكر، كان يصلي لهم في وجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الذي توفي فيه
حتى إذا كان يوم الاثنين - وهم صفوف في الصلاة - كشف رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ستر الحجرة فنظر إلينا وهو قائم كأن وجهه ورقة مصحف
‏.‏ ثم تبسم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضاحكا - قال - فبهتنا ونحن
في الصلاة من فرح بخروج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ونكص أبو بكر
على عقبيه ليصل الصف وظن أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خارج للصلاة
فأشار إليهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بيده أن أتموا صلاتكم - قال
- ثم دخل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأرخى الستر - قال - فتوفي
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من يومه ذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported, Abu Bakr led them in prayer
due to the illness of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) of which be died. It was a Monday and they stood in rows for
prayer. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) drew aside
the curtain of ('A'isha's) apartment and looked at us while he was
standing, and his (Prophet's) face was (as bright) as the paper of
the Holy Book. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) felt
happy and smiled. And we were confounded with joy while in prayer
due to the arrival (among our midst) of the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him), Abu Bakr stepped back upon his heels to say
prayer in a row perceiving that the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) had come out for prayer. The Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) with the help of his hand signed to them to
complete their prayer. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) went back (to his apartment) and drew the curtain. He (the
narrator) said: The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
breathed his last on that very day.</english-text>
</hadith>
