<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10964</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>421</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن أبي حازم، عن
سهل بن سعد الساعدي، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذهب إلى بني
عمرو بن عوف ليصلح بينهم فحانت الصلاة فجاء المؤذن إلى أبي بكر فقال
أتصلي بالناس فأقيم قال نعم ‏.‏ قال فصلى أبو بكر فجاء رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم والناس في الصلاة فتخلص حتى وقف في الصف فصفق الناس -
وكان أبو بكر لا يلتفت في الصلاة - فلما أكثر الناس التصفيق التفت
فرأى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأشار إليه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أن امكث مكانك فرفع أبو بكر يديه فحمد الله عز وجل على ما
أمره به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من ذلك ثم استأخر أبو بكر حتى
استوى في الصف وتقدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى ثم انصرف فقال ‏"‏
يا أبا بكر ما منعك أن تثبت إذ أمرتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو بكر ما كان لابن
أبي قحافة أن يصلي بين يدى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما لي رأيتكم أكثرتم التصفيق من
نابه شىء في صلاته فليسبح فإنه إذا سبح التفت إليه وإنما التصفيح
للنساء ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl b. Sa'd al-Sa'idi reported: The Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) went to the tribe of Bani Amr b. Auf
in order to bring reconciliation amongst (its members), and It was
a time of prayer. The Mu'adhdhin came to Abu Bakr and said: Would
you lead the prayer in case I recite takbir (tahrima, with which
the prayer begins)? He (Abu Bakr) said: Yes. He (the narrator)
said: He (Abu Bakr) started (leading) the prayer. The people were
engaged in observing prayer when the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) happened to come there and made his way (through the
people) till he stood in a row. The people began to clap (their
hands), but Abu Bakr paid no heed (to it) in prayer. When the
people clapped more vigorously, he (Abu Bakr) then paid heed and
saw the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) there. (He was
about to withdraw when) the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) signed to him to keep standing at his place. Abu Bakr lifted
his hands and praised Allah for what the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) had commanded him and then Abu Bakr withdrew
himself till he stood in the midst of the row and the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) stepped forward and led the prayer.
When (the prayer) was over, he (the Holy Prophet) said: 0 Abu Bakr,
what prevented you from standing (at that place) as I ordered you
to do? Abu Bakr said: It does not become the son of Abu Quhafa to
lead prayer before the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him).
The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said (to the people)
around him: What is it that I saw you clapping so vigorously?
(Behold) when anything happens in prayer, say: Subha Allah, for
when you would utter it, it would attract the attention, while
clapping of hands is meant for women.</english-text>
</hadith>
