<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>10967</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>274</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20121, 20121, 11070, 11013, 11373,
166</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن رافع، وحسن بن علي الحلواني، جميعا عن عبد
الرزاق، قال ابن رافع حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا ابن جريج، حدثني ابن
شهاب، عن حديث، عباد بن زياد أن عروة بن المغيرة بن شعبة، أخبره أن
المغيرة بن شعبة أخبره أنه، غزا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تبوك
- قال المغيرة - فتبرز رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قبل الغائط فحملت
معه إداوة قبل صلاة الفجر فلما رجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى
أخذت أهريق على يديه من الإداوة وغسل يديه ثلاث مرات ثم غسل وجهه ثم
ذهب يخرج جبته عن ذراعيه فضاق كما جبته فأدخل يديه في الجبة حتى أخرج
ذراعيه من أسفل الجبة ‏.‏ وغسل ذراعيه إلى المرفقين ثم توضأ على خفيه
ثم أقبل - قال المغيرة - فأقبلت معه حتى نجد الناس قد قدموا عبد
الرحمن بن عوف فصلى لهم فأدرك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إحدى
الركعتين فصلى مع الناس الركعة الآخرة فلما سلم عبد الرحمن بن عوف قام
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يتم صلاته فأفزع ذلك المسلمين فأكثروا
التسبيح فلما قضى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاته أقبل عليهم ثم قال
‏"‏ أحسنتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ قد أصبتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ يغبطهم أن صلوا
الصلاة لوقتها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mughira b. Shu'ba reported that he participated In
the expedition of Tabuk along with the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him). The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
went out to answer the call of nature before the morning prayer.
and I carried along with him a jar (full of water). When the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) came back to me (after
relieving himself). I began to pour water upon his hands out of the
jar and he washed his hands three times, then washed his face three
times. He then tried to tuck up the sleeves of his cloak upon his
forearms but since the sleeves were tight he inserted his hands in
the cloak and then brought out his forearms up to the elbow below
the cloak, and then wiped over his shoes and then moved on. Mughira
said: I also moved along with him till he came to the people and
(he found) that they had been saying their prayer under the Imamah
of 'Abd al-Rahman b. 'Auf. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) could get one rak ah out of two and said (this) last
rak'ah along with the people. When Abd al-Rahman b. 'Auf pronounced
the salutation, the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) got
up to complete the prayer. This made the Muslims terrified and most
of them began to recite the glory of the Lord. When the Apostle of
Allah (may peace be upon him) finished his prayer, he turned
towards them and then said: You did well, or said with a sense of
joy: You did the right thing that you said prayer at the appointed
hour.</english-text>
</hadith>
