<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11073</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>471</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30150, 20286, 20020, 11069</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا عبيد الله بن معاذ العنبري، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
شعبة، عن الحكم، قال غلب على الكوفة رجل - قد سماه - زمن ابن الأشعث
فأمر أبا عبيدة بن عبد الله أن يصلي بالناس فكان يصلي فإذا رفع رأسه
من الركوع قام قدر ما أقول اللهم ربنا لك الحمد ملء السموات وملء
الأرض وملء ما شئت من شىء بعد أهل الثناء والمجد لا مانع لما أعطيت
ولا معطي لما منعت ولا ينفع ذا الجد منك الجد ‏.‏ قال الحكم فذكرت ذلك
لعبد الرحمن بن أبي ليلى فقال سمعت البراء بن عازب يقول كانت صلاة
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وركوعه وإذا رفع رأسه من الركوع وسجوده
وما بين السجدتين قريبا من السواء ‏.‏ قال شعبة فذكرته لعمرو بن مرة
فقال قد رأيت ابن أبي ليلى فلم تكن صلاته هكذا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hakam reported: There dominated in Kufa a man whose
name was men- tioned as Zaman b. al-Ash'ath, who ordered Abu
'Ubaidah b. 'Abdullah to lead people in prayer and he accordingly
used to lead them. Whenever he raised his head after bowing, he
stood up equal to the time that I can recite (this supplication): O
Allah! our Lord! unto Thee be the praise which would fill the
heavens and the earth, and that which will please Thee besides them
I Worthy art Thou of all praise and glory. None can prevent that
which Thou bestowest, and none can bestow that whichthou
preventest. And the greatness of the great will not avail him
against Thee. Hakam (the narrator) said: I made a mention of that
to Abd al-Rahman ibn Abi Laila who reported: I heard al-Bara' b.
'Azib say that the prayer of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) and his bowing, and when he lifted his head from bowing,
and his prostration, and between the two prostrations (all these
acts) were nearly proportionate. I made a mention of that to 'Ar b.
Murrah and he said: I saw Ibn Abi Laili (saying the prayer), but
his prayer was not like this.</english-text>
</hadith>
