<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11144</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>505</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayers - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20656, 20236, 11161</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا شيبان بن فروخ، حدثنا سليمان بن المغيرة، حدثنا
ابن هلال، - يعني حميدا - قال بينما أنا وصاحب، لي نتذاكر حديثا إذ
قال أبو صالح السمان أنا أحدثك، ما سمعت من أبي سعيد، ورأيت، منه قال
بينما أنا مع أبي سعيد، يصلي يوم الجمعة إلى شىء يستره من الناس إذ
جاء رجل شاب من بني أبي معيط أراد أن يجتاز بين يديه فدفع في نحره
فنظر فلم يجد مساغا إلا بين يدى أبي سعيد فعاد فدفع في نحره أشد من
الدفعة الأولى فمثل قائما فنال من أبي سعيد ثم زاحم الناس فخرج فدخل
على مروان فشكا إليه ما لقي - قال - ودخل أبو سعيد على مروان فقال له
مروان ما لك ولابن أخيك جاء يشكوك ‏.‏ فقال أبو سعيد سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إذا صلى أحدكم إلى شىء يستره من الناس
فأراد أحد أن يجتاز بين يديه فليدفع في نحره فإن أبى فليقاتله فإنما
هو شيطان ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Salih al-Samman reported: I narrate to you what I
heard and saw from Abu Sa'id al-Khudri: One day I was with Abu
Sa'id and he was saying prayer on Friday turning to a thing which
concealed him from the people when a young man from Banu Mu'ait
came there and he tried to pass in front of him; he turned him back
by striking his chest. He looked about but finding no other way to
pass except in front of Abu Sa'id, made a second attempt. He (Abu
Sa'id) turned him away by Striking his chest more vigorously than
the first stroke. He stood up and had a scuffle with Abu Sa'id.
Then the people gathered there He came out and went to Marwan and
complained to him what had happened to him. Abu Sa'id too came to
Marwan. Marwin said to him: What has happened to you and the son of
your brother that he came to complain against you? Abu Sa'id said:
I heard from the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) saying:
When any one of you prays facing something which conceals him from
people and anyone tries to pass in front of him, he should be
turned away, but if he refuses, he should be forcibly restrained
from it, for he is a devil.</english-text>
</hadith>
