<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11206</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1219</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20354, 11060, 11051, 11054, 11017</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن العلاء الهمداني أبو كريب، قال حدثنا أبو
معاوية، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، عن الأسود، وعلقمة، قالا أتينا عبد
الله بن مسعود في داره فقال أصلى هؤلاء خلفكم فقلنا لا ‏.‏ قال فقوموا
فصلوا ‏.‏ فلم يأمرنا بأذان ولا إقامة - قال - وذهبنا لنقوم خلفه فأخذ
بأيدينا فجعل أحدنا عن يمينه والآخر عن شماله - قال - فلما ركع وضعنا
أيدينا على ركبنا - قال - فضرب أيدينا وطبق بين كفيه ثم أدخلهما بين
فخذيه - قال - فلما صلى قال إنه ستكون عليكم أمراء يؤخرون الصلاة عن
ميقاتها ويخنقونها إلى شرق الموتى فإذا رأيتموهم قد فعلوا ذلك فصلوا
الصلاة لميقاتها واجعلوا صلاتكم معهم سبحة وإذا كنتم ثلاثة فصلوا
جميعا وإذا كنتم أكثر من ذلك فليؤمكم أحدكم وإذا ركع أحدكم فليفرش
ذراعيه على فخذيه وليجنأ وليطبق بين كفيه فلكأني أنظر إلى اختلاف
أصابع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأراهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Aswad and 'Alqama reported: We came to the house
of 'Abdullah b. Mas'ud. He said: Have these people said prayer
behind you? We said: No. He said: Then stand up and say prayer. He
neither ordered us to say Adhan nor Iqama. We went to stand behind
him. He caught hold of our hands and mode one of us stand on his
right hand and the other on his left side. When we bowed, we placed
our hands on our knees. He struck our hands and put his hands
together, palm to palm, then put them between his thighs. When he
completed the prayer he said. There would soon come your Amirs, who
would defer prayers from their appointed time and would make such
delay that a little time is left before sunset. So when you see
them doing so, say prayer at its appointed time and then say prayer
along with them as (Nafl), and when you are three, pray together
(standing in one row), and when you are more than three, appoint
one amongst you as your Imam. And when any one of you bows he must
place his hands upon hie thighs and kneel down. and putting his
palms together place (them within his thighs). I perceive as if I
am seeing the gap between the fingers of the Messenger of Allah
(may peace he upon him).</english-text>
</hadith>
