<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11214</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1227</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>20208, 11449, 11229, 11020, 5300</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو جعفر، محمد بن الصباح وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة -
وتقاربا في لفظ الحديث - قالا حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، عن حجاج
الصواف، عن يحيى بن أبي كثير، عن هلال بن أبي ميمونة، عن عطاء بن
يسار، عن معاوية بن الحكم السلمي، قال بينا أنا أصلي، مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ عطس رجل من القوم فقلت يرحمك الله ‏.‏ فرماني
القوم بأبصارهم فقلت واثكل أمياه ما شأنكم تنظرون إلى ‏.‏ فجعلوا
يضربون بأيديهم على أفخاذهم فلما رأيتهم يصمتونني لكني سكت فلما صلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فبأبي هو وأمي ما رأيت معلما قبله ولا
بعده أحسن تعليما منه فوالله ما كهرني ولا ضربني ولا شتمني قال ‏"‏ إن
هذه الصلاة لا يصلح فيها شىء من كلام الناس إنما هو التسبيح والتكبير
وقراءة القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو كما قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قلت
يا رسول الله إني حديث عهد بجاهلية وقد جاء الله بالإسلام وإن منا
رجالا يأتون الكهان ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فلا تأتهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ومنا رجال
يتطيرون ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ذاك شىء يجدونه في صدورهم فلا يصدنهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
ابن الصباح ‏"‏ فلا يصدنكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت ومنا رجال يخطون ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ كان نبي من الأنبياء يخط فمن وافق خطه فذاك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وكانت لي
جارية ترعى غنما لي قبل أحد والجوانية فاطلعت ذات يوم فإذا الذيب قد
ذهب بشاة من غنمها وأنا رجل من بني آدم آسف كما يأسفون لكني صككتها
صكة فأتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فعظم ذلك على قلت يا رسول
الله أفلا أعتقها قال ‏"‏ ائتني بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتيته بها فقال لها ‏"‏
أين الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت في السماء ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ من أنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت أنت
رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أعتقها فإنها مؤمنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mu'awiya b. al-Hakam said: While I was praying with
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him), a man in the
company sneezed. I said: Allah have mercy on you! The people stared
at me with disapproving looks, so I said: Woe be upon me, why is it
that you stare at me? They began to strike their hands on their
thighs, and when I saw them urging me to observe silence (I became
angry) but I said nothing. When the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) had said the prayer (and I declare that neither before
him nor after him have I seen a leader who gave better instruction
than he for whom I would give my father and mother as ransom). I
swear that he did not scold, beat or revile me but said: Talking to
persons is not fitting during the prayer, for it consists of
glorifying Allah, declaring his Greatness. and recitation of the
Qur'an or words to that effect. I said: Messenger of Allah. I was
till recently a pagan, but Allah has brought Islam to us; among us
there are men who have recourse to Kahins. He said, Do not have
recourse to them. I said. There are men who take omens. That is
something which they find in their breasts, but let it not turn
their way (from freedom of action). I said: Among us there are men
who draw lines. He said: There was a prophet who drew lines, so if
they do it as they did, that is allowable. I had a maid-servant who
tended goats by the side of Uhud and Jawwaniya. One day I happened
to pass that way and found that a wolf had carried a goat from her
flock. I am after all a man from the posterity of Adam. I felt
sorry as they (human beings) feel sorry. So I slapped her. I came
to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) and felt (this
act of mine) as something grievous I said: Messenger of Allah,
should I not grant her freedom? He (the Holy Prophet) said: Bring
her to me. So I brought her to him. He said to her: Where is Allah?
She said: He is in the heaven. He said: Who am I? She said: Thou
art the Messenger of Allah. He said: Grant her freedom, she is a
believing woman.</english-text>
</hadith>
