<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11231</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1244</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 30367, 20167, 20031, 20165, 11172</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، وقتيبة بن سعيد، كلاهما عن عبد
العزيز، قال يحيى أخبرنا عبد العزيز بن أبي حازم، عن أبيه، أن نفرا،
جاءوا إلى سهل بن سعد قد تماروا في المنبر من أى عود هو فقال أما
والله إني لأعرف من أى عود هو ومن عمله ورأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم أول يوم جلس عليه - قال - فقلت له يا أبا عباس فحدثنا ‏.‏ قال
أرسل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى امرأة قال أبو حازم إنه
ليسميها يومئذ ‏"‏ انظري غلامك النجار يعمل لي أعوادا أكلم الناس
عليها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فعمل هذه الثلاث درجات ثم أمر بها رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فوضعت هذا الموضع فهى من طرفاء الغابة ‏.‏ ولقد رأيت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قام عليه فكبر وكبر الناس وراءه وهو على
المنبر ثم رفع فنزل القهقرى حتى سجد في أصل المنبر ثم عاد حتى فرغ من
آخر صلاته ثم أقبل على الناس فقال ‏"‏ يا أيها الناس إني صنعت هذا
لتأتموا بي ولتعلموا صلاتي ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hazim is reported on the authority of his father:
Some people came to Sahl b. Sa'd and began to differ about the wood
of which the (Prophet's pulpit was made. He (Sahl b. Sa'd) said: By
Allah, I know of which wood it is made and who made it, and the day
when I saw the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) seated
himself on it on the first day. I said to him: O Abu Abbas (kunyah
of Sabl b. Sa'd), narrate to us (all these facts), He said: The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) sent a person to a woman
asking her to allow her slave, a carpenter, to work on woods (to
prepare a pulpit) so that I should talk to the people (sitting on
it). Abu Hazim said: He (Sahl b. Sa'd) pointed out the name of
(that lady) that day. So he (the carpenter) made (a pulpit) with
these three steps. Then the Messengerof Allah (may peace be upon
him) commanded it to be placed here (where it is lying now). It was
fashioned out of the wood of al-Ghaba. And I saw the Messenger of
Allah (may peace he upon him) standing upon it and glorifying Allah
and the people also glorified Allah after him, while he was on the
pulpit. He then raised (his head from prostration) and stepped back
(on his heels) till he prostrated himself at the base of pulpit,
and then returned (to the former place and this movement of one or
two steps continued) till the prayer was complete. He then turned
towards the people and said: O people, I have done it so that you
should follow me and learn (my mode of) prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
