<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11271</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1286</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20031, 11065, 11019, 11342, 10878</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، حدثنا هشام،
حدثنا قتادة، عن سالم بن أبي الجعد، عن معدان بن أبي طلحة، أن عمر بن
الخطاب، خطب يوم الجمعة فذكر نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وذكر أبا
بكر قال إني رأيت كأن ديكا نقرني ثلاث نقرات وإني لا أراه إلا حضور
أجلي وإن أقواما يأمرونني أن أستخلف وإن الله لم يكن ليضيع دينه ولا
خلافته ولا الذي بعث به نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم فإن عجل بي أمر
فالخلافة شورى بين هؤلاء الستة الذين توفي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وهو عنهم راض وإني قد علمت أن أقواما يطعنون في هذا الأمر أنا
ضربتهم بيدي هذه على الإسلام فإن فعلوا ذلك فأولئك أعداء الله الكفرة
الضلال ثم إني لا أدع بعدي شيئا أهم عندي من الكلالة ما راجعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في شىء ما راجعته في الكلالة وما أغلظ لي في
شىء ما أغلظ لي فيه حتى طعن بإصبعه في صدري فقال ‏"‏ يا عمر ألا تكفيك
آية الصيف التي في آخر سورة النساء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإني إن أعش أقض فيها
بقضية يقضي بها من يقرأ القرآن ومن لا يقرأ القرآن ثم قال اللهم إني
أشهدك على أمراء الأمصار وإني إنما بعثتهم عليهم ليعدلوا عليهم
وليعلموا الناس دينهم وسنة نبيهم صلى الله عليه وسلم ويقسموا فيهم
فيئهم ويرفعوا إلى ما أشكل عليهم من أمرهم ثم إنكم أيها الناس تأكلون
شجرتين لا أراهما إلا خبيثتين هذا البصل والثوم لقد رأيت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا وجد ريحهما من الرجل في المسجد أمر به فأخرج
إلى البقيع فمن أكلهما فليمتهما طبخا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ma'dan b. Talha reported: 'Umar b. Khattab, delivered
the Friday sermon and he made a mention of the Apostle of Allah
(may peace be upon him) and Abu Bakr. He (further) said: I saw in a
dream that a cock pecked me twice, and I perceive that my death is
near. Some people have suggested me to appoint my successor. And
Allah would not destroy His religion. His caliphate and that with
which He sent His Apostle (may peace be upon him) If death
approaches me soon, the (issue) of Caliphate (would be decided) by
the consent of these six men with whom the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) remained well pleased till his death. And I know
fully well that some people would blame me that I killed with these
very hands of mine some persons who apparently professed (Islam).
And if they do this (blame me) they are the enemies of Allah, and
are non-believers and have gone astray. And I leave not after me
anything which to my mind seems more important than Kalala. And I
never turned towards the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
(for guidance) more often than this Kalala, and he (the Holy
Prophet) was not annoyed with me on any other (issue) than this:
(And he was so perturbed) that he struck his fingers on my chest
and said: Does this verse. that is at the end of Surat al-Nisa'.
which was revealed in the hot season not suffice you? And if I live
longer I would decide this (problem so clearly) that one who reads
the Qur'an, or one who does not read it, would be able to take
(correct), decisions (under its light). He ('Umar) further said:
Allah! I call You witness on these governors of lands, that I sent
them to (the peoples of these lands) so that they should administer
justice amongst them, teach them their religion and the Sunnah of
the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him), and distribute
amongst them the spoils of war and refer to me that which they find
difficult to perform. O people. you eat 'these two plants and these
are onions and garlic. and I find them nothing but repugnant for I
saw that when the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) sensed
the odour of these two from a person in a mosque, he was made to go
to al-Baqi'. So he who eats it should (make its odour) die by
cooking it well.</english-text>
</hadith>
