<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11296</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1311</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>20028, 10755, 10887</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، - واللفظ له - حدثنا جرير، عن
الحسن بن عبيد الله، عن إبراهيم بن سويد، قال صلى بنا علقمة الظهر
خمسا فلما سلم قال القوم يا أبا شبل قد صليت خمسا ‏.‏ قال كلا ما فعلت
‏.‏ قالوا بلى - قال - وكنت في ناحية القوم وأنا غلام فقلت بلى قد
صليت خمسا ‏.‏ قال لي وأنت أيضا يا أعور تقول ذاك قال قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال
فانفتل فسجد سجدتين ثم سلم ثم قال قال عبد الله صلى بنا رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم خمسا فلما انفتل توشوش القوم بينهم فقال ‏"‏ ما شأنكم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله هل زيد في الصلاة قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالوا فإنك قد صليت خمسا ‏.‏ فانفتل ثم سجد سجدتين ثم سلم ثم قال ‏"‏
إنما أنا بشر مثلكم أنسى كما تنسون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وزاد ابن نمير في حديثه
‏"‏ فإذا نسي أحدكم فليسجد سجدتين ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibrahim b. Suwaid-reported: 'Alqama led us in the
noon prayer and be offered five rak'ahs; when the prayer was
complete, the people said to him: Abu Shibl, you have offered five
rak'ahs. He said: No, I have not done that. They said: Yes (you
said five rak'ahs). He (the narrator) said: And I was sitting in a
corner among people and I was just a boy. I (also) said: Yes, you
have offered five (rak'ahs). He said to me: O, one-eyed, do you say
the same thing? I said: Yes. Upon this he turned (his face) and
performed two prostrations and then gave salutations, and then
reported 'Abdullah as saying: The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) led us in prayer and offered five rak'ahs. And as he
turned away the people began to whisper amongst themselves. He (the
Holy Prophet) said: What is the matter with you? They said: Has the
prayer been extended? He said: No. They said: You have in fact said
five rak'ahs. He (the Holy Prophet) then turned his back (and faced
the Qibla) and performed two prostrations and then gave salutations
and further said: Verily I am a human being like you, I forget just
as you forget. Ibn Numair made this addition:" When any one of you
forgets, he must perform two prostrations."</english-text>
</hadith>
