<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11359</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1375</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>20288, 11201, 30367, 20023, 11428, 11161</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عاصم بن النضر التيمي، حدثنا المعتمر، حدثنا عبيد
الله، ح قال وحدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا ليث، عن ابن عجلان، كلاهما
عن سمى، عن أبي صالح، عن أبي هريرة، - وهذا حديث قتيبة أن فقراء،
المهاجرين أتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا ذهب أهل الدثور
بالدرجات العلى والنعيم المقيم ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ وما ذاك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا
يصلون كما نصلي ويصومون كما نصوم ويتصدقون ولا نتصدق ويعتقون ولا نعتق
‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أفلا أعلمكم شيئا تدركون
به من سبقكم وتسبقون به من بعدكم ولا يكون أحد أفضل منكم إلا من صنع
مثل ما صنعتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا بلى يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تسبحون
وتكبرون وتحمدون دبر كل صلاة ثلاثا وثلاثين مرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو صالح
فرجع فقراء المهاجرين إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا سمع
إخواننا أهل الأموال بما فعلنا ففعلوا مثله ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ذلك فضل الله يؤتيه من يشاء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وزاد غير
قتيبة في هذا الحديث عن الليث عن ابن عجلان قال سمى فحدثت بعض أهلي
هذا الحديث فقال وهمت إنما قال ‏"‏ تسبح الله ثلاثا وثلاثين وتحمد
الله ثلاثا وثلاثين وتكبر الله ثلاثا وثلاثين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجعت إلى أبي
صالح فقلت له ذلك فأخذ بيدي فقال الله أكبر وسبحان الله والحمد لله
والله أكبر وسبحان الله والحمد لله حتى تبلغ من جميعهن ثلاثة وثلاثين
‏.‏ قال ابن عجلان فحدثت بهذا الحديث رجاء بن حيوة فحدثني بمثله عن
أبي صالح عن أبي هريرة عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported: The poor amongst the emigrants
came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) and said:
The possessors of great wealth have obtained the highest ranks and
the lasting bliss. lie (the Holy Prophet) said: How Is that? They
said: They pray as we pray, and they observe fast as we observe
fast, and they give charity but we do not give charity, and they
set slaves free but we do not set slaves free. Upon this the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Shall A not teach
you something by which you will catch upon those who have preceded
you, and get ahead of those who come after you, only those who do
as you do being more excellent than you? They said: Yes, Messenger
of Allah. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Extol Allah, declare His
Greatness, and Praise Him thirty-three times after every prayer.
Abu Salih said: The poor amongst the emigrants returned to the
Messenger of Allah (may peace upon him) saying: Our brethren, the
possessors, of property have heard what we have done and they did
the same. So the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said:
This is Allah's Grace which He gives to whom He wishes. Sumayy
reported: I made a mention of this hadith to some members of my
family (and one of them) said: You have forgotten; he (the Holy
Prophet) had said (like this):." Extol Allah thirty-three time.
praise Allah thirty-three times and declare His Greatness
thirty-three times. Ibn 'Ajjan said: 1 made a mention of this
hadith to Raja' b. Haiwata and he narrated to me a hadith like this
from AbuSalih from the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
on the authority of Abu Huraira.</english-text>
</hadith>
