<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11400</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1422</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20321, 20411, 20012, 11374, 10916,
3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني زهير بن حرب، وعبيد الله بن سعيد، كلاهما عن
الأزرق، - قال زهير حدثنا إسحاق بن يوسف الأزرق، - حدثنا سفيان، عن
علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن أبيه، عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم أن رجلا سأله عن وقت الصلاة فقال له ‏"‏ صل معنا هذين ‏"‏ ‏.‏
يعني اليومين فلما زالت الشمس أمر بلالا فأذن ثم أمره فأقام الظهر ثم
أمره فأقام العصر والشمس مرتفعة بيضاء نقية ثم أمره فأقام المغرب حين
غابت الشمس ثم أمره فأقام العشاء حين غاب الشفق ثم أمره فأقام الفجر
حين طلع الفجر فلما أن كان اليوم الثاني أمره فأبرد بالظهر فأبرد بها
فأنعم أن يبرد بها وصلى العصر والشمس مرتفعة أخرها فوق الذي كان وصلى
المغرب قبل أن يغيب الشفق وصلى العشاء بعد ما ذهب ثلث الليل وصلى
الفجر فأسفر بها ثم قال ‏"‏ أين السائل عن وقت الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
الرجل أنا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وقت صلاتكم بين ما رأيتم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sulaiman b. Buraida narrated it on the authority of
his father that a person asked the Apostle of Allah (may peace be
upon him) about the time of prayer. Upon this he said: Pray with us
these two, meaning two days. When the sun passed the meridian. he
gave command to Bilal who uttered the call to prayer. then lie
commanded him and pronounced Iqama for noon prayer (Then at the
tine of the afternoon prayer) he again commanded and Iqama for the
afternoon prayer was pronounced when the sun was high, white and
clear. He then commanded and Iqama for the evening prayer was
pronounced, when the sun had set. He then commanded him and the
Iqama for the night prayer was pronounced When the twilight had
disappeared. He then commanded him and the Iqama for the morning
prayer was pronounced, when the dawn had appeared. When it was the
next day, he commanded him to delay the noon prayer till the
extreme heat had passed and he did so, and he allowed it to be
delayed till the extreme heat had passed. He observed the afternoon
prayer when the sun was high, delaying it beyond the time he had
previously observed it. He observed the evening prayer before the
twilight had vanished; he observed the night prayer when a third of
the night had passed; and he observed the dawn prayer when there
was clear daylight. He (the Holy Prophet) then said: Where is the
man who inquired about the time of prayer? He (the inquirer) said:
Messenger of Allah I here I am. He (the Holy Prophet) said: The
time for your prayer is within the limits of what you have
seen.</english-text>
</hadith>
