<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11401</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1423</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>20221, 20020, 11374, 10916, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني إبراهيم بن محمد بن عرعرة السامي، حدثنا حرمي بن
عمارة، حدثنا شعبة، عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن أبيه،
أن رجلا، أتى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسأله عن مواقيت الصلاة فقال
‏"‏ اشهد معنا الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأمر بلالا فأذن بغلس فصلى الصبح حين
طلع الفجر ثم أمره بالظهر حين زالت الشمس عن بطن السماء ثم أمره
بالعصر والشمس مرتفعة ثم أمره بالمغرب حين وجبت الشمس ثم أمره بالعشاء
حين وقع الشفق ثم أمره الغد فنور بالصبح ثم أمره بالظهر فأبرد ثم أمره
بالعصر والشمس بيضاء نقية لم تخالطها صفرة ثم أمره بالمغرب قبل أن يقع
الشفق ثم أمره بالعشاء عند ذهاب ثلث الليل أو بعضه - شك حرمي - فلما
أصبح قال ‏"‏ أين السائل ما بين ما رأيت وقت ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Buraida narrated on the authority of his father that
a man came to the Prophet (may peace be upon him) and asked about
the times of prayer. He said: You observe with us the prayer. He
commanded Bilal, and he uttered the call to prayer in the darkness
of night preceding daybreak and he said the morning prayer till
dawn had appeared. He then commanded him (Bilal) to call for the
noon prayer when the sun had declined from the zenith. He then
commanded him (Bilal) to call for the afternoon prayer when the sun
was high. He then commanded him for the evening prayer when the sun
had set. He then commanded him for the night prayer when the
twilight had disappeared. Then on the next day he commanded him (to
call for prayer) when there was light in the morning. He then
commanded him (to call) for the noon prayer when the extreme heat
was no more. He then commanded him for the afternoon prayer when
the sun was bright and clear and yellowness did not blend with it.
He then commanded him to observe the sunset prayer. He then
commanded him for the night prayer when a third part of the night
bad passed or a bit less than that. Harami (the narrator of this
hadith) was in doubt about that part of the mentioned hadith which
concerned the portion of the night. When it was dawn, he (the Holy
Prophet) said: Where is the inquirer (who inquired about the times
of prayer and added): Between (these two extremes) is the time for
prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
