<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11402</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1424</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20331, 10745</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا بدر
بن عثمان، حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي موسى، عن أبيه، عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أنه أتاه سائل يسأله عن مواقيت الصلاة فلم يرد عليه شيئا -
قال - فأقام الفجر حين انشق الفجر والناس لا يكاد يعرف بعضهم بعضا ثم
أمره فأقام بالظهر حين زالت الشمس والقائل يقول قد انتصف النهار وهو
كان أعلم منهم ثم أمره فأقام بالعصر والشمس مرتفعة ثم أمره فأقام
بالمغرب حين وقعت الشمس ثم أمره فأقام العشاء حين غاب الشفق ثم أخر
الفجر من الغد حتى انصرف منها والقائل يقول قد طلعت الشمس أو كادت ثم
أخر الظهر حتى كان قريبا من وقت العصر بالأمس ثم أخر العصر حتى انصرف
منها والقائل يقول قد احمرت الشمس ثم أخر المغرب حتى كان عند سقوط
الشفق ثم أخر العشاء حتى كان ثلث الليل الأول ثم أصبح فدعا السائل
فقال ‏"‏ الوقت بين هذين ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa narrated on the authority of his father that
a person came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) for
inquiring about the times of prayers. He (the Holy Prophet) gave
him no reply (because he wanted to explain to him the times by
practically observing these prayers). He then said the morning
player when it was daybreak, but the people could hardly recognise
one another. He then commanded and the Iqama for the noon prayer
was pronounced when the tan had passed the meridian and one would
say that it was midday but he (the Holy Prophet) knew batter than
them. He then again commanded and the Iqama for the afternoon
prayer was pronounced when the sun was high. He then commanded and
Iqama for the evening prayer was pronounced when the sun had sunk.
He then commanded and Iqama for the night prayer was pronounced
when the twilight had disappeared. He then delayed the morning
prayer on the next day (so much so) that after returning from it
one would say that the sun had risen or it was about to rise. He
then delayed the noon prayer till it was near the time of afternoon
prayer (as it was observed yesterday). He then delayed the
afternoon prayer till one after returning from it would say that
the sun had become red. He then delayed the evening prayer till the
twilight was about to disappear. He then delayed the night prayer
till it was one-third of the night. He then called the inquirer in
the morning and said: The time for prayers is between these two
(extremes).</english-text>
</hadith>
