<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11463</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1484</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30375, 20121, 11070, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا محمد بن رافع، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا ابن
جريج، قال قلت لعطاء أى حين أحب إليك أن أصلي العشاء التي يقولها
الناس العتمة إماما وخلوا قال سمعت ابن عباس يقول أعتم نبي الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ذات ليلة العشاء - قال - حتى رقد ناس واستيقظوا ورقدوا
واستيقظوا فقام عمر بن الخطاب فقال الصلاة ‏.‏ فقال عطاء قال ابن عباس
فخرج نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كأني أنظر إليه الآن يقطر رأسه ماء
واضعا يده على شق رأسه قال ‏"‏ لولا أن يشق على أمتي لأمرتهم أن
يصلوها كذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فاستثبت عطاء كيف وضع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم يده على رأسه كما أنبأه ابن عباس فبدد لي عطاء بين أصابعه شيئا
من تبديد ثم وضع أطراف أصابعه على قرن الرأس ثم صبها يمرها كذلك على
الرأس حتى مست إبهامه طرف الأذن مما يلي الوجه ثم على الصدغ وناحية
اللحية لا يقصر ولا يبطش بشىء إلا كذلك ‏.‏ قلت لعطاء كم ذكر لك أخرها
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ليلتئذ قال لا أدري ‏.‏ قال عطاء أحب إلى أن
أصليها إماما وخلوا مؤخرة كما صلاها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ليلتئذ
فإن شق عليك ذلك خلوا أو على الناس في الجماعة وأنت إمامهم فصلها وسطا
لا معجلة ولا مؤخرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Juraij reported: I said to Ata': Which time do
you deem fit for me to say the 'Isya' prayer, -as an Imam or alone,
-that time which is called by people 'Atama? He said: I heard Ibn
'Abbas saying: The Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) one
night delayed the 'Isya' prayer till the people went to sleep. They
woke up and again went to sleep and again woke up. Then 'Umar b.
Khattab stood up and said (loudly)" Prayer." Ata' further reported
that Ibn 'Abbas said: The Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him)
came out, and as if I am still seeing him with water trickling from
his head, and with his hand placed on one side of the head, and he
said: Were it not hard for my Ummah, I would have ordered them to
observe this prayer like this (i. e. at late hours). I inquired
from 'Ata' how the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) placed
his hand upon his head as Ibn Abbas had informed. So Ata' spread
his fingers a little and then placed the ends of his fingers on the
side of his head. He then moved them like this over his head till
the thumb touched that part of the ear which is near the face and
then it (went) to the earlock and the part of the heard. It (the
bind) neither held nor caught anything but this is how (it moved
oil). I said to Ata': Was it mentioned to you (by Ibn Abbas) how
long did the Apostle (may peace be upon him) delay it (the prayer)
during that eight? He said: I do not know (I cannot give you the
exact time). Ali' said: I love that I should say prayer, whether as
an Imam or alone at delayed hours as the Apostle of Allah (may
peace be upon him) said that night, but if It is hard upon you in
your individual capacity or upon people in the congregation and you
are their Imam, then say prayer ('Isha') at the middle hours
neither too early nor too late.</english-text>
</hadith>
