<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11507</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1528</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 5278</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حرملة بن يحيى التجيبي، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني
يونس، عن ابن شهاب، أن محمود بن الربيع الأنصاري، حدثه أن عتبان بن
مالك وهو من أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ممن شهد بدرا من الأنصار
أنه أتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله إني قد أنكرت
بصري وأنا أصلي لقومي وإذا كانت الأمطار سال الوادي الذي بيني وبينهم
ولم أستطع أن آتي مسجدهم فأصلي لهم وددت أنك يا رسول الله تأتي فتصلي
في مصلى ‏.‏ فأتخذه مصلى ‏.‏ قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ سأفعل إن شاء الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عتبان فغدا رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأبو بكر الصديق حين ارتفع النهار فاستأذن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأذنت له فلم يجلس حتى دخل البيت ثم قال ‏"‏ أين تحب
أن أصلي من بيتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأشرت إلى ناحية من البيت فقام رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فكبر فقمنا وراءه فصلى ركعتين ثم سلم - قال -
وحبسناه على خزير صنعناه له - قال - فثاب رجال من أهل الدار حولنا حتى
اجتمع في البيت رجال ذوو عدد فقال قائل منهم أين مالك بن الدخشن فقال
بعضهم ذلك منافق لا يحب الله ورسوله ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقل له ذلك ألا تراه قد قال لا إله إلا الله ‏.‏ يريد
بذلك وجه الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قالوا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال فإنما نرى
وجهه ونصيحته للمنافقين ‏.‏ قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ فإن الله قد حرم على النار من قال لا إله إلا الله ‏.‏ يبتغي بذلك
وجه الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب ثم سألت الحصين بن محمد الأنصاري - وهو
أحد بني سالم وهو من سراتهم - عن حديث محمود بن الربيع فصدقه بذلك
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mahmud b. al-Rabi' reported that 'Ibn b. Malik, who
was one of the Companions of the Apostle of Allah (may peace be
upon him) and who participated in the (Battle of) Badr and was
among the Ansar (of Medina), told that he came to the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) and said: Messenger of Allah, I have
lost my eyesight and I lead my people in prayer. When there is a
downpour there is then a current (of water) in the valley that
stands between me and them and I find it impossible to go to their
mosque and lead them in prayer. Messenger of Allah, I earnestly beg
of you that you should come and observe prayer at a place of
worship (in my house) so that I should then use it as a place of
worship. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Well,
it God so wills. I would soon do so. 'Itban said: On the following
day when the day dawned, the Messenger of Allah (may peace he upon
him) came along with Abu Bakr at-Siddiq, and the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) asked permission (to get into the house). I
gave him the permission, and be did not sit after entering the
house, when he said: At what place in your house you desire me to
say prayer? I ('Itban b. Malik) said: I pointed to a corner in the
house, The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) stood (at
that place for prayer) and pronounced Allah-o-Akbar (Allah is the
Greatest) (as an expression for the commencement of prayer). We too
stood behind him, and he said two rak'ahs and then pronounced
salutation (marking the end of the prayer). We detained him (the
Holy Prophet) for the meat curry we had prepared for, him. The
people of the neighbouring houses came and thus there was a good
gathering in (our house). One of them said: Where is Malik b.
Dukhshun? Upon this one of them remarked: He is a hypocrite; he
does not love Allah and His Messenger. Thereupon the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Do not say so about him. Don't
you see that he utters La ilaha ill-Allah (There is no god but
Allah) and seeks the pleasure of Allah through it? They said: Allah
and His Messenger know beet. One (among the audience) said: We see
his inclination and wellwishing for hypocrites only. Upon this the
Messenger of Allah' (may peace be upon him) again said: Verily
Allah has forbidden the Fire for one who says: There is no god but
Allah, thereby seeking Allah's pleasure. Ibn Shihab said: I asked
Husain b. Muhammad al-Ansar (he was one of the leaders of Banu
Salim) about the hadith transmitted by Mahmud b. Rabi' and he
testified it.</english-text>
</hadith>
