<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11571</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1592</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Mosques and Places of Prayer - كتاب
الْمَسَاجِدِ وَمَوَاضِعِ الصَّلاَةِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 11013, 11002, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حرملة بن يحيى التجيبي، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني
يونس، عن ابن شهاب، عن سعيد بن المسيب، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم حين قفل من غزوة خيبر سار ليله حتى إذا أدركه
الكرى عرس وقال لبلال ‏"‏ اكلأ لنا الليل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصلى بلال ما قدر له
ونام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأصحابه فلما تقارب الفجر استند
بلال إلى راحلته مواجه الفجر فغلبت بلالا عيناه وهو مستند إلى راحلته
فلم يستيقظ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ولا بلال ولا أحد من أصحابه
حتى ضربتهم الشمس فكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أولهم استيقاظا
ففزع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أى بلال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
بلال أخذ بنفسي الذي أخذ - بأبي أنت وأمي يا رسول الله - بنفسك قال
‏"‏ اقتادوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاقتادوا رواحلهم شيئا ثم توضأ رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وأمر بلالا فأقام الصلاة فصلى بهم الصبح فلما قضى
الصلاة قال ‏"‏ من نسي الصلاة فليصلها إذا ذكرها فإن الله قال ‏{‏ أقم
الصلاة لذكري‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يونس وكان ابن شهاب يقرؤها للذكرى
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported that when the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) returned from the expedition to Khaibar, he
travelled one night, and stopped for rest when he became sleepy. He
told Bilal to remain on guard during the night and he (Bilal)
prayed as much as he could, while the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) and his Companions slept. When the time for dawn
approached Bilal leaned against his camel facing the direction from
which the dawn would appear but he was overcome by sleep while he
was leaning against his camel, and neither the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) nor Bilal, nor anyone else among his
Companions got up, till the sun shone on them. Allah's Messenger
(may peace be upon him) was the first of them to awake and, being
startled, he called to Bilal who said: Messenger of Allah I may my
father and mother be offered as ransom for thee, the same thing
overpowered me which overpowered you. He (the Holy Prophet, then)
said: Lead the beasts on: so they led their camels to some
distance. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) then
performed ablution and gave orders to Bilal who pronounced the
Iqama and then led them in the morning prayer. When he finished the
prayer he said: When anyone forgets the prayer, he should observe
it when he remembers it, for Allah has said:" And observe the
prayer for remembrance of Me" (Qur'an. xx. 14). Yunus said: Ibn
Shilab used to recite it like this:" (And observe the prayer) for
remembrance."</english-text>
</hadith>
