<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11798</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1819</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Travellers) - كتاب صلاة المسافرين
وقصرها</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن ابن شهاب، عن
عروة، عن عائشة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صلى في المسجد ذات
ليلة فصلى بصلاته ناس ثم صلى من القابلة فكثر الناس ثم اجتمعوا من
الليلة الثالثة أو الرابعة فلم يخرج إليهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فلما أصبح قال ‏"‏ قد رأيت الذي صنعتم فلم يمنعني من الخروج
إليكم إلا أني خشيت أن تفرض عليكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وذلك في رمضان
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported: The Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) came out during the night and observed prayer in the
mosque and some of the people prayed along with him. When it was
morning the people talked about this and so a large number of
people gathered there. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) went out for the second night, and they (the people) prayed
along with him. When it was morning the people began to talk about
it. So the mosque thronged with people on the third night. He (the
Holy Prophet) came out and they prayed along with him. When it was
the fourth night, the mosque was filled to its utmost capacity but
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) did not come out.
Some persons among then cried:" Prayer." But the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) did not come to them till he came out for
the morning prayer. When he had completed the morning prayer, he
turned his face to the people and recited Tashahhud (I bear testi-
mony that there is no god but Allah and I bear testimony that
Muhammad is His Messen- ger) and then said: Your affair was not
hidden from me in the night, but I was afraid that (my observing
prayer continuously) might make the night prayer obligatory for you
and you might be unable to perform it.</english-text>
</hadith>
