<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11808</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1829</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Travellers) - كتاب صلاة المسافرين
وقصرها</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 38487, 20005, 30421, 20005, 11081, 11211,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، ومحمد بن حاتم، عن ابن عيينة، - قال
ابن أبي عمر حدثنا سفيان، - عن عمرو بن دينار، عن كريب، مولى ابن عباس
عن ابن عباس، أنه بات عند خالته ميمونة فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم من الليل فتوضأ من شن معلق وضوءا خفيفا - قال وصف وضوءه وجعل
يخففه ويقلله - قال ابن عباس فقمت فصنعت مثل ما صنع النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم جئت فقمت عن يساره فأخلفني فجعلني عن يمينه فصلى ثم
اضطجع فنام حتى نفخ ثم أتاه بلال فآذنه بالصلاة فخرج فصلى الصبح ولم
يتوضأ ‏.‏ قال سفيان وهذا للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم خاصة لأنه بلغنا
أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم تنام عيناه ولا ينام قلبه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Abbas said: I spent the night in the house of my
mother's sister, Maimuna, and observed how the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) prayed (at night). He got up and relieved
himself. He then washed his face and hands and then went to sleep.
He again got up and went near the water-skin and loosened its
straps and then poured some water in a bowl and inclined it with
his hands (towards himself). He then performed a good ablution
between the two extremes and then stood up to pray. I also came and
stood by his left side. He took hold of me and made me stand on his
right side. It was in thirteen rak'ahs that the (night) prayer of
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) was completed. He
then slept till he began to snore, and we knew that he had gone to
sleep by his snoring. He then went out (for the dawn prayer) and
then again slept, and said while praying or prostrating himself:" O
Allah! place light in my heart, light in my hearing, light in my
sight, light on my right, light on my left, light in front of me,
light behind me, light above me, light below me, make light for
me," or he said:" Make me light."</english-text>
</hadith>
