<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11828</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1849</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Travellers) - كتاب صلاة المسافرين
وقصرها</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 20033, 30123, 20390, 20026</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثناه زهير بن حرب، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن مهدي، ح
وحدثنا إسحاق بن، إبراهيم أخبرنا أبو النضر، قال حدثنا عبد العزيز بن
عبد الله بن أبي سلمة، عن عمه، الماجشون بن أبي سلمة عن الأعرج، بهذا
الإسناد وقال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا استفتح الصلاة كبر
ثم قال ‏"‏ وجهت وجهي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏ وأنا أول المسلمين ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وقال وإذا رفع رأسه من الركوع قال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ربنا ولك
الحمد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏ وصوره فأحسن صوره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال وإذا سلم قال
‏"‏ اللهم اغفر لي ما قدمت ‏"‏ .‏ إلى آخر الحديث ولم يقل بين التشهد
والتسليم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hudhaifa reported: I prayed with the Apostle of Allah
(may peace be upon him) one night and he started reciting
al-Baqara. I thought that he would bow at the end of one hundred
verses, but he proceeded on; I then thought that he would perhaps
recite the whole (surah) in a rak'ah, but he proceeded and I
thought he would perhaps bow on completing (this surah). He then
started al-Nisa', and recited it; he then started Al-i-'Imran and
recited leisurely. And when he recited the verses which referred to
the Glory of Allah, he glorified (by saying Subhan Allah-Glory to
my Lord the Great), and when he recited the verses which tell (how
the Lord) is to be begged, he (the Holy Prophet) would then beg
(from Him), and when he recited the verses dealing with protection
from the Lord, he sought (His) protection and would then bow and
say: Glory be to my Mighty Lord; his bowing lasted about the same
length of time as his standing (and then on returning to the
standing posture after ruku') he would say: Allah listened to him
who praised Him, and he would then stand about the same length of
time as he had spent in bowing. He would then prostrate himself and
say: Glory be to my Lord most High, and his prostration lasted
nearly the same length of time as his standing. In the hadith
transmitted by Jarir the words are:" He (the Holy Prophet) would
say:" Allah listened to him who praised Him, our Lord, to Thee i
the praise."</english-text>
</hadith>
