<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>11961</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1982</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Travellers) - كتاب صلاة المسافرين
وقصرها</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20331, 10945, 11029, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا عبد
الملك بن أبي سليمان، عن عطاء، عن جابر بن عبد الله، قال شهدت مع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاة الخوف فصفنا صفين صف خلف رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم والعدو بيننا وبين القبلة فكبر النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم وكبرنا جميعا ثم ركع وركعنا جميعا ثم رفع رأسه من الركوع ورفعنا
جميعا ثم انحدر بالسجود والصف الذي يليه وقام الصف المؤخر في نحر
العدو فلما قضى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم السجود وقام الصف الذي يليه
انحدر الصف المؤخر بالسجود وقاموا ثم تقدم الصف المؤخر وتأخر الصف
المقدم ثم ركع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وركعنا جميعا ثم رفع رأسه من
الركوع ورفعنا جميعا ثم انحدر بالسجود والصف الذي يليه الذي كان مؤخرا
في الركعة الأولى وقام الصف المؤخر في نحور العدو فلما قضى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم السجود والصف الذي يليه انحدر الصف المؤخر بالسجود
فسجدوا ثم سلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وسلمنا جميعا ‏.‏ قال جابر
كما يصنع حرسكم هؤلاء بأمرائهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir reported: We fought In the company of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) with the tribe of
Juhaina. They fought with us terribly. When we had finished the
noon prayer, the polytheists said: Had we attacked them at once. we
would have killed them. Gabriel informed the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) about It (about their evil design). The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) made a mention of it to
us, adding that they (the polytheists) had also said: Shortly there
would be time for the 'Asr prayer. which is dearer o them (the
Muslims) than even their children. So when the time of the 'Asr
prayer came. we formed ourselves into two rows, while the
polytheists were between us and the Qibla. The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) said: Allah is Most Great, and we also said
so. He bowed and we also bowed. He went down in prostration and the
first row prostrated along with him. When they stood up, the second
row went down in prostration. Then the first row went into the
rear, and the second row came in the front and occupied the place
of the first row. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
then said: Allah is Most Great, and we also said so. He then bowed,
and we also bowed. He then went down in prostration and along with
him the row also (went down in prostration), and the second row
remained standing. And when the second row had also prostrated and
all of them sat down then the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) pronounced salutation to them. Abu Zubair said: Jabir made a
mention specially of this thing: just as your chiefs observe
prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
