<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12024</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2045</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Friday) - كتاب الجمعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 30170, 20246, 20246, 10602, 11050,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، ومحمد بن المثنى، كلاهما عن
عبد الأعلى، - قال ابن المثنى حدثني عبد الأعلى، وهو أبو همام - حدثنا
داود، عن عمرو بن سعيد، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس، أن ضمادا، قدم
مكة وكان من أزد شنوءة وكان يرقي من هذه الريح فسمع سفهاء من أهل مكة
يقولون إن محمدا مجنون ‏.‏ فقال لو أني رأيت هذا الرجل لعل الله يشفيه
على يدى - قال - فلقيه فقال يا محمد إني أرقي من هذه الريح وإن الله
يشفي على يدي من شاء فهل لك فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن
الحمد لله نحمده ونستعينه من يهده الله فلا مضل له ومن يضلل فلا هادي
له وأشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له وأن محمدا عبده ورسوله
أما بعد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقال أعد على كلماتك هؤلاء ‏.‏ فأعادهن عليه رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثلاث مرات - قال - فقال لقد سمعت قول الكهنة
وقول السحرة وقول الشعراء فما سمعت مثل كلماتك هؤلاء ولقد بلغن ناعوس
البحر - قال - فقال هات يدك أبايعك على الإسلام - قال - فبايعه ‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعلى قومك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وعلى
قومي - قال - فبعث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سرية فمروا بقومه
فقال صاحب السرية للجيش هل أصبتم من هؤلاء شيئا فقال رجل من القوم
أصبت منهم مطهرة ‏.‏ فقال ردوها فإن هؤلاء قوم ضماد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn 'Abbas reported: Dimad came to Mecca and he
belonged to the tribe of Azd Shanu'a, and he used to protect the
person who was under the influence of charm. He heard the foolish
people of Mecca say that Muhammad (may peace be upon him) was under
the spell. Upon this he said: If 1 were to come across this man,
Allah might cure him at my hand. He met him and said: Muhammad, I
can protect (one) who is under the influence of charm, and Allah
cures one whom He so desires at my hand. Do you desire (this)? Upon
this the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Praise is
due to Allah, we praise Him, ask His help; and he whom Allah guides
aright there is none to lead him astray, and he who is led astray
there is none to guide him, and I bear testimony to the fact that
there is no god but Allah, He is One, having no partner with Him,
and that Muhammad is His Servant and Messenger. Now after this he
(Dimad) said: Repeat these words of yours before me, and the
messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) repeated these to him
thrice; and he said I have heard the words of soothsayers and the
words of magicians, and the words of poets, but I have never heard
such words as yours, and they reach the depth (of the ocean of
eloquence) ; bring forth your hand so that I should take oath of
fealty to you on Islam. So he took an oath of allegiance to him.
The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: It (this
allegiance of yours) is on behalf of your people too. He said: It
is on behalf of my people too. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) sent an expedition and the flying column passed by his
people. The leader of the flying column said to the detachment: Did
you find anything from these people? One of the people said: I
found a utensil for water. Upon this he (the commander) said:
Return it, for he is one of the people of Dimad.</english-text>
</hadith>
