<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12068</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2090</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Two Eids) - كتاب صلاة
العيدين</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 30367, 20155, 11845, 11260, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وقتيبة، وابن، حجر قالوا حدثنا
إسماعيل بن جعفر، عن داود بن قيس، عن عياض بن عبد الله بن سعد، عن أبي
سعيد الخدري، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يخرج يوم الأضحى
ويوم الفطر فيبدأ بالصلاة فإذا صلى صلاته وسلم قام فأقبل على الناس
وهم جلوس في مصلاهم فإن كان له حاجة ببعث ذكره للناس أو كانت له حاجة
بغير ذلك أمرهم بها وكان يقول ‏"‏ تصدقوا تصدقوا تصدقوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكان
أكثر من يتصدق النساء ثم ينصرف فلم يزل كذلك حتى كان مروان بن الحكم
فخرجت مخاصرا مروان حتى أتينا المصلى فإذا كثير بن الصلت قد بنى منبرا
من طين ولبن فإذا مروان ينازعني يده كأنه يجرني نحو المنبر وأنا أجره
نحو الصلاة فلما رأيت ذلك منه قلت أين الابتداء بالصلاة فقال لا يا
أبا سعيد قد ترك ما تعلم ‏.‏ قلت كلا والذي نفسي بيده لا تأتون بخير
مما أعلم ‏.‏ ثلاث مرار ثم انصرف ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Sa'id al-Khudri reported that the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) used to go out on the day of Adha and
on the day of Fitr and commenced the prayer. And after having
observed his prayer and pronounced the salutation, he stood up
facing people as they were seated at their places of worship. And
if he intended to send out an army he made mention of it to the
people, and if he intended any other thing besides it, he commanded
them (to do that). He used to say (to the people): Give alms, give
alms, give alms, and the majority that gave alms was of women. He
then returned and this (practice) remained (in vogue) till Marwan
b. al- Hakam (came into power). I went out hand in hand with Marwan
till we came to the place of worship and there Kathir b. Salt had
built a pulpit of clay and brick. Marwan began to tug me with his
hand as though he were pulling me towards the pulpit, while I was
pulling him towards the prayer. When I saw him doing that I said:
What has happened to the practice of beginning with prayer? He
said: No, Abu Sa'id, what you are familiar with has been abandoned.
I thereupon said (three times and went back): By no means, by Him
in Whose hand my life is, you are not doing anything better than
what I am familiar with.</english-text>
</hadith>
