<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12079</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2102</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Two Eids) - كتاب صلاة
العيدين</chapter>
<chain-index>30492, 20029, 20377, 11105, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني هارون بن سعيد الأيلي، ويونس بن عبد الأعلى، -
واللفظ لهارون - قالا حدثنا ابن وهب، أخبرنا عمرو، أن محمد بن عبد
الرحمن، حدثه عن عروة، عن عائشة، قالت دخل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وعندي جاريتان تغنيان بغناء بعاث فاضطجع على الفراش وحول وجهه
فدخل أبو بكر فانتهرني وقال مزمار الشيطان عند رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأقبل عليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ دعهما
‏"‏ فلما غفل غمزتهما فخرجتا وكان يوم عيد يلعب السودان بالدرق
والحراب فإما سألت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وإما قال ‏"‏ تشتهين
تنظرين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت نعم فأقامني وراءه خدي على خده وهو يقول ‏"‏
دونكم يا بني أرفدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى إذا مللت قال ‏"‏ حسبك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت
نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاذهبي ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported: The Messenger of Allah (way peace
be upon him) came (in my apartment) while there were two girls with
me singing the song of the Battle of Bu'ath. He lay down on the bed
and turned away his face. Then came Abu Bakr and he scolded me and
said: Oh! this musical instrument of the devil in the house of the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)! The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) turned towards him and said: Leave them
alone. And when he (the Holy Prophet) became unattentive, I hinted
them and they went out, and it was the day of 'Id and negroes were
playing with shields and speare. (I do not remember) whether I
asked the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) or whether he
said to me if I desired to see (that sport). I said: Yes. I stood
behind him with his face parallel to my face, and he said: O Banu
Arfada, be busy (in your sports) till I was satiated. He said (to
me): Is that enough? I said: Yes. Upon this he asked me to
go.</english-text>
</hadith>
