<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12105</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2129</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Eclipse) - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30487, 20029, 20475, 30491, 20029, 20475, 11013,
10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حرملة بن يحيى، أخبرني ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس، ح
وحدثني أبو الطاهر، ومحمد بن سلمة المرادي قالا حدثنا ابن وهب، عن
يونس، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة، زوج النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت خسفت الشمس في حياة رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فخرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى المسجد فقام وكبر وصف
الناس وراءه فاقترأ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قراءة طويلة ثم كبر
فركع ركوعا طويلا ثم رفع رأسه فقال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ربنا ولك
الحمد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قام فاقترأ قراءة طويلة هي أدنى من القراءة الأولى
ثم كبر فركع ركوعا طويلا هو أدنى من الركوع الأول ثم قال ‏"‏ سمع الله
لمن حمده ربنا ولك الحمد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم سجد - ولم يذكر أبو الطاهر ثم سجد
- ثم فعل في الركعة الأخرى مثل ذلك حتى استكمل أربع ركعات وأربع سجدات
وانجلت الشمس قبل أن ينصرف ثم قام فخطب الناس فأثنى على الله بما هو
أهله ثم قال ‏"‏ إن الشمس والقمر آيتان من آيات الله لا يخسفان لموت
أحد ولا لحياته فإذا رأيتموها فافزعوا للصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال أيضا ‏"‏
فصلوا حتى يفرج الله عنكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ رأيت في مقامي هذا كل شىء وعدتم حتى لقد رأيتني أريد أن آخذ قطفا
من الجنة حين رأيتموني جعلت أقدم - وقال المرادي أتقدم - ولقد رأيت
جهنم يحطم بعضها بعضا حين رأيتموني تأخرت ورأيت فيها ابن لحى وهو الذي
سيب السوائب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وانتهى حديث أبي الطاهر عند قوله ‏"‏ فافزعوا
للصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولم يذكر ما بعده ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha, the wife of the Apostle of Allah (may peace
be upon him), reported There was an eclipse of the sun during the
lifetime of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him). So, the
Messenger of Allah (may peace he upon him) went to the mosque and
stood up and glorified Allah, and the people formed themselves in
rows behind him. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
made a long recital (of the Qur'an) and then pronounced takbir and
then observed a long ruku'. He then raised his head and said: Allah
listened to him who praised Him: our Lord, praise is due to Thee.
He then again stood up and made a long recital, which was less than
the first recital. He pronounced takbir and observed a long ruku',
and it was less than the first one. He again said: Allah listened
to him who praised Him; our Lord, praise is due to Thee. (Abu
Tahir, one of the narrators) made no mention of:" He then
prostrated himself." He did like this in the second rak'ah, till he
completed four rak'ahs and four prostrations and the sun became
bright before he deported. He then stood up and addressed people,
after lauding Allah as He deserved, and then said: The sun and the
moon are two signs among the signs of Allah These do not eclipse
either on the death of anyone or on his birth. So when you see
them, hasten to prayer. He also said this: Observe prayer till
Allah dispels the anxiety (of this extraordinary phenomenon) from
you. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: I saw in
my place everything which you have been promised. I even saw myself
desiring to pluck a bunch (of grapes) from Paradise (and it was at
the time) when you saw me moving forward. And I saw Hell and some
of its parts crushing the others, when you saw me moving back; and
I saw in it Ibn Luhayy and he was the person who made the
she-camels loiter about. In the hadith transmitted by Abu Tahir the
words are:" He hastened to prayer," and he made no mention of what
follows.</english-text>
</hadith>
