<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12111</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2136</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Eclipse) - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20160, 20031, 11455</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة القعنبي، حدثنا سليمان، - يعني
ابن بلال - عن يحيى، عن عمرة، أن يهودية، أتت عائشة تسألها فقالت
أعاذك الله من عذاب القبر ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فقلت يا رسول الله يعذب
الناس في القبور قالت عمرة فقالت عائشة قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم عائذا بالله ثم ركب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات غداة مركبا
فخسفت الشمس ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فخرجت في نسوة بين ظهرى الحجر في المسجد
فأتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من مركبه حتى انتهى إلى مصلاه الذي
كان يصلي فيه فقام وقام الناس وراءه - قالت عائشة - فقام قياما طويلا
ثم ركع فركع ركوعا طويلا ثم رفع فقام قياما طويلا وهو دون القيام
الأول ثم ركع فركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون ذلك الركوع ثم رفع وقد تجلت
الشمس فقال ‏"‏ إني قد رأيتكم تفتنون في القبور كفتنة الدجال ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت عمرة فسمعت عائشة تقول فكنت أسمع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
بعد ذلك يتعوذ من عذاب النار وعذاب القبر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Amra reported that a Jewess came to 'A'isha to ask
(about something) and said: May Allah protect you from the torment
of the grave! 'A'isha said: Messenger of Allah, would people be
tormented in the graves? The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) said: (May there be) protection of Allah! The Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) mounted one morning on the ride, and
the sun eclipsed. 'A'isha said: I came in the company of the women
in the mosque from behind the rooms. The Messenger of Allah (way
peace he upon him) dismounted from his ride and came to the place
of worship where he used to pray. He stood up (to pray) and the
people stood behind him. 'A'isha said: He stood for a long time. He
then bowed and it was a long ruku'. He then raised his head and he
stood for a long time, less than the first standing. He then bowed
and his ruku' was long, but it was less than that (the first)
ruku'. He then raised (his head) and the sun had become bright. He
(the Holy Prophet) then said: I saw you under trial in the grave
like the turmoil of Dajjal. 'Amra said: I heard 'A'isha say: I
listened after this to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) seeking refuge from the torment of Fire and the torment of the
grave.</english-text>
</hadith>
