<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12113</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2138</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Eclipse) - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30400, 20208, 20295, 11263, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني يعقوب بن إبراهيم الدورقي، حدثنا إسماعيل ابن
علية، عن هشام الدستوائي، قال حدثنا أبو الزبير، عن جابر بن عبد الله،
قال كسفت الشمس على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في يوم شديد
الحر فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بأصحابه فأطال القيام حتى
جعلوا يخرون ثم ركع فأطال ثم رفع فأطال ثم ركع فأطال ثم رفع فأطال ثم
سجد سجدتين ثم قام فصنع نحوا من ذاك فكانت أربع ركعات وأربع سجدات ثم
قال ‏"‏ إنه عرض على كل شىء تولجونه فعرضت على الجنة حتى لو تناولت
منها قطفا أخذته - أو قال تناولت منها قطفا - فقصرت يدي عنه وعرضت على
النار فرأيت فيها امرأة من بني إسرائيل تعذب في هرة لها ربطتها فلم
تطعمها ولم تدعها تأكل من خشاش الأرض ورأيت أبا ثمامة عمرو بن مالك
يجر قصبه في النار ‏.‏ وإنهم كانوا يقولون إن الشمس والقمر لا يخسفان
إلا لموت عظيم وإنهما آيتان من آيات الله يريكموهما فإذا خسفا فصلوا
حتى تنجلي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وحدثنيه أبو غسان المسمعي، حدثنا عبد الملك بن
الصباح، عن هشام، بهذا الإسناد مثله إلا أنه قال ‏"‏ ورأيت في النار
امرأة حميرية سوداء طويلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ولم يقل ‏"‏ من بني إسرائيل ‏"‏
‏.</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir b. 'Abdullah reported: The sun eclipsed on one
extremely hot day during the lifetime of the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him). The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him) prayed along with his Companions. He prolonged his qiyam
(standing posture in prayer) till they (his Companions) began to
fall down. He then observed a long ruku'. He raised his head (and
stood up for long) and then observed a long ruku'. He then raised
(his head and stood up) for a long time and then made two
prostrations. He then stood up and did like this and thus he
observed four ruku's and four prostrations (in two rak'ahs) and
then said: All these things were brought to me in which you will be
made to enter. Paradise was brought to me till (I was so close to
it) that if I (had intended) to pluck a bunch (of grapes) out of
it. I would have got it, or he (the Holy Prophet) said: I intended
to get a bunch (out of that) but my hand could not reach it. Hell
was also brought to me and I saw in it a woman belonging to the
tribe of Israel who was tormented for a cat whom she had tied, but
did not give it food nor set it free to eat the creatures of the
earth; and I saw Abu Thumama 'Amr b. Malik who was dragging his
intestines in Hell. They (the Arabs) used to say that the sun and
the moon do not eclipse but on the death of some great person; but
(in reality) both these (the sun and the moon) are among the signs
of Allah which are shown to you; so when there is an eclipse,
observe prayer till it (the sun or the moon) brightens. This hadith
has been narrated by Hisham with the same chain of transmitters
except this" I saw a dark woman with a tail stature and loud
voice," but he made no mention of" from among Bani
Israel".</english-text>
</hadith>
