<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12115</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2140</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Eclipse) - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 30212, 20295, 10526, 70</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن العلاء الهمداني، حدثنا ابن نمير، حدثنا
هشام، عن فاطمة، عن أسماء، قالت خسفت الشمس على عهد رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فدخلت على عائشة وهي تصلي فقلت ما شأن الناس يصلون
فأشارت برأسها إلى السماء فقلت آية قالت نعم ‏.‏ فأطال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم القيام جدا حتى تجلاني الغشى فأخذت قربة من ماء إلى
جنبي فجعلت أصب على رأسي أو على وجهي من الماء - قالت - فانصرف رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقد تجلت الشمس فخطب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم الناس فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد ما من شىء لم أكن
رأيته إلا قد رأيته في مقامي هذا حتى الجنة والنار وإنه قد أوحي إلى
أنكم تفتنون في القبور قريبا أو مثل فتنة المسيح الدجال - لا أدري أى
ذلك قالت أسماء - فيؤتى أحدكم فيقال ما علمك بهذا الرجل فأما المؤمن
أو الموقن - لا أدري أى ذلك قالت أسماء - فيقول هو محمد هو رسول الله
جاءنا بالبينات والهدى فأجبنا وأطعنا ‏.‏ ثلاث مرار فيقال له نم قد
كنا نعلم إنك لتؤمن به فنم صالحا وأما المنافق أو المرتاب - لا أدري
أى ذلك قالت أسماء - فيقول لا أدري سمعت الناس يقولون شيئا فقلت ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Asma' reported: The sun eclipsed during the lifetime
of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him). As I went to
'A'isha who was busy in prayer. I said: What is the matter with the
people that they are praying (a special prayer)? She ('A'isha)
pointed towards the sky with her head. I said: Is it (an unusual)
sign? She said: Yes. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
stood up for prayer for such a long time that I was about to faint.
I caught hold of a waterskin lying by my side, and began to pour
water over my head, or (began to sprinkle water) on my face. The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) then finished and the
sun had brightened. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
then addressed the people, (after) praising Allah and lauding Him,
and then said: There was no such thing as I did not see earlier,
but I saw it at this very place of mine. I ever saw Paradise and
Hell. It was also revealed to me that you would be tried in the
graves, as you would he tried something like the turmoil of the
Dajjal. Asma' said: I do not know which word he actually used
(qariban or mithl), and each one of you would be brought and it
would be said: What is your knowledge about this man? If the person
is a believer, (Asma' said: I do not know whether it was the word
al-Mu'min or al-Mu'qin) he would say: He is Muhammad and he is the
Messenger of Allah. He brought to us the clear signs and right
guidance. So we responded and obeyed him. (He would repeat this
three times), and it would be said to him: You should go to sleep.
We already knew that you are a believer in him. So the pious man
would go to sleep. So far as the hypocrite or sceptic is concerned
(Asma' said: I do not know which word was that: al-Munafiq
(hypocrite) or al-Murtad (doubtful) he would say: I do not know. I
only uttered whatever I heard people say.</english-text>
</hadith>
