<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12134</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>0</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Eclipse) - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index />
<english-text>KITAB-UL-JANA'IZ BOOK RELATING TO THE DEAD A Divine
Service is held over the dead body of every Muslim, young or old,
even of infants who have lived only for a few minutes. A Muslim
opens his eyes in the world with the words of Adhan in his ears in
which he is told that he is a moral being having moral and
spiritual responsibilities far more important than the physical
needs. He should live in the world with a firm belief in the
Creator of the Universe as his only Deity. Then he should spend his
life as a sincere and devoted follower of Muhammad (may peace be
upon him), for it is through him that he has received full
information about the Will of God and the Divine Code of life. It
Is also imprinted upon his fresh and clear mind that prayer
elevates the soul of man and herein lies his success in this world
and the world to come. With this sacred message he is made to start
his life. Both the paths are shown to him, the path of
righteousness and religious piety and the path of evil and
irreligiousness, and then it is left to his discretion to choose
the path he likes. After spending the allotted length of time he is
called back to his Master. When the soul leaves the body,
preparations are made for bidding him the last farewell. He is
washed and perfumed and is wrapped in white sheets. Then the
funeral prayer is observed keeping his dead body in front of the
Imam in which God to requested in congregation to grant him pardon
for his minor and major sins, for all his failings and to wrap him
in His Mercy. A Muslim is received in this world with Adhan and
lqama and he is given a send- off with prayer and supplication to
Allah for treating him kindly in his heavenly home. There is
neither Adhan nor Iqama in the funeral prayer which has very deep
significance. It implies that the Adhan and lqama for the funeral
prayer had been pronounced at the time of his birth. He is thus
awakened to the realisation of the fact that he should spend the
whole span of his life with such single-minded devotion as is found
in a worshipper waiting for the commencement of prayer after the
Adhan and Iqama are pronounced.</english-text>
</hadith>
