<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12138</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2165</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Funerals) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 30367, 20155, 11418, 10601, 56</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وقتيبة، وابن، حجر جميعا عن إسماعيل
بن جعفر، - قال ابن أيوب حدثنا إسماعيل، - أخبرني سعد بن سعيد، عن عمر
بن كثير بن أفلح، عن ابن، سفينة عن أم سلمة، أنها قالت سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ ما من مسلم تصيبه مصيبة فيقول ما أمره
الله إنا لله وإنا إليه راجعون اللهم أجرني في مصيبتي وأخلف لي خيرا
منها ‏.‏ إلا أخلف الله له خيرا منها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فلما مات أبو سلمة
قلت أى المسلمين خير من أبي سلمة أول بيت هاجر إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏ ثم إني قلتها فأخلف الله لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ قالت أرسل إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حاطب بن أبي
بلتعة يخطبني له فقلت إن لي بنتا وأنا غيور ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أما ابنتها
فندعو الله أن يغنيها عنها وأدعو الله أن يذهب بالغيرة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Umm Salama reported Allah's Messenger (may peace be
upon him) as saying: If any Muslim who suffers some calamity says,
what Allah has commanded him," We belong to Allah and to Him shall
we return; O Allah, reward me for my affliction and give me
something better than it in exchange for it," Allah will give him
something better than it in exchange. When Abu Salama died she
said: What Muslim is better than Abu Salama whose family was the
first to emigrate to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him). I then said the words, and Allah gave me God's Messenger (may
peace be upon him) in exchange. She said: The Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) sent Hatib b. Abu Balta'a to deliver me the
message of marriage with him. I said to him: I have a daughter (as
my dependant) and I am of jealous temperament. He (the Holy
Prophet) said: So far as her daughter is concerned, we would
supplicate Allah, that He may free her (of her responsibility) and
I would also supplicate Allah to do away with (her) jealous
(temperament).</english-text>
</hadith>
