<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12166</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2197</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Funerals) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20318, 11065, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كريب، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن أبيه، قال
ذكر عند عائشة أن ابن عمر، يرفع إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن
الميت يعذب في قبره ببكاء أهله عليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت وهل إنما قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنه ليعذب بخطيئته أو بذنبه وإن أهله
ليبكون عليه الآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذاك مثل قوله إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قام على القليب يوم بدر وفيه قتلى بدر من المشركين فقال لهم ما
قال ‏"‏ إنهم ليسمعون ما أقول ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقد وهل إنما قال ‏"‏ إنهم
ليعلمون أن ما كنت أقول لهم حق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قرأت ‏{‏ إنك لا تسمع
الموتى‏}‏ ‏{‏ وما أنت بمسمع من في القبور‏}‏ يقول حين تبوءوا مقاعدهم
من النار ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hisham narrated on the authority of his father that
it was mentioned to 'A'isha that Ibn 'Umar had narrated as marfu'
hadith from the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) that the
dead would be punished in the grave because of the lamentation of
his family for him. Upon this she said: He (Ibn 'Umar) missed (the
point). The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) had (in
fact) said: He (the dead) is punished for his faults or for his
sins, and the members of his family are wailing for him now. (This
misunderstanding of Ibn 'Umar is similar to his saying: ) The
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) stood by the well in
which were lying the dead bodies of those polytheists who had been
killed on the Day of Badr, and he said to them what he had to say,
i. e.: They hear what I say. But he (Ibn 'Umar) misunderstood. The
Holy Prophet (may peace be upon him) had only said: They (the dead)
understand that what I used to say to them was truth. She then
recited:" Certainly, thou canst not make the dead hear the call"
(xxvii. 80), nor can you make those hear who are in the graves, nor
can you inform them when they have taken their seats in
Hell.</english-text>
</hadith>
