<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12173</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2204</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Funerals) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20259, 11062, 11455</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا ابن المثنى، وابن أبي عمر، قال ابن المثنى حدثنا
عبد الوهاب، قال سمعت يحيى بن سعيد، يقول أخبرتني عمرة، أنها سمعت
عائشة، تقول لما جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قتل ابن حارثة
وجعفر بن أبي طالب وعبد الله بن رواحة جلس رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يعرف فيه الحزن قالت وأنا أنظر من صائر الباب - شق الباب - فأتاه
رجل فقال يا رسول الله إن نساء جعفر وذكر بكاءهن فأمره أن يذهب
فينهاهن فذهب فأتاه فذكر أنهن لم يطعنه فأمره الثانية أن يذهب فينهاهن
فذهب ثم أتاه فقال والله لقد غلبننا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قالت فزعمت أن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ اذهب فاحث في أفواههن من التراب
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فقلت أرغم الله أنفك والله ما تفعل ما أمرك رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وما تركت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من
العناء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'A'isha reported that when the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) was told that Ibn Haritha, Ja'far b. Abu
Talib and Abdullah b. Rawaha were killed, he sat down, showing
signs of grief. She (further) said: I was looking (at him) through
the crevice of the door. A man came to him and mentioned that
Ja'far's women were lamenting. He (the Holy Prophet) commanded him
to go and forbid them (to do so). So he went away but came back and
told (him) that they did not obey (him). He commanded him a second
time to go and forbid them (to do so). He again went but came back
to him and said: I swear by God, Messenger of Allah, that they have
overpowered us. She ('A'isha) said that she thought the Messenger
of Allah (may peace be upon him) had told (her) to throw dust in
their mouths. Thereupon 'A'isha said: May Allah humble you! You did
not do what Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon him) ordered you,
nor did you stop annoying Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him).</english-text>
</hadith>
