<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12212</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2243</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Prayer (Funerals) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>20379, 20208, 11295, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن أيوب، وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة وزهير بن حرب
وعلي بن حجر السعدي كلهم عن ابن علية، - واللفظ ليحيى قال حدثنا ابن
علية، - أخبرنا عبد العزيز، بن صهيب عن أنس بن مالك، قال مر بجنازة
فأثني عليها خير فقال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وجبت وجبت وجبت
‏"‏ ‏.‏ ومر بجنازة فأثني عليها شر فقال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ وجبت وجبت وجبت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عمر فدى لك أبي وأمي مر بجنازة فأثني
عليها خيرا فقلت وجبت وجبت وجبت ‏.‏ ومر بجنازة فأثني عليها شر فقلت
وجبت وجبت وجبت فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أثنيتم عليه
خيرا وجبت له الجنة ومن أثنيتم عليه شرا وجبت له النار أنتم شهداء
الله في الأرض أنتم شهداء الله في الأرض أنتم شهداء الله في الأرض ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik reported: There passed a bier (being
carried by people) and it was lauded in good terms. Upon this the
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: It has become
certain, it has become certain, it has become certain. And there
passed a bier and it was condemned in bad words. Upon this the
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: It has become
certain, it has become certain, it has become certain. 'Umar said:
May my father and mother be ransom for you! There passed a bier and
it was praised in good terms, and you said: It has become certain,
it has become certain, it has become certain. And there passed a
bier and it was condemned in bad words, and you said: It has become
certain, it has become certain, it has become certain. Upon this
the Messenger of Allah (way peace be upon him) said: He whom you
praised in good terms, Paradise has become certain for him, and he
whom you condemned in bad words, Hell has become certain for him.
You are Allah's witnesses in the earth, you are Allah's witnesses
in the earth, you are Allah's witnesses in the
earth.</english-text>
</hadith>
