<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12300</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2337</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30547, 20421, 11163, 11161, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثني سويد بن سعيد، حدثنا حفص، - يعني ابن ميسرة
الصنعاني - عن زيد بن أسلم، أن أبا صالح، ذكوان أخبره أنه، سمع أبا
هريرة، يقول قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما من صاحب ذهب ولا
فضة لا يؤدي منها حقها إلا إذا كان يوم القيامة صفحت له صفائح من نار
فأحمي عليها في نار جهنم فيكوى بها جنبه وجبينه وظهره كلما بردت أعيدت
له في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة حتى يقضى بين العباد فيرى سبيله
إما إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا رسول الله فالإبل قال
‏"‏ ولا صاحب إبل لا يؤدي منها حقها ومن حقها حلبها يوم وردها إلا إذا
كان يوم القيامة بطح لها بقاع قرقر أوفر ما كانت لا يفقد منها فصيلا
واحدا تطؤه بأخفافها وتعضه بأفواهها كلما مر عليه أولاها رد عليه
أخراها في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة حتى يقضى بين العباد فيرى
سبيله إما إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا رسول الله فالبقر
والغنم قال ‏"‏ ولا صاحب بقر ولا غنم لا يؤدي منها حقها إلا إذا كان
يوم القيامة بطح لها بقاع قرقر لا يفقد منها شيئا ليس فيها عقصاء ولا
جلحاء ولا عضباء تنطحه بقرونها وتطؤه بأظلافها كلما مر عليه أولاها رد
عليه أخراها في يوم كان مقداره خمسين ألف سنة حتى يقضى بين العباد
فيرى سبيله إما إلى الجنة وإما إلى النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا رسول الله
فالخيل قال ‏"‏ الخيل ثلاثة هي لرجل وزر وهي لرجل ستر وهي لرجل أجر
فأما التي هي له وزر فرجل ربطها رياء وفخرا ونواء على أهل الإسلام فهي
له وزر وأما التي هي له ستر فرجل ربطها في سبيل الله ثم لم ينس حق
الله في ظهورها ولا رقابها فهي له ستر وأما التي هي له أجر فرجل ربطها
في سبيل الله لأهل الإسلام في مرج وروضة فما أكلت من ذلك المرج أو
الروضة من شىء إلا كتب له عدد ما أكلت حسنات وكتب له عدد أرواثها
وأبوالها حسنات ولا تقطع طولها فاستنت شرفا أو شرفين إلا كتب الله له
عدد آثارها وأرواثها حسنات ولا مر بها صاحبها على نهر فشربت منه ولا
يريد أن يسقيها إلا كتب الله له عدد ما شربت حسنات ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا
رسول الله فالحمر قال ‏"‏ ما أنزل على في الحمر شىء إلا هذه الآية
الفاذة الجامعة ‏{‏ فمن يعمل مثقال ذرة خيرا يره * ومن يعمل مثقال ذرة
شرا يره‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira reported Allah's Messenger (way peace be
upon him) as saying: If any owner of gold or silver does not pay
what is due on him, when the Day of Resurrection would come, plates
of fire would be beaten out for him; these would then be heated in
the fire of Hell and his sides, his forehead and his back would be
cauterized with them. Whenever these cool down, (the process is)
repeated during a day the extent of which would be fifty thousand
years, until judgment is pronounced among servants, and he sees
whether his path is to take him to Paradise or to Hell. It was
said: Messenger of Allah, what about the camel? He (the Holy
Prophet) said: If any owner of the camel does not pay what is due
on him, and of his due in that (camel) is (also) to milk it on the
day when it comes down to water. When the Day of Resurrection comes
a soft sandy plain would be set for him, as extensive as possible,
(he will find) that not a single young one is missing, and they
will trample him with their hoofs and bite him with their mouths.
As often as the first of them passes him, the last of them would be
made to return during a day the extent of which would be fifty
thousand years, until judgment is pronounced among servants and he
sees whether his path is to take him to Paradise or to Hell. It was
(again) said: Messenger of Allah, what about cows (cattle) and
sheep? He said: It any owner of the cattle and sheep does not pay
what is due on them, when the Day of Resurrection comes a soft
sandy plain would be spread for them, he will find none of them
missing, with twisted horns, without horns or with a broken horn,
and they will gore him with their horns and trample him with their
hoofs. As often as the first of them passes him the last of them
would be made to return to him during a day the extent of which
would be fifty thousand years, until judgment would be pronounced
among the servants. And he would be shown his path-path leading him
to Paradise or to Hell. It was said: Messenger of Allah, what about
the horse? Upon this he said: The horses are of three types. To one
than (these are) a burden, and to another man (these are) a
covering, and still to another man (these are) a source of reward.
The one for whom these are a burden is the person who rears them in
order to show off, for vainglory and for opposing the Muslims; so
they are a burden for him. The one for whom these are a covering is
the person who rears them for the sake of Allah but does not forget
the right of Allah concerning their backs and their necks, and so
they are a covering for him. As for those which bring reward (these
refer to) the person who rears them for the sake of Allah to be
used for Muslims and he puts them in meadow and field. And whatever
thing do these eat from that meadow and field would be recorded on
his behalf as good deeds, as would also the amount of their dung
and urine. And these would not break their halter and prance a
course or two without having got recorded the amount of their hoof
marks and their dung as a good deed on his behalf (on behalf of
their owner). And their master does not bring them past a river
from which they drink, though he did not intend to quench their
thirst, but Allah would record for him the amount of what they
drink on his behalf as deeds. It was said: Messenger of Allah, what
about the asses?, Upon this he said: Nothing has been revealed to
me in regard to the asses (in particular) except this one verse of
a comprehensive nature:" He who does an atom's weight of good will
see it, and he who does an atom's weight of evil will see it"
(xcix. 7)</english-text>
</hadith>
