<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12324</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2362</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، قال قرأت على مالك عن إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي، طلحة أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول كان أبو طلحة أكثر
أنصاري بالمدينة مالا وكان أحب أمواله إليه بيرحى وكانت مستقبلة
المسجد وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يدخلها ويشرب من ماء فيها
طيب ‏.‏ قال أنس فلما نزلت هذه الآية ‏{‏ لن تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا
مما تحبون‏}‏ قام أبو طلحة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال إن
الله يقول في كتابه ‏{‏ لن تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏ وإن
أحب أموالي إلى بيرحى وإنها صدقة لله أرجو برها وذخرها عند الله فضعها
يا رسول الله حيث شئت ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بخ
ذلك مال رابح ذلك مال رابح قد سمعت ما قلت فيها وإني أرى أن تجعلها في
الأقربين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقسمها أبو طلحة في أقاربه وبني عمه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas b. Malik is reported as saying: Abu Talha was
the one among the Ansar of Medina who possessed the largest
property and among his property he valued most was his garden known
as Bairaha' which was opposite the mosque, and the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) often visited it and he drank of its
sweet water. When this verse was revealed:" You will never attain
righteousness till you give freely of what you Have" (iii. 91), Abu
Talha got up and, going to Allah's Messenger (may peace be upon
him), said: Allah says in His Book:" You will never attain
righteousness till you give freely of what you love," and the
dearest of my property is Bairaha' so I give it as Sadaqa to God
from Whom I hope for reward for it and the treasure with Allah; so
spend it, Messenger of Allah, on whatever purpose you deem it
proper. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: Bravo
I that is profit earning property. I have heard what you have said,
but I think you should spend it on your nearest relatives. So Abu
Talha distributed it among the neatest relatives and his cousins on
his father's side.</english-text>
</hadith>
