<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12412</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2450</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 30417, 237, 30025, 20201, 20638, 11414, 11027,
11026</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن الدارمي، وسلمة بن شبيب، -
قال سلمة حدثنا وقال الدارمي، أخبرنا مروان، وهو ابن محمد الدمشقي -
حدثنا سعيد، - وهو ابن عبد العزيز - عن ربيعة بن يزيد، عن أبي إدريس
الخولاني، عن أبي مسلم الخولاني، قال حدثني الحبيب الأمين، أما هو
فحبيب إلى وأما هو عندي فأمين عوف بن مالك الأشجعي قال كنا عند رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تسعة أو ثمانية أو سبعة فقال ‏"‏ ألا تبايعون
رسول الله ‏"‏ وكنا حديث عهد ببيعة فقلنا قد بايعناك يا رسول الله ‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ ألا تبايعون رسول الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلنا قد بايعناك يا رسول
الله ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ألا تبايعون رسول الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبسطنا أيدينا
وقلنا قد بايعناك يا رسول الله فعلام نبايعك قال ‏"‏ على أن تعبدوا
الله ولا تشركوا به شيئا والصلوات الخمس وتطيعوا - وأسر كلمة خفية -
ولا تسألوا الناس شيئا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلقد رأيت بعض أولئك النفر يسقط سوط
أحدهم فما يسأل أحدا يناوله إياه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Malik al-Ashja'i reported: We, nine, eight or seven
men, were in the company of the Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) and he said: Why don't you pledge allegiance to the
Messenger of Allah? -while we had recently pledged allegiance. So
we said: Messenger of Allah, we have already pledged allegiance to
you. He again said: Why don't you pledge allegiance to the
Messenger of Allah? And we said: Messenger of Allah, we have
already pledged allegiance to you. He again said: Why don't you
pledge allegiance to the Messenger of Allah? We stretched our hands
and said: Messenger of Allah. we have already pledged allegiance to
you. Now tell (on what things) should we pledge allegiance to you.
He said I (You must pledge allegiance) that you would worship Allah
only and would not associate with Him anything, (and observe) five
prayers, and obey- (and he said onething in an undertone) -that you
would not beg people of anything. (And as a consequence of that) I
saw that some of these people did not ask anyone to pick up the
whip for them if it fell down.</english-text>
</hadith>
