<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12431</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2468</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 30367, 20023, 11168, 11260,
38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وحدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، أخبرنا الليث بن سعد، ح وحدثنا
قتيبة بن سعيد، - وتقاربا في اللفظ - قال حدثنا ليث، عن سعيد بن أبي
سعيد المقبري، عن عياض بن، عبد الله بن سعد أنه سمع أبا سعيد الخدري،
يقول قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخطب الناس فقال ‏"‏ لا والله
ما أخشى عليكم أيها الناس إلا ما يخرج الله لكم من زهرة الدنيا ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقال رجل يا رسول الله أيأتي الخير بالشر فصمت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ساعة ثم قال ‏"‏ كيف قلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله
أيأتي الخير بالشر فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الخير
لا يأتي إلا بخير أو خير هو إن كل ما ينبت الربيع يقتل حبطا أو يلم
إلا آكلة الخضر أكلت حتى إذا امتلأت خاصرتاها استقبلت الشمس ثلطت أو
بالت ثم اجترت فعادت فأكلت فمن يأخذ مالا بحقه يبارك له فيه ومن يأخذ
مالا بغير حقه فمثله كمثل الذي يأكل ولا يشبع ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Sa'id al-Khudri reported that the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) stood up and addressed the people
thus: 0 people, by Allah, I do not entertain fear about you in
regard to anything else than that which Allah would bring forth for
you in the form of adornment of the world. A person said: Messenger
of Allah, does good produce evil? The Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) remained silent for a while and he then said: What did
you say? He replied: Messenger of Allah, I said: Does good produce
evil? The Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said to him:
The good does not produce but good. but among the plants the spring
rain produces There some which kill with a tremour or nearly kill
all but the animal which feeds on vegetation. It eats and when its
flanks are distended, it faces the can. then when it has donged or
urinated and chewed it returns and eats. He who accepts wealth
rightly, Allah confers blessing on it for him. and he who takes
wealth without any right, he is like one who eats and is not
satisfied.</english-text>
</hadith>
