<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12456</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2493</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30251, 20155, 11210, 639, 605</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سريج بن يونس، حدثنا إسماعيل بن جعفر، عن عمرو بن
يحيى بن عمارة، عن عباد بن تميم، عن عبد الله بن زيد، أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم لما فتح حنينا قسم الغنائم فأعطى المؤلفة قلوبهم
فبلغه أن الأنصار يحبون أن يصيبوا ما أصاب الناس فقام رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فخطبهم فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ يا معشر
الأنصار ألم أجدكم ضلالا فهداكم الله بي وعالة فأغناكم الله بي
ومتفرقين فجمعكم الله بي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ويقولون الله ورسوله أمن ‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ ألا تجيبوني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا الله ورسوله أمن ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أما
إنكم لو شئتم أن تقولوا كذا وكذا وكان من الأمر كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
لأشياء عددها ‏.‏ زعم عمرو أن لا يحفظها فقال ‏"‏ ألا ترضون أن يذهب
الناس بالشاء والإبل وتذهبون برسول الله إلى رحالكم الأنصار شعار
والناس دثار ولولا الهجرة لكنت امرأ من الأنصار ولو سلك الناس واديا
وشعبا لسلكت وادي الأنصار وشعبهم إنكم ستلقون بعدي أثرة فاصبروا حتى
تلقوني على الحوض ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah b. Zaid reported that when the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) conquered Hunain he distributed the
booty, and he bestowed upon those whose hearts it was intended to
win. It was conveyed to him (the Holy Prophet) that the Ansar
cherished a desire that they should be given (that very portion)
which the people (of Quraish) had got. Upon this the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him) stood up and, after having praised
Allah and lauded Him, addressed them thus: 0 people of Ansar, did I
not find you erring and Allah guided you aright through me, and (in
the state of) being destitute and Allah made you free from want
through me, and in a state of disunity and Allah united you through
me, and they (the Ansar) said: Allah and His Messenger are most
benevolent. He (again) said: Why do you not answer me? They said:
Allah and His Messenger are the most benevolent. He said, If you
wish you should say so and so, and the event (should take) such and
such course (and in this connection he made a mention) of so many
things. 'Amr is under the impressionthat he has not been able to
remember them. He (the Holy Prophet) further said: Don't you feel
happy (over this state of affairs) that the people should go away
with goats and camels, and you go to your places along with the
Messenger of Allah? The Ansar are inner garments (more close to me)
and (other) people are outer garments. Had there not been
migration, I would have been a man from among the Ansar. If the
people were to tread a valley or a narrow path, I would tread the
valley (chosen) by the Ansar or narrow path (trodden) by them. And
you would soon find after me preferences (over you in getting
material benefits). So you should show patience till you meet me at
the Haud (Kauthar).</english-text>
</hadith>
