<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12457</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2494</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30022, 30203, 30123, 30312, 4057, 11067, 11353,
16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زهير بن حرب، وعثمان بن أبي شيبة، وإسحاق بن
إبراهيم، قال إسحاق أخبرنا وقال الآخران، حدثنا جرير، عن منصور، عن
أبي وائل، عن عبد الله، قال لما كان يوم حنين آثر رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ناسا في القسمة فأعطى الأقرع بن حابس مائة من الإبل وأعطى
عيينة مثل ذلك وأعطى أناسا من أشراف العرب وآثرهم يومئذ في القسمة
فقال رجل والله إن هذه لقسمة ما عدل فيها وما أريد فيها وجه الله ‏.‏
قال فقلت والله لأخبرن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - قال - فأتيته
فأخبرته بما قال - قال - فتغير وجهه حتى كان كالصرف ثم قال ‏"‏ فمن
يعدل إن لم يعدل الله ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم قال ‏"‏ يرحم الله موسى
قد أوذي بأكثر من هذا فصبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت لا جرم لا أرفع إليه بعدها
حديثا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah reported: On the day of Hunain, the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) showed preference (to
some) People in the distribution of the spoils. He bestowed on
Aqra' b. Habis one hundred camels, and bestowed an equal (number)
upon 'Uyaina, and bestowed on people among the elites of Arabia,
and pre. ferred them) (to others) on that day, in the distribution
(of spoils). Upon this a person said: By Allah, neither justice has
been done In this distribution (of spoils), nor has the pleasure of
Allah been sought in it. I (the Narrator ) said: By Allah, I will
certainly inform the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him)
about it. so I came to him and informed him about what he had said.
- The colour of his (the Prophet's) face changed red like blood and
he then said: Who would do justice, if Allah and His Messenger do
not do justice? He further said: May Allah have mercy upon Moses;
he was tormented more than this, but he showed patience. I said:
Never would I convey him (the Holy Prophet) after this (unpleasant)
narration.</english-text>
</hadith>
