<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12461</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2499</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20327, 20016, 11366, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد بن السري، حدثنا أبو الأحوص، عن سعيد بن
مسروق، عن عبد الرحمن، بن أبي نعم عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال بعث علي -
رضى الله عنه - وهو باليمن بذهبة في تربتها إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقسمها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بين أربعة نفر الأقرع
بن حابس الحنظلي وعيينة بن بدر الفزاري وعلقمة بن علاثة العامري ثم
أحد بني كلاب وزيد الخير الطائي ثم أحد بني نبهان - قال - فغضبت قريش
فقالوا أتعطي صناديد نجد وتدعنا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ إني إنما فعلت ذلك لأتألفهم ‏"‏ فجاء رجل كث اللحية مشرف الوجنتين
غائر العينين ناتئ الجبين محلوق الرأس فقال اتق الله يا محمد ‏.‏ -
قال - فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فمن يطع الله إن عصيته
أيأمنني على أهل الأرض ولا تأمنوني ‏"‏ قال ثم أدبر الرجل فاستأذن رجل
من القوم في قتله - يرون أنه خالد بن الوليد - فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن من ضئضئ هذا قوما يقرءون القرآن لا يجاوز
حناجرهم يقتلون أهل الإسلام ويدعون أهل الأوثان يمرقون من الإسلام كما
يمرق السهم من الرمية لئن أدركتهم لأقتلنهم قتل عاد ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Said Khudri reported that 'Ali (Allah be pleased
with him) sent some gold alloyed with dust to the Messenger of
Allah (may peace be upon him), and the Messenger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) distributed that among four men, al-Aqra b.
Habis Hanzali and Uyaina b. Badr al-Fazari and 'Alqama b. 'Ulatha
al-'Amiri, then to one person of the tribe of Kilab and to Zaid
al-Khair al-Ta'l, and then to one person of the tribe of Nabhan.
Upon this the people of Quraish felt angry and said: He (the Holy
Prophet) gave to the chiefs of Najd and ignored us. Upon this the
Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: I have done it
with a view to con- cillating them. Then there came a person with
thick beard, prominent cheeks, deep sunken eyes and protruding
forehead and shaven head. He said: Muhammad, fear Allah. Upon this
the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) said: If I disobey
Allah, who would then obey Him? Have I not been (sent as the) most
trustworthy among the people of the-world? -but you do not repose
trust in me. That person then went back. A person among the people
then sought permission (from the Holy Prophet) for his murder.
According to some, it was Khalid b. Walid who sought the
permission. Upon this the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon
him), said: From this very person's posterity there would arise
people who would recite the Qur'an, but it would not go beyond
their throat; they would kill the followers of Islam and would
spare the idol-worshippers. They would glance through the teachings
of Islam so hurriedly just as the arrow passes through the pray. If
I were to ever find them I would kill them like 'Ad.</english-text>
</hadith>
