<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12462</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2500</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20256, 11379, 11366, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا عبد الواحد، عن عمارة بن
القعقاع، حدثنا عبد، الرحمن بن أبي نعم قال سمعت أبا سعيد الخدري،
يقول بعث علي بن أبي طالب إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من اليمن
بذهبة في أديم مقروظ لم تحصل من ترابها - قال - فقسمها بين أربعة نفر
بين عيينة بن حصن والأقرع بن حابس وزيد الخيل والرابع إما علقمة بن
علاثة وإما عامر بن الطفيل فقال رجل من أصحابه كنا نحن أحق بهذا من
هؤلاء - قال - فبلغ ذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ألا
تأمنوني وأنا أمين من في السماء يأتيني خبر السماء صباحا ومساء ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فقام رجل غائر العينين مشرف الوجنتين ناشز الجبهة كث اللحية
محلوق الرأس مشمر الإزار فقال يا رسول الله اتق الله ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
ويلك أولست أحق أهل الأرض أن يتقي الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم ولى الرجل فقال
خالد بن الوليد يا رسول الله ألا أضرب عنقه فقال ‏"‏ لا لعله أن يكون
يصلي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال خالد وكم من مصل يقول بلسانه ما ليس في قلبه ‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني لم أومر أن أنقب عن قلوب
الناس ولا أشق بطونهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم نظر إليه وهو مقف فقال ‏"‏ إنه
يخرج من ضئضئ هذا قوم يتلون كتاب الله رطبا لا يجاوز حناجرهم يمرقون
من الدين كما يمرق السهم من الرمية - قال أظنه قال - لئن أدركتهم
لأقتلنهم قتل ثمود ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Said al-Khudri reported: 'Ali b. Abu Talib sent
to the Messenger of Allah (may peace be upon him) from Yemen some
gold alloyed with clay in a leather bag dyed in the leaves of
Mimosa flava. He distributed it among four men. 'Uyaina b. Hisna,
Aqra' b. Habis and Zaid al-Khail, and the fourth one was either
Alqama b. 'Ulatha or 'Amir b. Tufail. A person from among his
(Prophet's) Companions said: We had a better claim to this (wealth)
than these (persons). This (remark) reached the Apostle of Allah
(may peace be upon him) upon which he said: Will you not trust me,
whereas I am a trustee of Him Who is in the heaven? The news come
to me from the heaven morning and evening. Then there stood up a
person with deep snnken eyes, prominent cheek bones, and elevated
forehead, thick beard, shaven head, tucked up loin cloth, and he
said: Messenger of Allah, fear Allah. He (the Holy Prophet) said:
Woe to thee. do I not deserve most to fear Allah amongst the people
of the earth? That man then returned. Khalid b. Walid then said:
Messenger of Allah, should I not strike his neck? Upon this he (the
Holy Prophet) said: Perhaps he may be observing the prayer. Khalid
said: How many observers of prayer are there who profess with their
tongue what is not in their heart? Upon this the Messenger of Allah
(may peace be upon him) said: I have not been commanded to pierce
through the hearts of people, nor to split their bellies (insides).
He again looked at him and he was going back. Upon this he (the
Holy Prophet) said: There would arise a people from the progeny of
this (man) who would recite the Qur'an glibly, but it would not go
beyond their throats; they would (hurriedly) pass through (the
teachings of their) religion just as the arrow passes through the
prey. I conceive that he (the Holy Prophet) also said this: If I
find them I would certainly kill them as were killed the (people
of) Thamud.</english-text>
</hadith>
