<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12537</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2580</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20379, 30367, 30399, 20155, 11535,
11211</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، ويحيى بن أيوب، وقتيبة، وابن، حجر
قال يحيى بن يحيى أخبرنا وقال الآخرون، حدثنا إسماعيل، - وهو ابن جعفر
- عن محمد، - وهو ابن أبي حرملة - عن كريب، أن أم الفضل بنت الحارث،
بعثته إلى معاوية بالشام قال فقدمت الشام فقضيت حاجتها واستهل على
رمضان وأنا بالشام فرأيت الهلال ليلة الجمعة ثم قدمت المدينة في آخر
الشهر فسألني عبد الله بن عباس - رضى الله عنهما - ثم ذكر الهلال فقال
متى رأيتم الهلال فقلت رأيناه ليلة الجمعة ‏.‏ فقال أنت رأيته فقلت
نعم ورآه الناس وصاموا وصام معاوية ‏.‏ فقال لكنا رأيناه ليلة السبت
فلا نزال نصوم حتى نكمل ثلاثين أو نراه ‏.‏ فقلت أولا تكتفي برؤية
معاوية وصيامه فقال لا هكذا أمرنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏
وشك يحيى بن يحيى في نكتفي أو تكتفي ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Kuraib reported that Umm Fadl, daughter of Harith,
sent him (Fadl, i. e. her son) to Mu'awiya in Syria. I (Fadl)
arrived in Syria, and did the needful for her. It was there in
Syria that the month of Ramadan commenced. I saw the new moon (of
Ramadan) on Friday. I then came back to Medina at the end of the
month. Abdullah b. 'Abbas (Allah be pleased with him) asked me
(about the new moon of Ramadan) and said: When did you see it? I
said.: We saw it on the night of Friday. He said: (Did) you see it
yourself? -I said: Yes, and the people also saw it and they
observed fast and Mu'awiya also observed fast, whereupon he said:
But we saw it on Saturday night. So we would continue to observe
fast till we complete thirty (lasts) or we see it (the new moon of
Shawwal). I said: Is the sightidg of the moon by Mu'awiya not valid
for you? He said: No; this is how the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) has commanded us. Yahya b. Yahya was in doubt (whether
the word used in the narration by Kuraib) was Naktafi or
Taktafi.</english-text>
</hadith>
