<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12604</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2651</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20005, 20031, 20005, 11013, 10561,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن يحيى، وأبو بكر بن أبي شيبة وزهير بن حرب
وابن نمير كلهم عن ابن عيينة، - قال يحيى أخبرنا سفيان بن عيينة، - عن
الزهري، عن حميد بن عبد، الرحمن عن أبي هريرة، - رضى الله عنه - قال
جاء رجل إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال هلكت يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ وما أهلكك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقعت على امرأتي في رمضان ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل
تجد ما تعتق رقبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فهل تستطيع أن تصوم
شهرين متتابعين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فهل تجد ما تطعم ستين
مسكينا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا - قال - ثم جلس فأتي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بعرق فيه تمر ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ تصدق بهذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أفقر منا فما بين
لابتيها أهل بيت أحوج إليه منا ‏.‏ فضحك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى
بدت أنيابه ثم قال ‏"‏ اذهب فأطعمه أهلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Huraira (Allah be pleased with him) reported that
a person came to the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) and
said: Messenger of Allah, I am undone. He (the Holy Prophet) said:
What has brought about your ruin? He said: I have had intercourse
with my wife during the month of Ramadan. Upon this he (the Holy
prophet) said: Can you find a slave to set him free? He said: NO He
(the Holy Prophet again) said: Can you observe fast for two
consecutive months? He said: No. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Can
you provide food to sixty poor people?, He said: No. He then sat
down and (in the meanwhile) there was brought to the Apostle of
Allah (may peace be upon him) a basket which contained dates. He
(the Holy Prophet) said: Give these (dates) in charity. He (the
man) said: Am I to give to one who is poorer than I? There is no
family poorer than mine between the two lava plains of Medina. The
Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon him) laughed so that his molar
teeth became visible and said: Go and give it to your family to
eat.</english-text>
</hadith>
