<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>12612</id>
<source>Sahih Muslim</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2659</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20377, 10530, 11215, 11250</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو الطاهر، أخبرنا ابن وهب، أخبرني عمرو بن
الحارث، أن عبد الرحمن، بن القاسم حدثه أن محمد بن جعفر بن الزبير
حدثه أن عباد بن عبد الله بن الزبير حدثه أنه، سمع عائشة، زوج النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم تقول أتى رجل إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
المسجد في رمضان فقال يا رسول الله احترقت احترقت ‏.‏ فسأله رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما شأنه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أصبت أهلي ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
تصدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال والله يا نبي الله ما لي شىء وما أقدر عليه ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ اجلس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجلس فبينا هو على ذلك أقبل رجل يسوق حمارا عليه
طعام فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أين المحترق آنفا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقام الرجل فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تصدق بهذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقال يا رسول الله أغيرنا فوالله إنا لجياع ما لنا شىء ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فكلوه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abbad b. Abdullah b. Zubair reported that he had
heard 'A'isha, the wife of the Apostle of Allah (may peace be upon
him), as saying: A person came to the Messenger of Allah (may peace
be upon him) in the mosque during (the month of) Ramadan and said:
Messenger of Allah, I am burnt I am burnt, whereupon the Mes-
senger of Allah (may peace be upon him) asked him as to what the
matter was. Upon this he said: I had intercourse with my wife (in a
state of fasting) Thereupon he (the Holy Prophet) said: Give
charity. Upon this he said: Apostle of Allah, I swear by God, there
is nothing with me (to give in charity) as I do not possess
anything. He (the Holy Prophet) said: Sit down. So he sat down and
he was in this very state when there came a person urging a donkey
with a load of eatables upon it. The Mes- senger of Allah (may
peace be upon him) said: Where is that burnt one who was just here?
Thereupon the person stood up. The Messenger of Allah (may peace be
upon him) said: Give this (eatables brought by the man) in charity.
Upon this the person said: Messenger of Allah, can there be anyone
else (more deserving than I)? By Allah. we are hungry, we have
nothing with us. Upon this he (the Holy Prophet) said: Then eat
(these eatables).</english-text>
</hadith>
