<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30149</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>149</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salat (Prayer) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20509, 20701, 19803, 11059, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد بن السري، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن أبي الزناد،
عن عبد الرحمن بن الحارث بن عياش بن أبي ربيعة، عن حكيم بن حكيم، وهو
ابن عباد بن حنيف أخبرني نافع بن جبير بن مطعم، قال أخبرني ابن عباس،
أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أمني جبريل عليه السلام عند
البيت مرتين فصلى الظهر في الأولى منهما حين كان الفىء مثل الشراك ثم
صلى العصر حين كان كل شيء مثل ظله ثم صلى المغرب حين وجبت الشمس وأفطر
الصائم ثم صلى العشاء حين غاب الشفق ثم صلى الفجر حين برق الفجر وحرم
الطعام على الصائم ‏.‏ وصلى المرة الثانية الظهر حين كان ظل كل شيء
مثله لوقت العصر بالأمس ثم صلى العصر حين كان ظل كل شيء مثليه ثم صلى
المغرب لوقته الأول ثم صلى العشاء الآخرة حين ذهب ثلث الليل ثم صلى
الصبح حين أسفرت الأرض ثم التفت إلى جبريل فقال يا محمد هذا وقت
الأنبياء من قبلك ‏.‏ والوقت فيما بين هذين الوقتين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو
عيسى وفي الباب عن أبي هريرة وبريدة وأبي موسى وأبي مسعود الأنصاري
وأبي سعيد وجابر وعمرو بن حزم والبراء وأنس ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Abbas narrated that : the Prophet said: "Jibril
(peace be upon him] led me (in Salat) twice at the House. So he
prayed Zuhr the first time when the shadow was similar to (the
length of) the strap a sandal. Then he prayed Asr when everything
was similar (to the length of) its shadow. Then he prayed Maghrib
when the sun had set and the fasting person breaks fast. Then he
prayed Isha when the twilight had vanished. Then he prayed Fajr
when Fajr (dawn) began, and when eating is prohibited for the
fasting person. The second time he prayed Zuhr when the shadow of
everything was similar to (the length of) it, at the time of Asr
the day before. Then he prayed Asr when the shadow of everything
was about twice as long as it. Then he prayed Maghrib at the same
time as he did the first time. Then he prayed Isha, the later one,
when a third of the night had gone. Then he prayed Subh when the
land glowed. The Jibril turned towards me and said: "O Muhammad!
These are the times of the Prophets before you, and the (best) time
is what is between these two times."</english-text>
</hadith>
