<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30414</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>413</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Salat (Prayer) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20264, 20548, 20297, 11019, 11016</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن نصر بن علي الجهضمي، حدثنا سهل بن حماد،
حدثنا همام، قال حدثني قتادة، عن الحسن، عن حريث بن قبيصة، قال قدمت
المدينة فقلت اللهم يسر لي جليسا صالحا ‏.‏ قال فجلست إلى أبي هريرة
فقلت إني سألت الله أن يرزقني جليسا صالحا فحدثني بحديث سمعته من رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لعل الله أن ينفعني به فقال سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إن أول ما يحاسب به العبد يوم القيامة من
عمله صلاته فإن صلحت فقد أفلح وأنجح وإن فسدت فقد خاب وخسر فإن انتقص
من فريضته شيء قال الرب عز وجل انظروا هل لعبدي من تطوع فيكمل بها ما
انتقص من الفريضة ثم يكون سائر عمله على ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وفي الباب عن
تميم الداري ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى حديث أبي هريرة حديث حسن غريب من هذا
الوجه ‏.‏ وقد روي هذا الحديث من غير هذا الوجه عن أبي هريرة وقد روى
بعض أصحاب الحسن عن الحسن عن قبيصة بن حريث غير هذا الحديث والمشهور
هو قبيصة بن حريث ‏.‏ وروي عن أنس بن حكيم عن أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم نحو هذا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Huraith bin Qabisah narrated: "I arrived in
Al-Madinah and said: 'O Allah! Facilitate me to be in a righteous
gathering.'" He said: "I sat with Abu Hurairah and said: 'Indeed I
asked Allah to provide me with a righteous gathering. So narrate a
hadith to me which you heard from Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) so that
perhaps Allah would cause me to benefit from it.' He said: 'I heard
Allah's Messenger (ﷺ) say: "Indeed the first deed by which a
servant will be called to account on the Day of Resurrection is his
Salat. If it is complete, he is successful and saved, but if it is
defective, he has failed and lost. So if something is deficient in
his obligatory (prayers) then the Lord, Mighty and Sublime says:
'Look! Are there any voluntary (prayers) for my worshipper?' So
with them, what was deficient in his obligatory (prayers) will be
completed. Then the rest of his deeds will be treated like
that."</english-text>
</hadith>
