<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30480</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>479</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Al-Witr - أَبْوَابُ الْوِتْرِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30353, 20244, 5115</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عيسى بن يزيد البغدادي، حدثنا عبد الله بن
بكر السهمي، ‏.‏ وحدثنا عبد الله بن منير، عن عبد الله بن بكر، عن
فائد بن عبد الرحمن، عن عبد الله بن أبي أوفى، قال قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من كانت له إلى الله حاجة أو إلى أحد من بني آدم
فليتوضأ وليحسن الوضوء ثم ليصل ركعتين ثم ليثن على الله وليصل على
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم ليقل لا إله إلا الله الحليم الكريم
سبحان الله رب العرش العظيم الحمد لله رب العالمين أسألك موجبات رحمتك
وعزائم مغفرتك والغنيمة من كل بر والسلامة من كل إثم لا تدع لي ذنبا
إلا غفرته ولا هما إلا فرجته ولا حاجة هي لك رضا إلا قضيتها يا أرحم
الراحمين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب وفي إسناده مقال ‏.‏
فائد بن عبد الرحمن يضعف في الحديث وفائد هو أبو الورقاء
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah bin Abi Awfa narrated that : Allah's
Messenger said: "Whomever has a need from Allah, or from one of the
sons of Adam, then let him perform Wudu, performing it well, then
pry two Rak'ah, then pray Allah and say Salat upon the Prophet.
Then let him say: (L ilaha illallah Al-Halimul-Karim. Subhan Alla
Rabbil-Arshil-Azim. Al-Hamdulillahi Rabbil-Alamin. Asaluka mujibati
rahmatika wa aza'im maghfiratika, wal-ghanimata min kulli birrin,
was-salamata min kulli ithmin la tada li dhanban illa ghafartahu,
wa la hamman illa farrajtahu, wa la Hajatan hiya laka radan Illa
Qadaitaha, ya arham ar-rahimin.) 'None has the right t be worshiped
but Allah. Al-Halim (the Forbearing) Al-Karim (the Generous).
Glorious is Allah, Lord of the Magnificent Throne. All praise is
due to Allah, Lord of the worlds. I ask You for that which warrants
Your mercy, and that which will determine Your forgiveness, and the
spoils (fruits) of every righteous deed, and safety from every sin;
do not leave a sin for me without forgiving it, nor a worry without
relieving it. Or a need that pleases you without granting it. O
Most-Merciful of those who have mercy.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
