<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30481</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>480</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Al-Witr - أَبْوَابُ الْوِتْرِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20441, 11048, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن أبي الموالي، عن محمد
بن المنكدر، عن جابر بن عبد الله، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يعلمنا الاستخارة في الأمور كلها كما يعلمنا السورة من القرآن
يقول ‏"‏ إذا هم أحدكم بالأمر فليركع ركعتين من غير الفريضة ثم ليقل
اللهم إني أستخيرك بعلمك وأستقدرك بقدرتك وأسألك من فضلك العظيم فإنك
تقدر ولا أقدر وتعلم ولا أعلم وأنت علام الغيوب اللهم إن كنت تعلم أن
هذا الأمر خير لي في ديني ومعيشتي وعاقبة أمري أو قال في عاجل أمري
وآجله فيسره لي ثم بارك لي فيه وإن كنت تعلم أن هذا الأمر شر لي في
ديني ومعيشتي وعاقبة أمري أو قال في عاجل أمري وآجله فاصرفه عني
واصرفني عنه واقدر لي الخير حيث كان ثم أرضني به قال ويسمي حاجته ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال وفي الباب عن عبد الله بن مسعود وأبي أيوب ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى
حديث جابر حديث حسن صحيح غريب لا نعرفه إلا من حديث عبد الرحمن بن أبي
الموالي ‏.‏ وهو شيخ مديني ثقة روى عنه سفيان حديثا وقد روى عن عبد
الرحمن غير واحد من الأئمة وهو عبد الرحمن بن زيد بن أبي الموالي
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir bin Abdullah narrated: "Allah's Messenger would
teach us Al-Isthikhara for all of our affairs just as he would
teach us a Surah of the Qur'an, saying: 'When one of you is worried
about a matter, then let him perform two Rak'ah other than the
obligatory (prayer), then let him say: (Allahumma inni astakhiruka
bi'ilmika, wa astaqdiruka biqudratika, wa as'aluka min
falikal-azim, fa innaka taqdiru wa la qadiru, wa ta'lami wa la
a'lamu, wa anta allamul-ghayub. Allahumma in kunta ta'lamu anna
hadhal-amra khairun li fi dini wa ma'ishati wa aqibati amri, or
said: Fi ajili amri wa ajilihi fayassirhu li,thumma barik li fihi,
wa in kunta ta'lamu anna hadhal-amra sharrun li fi dini wa
ma'ishati wa aqibati amri, or said: Fi ajili amri wa ajilihi
fasrifhu anni wasrifni anhu waqdur Lil-khaira haithu kana, thumma
ardini bih.)" 'O Allah! I consult Your knowledge, and seek ability
from Your power, and I ask You from Your magnificent bounty, for
indeed You have power and I do not have power, and You know while I
do not know, and You know the unseen. O Allah! If you know that
this matter is good for me in my religion or my livelihood, and for
my life in the Hereafter - or he said: for my present and future -
then make it easy for me, then bless me in it. If You know that
this matter is bad for me in my religion and my livelihood and my
life in the Hereafter - or he said: for my present and future -
then divert it from me and divert me from it, enable me to find the
good wherever it is, then make me pleased with it."He said: "And he
mentions his need."</english-text>
</hadith>
