<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30492</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>491</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on the Day of Friday - كِتَاب الْجُمُعَةِ عَنْ
رَسُولِ اللَّهِ صَلَّى اللَّهُ عَلَيْهِ وَسَلَّمَ</chapter>
<chain-index>30410, 30112, 20001, 11234, 11213, 10567,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن موسى الأنصاري، حدثنا معن، حدثنا مالك بن
أنس، عن يزيد بن عبد الله بن الهاد، عن محمد بن إبراهيم، عن أبي سلمة،
عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خير يوم طلعت
فيه الشمس يوم الجمعة فيه خلق آدم وفيه أدخل الجنة وفيه أهبط منها
وفيه ساعة لا يوافقها عبد مسلم يصلي فيسأل الله فيها شيئا إلا أعطاه
إياه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو هريرة فلقيت عبد الله بن سلام فذكرت له هذا
الحديث فقال أنا أعلم بتلك الساعة ‏.‏ فقلت أخبرني بها ولا تضنن بها
على قال هي بعد العصر إلى أن تغرب الشمس ‏.‏ فقلت كيف تكون بعد العصر
وقد قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا يوافقها عبد مسلم وهو
يصلي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وتلك الساعة لا يصلى فيها فقال عبد الله بن سلام أليس قد
قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من جلس مجلسا ينتظر الصلاة فهو
في صلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت بلى ‏.‏ قال فهو ذاك ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وفي الحديث
قصة طويلة ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وهذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ قال ومعنى قوله
‏"‏ أخبرني بها ولا تضنن بها على ‏"‏ ‏.‏ لا تبخل بها على والضن البخل
والظنين المتهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated: "Allah's Messenger said: The
best day that the sun has risen upon is Friday. On it Adam was
created, on it he entered Paradise, and on it, he was sent down
from it. And in it there is an hour in which the Muslim worshipper
would not stand in Salat, asking Allah for anything except that He
would give it to him.'" Abu Hurairah said: "I met Abdullah bin
Salam, and I mentioned this Hadith to him. He said: 'I am more
knowledgeable about that hour.' So I said: 'Inform me about it, and
do not keep any of it from me.' He said: 'It is after al-Asr until
the sun has set.' I said: 'How can it be after Al-Asr when Allah's
Messenger said: ' the Muslim worshipper would not stand in Salat.'
And that is a time that prayer is not performed in?" So Abdullah
bin Salam said: 'Didn't Allah's Messenger say: "Whoever sat in a
gathering awaiting the Salat then he is in Salat"? I said: 'Of
course.' He said: 'Then that is it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
