<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30580</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>579</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Traveling - أَبْوَابُ السَّفَرِ</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 23059, 23011, 11258, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا محمد بن يزيد بن خنيس، حدثنا الحسن
بن محمد بن عبيد الله بن أبي يزيد، قال قال لي ابن جريج يا حسن أخبرني
عبيد الله بن أبي يزيد، عن ابن عباس، قال جاء رجل إلى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله إني رأيتني الليلة وأنا نائم كأني أصلي
خلف شجرة فسجدت فسجدت الشجرة لسجودي فسمعتها وهي تقول اللهم اكتب لي
بها عندك أجرا وضع عني بها وزرا واجعلها لي عندك ذخرا وتقبلها مني كما
تقبلتها من عبدك داود ‏.‏ قال الحسن قال لي ابن جريج قال لي جدك قال
ابن عباس فقرأ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم سجدة ثم سجد ‏.‏ قال فقال ابن
عباس فسمعته وهو يقول مثل ما أخبره الرجل عن قول الشجرة ‏.‏ قال وفي
الباب عن أبي سعيد ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب من حديث ابن
عباس لا نعرفه إلا من هذا الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Hasan bin Muhammad bin Ubaidullah bin Abi Yazid
said: Ibn Juraij said to me: O Hasan! Ubaidullah bin Abi Yazid
informed me that Ibn Abbas said: "A man came to the Prophet and
said: 'O Messenger of Allah! I had a dream at night while I was
sleeping in which I was praying behind a tree, when I prostrated
the tree prostrated along with me. Then I heard it saying:
(Allahummaktuh li biha indaka ajran, wad a anni biha wizran,
waj'alha li biha indaka dhukhran, wa taqabbalha minni kama
taqabbaltaha min abdiki Dawud.)" (O Allah! Record for me, a reward
with You for it, remove a sin for me by it, and store it away for
me with You, and accept it from me as You accepted it from Your
worshipper Dawud). Al-Hasan said: "Ibn Juraij said to me: 'Your
grandfather said to me: 'Ibn Abbas said: 'So the Prophet recited
(an Ayah of) prostration then prostrated.'" (He said) "So Ibn Abbas
said: 'I listened to him, and he was saying the same as the man
informed that the tree had said.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
