<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>30615</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>614</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Traveling - أَبْوَابُ السَّفَرِ</chapter>
<chain-index>20340, 11621, 11386, 3680, 4052</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن أبي زياد القطواني الكوفي، حدثنا عبيد
الله بن موسى، حدثنا غالب أبو بشر، عن أيوب بن عائذ الطائي، عن قيس بن
مسلم، عن طارق بن شهاب، عن كعب بن عجرة، قال قال لي رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أعيذك بالله يا كعب بن عجرة من أمراء يكونون من
بعدي فمن غشي أبوابهم فصدقهم في كذبهم وأعانهم على ظلمهم فليس مني
ولست منه ولا يرد على الحوض ومن غشي أبوابهم أو لم يغش فلم يصدقهم في
كذبهم ولم يعنهم على ظلمهم فهو مني وأنا منه وسيرد على الحوض يا كعب
بن عجرة الصلاة برهان والصوم جنة حصينة والصدقة تطفئ الخطيئة كما يطفئ
الماء النار ‏.‏ يا كعب بن عجرة إنه لا يربو لحم نبت من سحت إلا كانت
النار أولى به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب من هذا الوجه
لا نعرفه إلا من حديث عبيد الله بن موسى ‏.‏ وأيوب بن عائذ الطائي
يضعف ويقال كان يرى رأى الإرجاء ‏.‏ وسألت محمدا عن هذا الحديث فلم
يعرفه إلا من حديث عبيد الله بن موسى واستغربه جدا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ka'b bin Ujrah narrated: "The Messenger of Allah said
to me: 'I seek refuge in Allah for you O Ka'b bin Ujrah from leader
that will be after me. Whoever comes to their doors to approve of
their lies and supports them in their oppression, then he is not of
me and I am not of him, and he will not meet me at the Hawd. And
whoever comes to their doors, or he does not come, and he does not
approve of their lies and he does not support them in their
oppression, then he is from me and I am from him, and he will meet
me at the Hawd. Ka'ab bin Ujrah! Salat is clear proof, and Sawm
(fasting) is an impregnable shield, and Sadaqah (charity)
extinguishes sins just as water extinguishes fire. O Ka'b bin
Ujrah! There is no flesh raised that sprouts from the unlawful
except that the Fire is more appropriate for it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
