<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31247</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1231</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Business - كتاب البيوع عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20337, 11220, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد، حدثنا عبدة بن سليمان، عن محمد بن عمرو، عن
أبي سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، قال نهى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن
بيعتين في بيعة ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن عبد الله بن عمرو وابن عمر وابن
مسعود ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى حديث أبي هريرة حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ والعمل على
هذا عند أهل العلم وقد فسر بعض أهل العلم قالوا بيعتين في بيعة ‏.‏ أن
يقول أبيعك هذا الثوب بنقد بعشرة وبنسيئة بعشرين ولا يفارقه على أحد
البيعين فإذا فارقه على أحدهما فلا بأس إذا كانت العقدة على واحد
منهما ‏.‏ قال الشافعي ومن معنى نهى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن
بيعتين في بيعة أن يقول أبيعك داري هذه بكذا على أن تبيعني غلامك بكذا
فإذا وجب لي غلامك وجب لك داري ‏.‏ وهذا يفارق عن بيع بغير ثمن معلوم
ولا يدري كل واحد منهما على ما وقعت عليه صفقته ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
prohibited two sales in one."There are narrations on this topic
from 'Abdullah bin 'Amr, Ibn 'Umar, and Ibn Mas'ud.[Abu Eisa said:]
The Hadith of Abu Hurairah is a Hasan Sahih Hadith.This is acted
upon according to the people of knowledge. Some of the people of
knowledge have explained it by saying that two sales in one is when
one says: "I will sell you this garment for ten in cash, and twenty
on credit." He does not distinguish between either of the two
sales. But when he distinguishes it as being one of them, then
there is no harm when one of them is agreed upon.Ash-Shafi'i said:
"Included in the meaning of what the Prophet (ﷺ) prohibited of
regarding two sales in one, is if one said: 'I will sell you the
house of mine for that (price), upon the condition that you sell me
you alve for this (price). When I get the slave, then you get the
house.' In this way the sales are distinguished without the prices
being known, and neither of them knows what will happen at the
conclusion of it (the agreement)."</english-text>
</hadith>
