<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31273</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1256</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Business - كتاب البيوع عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20033, 20012, 11067, 11051, 11054,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن مهدي، حدثنا
سفيان، عن منصور، عن إبراهيم، عن الأسود، عن عائشة، أنها أرادت أن
تشتري، بريرة فاشترطوا الولاء فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
اشتريها فإنما الولاء لمن أعطى الثمن أو لمن ولي النعمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
وفي الباب عن ابن عمر ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى حديث عائشة حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏
والعمل على هذا عند أهل العلم ‏.‏ قال ومنصور بن المعتمر يكنى أبا
عتاب ‏.‏ حدثنا أبو بكر العطار البصري عن علي بن المديني قال سمعت
يحيى بن سعيد يقول إذا حدثت عن منصور فقد ملأت يدك من الخير لا ترد
غيره ‏.‏ ثم قال يحيى ما أجد في إبراهيم النخعي ومجاهد أثبت من منصور
‏.‏ قال وأخبرني محمد عن عبد الله بن أبي الأسود قال قال عبد الرحمن
بن مهدي منصور أثبت أهل الكوفة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Aswad: From 'Aishah that she wanted to
purchase Barirah, but they (he owners) made the condition that they
would retain the Wala'. So the Prophet (ﷺ) said: "Buy her, the
Wala' is only for the one who gives the price, or for the one who
grants the favor."[He said:] There is something on this topic from
Ibn 'Umar.[Abu 'Eisa said:] The Hadith of 'Aishah is a Hasan Sahih
Hadith. This is acted upon according to the people of knowledge.
And Mansur bin Al-Mu'tamir's Kunyah is Abu 'Attab.Abu Bakr
Al-'Attar Al-Basri narrated to us from 'Ali bin Al-Madini who said:
"I heard Yahya bin Sa'eed saying: 'When you get a narration from
Mansur, then your hand has been filled with goodness without
needing others.' Then Yahya said: 'I did not find anyone more
reliable in (narrating from) Ibrahim An-Nakha'i and Mujahid than
Mansur."[He said:] Muhammad informed me from 'Abdullah bin Abi
Al-Aswad who said: " 'Abdur-Rahman bin Mahdi said: 'Mansur is the
most reliable of the people of Al-Kufah.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
