<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31331</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1312</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Business - كتاب البيوع عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30556, 20347, 11168, 11019, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن خشرم، حدثنا عيسى بن يونس، عن سعيد، عن
قتادة، عن سليمان اليشكري، عن جابر بن عبد الله، أن نبي الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من كان له شريك في حائط فلا يبيع نصيبه من ذلك حتى
يعرضه على شريكه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث إسناده ليس بمتصل ‏.‏
سمعت محمدا يقول سليمان اليشكري يقال إنه مات في حياة جابر بن عبد
الله ‏.‏ قال ولم يسمع منه قتادة ولا أبو بشر ‏.‏ قال محمد ولا نعرف
لأحد منهم سماعا من سليمان اليشكري إلا أن يكون عمرو بن دينار فلعله
سمع منه في حياة جابر بن عبد الله ‏.‏ قال وإنما يحدث قتادة عن صحيفة
سليمان اليشكري وكان له كتاب عن جابر بن عبد الله ‏.‏ حدثنا أبو بكر
العطار عبد القدوس قال قال علي بن المديني قال يحيى بن سعيد قال
سليمان التيمي ذهبوا بصحيفة جابر بن عبد الله إلى الحسن البصري فأخذها
أو قال فرواها وذهبوا بها إلى قتادة فرواها وأتوني بها فلم أروها ‏.‏
يقول رددتها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin ‘Abdullah : That Allah's Prophet
(ﷺ) said: "Whoever has a partner in an orchard, then he is not to
sell his share of that until he proposes that to his partner."[Abu
'Eisa said:] The chain of this Hadith is not connected. I heard
Muhammad bin Isma'il saying: It is said that "Sulaiman Al-Yashkuri
died during the lifetime of Jabir bin 'Abdullah." He said: "And
Qatadah did not hear from him, nor did Abu Bishr." Muhammad said:
"We do not know of any of them hearing from Sulaiman Al-Yashkuri
except that 'Amr bin Dinar possibly heard from his during the
lifetome of Jabir bin 'Abdullah." He said: "Qatadah only narrated
from a writing of Sulaiman Al-Yashkuri, and he has a book from
Jabir bin 'Abdullah."Abu Bakr Al-'Attar 'Abdul Quddus narrates to
us, he said: " 'Ali bin Al-Madini said: 'Yahya bin Sa'eed said:
"Sulaiman At-Taymi said: 'They went with the book of Jabir bin
'Abdullah to Al-Hasan Al-Basri and he took it' - or he said - 'and
they reported it. Then they took it to Qatadah and reported it, so
they gave it to me but I did not report it [he said: 'I refused
it'] This was narrated to us by Abu Bakr Al-'Attar from 'Ali bin
Al-Madini.</english-text>
</hadith>
