<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31328</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1309</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Business - كتاب البيوع عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20468, 11075, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن عبد الله الهروي، قال حدثنا هشيم، قال
حدثنا يونس بن عبيد، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر، عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ‏"‏ مطل الغني ظلم وإذا أحلت على مليء فاتبعه ولا تبع بيعتين
في بيعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى حديث أبي هريرة حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏
ومعناه أنه إذا أحيل أحدكم على ملي فليتبع ‏.‏ فقال بعض أهل العلم إذا
أحيل الرجل على ملي فاحتاله فقد برئ المحيل وليس له أن يرجع على
المحيل ‏.‏ وهو قول الشافعي وأحمد وإسحاق ‏.‏ وقال بعض أهل العلم إذا
توي مال هذا بإفلاس المحال عليه فله أن يرجع على الأول ‏.‏ واحتجوا
بقول عثمان وغيره حين قالوا ليس على مال مسلم توى ‏.‏ قال إسحاق معنى
هذا الحديث ‏"‏ ليس على مال مسلم توى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ هذا إذا أحيل الرجل على
آخر وهو يرى أنه ملي فإذا هو معدم فليس على مال مسلم توى
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Umar: That the Prophet (ﷺ) said:
"Procrastination (in paying a debt) by a rich person is oppression.
So if your debt is transfered from your debtor you should agree,
and do not make two sales in one sale."[Abu 'Eisa said:] The Hadith
is the Abu Hurairah (no. 1308) is a Hasan Sahih Hadith. And its
meaning is that when the debt of one of you is transferred then
agree. Some of the people of knowledge said when a man is offered
to transfer his debt to a rich man and he does so, then the
transferor is free of it, he is not to seek its return from the
transferor. This is the view of Ash-Shafi'i, Ahmad, and Ishaq. Some
of the people of knowledge said: "When this wealth could not be
collected due to bankruptcy of the one it was transferred to, then
he may seek its return to the first one." They argue this view with
the saying of 'Uthman and others, when they said: "There is nothing
due on a Muslim's wealth that is lost." Ishaq said: "The meaning of
this Hadith: 'There is nothing due on a Muslim's wealth that is
lost' this is when a man transfers it to another whom he thinks is
wealthy, then he becomes bankrupt, so there is nothing due on the
Muslim's wealth that is lost."</english-text>
</hadith>
