<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31384</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1363</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters On Judgements From The Messenger of Allah -
كتاب الأحكام عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11013, 10511, 106</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا الليث، عن ابن شهاب، عن عروة، أنه
حدثه أن عبد الله بن الزبير حدثه أن رجلا من الأنصار خاصم الزبير عند
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في شراج الحرة التي يسقون بها النخل
فقال الأنصاري سرح الماء يمر ‏.‏ فأبى عليه فاختصموا عند رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم للزبير ‏"‏ اسق
يا زبير ثم أرسل الماء إلى جارك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغضب الأنصاري فقال يا رسول
الله أن كان ابن عمتك فتلون وجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم قال
‏"‏ يا زبير اسق ثم احبس الماء حتى يرجع إلى الجدر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال
الزبير والله إني لأحسب نزلت هذه الآية في ذلك ‏:‏ ‏(‏فلا وربك لا
يؤمنون حتى يحكموك فيما شجر بينهم ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن
صحيح ‏.‏ وروى شعيب بن أبي حمزة عن الزهري عن عروة بن الزبير عن
الزبير ولم يذكر فيه عن عبد الله بن الزبير ‏.‏ ورواه عبد الله بن وهب
عن الليث ويونس عن الزهري عن عروة عن عبد الله بن الزبير نحو الحديث
الأول ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin Az-Zubair: "A man from the
Ansar disputed with Az-Zubair before the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
about the canals of Harrah which they used to irrigate the date
palms. The Ansari said: 'Let the water pass'. But he refused, So
they brought their dispute to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to Az-Zubair: 'O Zubar! Irrigate (your
land) then let the water pass to you neighbor.' The Ansari became
angry and said:'[O Messenger of Allah!]Is this because he is your
aunt's son?' The face of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) changed color.
Then he said: 'O Zubair! Irrigate (your land) and then withold the
water until it reaches the walls.' Az-Zubair said: 'By Allah! I
think that this Ayah was revealed about that: But no, by your Lord,
they can have no Faith until they make you (O Muhammad) judge in
all disputes between them, and find in themselves no resistance
against your decisions and accept (them) with full
submission.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
