<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31415</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1393</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Blood Money - كتاب الديات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30304, 20025, 10846</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن محمد، حدثنا عبد الله بن المبارك، حدثنا
يونس بن أبي إسحاق، حدثنا أبو السفر، قال دق رجل من قريش سن رجل من
الأنصار فاستعدى عليه معاوية فقال لمعاوية يا أمير المؤمنين إن هذا دق
سني ‏.‏ قال معاوية إنا سنرضيك وألح الآخر على معاوية فأبرمه فلم يرضه
فقال له معاوية شأنك بصاحبك ‏.‏ وأبو الدرداء جالس عنده قال أبو
الدرداء سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ ما من رجل يصاب
بشيء في جسده فيتصدق به إلا رفعه الله به درجة وحط عنه به خطيئة ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال الأنصاري أأنت سمعته من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
سمعته أذناى ووعاه قلبي ‏.‏ قال فإني أذرها له ‏.‏ قال معاوية لا جرم
لا أخيبك ‏.‏ فأمر له بمال ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث غريب لا نعرفه
إلا من هذا الوجه ‏.‏ ولا أعرف لأبي السفر سماعا من أبي الدرداء وأبو
السفر اسمه سعيد بن أحمد ويقال ابن يحمد الثوري ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu As-Safar: "A man from the Quraish broke
a tooth of a man from the Ansar. So he appealed to Mu'awiyah
against him. He said to Mu'awiyah: 'O Commander of the Believers!
This person broke one of my teeth.' Mu'awiyah said: 'We will try to
get satisfaction for you.' And the other person insisted that
Mu'awiyah get him to agree [but he was not satisfied]. So Mu'awiyah
said him: 'It is up to your companion.' Abu Ad-Darda' was sitting
with him, so Abu Ad-Darda said: 'I heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
saying [he said: 'My ears heard and my heart remembered]: "There is
no man who is struck in his body and he forgives for it, except
that Allah raises him a level and removes a sin from him.'" The
Ansari said: 'Did you hear that from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)?'
He said: "My ears heard it and my heart remembered it.' He said:
'Then I will leave it to him.' Mu'awiyah said: 'Surely you should
not suffer.' So he ordered that he be given some
wealth."</english-text>
</hadith>
