<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31446</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1422</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Blood Money - كتاب الديات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11062, 11810, 1822, 1986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا الليث بن سعد، عن يحيى بن سعيد، عن
بشير بن يسار، عن سهل بن أبي حثمة، قال يحيى وحسبت عن رافع بن خديج،
أنهما قالا خرج عبد الله بن سهل بن زيد ومحيصة بن مسعود بن زيد حتى
إذا كانا بخيبر تفرقا في بعض ما هناك ثم إن محيصة وجد عبد الله بن سهل
قتيلا قد قتل فدفنه ثم أقبل إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هو
وحويصة بن مسعود وعبد الرحمن بن سهل وكان أصغر القوم ذهب عبد الرحمن
ليتكلم قبل صاحبيه قال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كبر الكبر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصمت وتكلم صاحباه ثم تكلم معهما فذكروا لرسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم مقتل عبد الله بن سهل فقال لهم ‏"‏ أتحلفون خمسين يمينا
فتستحقون صاحبكم أو قاتلكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا وكيف نحلف ولم نشهد قال ‏"‏
فتبرئكم يهود بخمسين يمينا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا وكيف نقبل أيمان قوم كفار
فلما رأى ذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أعطى عقله ‏.‏ حدثنا الحسن
بن علي الخلال، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، أخبرنا يحيى بن سعيد، عن بشير بن
يسار، عن سهل بن أبي حثمة، ورافع بن خديج، نحو هذا الحديث بمعناه ‏.‏
قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ والعمل على هذا الحديث عند أهل
العلم في القسامة وقد رأى بعض فقهاء المدينة القود بالقسامة ‏.‏ وقال
بعض أهل العلم من أهل الكوفة وغيرهم إن القسامة لا توجب القود وإنما
توجب الدية ‏.‏ آخر أبواب الديات والحمد لله ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Abi Hatamah: Yahya (one of the
narrators) said: And I think it was from Rafi' bin Khadij - that
'Abdullah bin Sahl bin Zaid and Muhaiysah bin Mas'ud bin Zaid went
out and when they reached Khaibar they separated while there. Then
Muhayyisah found 'Abdullah bin Sahl murdered [so he buried him].
Then he went to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) along with Huwayyisah
bin Mas'ud and Abdur-Rahman bin Sahl. The youngest of the people,
Abdur-Rahman, went to speak ahead of his companions. The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) said to him: "Let the eldest of you speak." So he was
silent and two companions spoke. So he conversed with them and they
mentioned to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) about the murder of
'Abdullah bin Sahl. He said to them: "If fifty of you can swear an
oath then you will have the right against the murderer." They said:
"How can we take an oath when we did not witness it?" He said:
"Then fifty of Jews can swear to clear the charge with you?" They
said: "How could we accept the oaths of a disbelieving people?" So
when he saw that, the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) paid the blood-money."
(Another Chain) from Sahl bin Abi Hathman and Rafi' bin Khadij, and
the meaning is similar to this Hadith.</english-text>
</hadith>
