<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31459</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1433</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Legal Punishments (Al-Hudud) - كتاب الحدود عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20005, 11013, 11004, 3625</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي، وغير، واحد، حدثنا سفيان بن عيينة، عن
الزهري، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، سمعه من أبي هريرة، وزيد
بن خالد، وشبل، أنهم كانوا عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأتاه رجلان
يختصمان فقام إليه أحدهما وقال أنشدك الله يا رسول الله لما قضيت
بيننا بكتاب الله ‏.‏ فقال خصمه وكان أفقه منه أجل يا رسول الله اقض
بيننا بكتاب الله وائذن لي فأتكلم إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا فزنا
بامرأته فأخبروني أن على ابني الرجم ففديت منه بمائة شاة وخادم ثم
لقيت ناسا من أهل العلم فزعموا أن على ابني جلد مائة وتغريب عام وإنما
الرجم على امرأة هذا ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي
نفسي بيده لأقضين بينكما بكتاب الله المائة شاة والخادم رد عليك وعلى
ابنك جلد مائة وتغريب عام واغد يا أنيس على امرأة هذا فإن اعترفت
فارجمها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغدا عليها فاعترفت فرجمها ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah bin 'Abdullah bin 'Uthbah: That
he heard from Abu Hurairah, Zaid bin Khalid, and Shibl, that they
were with the Prophet (ﷺ) and two men came to him disputing. So one
of them stood before him and said: "I ask you by Allah, O Messenger
of Allah! Only that you would judge between us by the book of
Allah." So his disputant said - and he was more eloquent that him:
"I agree of O Messenger of Allah! Judge between us by the Book of
Allah, and allow me to speak. My son was a servant for this man and
he committed adultery with his wife. So they told me that my son
was to be stoned. I paid him one hundred female sheep and a female
slave. Then I met some people from the people of knowledge and they
said that my son was to be lashed one hundred times, and to be
banished for a year and that stoning is only for this man's wife."
So the Prophet (ﷺ) said: "By the One in Whose Hand is my soul! I
will judge between you two by the Book of Allah. The one hundred
female sheep and the female slave should be returned to you. For
your son is one hundred lashes and banishment for a year. O Unais!
Go to this Man's wife, and if she confesses then stone her." He
went to her and she confessed, so he stoned her.</english-text>
</hadith>
