<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31483</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1454</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Legal Punishments (Al-Hudud) - كتاب الحدود عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 30388, 20311, 10770, 10801</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى النيسابوري، حدثنا محمد بن يوسف، عن
إسرائيل، حدثنا سماك بن حرب، عن علقمة بن وائل الكندي، عن أبيه، أن
امرأة، خرجت على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تريد الصلاة
فتلقاها رجل فتجللها فقضى حاجته منها فصاحت فانطلق ومر عليها رجل
فقالت إن ذاك الرجل فعل بي كذا وكذا ‏.‏ ومرت بعصابة من المهاجرين
فقالت إن ذاك الرجل فعل بي كذا وكذا ‏.‏ فانطلقوا فأخذوا الرجل الذي
ظنت أنه وقع عليها وأتوها فقالت نعم هو هذا ‏.‏ فأتوا به رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما أمر به ليرجم قام صاحبها الذي وقع عليها فقال
يا رسول الله أنا صاحبها ‏.‏ فقال لها ‏"‏ اذهبي فقد غفر الله لك ‏"‏
‏.‏ وقال للرجل قولا حسنا وقال للرجل الذي وقع عليها ‏"‏ ارجموه ‏"‏
‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏ لقد تاب توبة لو تابها أهل المدينة لقبل منهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب صحيح ‏.‏ وعلقمة بن وائل بن حجر سمع
من أبيه وهو أكبر من عبد الجبار بن وائل وعبد الجبار بن وائل لم يسمع
من أبيه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Alqamah bin Wa'il Al-Kindi: From his
father: "A women went out during the time of the Prophet (ﷺ) to go
to Salat, but she was caught by a man and he had relations with
her, so she screamed and he left. Then a man came across her and
she said: 'That man has done this and that to me', then she came
across a group of Emigrants (Muhajirin) and she said: 'That man did
this and that to me.' They went to get the man she thought had
relations with her, and they brought him to her. She said: 'Yes,
that's him.' So they brought him to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), and
when he ordered that he be stoned, the man who had relations with
her, said: 'O Messenger of Allah, I am the one who had relations
with her.' So he said to her: 'Go, for Allah has forgiven you.'
Then he said some nice words to the man (who was brought). And he
said to the man who had relations with her: 'Stone him.' Then he
said: 'He has repented a repentance that, if the inhabitants of
Al-Madinah had repented with, it would have been accepted from
them.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
