<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31610</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1561</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Military Expeditions - كتاب السير عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20509, 11061, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد، حدثنا ابن أبي الزناد، عن أبيه، عن عبيد
الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، عن ابن عباس، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
تنفل سيفه ذا الفقار يوم بدر وهو الذي رأى فيه الرؤيا يوم أحد ‏.‏ هذا
حديث حسن غريب إنما نعرفه من هذا الوجه من حديث ابن أبي الزناد ‏.‏
وقد اختلف أهل العلم في النفل من الخمس فقال مالك بن أنس لم يبلغني أن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نفل في مغازيه كلها وقد بلغني أنه نفل
في بعضها وإنما ذلك على وجه الاجتهاد من الإمام في أول المغنم وآخره
‏.‏ قال ابن منصور قلت لأحمد إن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم نفل إذا فصل
بالربع بعد الخمس وإذا قفل بالثلث بعد الخمس فقال يخرج الخمس ثم ينفل
مما بقي ولا يجاوز هذا ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وهذا الحديث على ما قال ابن
المسيب النفل من الخمس ‏.‏ قال إسحاق كما قال ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Another chain from Ibn 'Abbas that the Prophet (ﷺ)
took his sword Dhul-Fiqar on the Day of Badr, and it is the one
that he saw in the dream on the Day of Uhud.This Hadith is Hasan
Gharib. We only know it from this route through the report of Ibn
Abi Az-Zinad.The people of knowledge differ over giving the Nafl
from the Khumus. Malik bin Anas said: "It has not reached me that
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gave the Nafl during every expedition,
but it has been conveyed to me that he gave the Nafl in some of
them. That is according to the discretion of the Imam during the
beginning of the division of the spoils or the end of it."Ibn
Mansur said: "I said to Ahmad: 'The Prophet (ﷺ) gave the Nafl when
he divided the fourth, after the Khumus, and when he was returning
(he gave) the third from the Khumus.' So he said: 'The Khumus is
taken, and then the Nafl is given from what remains, nothing beyond
this.''"[Abu 'Eisa said:] This Hadith is (understood) as Ibn
Musayyab said: "The Nafl is from te Khumus." Ishaq said as he
said.</english-text>
</hadith>
