<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31619</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1567</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Military Expeditions - كتاب السير عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20668, 20366, 20012, 11065, 11035, 11370,
5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عبيدة بن أبي السفر، - واسمه أحمد بن عبد الله
الهمداني ومحمود بن غيلان قالا حدثنا أبو داود الحفري، حدثنا يحيى بن
زكريا بن أبي زائدة، عن سفيان بن سعيد، عن هشام، عن ابن سيرين، عن
عبيدة، عن علي، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن جبرائيل
هبط عليه فقال له خيرهم يعني أصحابك في أسارى بدر القتل أو الفداء على
أن يقتل منهم قابلا مثلهم ‏.‏ قالوا الفداء ويقتل منا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وفي
الباب عن ابن مسعود وأنس وأبي برزة وجبير بن مطعم ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى
هذا حديث حسن غريب من حديث الثوري لا نعرفه إلا من حديث ابن أبي زائدة
‏.‏ وروى أبو أسامة عن هشام عن ابن سيرين عن عبيدة عن علي عن النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم نحوه ‏.‏ وروى ابن عون عن ابن سيرين عن عبيدة عن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مرسلا ‏.‏ وأبو داود الحفري اسمه عمر بن سعد
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ali: That the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said
that Jibra'il had indeed descended upon him to say to him: "Tell
them - meaning your Companions - to choose regarding the captives
of Badr, between either killing them or ransoming the, so that the
amount killed by them will correspond similarly to them." So they
said: "Ranson, even though some of us may be killed."There are
narrations on this topic from Ibn Mas'ud, Anas, Abu Barzah, and
Jubair bin Mut'im.[Abu 'Eisa said:] This Hadith is Hasan Gharib as
a narration of Ath-Thawri. We do not know of it except through the
report of Za'idah.Abu Usamah reported similar to this from Hisham,
from Ibn Sirin, from 'Abidah, from 'Ali, from the Prophet (ﷺ)Ibn
'Awn reported it from Ibn Sirin, from 'Abidah, from 'Ali, from the
Prophet (ﷺ) in Mursal form.Abu Dawud Al-Hafiri's ( a narrator in
this chain) name is 'Umar bin Sa'd.</english-text>
</hadith>
