<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31632</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1579</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Military Expeditions - كتاب السير عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20733, 20177, 11168, 11237, 198</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو الوليد الدمشقي، حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، أخبرني
ابن أبي ذئب، عن سعيد المقبري، عن أبي مرة، مولى عقيل بن أبي طالب عن
أم هانئ، أنها قالت أجرت رجلين من أحمائي فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد أمنا من أمنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن
صحيح ‏.‏ والعمل على هذا عند أهل العلم أجازوا أمان المرأة وهو قول
أحمد وإسحاق أجازا أمان المرأة والعبد ‏.‏ وأبو مرة مولى عقيل بن أبي
طالب ويقال له أيضا مولى أم هانئ واسمه يزيد ‏.‏ وقد روي عن عمر بن
الخطاب أنه أجاز أمان العبد ‏.‏ وقد روي عن علي بن أبي طالب وعبد الله
بن عمرو عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ ذمة المسلمين واحدة يسعى
بها أدناهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى ومعنى هذا عند أهل العلم أن من أعطى
الأمان من المسلمين فهو جائز على كلهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Another chain from Umm Hani' who said: "I granted
asylum for two men among my brother-in-laws. So the Messeneger of
Allah (ﷺ) said: 'We grant security to whomever you have granted
security.'"[Abu 'Eisa said:] This Hadith is Hasan Sahih.This is
acted upon according to the people of knowledge. They permit
assurance of protection by a women. This is the view of Ahmad and
Ishaq. They permitted the asylum of a woman and slaveIt has been
related from other routes from 'Umar bin Al-Khattab that he
permitted the asylum granted by a slave.One of the narrators of
this last narration Abu Murrah is the freed slave of 'Aqil bin Abi
Talib - they also say that he was freed slave of Umm Hani' - and
his name was Yazid.It has been related from 'Ali bin Abi Talib and
'Abdullah bin 'Amr that the Prophet (ﷺ) said: "The covenants of the
Muslims are one, it covers the rest of them."[Abu 'Eisa said:]
According to the people of knowledge, the meaning of this Hadith is
that whoever gives assurance of protection among the Muslims, then
it is valis to all of them.</english-text>
</hadith>
