<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31662</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1608</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Military Expeditions - كتاب السير عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20296, 20021, 11220, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا أبو الوليد، حدثنا حماد بن
سلمة، عن محمد بن عمرو، عن أبي سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، قال جاءت فاطمة
إلى أبي بكر فقالت من يرثك قال أهلي وولدي ‏.‏ قالت فما لي لا أرث أبي
فقال أبو بكر سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ لا نورث ‏"‏
‏.‏ ولكني أعول من كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعوله وأنفق على
من كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينفق عليه ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وفي
الباب عن عمر وطلحة والزبير وعبد الرحمن بن عوف وسعد وعائشة ‏.‏ وحديث
أبي هريرة حديث حسن غريب من هذا الوجه إنما أسنده حماد بن سلمة وعبد
الوهاب بن عطاء عن محمد بن عمرو عن أبي سلمة عن أبي هريرة ‏.‏ وسألت
محمدا عن هذا الحديث فقال لا أعلم أحدا رواه عن محمد بن عمرو عن أبي
سلمة عن أبي هريرة إلا حماد بن سلمة ‏.‏ وروى عبد الوهاب بن عطاء عن
محمد بن عمرو عن أبي سلمة عن أبي هريرة نحو رواية حماد بن سلمة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: "Fatimah came to Abu Bakr and
said: 'Who will inherit from you?' He said: 'My family and my son.'
She said: 'So what about me? I do not get inheritance from my
father?' So Abu Bakr said: 'I heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say:
'We are not inherited from' but I support those whom the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) used to support, and I spend upon those whom the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) spent upon."[Abu 'Eisa said:] There are
narrations on this topic from 'Umar, Talhah, Az-Zubair,
'Abdur-Rahman bin 'Awf, Sa'd and 'Aishah.The Hadith of Abu Hurairah
is Hasan Gharib from this route. It is only reported with a chain
by Hammad bin Salamah and 'Abdul Wahhab bin 'Ata, from Muhammad bin
'Amr, from Abu Salamah, from Abu Hurairah.I asked Muhammad about
this Hadith and he said: "No one is known to have reported it from
Muhammad bin 'Amr, from Abu Salamah, from Abu Hurairah except from
Hammad bin Salamah. 'Abdul Wahhab bin 'Ata reported it from
Muhammad bib 'Amr, from Abu Salamah, and from Abu Hurairah and it
is similar to the narration of Hammad bin Salamah. And this Hadith
has been reported through other routes from Abu Bakr As-Siddiq,
from the Prophet (ﷺ).</english-text>
</hadith>
