<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>31671</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1617</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Military Expeditions - كتاب السير عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20033, 20012, 11374, 10916, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن مهدي، عن
سفيان، عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن أبيه، قال كان رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا بعث أميرا على جيش أوصاه في خاصة نفسه
بتقوى الله ومن معه من المسلمين خيرا وقال ‏"‏ اغزوا بسم الله وفي
سبيل الله قاتلوا من كفر بالله ولا تغلوا ولا تغدروا ولا تمثلوا ولا
تقتلوا وليدا فإذا لقيت عدوك من المشركين فادعهم إلى إحدى ثلاث خصال
أو خلال أيتها أجابوك فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم ادعهم إلى الإسلام والتحول
من دارهم إلى دار المهاجرين وأخبرهم إن فعلوا ذلك فإن لهم ما
للمهاجرين وعليهم ما على المهاجرين وإن أبوا أن يتحولوا فأخبرهم أنهم
يكونوا كأعراب المسلمين يجري عليهم ما يجري على الأعراب ليس لهم في
الغنيمة والفىء شيء إلا أن يجاهدوا فإن أبوا فاستعن بالله عليهم
وقاتلهم وإذا حاصرت حصنا فأرادوك أن تجعل لهم ذمة الله وذمة نبيه فلا
تجعل لهم ذمة الله ولا ذمة نبيه واجعل لهم ذمتك وذمم أصحابك لأنكم إن
تخفروا ذمتكم وذمم أصحابكم خير من أن تخفروا ذمة الله وذمة رسوله وإذا
حاصرت أهل حصن فأرادوك أن تنزلهم على حكم الله فلا تنزلوهم ولكن
أنزلهم على حكمك فإنك لا تدري أتصيب حكم الله فيهم أم لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو
نحو هذا ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وفي الباب عن النعمان بن مقرن ‏.‏ وحديث
بريدة حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sulaiman bin Buraidah: From his father who
said: "When the Messenger of Allah (sawS) sent a commander of an
army, he would exhort him concerning himself to have Taqwa of
Allah, and he would exhort him to be good to those who are with him
among the Muslims. He would say: 'Fight in the Name of Allah, in
the cause of Allah. Fight those who disbelieve in Allah, and do not
steal from the spoils of war or be treacherous, nor mutilate, and
do not kill a child. When you meet your enemy among the idolaters,
then call them to one of the three options or choices, whichever of
them they respond to then accept it from them, and refrain from
them. Call them to Islam, and to relocate from their land to the
land of Emigrants. Inform them that if they do that, then they will
have similar to what those who emigrated have, and from them will
be required similar to what is required from those who have
emigrated. And if they refuse to relocate, then inform them that
they will be like the Bedouins among the Muslim, and they will be
treated the same as Bedouins aretreated. There is no war spoils or
Fay' for them, unless they fight along with the Muslims. If they
refuse then seek aid from Allah against them and fight them. And if
you lay siege to a fortress and they want you to grant them
covenant from Allah and a covenant of His Prophet, then do not
grant them the covenant of Allah nor the covenant of His Prophet.
Rather grant them your own covenant and the covenant of your
companions, it will be better than breaking Allah's covenant and
the covenant of His Messenger. And if you lay siege to the people
of a fortress and they want you to lift the siege for negotiating
upon the judgement of Allah, then do not stop, but rather make them
surrender to your judgement, for you do not know if you will come
upon the judgement of Allah regarding them or not.' Or similar to
that."[Abu 'Eisa said:] There is something on this topic from
An-Nu'man bin Muqarrin, and the Hadith of Buraidah is a Hasan Sahih
Hadith</english-text>
</hadith>
