<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32157</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>28</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2204</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Medicine - كتاب الطب عن رسول اللَّهِ صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20354, 11060, 11419, 10721, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد، حدثنا أبو معاوية، عن الأعمش، عن جعفر بن
إياس، عن أبي نضرة، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال بعثنا رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في سرية فنزلنا بقوم فسألناهم القرى فلم يقرونا فلدغ سيدهم
فأتونا فقالوا هل فيكم من يرقي من العقرب قلت نعم أنا ولكن لا أرقيه
حتى تعطونا غنما ‏.‏ قالوا فإنا نعطيكم ثلاثين شاة ‏.‏ فقبلنا فقرأت
عليه ‏(‏الحمد لله ‏)‏ سبع مرات فبرأ وقبضنا الغنم ‏.‏ قال فعرض في
أنفسنا منها شيء فقلنا لا تعجلوا حتى تأتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ قال فلما قدمنا عليه ذكرت له الذي صنعت قال ‏"‏ وما علمت
أنها رقية اقبضوا الغنم واضربوا لي معكم بسهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى
هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وأبو نضرة اسمه المنذر بن مالك بن قطعة ‏.‏
ورخص الشافعي للمعلم أن يأخذ على تعليم القرآن أجرا ويرى له أن يشترط
على ذلك ‏.‏ واحتج بهذا الحديث ‏.‏ وروى شعبة وأبو عوانة وغير واحد عن
أبي بشر هذا الحديث عن أبي المتوكل عن أبي سعيد عن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>"Abu Sa'eed narrated: "The Messenger of Allah (s.a.w)
dispatched us on a military expedition. We camped with some people
and asked them to entertain us but they did not entertain us. Their
leader was stung so they came to us saying: 'Is there anyone among
you who can treat a scorpion sting with Ruqyah?' I said: 'Yes I
can. But I will not do any Ruqyah until you give us some sheep.'
They said: 'Then we shall give you thirty sheep.' We accepted
that,and I recited Al-Hamda [Lillah] seven times. He became better
and we took the sheep." He said: "We became concerned about that
being permissible and said: 'Do not be hasty until we reach the
Messenger of Allah (S.A.W)." He said: "When we arrived with him I
mentioned what I did to him. He(S.A.W)said: 'How did you know that
it was a Ruqyah? Take the sheep, and assign me a share among
you.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
