<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32219</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>30</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2266</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Wasaya (Wills and Testament) - كتاب الوصايا عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20387, 30480, 20736, 17036, 4048</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن حجر، وهناد، قالا حدثنا إسماعيل بن عياش،
حدثنا شرحبيل بن مسلم الخولاني، عن أبي أمامة الباهلي، قال سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في خطبته عام حجة الوداع ‏"‏ إن الله قد أعطى
كل ذي حق حقه فلا وصية لوارث الولد للفراش وللعاهر الحجر وحسابهم على
الله ومن ادعى إلى غير أبيه أو انتمى إلى غير مواليه فعليه لعنة الله
التابعة إلى يوم القيامة لا تنفق امرأة من بيت زوجها إلا بإذن زوجها
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا رسول الله ولا الطعام قال ‏"‏ ذلك أفضل أموالنا ‏"‏
‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ العارية مؤداة والمنحة مردودة والدين مقضي والزعيم
غارم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وفي الباب عن عمرو بن خارجة وأنس بن مالك
‏.‏ وهو حديث حسن صحيح وقد روي عن أبي أمامة عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم من غير هذا الوجه ‏.‏ ورواية إسماعيل بن عياش عن أهل العراق وأهل
الحجاز ليس بذلك فيما تفرد به لأنه روى عنهم مناكير وروايته عن أهل
الشام أصح هكذا قال محمد بن إسماعيل ‏.‏ قال سمعت أحمد بن الحسن يقول
قال أحمد بن حنبل إسماعيل بن عياش أصلح حديثا من بقية ولبقية أحاديث
مناكير عن الثقات ‏.‏ وسمعت عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن يقول سمعت زكريا
بن عدي يقول قال أبو إسحاق الفزاري خذوا عن بقية ما حدث عن الثقات ولا
تأخذوا عن إسماعيل بن عياش ما حدث عن الثقات ولا عن غير الثقات
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Ummah said: "During the year of the Farewell
Pilgrimage, I heard the Messenger of Allah (S.A.W) saying in the
Khutbah: 'Indeed Allah, Most Blessed and Most High, has given the
right due to everyone deserving a right. So there is no will for an
heir, the child is for the bed, and for the fornicator is the
stone, and their reckoning is for Allah, Most High. And whoever
claims someone other than his father, or an affiliation with other
than his Mawali, then upon him is the continued curse of Allah
until the Day of Judgment. The wife is not to spend from her
husband's house except with her husband's permission.' They said:
'O Messenger of Allah! Not even food?' He said: 'That is the most
virtuous of our wealth.' And he said: 'The borrowed is to be
returned, the endowment is to be refunded and the debt is to be
repaid, and the guarantor is responsible.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
