<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32226</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>31</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2127</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Wala' And Gifts - كتاب الولاء والهبة عن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20354, 11060, 11322, 11405</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هناد، حدثنا أبو معاوية، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم
التيمي، عن أبيه، قال خطبنا علي فقال من زعم أن عندنا شيئا نقرؤه إلا
كتاب الله وهذه الصحيفة صحيفة فيها أسنان الإبل وأشياء من الجراحات
فقد كذب وقال فيها قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ المدينة حرام
ما بين عير إلى ثور فمن أحدث فيها حدثا أو آوى محدثا فعليه لعنة الله
والملائكة والناس أجمعين لا يقبل الله منه يوم القيامة صرفا ولا عدلا
ومن ادعى إلى غير أبيه أو تولى غير مواليه فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة
والناس أجمعين لا يقبل منه صرف ولا عدل وذمة المسلمين واحدة يسعى بها
أدناهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح وقد روي من غير وجه عن
علي عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وروى بعضهم عن
الأعمش عن إبراهيم التيمي عن الحارث بن سويد عن علي نحوه ‏.‏ قال أبو
عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح وقد روي من غير وجه عن علي عن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibrahim At-Taimi narrated from his father: "'Ali
delivered a Khutbah for us in which he said: 'Whoever claims that
we have some book to read other than Allah's Book and this paper,
which include camel's ages and things related to (relatiation for)
wounds, then he has lied." And he said in it: "Al-Madinah is
sacred, what is between 'Air to Thawr, so whoever introduces in it
any innovation or shelters an innovator then upon him is the curse
of Allah, the angels, and all people. On the Day of Judgment, Allah
will not accept his compulsory nor optional good deeds. And whoever
claims someone else to be his father, or claims Wala' for someone
other than his Mawali, then upon him is the curse of Allah, the
angels, and the people; his compulsory and optional good deeds
shall not be accepted. The covenants of the Muslims are one, it
covers the rest of them.[Abu 'Eisa said:] This Hadith is Hasan
Sahih. Some of them reported it similarly from Al-A'mash, from
Ibrahim At-Taimi, from Al-Harith bin Suwaid from 'Ali.[Abu 'Eisa
said:] It has been reported through more than one route from 'Ali
[from the Prophet (ﷺ)].</english-text>
</hadith>
