<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32261</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>32</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2308</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Al-Qadar - كتاب القدر عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30221, 20547</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن موسى، حدثنا أبو داود الطيالسي، حدثنا عبد
الواحد بن سليم، قال قدمت مكة فلقيت عطاء بن أبي رباح فقلت له يا أبا
محمد إن أهل البصرة يقولون في القدر ‏.‏ قال يا بنى أتقرأ القرآن قلت
نعم ‏.‏ قال فاقرإ الزخرف ‏.‏ قال فقرأت ‏:‏ ‏(‏حم* والكتاب المبين *
إنا جعلناه قرآنا عربيا لعلكم تعقلون * وإنه في أم الكتاب لدينا لعلي
حكيم ‏)‏ فقال أتدري ما أم الكتاب قلت الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال فإنه
كتاب كتبه الله قبل أن يخلق السموات وقبل أن يخلق الأرض فيه إن فرعون
من أهل النار وفيه ‏:‏ ‏(‏تبت يدا أبي لهب وتب ‏)‏ قال عطاء فلقيت
الوليد بن عبادة بن الصامت صاحب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسألته
ما كان وصية أبيك عند الموت قال دعاني أبي فقال لي يا بنى اتق الله
واعلم أنك لن تتقي الله حتى تؤمن بالله وتؤمن بالقدر كله خيره وشره
فإن مت على غير هذا دخلت النار إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يقول ‏"‏ إن أول ما خلق الله القلم فقال اكتب ‏.‏ فقال ما أكتب قال
اكتب القدر ما كان وما هو كائن إلى الأبد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وهذا
حديث غريب من هذا الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdul-Wahid bin sulaim narrated: "I arrived in Makkah
and met 'Ata bin Abi Rabab. I said to him: 'O Abu Muhammad! The
people of Al-Basrah speak about Al-Qadar.' He said: 'O my son! Do
you recite the Quran?' I said: 'Yes.' He said: 'Then recite
Az-Zukhruf to me.'" He said: 'So I recited: Ha Mim. By the manifest
Book, Verily, We have made it a Quran in Arabic that you may be
able to understand. And verily, it is in the Mother of Book with
Us, indeed exalted, full of wisdom. Then he said: 'Do you know what
Mother of Books is?' I said: 'Allah and His Messenger know better.'
He said:'It is a book that Allah wrote before He created the
Heavens, and before He created the earth. In it, it is (written):
Fir'awn is among the inhabitants of the Fire, and in it is: Perish
the two hands of Abu Lahab, and perish he!'Ata said: 'I met
Al-Walid the son of Ubadah bin As-samit the Companion of the
Messenger of Allah (s.a.w) and asked him:'What was your father's
admonition when he died?" He said:"He called me and said: 'O my son
! Have Taqwa of Allah, and know that you will never have Taqwa of
Allah until you believe in Allah, and you believe in Al-Qadar-all
of it-its good and its bad. If you die upon other than this you
shall enter the Fire. Indeed I heard the Messenger of Allah (s.a.w)
saying: "Verily the first of what Allah created was the Pen. So He
said: 'Write Al-Qadar, what it is , and what shall be, until the
end.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
