<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32354</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2248</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Al-Fitan - كتاب الفتن عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>34120, 20021, 10664, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن معاوية الجمحي، حدثنا حماد بن سلمة،
عن علي بن زيد، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكرة، عن أبيه، قال قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يمكث أبو الدجال وأمه ثلاثين عاما لا
يولد لهما ولد ثم يولد لهما غلام أعور أضر شيء وأقله منفعة تنام عيناه
ولا ينام قلبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم نعت لنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أبويه
فقال ‏"‏ أبوه طوال ضرب اللحم كأن أنفه منقار وأمه امرأة فرضاخية
طويلة اليدين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أبو بكرة فسمعنا بمولود في اليهود بالمدينة
فذهبت أنا والزبير بن العوام حتى دخلنا على أبويه فإذا نعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فيهما فقلنا هل لكما ولد فقالا مكثنا ثلاثين عاما
لا يولد لنا ولد ثم ولد لنا غلام أعور أضر شيء وأقله منفعة تنام عيناه
ولا ينام قلبه ‏.‏ قال فخرجنا من عندهما فإذا هو منجدل في الشمس في
قطيفة له وله همهمة فكشف عن رأسه فقال ما قلتما قلنا وهل سمعت ما قلنا
قال نعم تنام عيناى ولا ينام قلبي ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب
لا نعرفه إلا من حديث حماد بن سلمة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Abdur-Rahman bin Abi Bakrah
from his father who said: "The Messenger of Allah(s.a.w) said: 'The
father of the Dajjal and hid mother, will abide for thirty years
without bearing a son. Then a boy shall be born to them, having one
eye in which there is some defect, providing little use. His eyes
sleep but his heart does not sleep.' Then the Messenger of
Allah(s.a.w) described his parents for us: 'His father is tall,
with little fat, with a nose as if it were a beak. His mother is a
bulky woman with long breasts.'" So Abu Bakrah said: "I heard about
a child being born to some Jews in Al-Madinah. So Az-Zubair bin
Al-'Awwam and I went until we entered upon his parents. They
appeared as the Messenger of Allah(s.a.w) had described them. We
said: 'Do you have any children?' They said: 'We remained for
thirty years without any children being born to us, then we bore a
boy, having one eye in which there is some defect, providing little
use. His eyes sleep but his heart does not sleep.'" He said: "So we
were leaving them, when he appeared, glittering in the sunlight in
a velvet garment, murmuring something. He uncovered his head and
said: 'What were you saying?' We said: 'Did you hear what we were
saying?' He said: 'Yes, that my eyes sleep but my heart does not
sleep.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
