<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32453</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2347</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Zuhd - كتاب الزهد عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>38265, 20025, 20379, 19927, 11648, 405</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا سويد بن نصر، أخبرنا عبد الله بن المبارك، عن
يحيى بن أيوب، عن عبيد الله بن زحر، عن علي بن يزيد، عن القاسم أبي
عبد الرحمن، عن أبي أمامة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن
أغبط أوليائي عندي لمؤمن خفيف الحاذ ذو حظ من الصلاة أحسن عبادة ربه
وأطاعه في السر وكان غامضا في الناس لا يشار إليه بالأصابع وكان رزقه
كفافا فصبر على ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم نفض بيده فقال ‏"‏ عجلت منيته قلت
بواكيه قل تراثه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وبهذا الإسناد عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ عرض على ربي ليجعل لي بطحاء مكة ذهبا قلت لا يا رب ولكن أشبع
يوما وأجوع يوما أو قال ثلاثا أو نحو هذا فإذا جعت تضرعت إليك وذكرتك
وإذا شبعت شكرتك وحمدتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن
فضالة بن عبيد ‏.‏ والقاسم هذا هو ابن عبد الرحمن ويكنى أبا عبد
الرحمن وهو مولى عبد الرحمن بن خالد بن يزيد بن معاوية وهو شامي ثقة
وعلي بن يزيد ضعيف الحديث ويكنى أبا عبد الملك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Umamah narrated that the Prophet (s.a.w) said:
"Indeed the best of my friends to me is the one of meager
conditions, whose share is in Salat, worshipping his Lord well and
obeying him (even) in private. He is obscure among the people such
that the fingers are not pointed towards him. His provisions are
only what is sufficient and he is patient with that." Then he
tapped with his fingers and said: "His death comes quickly, his
mourners are few, and his inheritance is little."With this (the
above), chain it is narrated that the Prophet (s.a.w) said: "My
Lord presented to me, that He would make the valley of Makkah into
gold for me, I said: 'No O Lord! But being filled for a day and
hungry for a day"-or he said: "three days" or something like that-
"So when I am hungry, I would beseech You and remember You, and
when I am full I would be grateful to You and praise
You."</english-text>
</hadith>
