<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32475</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2369</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Zuhd - كتاب الزهد عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>34188, 20404, 20240, 11368, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا آدم بن أبي إياس، حدثنا
شيبان أبو معاوية، حدثنا عبد الملك بن عمير، عن أبي سلمة بن عبد
الرحمن، عن أبي هريرة، قال خرج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في ساعة لا
يخرج فيها ولا يلقاه فيها أحد فأتاه أبو بكر فقال ‏"‏ ما جاء بك يا
أبا بكر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال خرجت ألقى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنظر
في وجهه والتسليم عليه ‏.‏ فلم يلبث أن جاء عمر فقال ‏"‏ ما جاء بك يا
عمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الجوع يا رسول الله قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ وأنا قد وجدت بعض ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانطلقوا إلى منزل أبي الهيثم
بن التيهان الأنصاري وكان رجلا كثير النخل والشاء ولم يكن له خدم فلم
يجدوه فقالوا لامرأته أين صاحبك فقالت انطلق يستعذب لنا الماء ‏.‏ فلم
يلبثوا أن جاء أبو الهيثم بقربة يزعبها فوضعها ثم جاء يلتزم النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ويفديه بأبيه وأمه ثم انطلق بهم إلى حديقته فبسط لهم
بساطا ثم انطلق إلى نخلة فجاء بقنو فوضعه فقال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أفلا تنقيت لنا من رطبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال يا رسول الله إني أردت
أن تختاروا أو قال تخيروا من رطبه وبسره ‏.‏ فأكلوا وشربوا من ذلك
الماء فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا والذي نفسي بيده من
النعيم الذي تسألون عنه يوم القيامة ظل بارد ورطب طيب وماء بارد ‏"‏
‏.‏ فانطلق أبو الهيثم ليصنع لهم طعاما فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ لا تذبحن ذات در ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فذبح لهم عناقا أو جديا فأتاهم بها
فأكلوا فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل لك خادم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإذا أتانا سبى فائتنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتي النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم برأسين ليس معهما ثالث فأتاه أبو الهيثم فقال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اختر منهما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال يا نبي الله اختر لي ‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن المستشار مؤتمن خذ هذا فإني رأيته
يصلي واستوص به معروفا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فانطلق أبو الهيثم إلى امرأته فأخبرها
بقول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت امرأته ما أنت ببالغ ما قال
فيه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلا أن تعتقه قال فهو عتيق ‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الله لم يبعث نبيا ولا خليفة إلا وله
بطانتان بطانة تأمره بالمعروف وتنهاه عن المنكر وبطانة لا تألوه خبالا
ومن يوق بطانة السوء فقد وقي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح
غريب ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated : "The Prophet (s.a.w) went out
during an hour in which he would normally not go out, nor meet with
anyone. Then Abu Bakr came to him. So he said:"What brought you O
Abu Bakr?" He said: "I came to meet the Messenger of Allah (s.a.w)
and to look at his face, and to make sure he was safe. It was not
long before 'Umar came. He said: "What has brought you O 'Umar ?"
He said: "Hunger O Messenger of Allah!"He said: "I also experienced
some of that" So they went to the home of Abu Al-Haitham
At-Taiyyihan Al-Ansari. He was a man with many date-palms and
sheep, but he had no servants so they did not find him there. They
said to his wife: "Where is your companion?" She said: "He has gone
to fetch us some good water." It was not long before Abu Al-Haitham
came along hauling to a large water-skin which he put down. Then he
came to hug the Prophet (s.a.w) and uttered that his father and
mother should be ransomed for him. Then he went to grove of his and
he spread out a mat for them. Then he went to a date-palm and
returned with a cluster of dates which he put down. The prophet
(s.a.w) said: "Why don't you select some ripe dates for us?" He
said: "O Messenger of Allah(s.a.w)! I wanted you to select from the
ripe dates and the unripe dates." So they ate and they drank from
that water. The Messenger of Allah(s.a.w) said: "By the One in
Whose Hand is my soul! This is among the favors which you shall be
asked about on the Day of Judgement. Cool shade, tasty ripe dates,
and cool water." Abu Al-Haitham left to prepare some food for them.
The Prophet (s.a.w) said: "Do not slaughter one with milk." So he
Slaughtered a small female or male goat and brought it to them so
they could eat it. The Prophet (s.a.w) said: "Do you have any
servants?" He said: "No." So he said: "Then if we get some captives
we shall bring them for you." So (later) the Prophet (s.a.w) came
with 2 males, there was no third among them and he brought them to
Abu Al-Haitham. The Prophet (s.a.w) said: "Choose from them." He
said: "O Prophet of Allah! Choose for me." So the Prophet (s.a.w)
said: "Indeed the one consulted is entrusted. Take this one for I
have seen him praying, and encourage him to do well." So Abu
Al-Haitham went to his wife and informed her of what the Messenger
of Allah (s.a.w) said. So his wife said: "You will not fulfill what
the Prophet (s.a.w) said until you have freed him." So he said: "He
is free." So the Prophet (s.a.w) said: "Indeed Allah has not send a
Prophet nor made a Khalifah except that he has two groups of
supporters, group ordering him to do good, and prohibiting him from
evil and a group that never ceases spoiling his affairs. So whoever
protected."</english-text>
</hadith>
