<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32497</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2391</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Zuhd - كتاب الزهد عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20280, 30112, 20001, 11159, 11420, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الأنصاري، حدثنا معن، حدثنا مالك، عن خبيب بن عبد
الرحمن، عن حفص بن عاصم، عن أبي هريرة، أو عن أبي سعيد، أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ سبعة يظلهم الله في ظله يوم لا ظل إلا ظله
إمام عادل وشاب نشأ بعبادة الله ورجل كان قلبه معلقا بالمسجد إذا خرج
منه حتى يعود إليه ورجلان تحابا في الله فاجتمعا على ذلك وتفرقا ورجل
ذكر الله خاليا ففاضت عيناه ورجل دعته امرأة ذات حسب وجمال فقال إني
أخاف الله ورجل تصدق بصدقة فأخفاها حتى لا تعلم شماله ما تنفق يمينه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وهكذا روي هذا الحديث عن
مالك بن أنس من غير وجه مثل هذا وشك فيه وقال عن أبي هريرة أو عن أبي
سعيد وعبيد الله بن عمر رواه عن خبيب بن عبد الرحمن ولم يشك فيه يقول
عن أبي هريرة ‏.‏ حدثنا سوار بن عبد الله العنبري، ومحمد بن المثنى،
قالا حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، عن عبيد الله بن عمر، حدثني خبيب، عن حفص بن
عاصم، عن أبي هريرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم نحو حديث مالك بن
أنس بمعناه إلا أنه قال ‏"‏ كان قلبه معلقا بالمساجد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏
ذات منصب وجمال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Hafs bin 'Asim narrated from Abu Hurairah or Abu
Sa'eed that the Messenger of Allah (s.a.w) said: "Seven shall be
shaded by Allah under his shade on a day in which there is no shade
except His Shade: A just Imam, a young person raised upon
worshiping Allah, a man whose heart is attached to the Masjid when
he leaves from it until he returns from it, two men who love each
other for Allah's sake, coming together upon that, and parting upon
that, a man who remembers Allah in privacy and his eyes swell with
tears, a man invited by a woman of status and beauty, but he says:
'I fear Allah, Mighty and Sublime is He,' and a man who conceals
the charity he gives such that his left hand does not know what his
right hand has spent."</english-text>
</hadith>
