<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32520</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2413</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters On Zuhd - كتاب الزهد عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20416, 20342, 11383, 4047</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا جعفر بن عون، حدثنا أبو
العميس، عن عون بن أبي جحيفة، عن أبيه، قال آخى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بين سلمان وبين أبي الدرداء فزار سلمان أبا الدرداء فرأى أم
الدرداء متبذلة فقال ما شأنك متبذلة قالت إن أخاك أبا الدرداء ليس له
حاجة في الدنيا ‏.‏ قال فلما جاء أبو الدرداء قرب إليه طعاما فقال كل
فإني صائم ‏.‏ قال ما أنا بآكل حتى تأكل ‏.‏ قال فأكل فلما كان الليل
ذهب أبو الدرداء ليقوم فقال له سلمان نم ‏.‏ فنام ثم ذهب يقوم فقال له
نم ‏.‏ فنام فلما كان عند الصبح قال له سلمان قم الآن فقاما فصليا
فقال إن لنفسك عليك حقا ولربك عليك حقا ولضيفك عليك حقا وإن لأهلك
عليك حقا فأعط كل ذي حق حقه ‏.‏ فأتيا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكرا
ذلك فقال له ‏"‏ صدق سلمان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث صحيح ‏.‏
وأبو العميس اسمه عتبة بن عبد الله وهو أخو عبد الرحمن بن عبد الله
المسعودي ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ubu Juhaifah narrated from his father who said: "The
Messenger of Allah (s.a.w) made a bond of brotherhood between
Salman and Abu Ad-Darda. Salman went to visit Abu Ad-Darda, and saw
Umm Ad-Darda wearing shabby clothes, So he said: 'Why are you
wearing such shabby clothes?' She said: 'Your brother Abu Ad-Darda
has no interest in the world.' So when Abu Ad-Darda arrived, he
prepared some food for him (Salman) and said: 'Eat, for I am
fasting.' He said: 'I shall not eat until you eat.'" He said: "So
he ate. When night came Abu Ad-Darda started to leave and stand (in
prayer), but Salman said to him: 'Sleep.' So he slept. Then he went
to stand (in prayer) but he said to him: 'Sleep'. So he slept. When
the morning (Fajr) came,Salman said: 'Get up now.'So he got up to
perform Salat. Then he (Salman) said: 'Indeed your self has a right
upon you, your Lord has a right upon you, your guest has a right
upon you, and your family has a right upon you. So give each the
right they are due. The Prophet (s.a.w), and that was mentioned to
him, so he said: 'Salman has told the truth.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
