<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32544</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2621</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of the Day of Judgement,
Ar-Riqaq, and Al-Wara' - كتاب صفة القيامة والرقائق والورع عن رسول
الله صلى الله</chapter>
<chain-index>38265, 20025, 11404, 11406, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا سويد بن نصر، أخبرنا عبد الله بن المبارك، أخبرنا
أبو حيان التيمي، عن أبي زرعة بن عمرو بن جرير، عن أبي هريرة، قال أتي
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بلحم فرفع إليه الذراع فأكله وكانت
تعجبه فنهس منها نهسة ثم قال ‏"‏ أنا سيد الناس يوم القيامة هل تدرون
لم ذاك يجمع الله الناس الأولين والآخرين في صعيد واحد فيسمعهم الداعي
وينفذهم البصر وتدنو الشمس منهم فيبلغ الناس من الغم والكرب ما لا
يطيقون ولا يحتملون فيقول الناس بعضهم لبعض ألا ترون ما قد بلغكم ألا
تنظرون من يشفع لكم إلى ربكم فيقول الناس بعضهم لبعض عليكم بآدم ‏.‏
فيأتون آدم فيقولون أنت أبو البشر خلقك الله بيده ونفخ فيك من روحه
وأمر الملائكة فسجدوا لك اشفع لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه ألا ترى
ما قد بلغنا فيقول لهم آدم إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله
مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله وإنه قد نهاني عن الشجرة فعصيت نفسي نفسي
نفسي اذهبوا إلى غيري اذهبوا إلى نوح ‏.‏ فيأتون نوحا فيقولون يا نوح
أنت أول الرسل إلى أهل الأرض وقد سماك الله عبدا شكورا اشفع لنا إلى
ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه ألا ترى ما قد بلغنا فيقول لهم نوح إن ربي قد
غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله وإنه قد كان لي
دعوة دعوتها على قومي نفسي نفسي نفسي اذهبوا إلى غيري اذهبوا إلى
إبراهيم ‏.‏ فيأتون إبراهيم فيقولون يا إبراهيم أنت نبي الله وخليله
من أهل الأرض اشفع لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه فيقول إن ربي قد
غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله وإني قد كذبت
ثلاث كذبات فذكرهن أبو حيان في الحديث نفسي نفسي نفسي اذهبوا إلى غيري
اذهبوا إلى موسى ‏.‏ فيأتون موسى فيقولون يا موسى أنت رسول الله فضلك
الله برسالته وبكلامه على البشر اشفع لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه
فيقول إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله
وإني قد قتلت نفسا لم أومر بقتلها نفسي نفسي نفسي اذهبوا إلى غيري
اذهبوا إلى عيسى ‏.‏ فيأتون عيسى فيقولون يا عيسى أنت رسول الله
وكلمته ألقاها إلى مريم وروح منه وكلمت الناس في المهد اشفع لنا إلى
ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه فيقول عيسى إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب
قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله ولم يذكر ذنبا نفسي نفسي نفسي اذهبوا
إلى غيري اذهبوا إلى محمد ‏.‏ قال فيأتون محمدا فيقولون يا محمد أنت
رسول الله وخاتم الأنبياء وقد غفر لك ما تقدم من ذنبك وما تأخر اشفع
لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى ما نحن فيه فأنطلق فآتي تحت العرش فأخر ساجدا
لربي ثم يفتح الله على من محامده وحسن الثناء عليه شيئا لم يفتحه على
أحد قبلي ثم يقال يا محمد ارفع رأسك سل تعطه واشفع تشفع ‏.‏ فأرفع
رأسي فأقول يا رب أمتي يا رب أمتي يا رب أمتي ‏.‏ فيقول يا محمد أدخل
من أمتك من لا حساب عليه من الباب الأيمن من أبواب الجنة وهم شركاء
الناس فيما سوى ذلك من الأبواب ثم قال والذي نفسي بيده إن ما بين
المصراعين من مصاريع الجنة كما بين مكة وهجر وكما بين مكة وبصرى ‏"‏
‏.‏ وفي الباب عن أبي بكر الصديق وأنس وعقبة بن عامر وأبي سعيد ‏.‏
قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وأبو حيان التيمي اسمه يحيى بن
سعيد بن حيان كوفي وهو ثقة وأبو زرعة بن عمرو بن جرير اسمه هرم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated: ""Some meat was brought to the
Prophet (s.a.w) and a foreleg was presented to him, and he used to
like it, so he bit from it. Then he said: 'I will be the 'Leader'
of the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know why that is?
Allah will gather the people, the first and the last, on one level
ground where they will (all) be able to hear a caller, and all of
them will be visible, and the sun will be brought near such that
the people will suffer distress and trouble that they cannot
tolerate nor bear. Then some people will say: "Don't you see the
state you have reached? Why don't you look for a person who can
intercede for you with your Lord? " Some of them will say to
others: " You should go to Adam." So they will go to Adam and say,
"You are the father of all mankind, Allah created you with His Own
Hands, and breathed into you from His spirit (which He creted for
you) and ordered the angels to prostrate for you. Will you not
intercede for us with your Lord? Don't you see what has happened to
us? Don't you see the state we have reached?" On that Adam will
reply, "Today my Lord has become angry such that He has never
before been angry, and will never be thereafter. He forbade me (to
eat from) the tree, but I disobeyed(Him), Myself! Myself! Myself!
Go to somebody else; Go to Nuh." They will go to Nuh and say: "O
Nuh! You are the first among the Messengers to the people of the
earth, and Allah named you a thankful slave. Will you not intercede
for us with your Lord? Don't you see what has happened to us? Don't
you see the state we have reached?" Nuh will say to them : "Today
my Lord has become angry as He has never before been angry, and
will never be thereafter. I had been given one supplication, and I
supplicated against my own people. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to
someone else! Go to Ibrahim." They will go to Ibrahim and say: "O
Ibrahim! You are Allah's Prophet and His Khalil among the people of
the earth, so intercede for us with your Lord, don't you see what
hads happened to us?" He will say: "Today my Lord has become angry
as He has never before been angry and will never be thereafter.
Indeed I uttered three lies."- Abu Hayyyan (a narrator) mentioned
them in his narration - " Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone
else! Go to Musa." So they will go to Musa and say: "O Musa! You
are the Messenger of Allah who Allah distinguished above the people
with His Message and His Speech, intercede for us with your Lord.
Don't you see what has happened to us?" So he will say "Today my
Lord has become angry as He has never before been angry and will
never be thereafter. Indeed I killed a person whom I was ordered
not to kill. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; Go to
'Eisa." They will go to 'Eisa and say: "O 'Eisa ! You are the
Messenger of Allah and His Word which He placed into Mariam, and a
Spirit from Him, and you spoke to the people in the cradle.
Intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see what has happened to
us?" Then 'Eisa will say: "Today my Lord has become angry as He has
never before been angry and will never be thereafter." He will not
mention a sin, but will say: "Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone
else! Go to Muhammad." He said: 'They will go to Muhammad(s.a.w)
and they say: "O Muhammad! You are the Messenger of Allah and the
last of the Prophets, and your past and future sins have been
pardoned. Will you not intercede for us with your Lord, don't you
see what has happened to us?" Then I will depart until I come to
under the Throne to fall prostrating before my Lord. Then Allah
will guide me to such praises and beautiful statements of
glorification which He did not guide anyone to before me. Then He
will say: "O Muhammad! Raise your head. Ask,so that you may be
granted and intercede so that your intercession may be accepted." I
will raise my head and say: "O Lord! My Ummah! O Lord! My Ummah! O
Lord! My Ummah!" He will say: "O Muhammad! Let those of your Ummah
who have no accounts enter the gate on the right among the gates of
Paradise, and they shall share in the gates other than that with
the people.'" Then he (s.a.w) said: 'By the One in Whose Hand is my
soul! What is between every two gate-posts in Paradise is as what
is between Makkah and Hajar, and what is between Makkah and
Busra.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
