<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32555</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2632</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of the Day of Judgement,
Ar-Riqaq, and Al-Wara' - كتاب صفة القيامة والرقائق والورع عن رسول
الله صلى الله</chapter>
<chain-index>34188, 20470, 100, 10968</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا يحيى بن صالح، حدثنا محمد
بن المهاجر، عن العباس، عن أبي سلام الحبشي، قال بعث إلى عمر بن عبد
العزيز فحملت على البريد ‏.‏ قال فلما دخل عليه قال يا أمير المؤمنين
لقد شق على مركبي البريد ‏.‏ فقال يا أبا سلام ما أردت أن أشق عليك
ولكن بلغني عنك حديث تحدثه عن ثوبان عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في
الحوض فأحببت أن تشافهني به ‏.‏ قال أبو سلام حدثني ثوبان عن النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ حوضي من عدن إلى عمان البلقاء ماؤه أشد
بياضا من اللبن وأحلى من العسل وأكاويبه عدد نجوم السماء من شرب منه
شربة لم يظمأ بعدها أبدا أول الناس ورودا عليه فقراء المهاجرين الشعث
رءوسا الدنس ثيابا الذين لا ينكحون المتنعمات ولا تفتح لهم السدد ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال عمر لكني نكحت المتنعمات وفتح لي السدد ونكحت فاطمة بنت عبد
الملك لا جرم أني لا أغسل رأسي حتى يشعث ولا أغسل ثوبي الذي يلي جسدي
حتى يتسخ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث غريب من هذا الوجه ‏.‏ وقد روي
هذا الحديث عن معدان بن أبي طلحة عن ثوبان عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ وأبو سلام الحبشي اسمه ممطور وهو شامي ثقة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-'Abbas narrated from Abu Sallam Al-Habashi who
said: "'Umar bin 'Abdul-'Aziz summoned me so I got a ride on a
mule." [He said:] "When he entered upon him, he said: 'O Commander
of the Beleivers! My riding mule was troublesome for me.' So he
said: 'O Abu Sallam!I did not want to trouble you, but a Hadith
which you narrated-from Thawban, from the Prophet (s.a.w) about the
Hawd-was conveyed to me,and I wanted you to narrate it directly to
me."'Abu Sallam said: "Thawban narrated to me from The Messenger of
Allah (s.a.w) who said 'My Hawd (is as large as) from 'Adan to
'Amman of Al-Balqa', its water is whiter than milk and sweeter than
honey. Its cups are as numerous as the stars, whoever drinks one
drink from it, he will never be thirsty after that again. The first
people to arrive at it are the poor among the Muhajirin with
disheveled heads, dirty clothes, those whom the women of favor
would not marry, nor would the doors be open for them.' 'Umar said:
'But I have married a women of favor and the doors are open for me.
I married Fatimah bint 'Abdul-Malik. I shall certainly not wash my
head until it is disheveled, nor wash my garment which touches my
body until it becomes dirty."</english-text>
</hadith>
