<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32574</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2651</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of the Day of Judgement,
Ar-Riqaq, and Al-Wara' - كتاب صفة القيامة والرقائق والورع عن رسول
الله صلى الله</chapter>
<chain-index>20025, 20475, 11013, 10511, 11002, 423</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سويد، أخبرنا عبد الله، عن يونس، عن الزهري، عن
عروة بن الزبير، وابن المسيب، أن حكيم بن حزام، قال سألت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأعطاني ثم سألته فأعطاني ثم سألته فأعطاني ثم قال
‏"‏ يا حكيم إن هذا المال خضرة حلوة فمن أخذه بسخاوة نفس بورك له فيه
ومن أخذه بإشراف نفس لم يبارك له فيه وكان كالذي يأكل ولا يشبع واليد
العليا خير من اليد السفلى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال حكيم فقلت يا رسول الله والذي
بعثك بالحق لا أرزأ أحدا بعدك شيئا حتى أفارق الدنيا ‏.‏ فكان أبو بكر
يدعو حكيما إلى العطاء فيأبى أن يقبله ثم إن عمر دعاه ليعطيه فأبى أن
يقبل منه شيئا فقال عمر إني أشهدكم يا معشر المسلمين على حكيم أني
أعرض عليه حقه من هذا الفىء فيأبى أن يأخذه ‏.‏ فلم يرزأ حكيم أحدا من
الناس شيئا بعد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى توفي ‏.‏ قال هذا
حديث صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Urwah bin Az-Zubair and Ibn Musayyab narrated that
Hakim bin Hizam said: "I (once) asked the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) (for something) and he gave it to me. Then I asked him
(again) and he gave it to me. Then I asked him (again) and he gave
it to me. Then I asked him (again), so he gave it to me. Then he
said: 'O Hakim! Indeed this wealth is green and sweet, so whoever
takes it without asking for it, he will be blessed in it. And
whoever takes it, insisting upon it, he will not be blessed in it.
He is like the one who eats but does not get satisfied and
contended. And the upper hand (giving) is better than the lower
hand (receiving)." So Hakim said: "I said: 'O Messenger of Allah!
By the One who sent you with the Truth! I shall not ask anyone for
anything after you until I depart the world.'"So Abu Bakr used to
call Hakim to give him something, but he refused to accept it. Then
'Umar called him to give to him, but he refused to accept it. So
'Umar said: "O you Muslims! I would like you to bear witness that I
presented Hakim with his due of these spoils of war but he refused
to accept it." So Hakim never asked anyone of the people for
anything after the Messenger of Allah, until he
died.</english-text>
</hadith>
