<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32641</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2717</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of Paradise - كتاب صفة الجنة
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20356, 20583, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كريب، حدثنا محمد بن فضيل، عن حمزة الزيات، عن
زياد الطائي، عن أبي هريرة، قال قلنا يا رسول الله ما لنا إذا كنا
عندك رقت قلوبنا وزهدنا في الدنيا وكنا من أهل الآخرة فإذا خرجنا من
عندك فآنسنا أهالينا وشممنا أولادنا أنكرنا أنفسنا ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو أنكم تكونون إذا خرجتم من عندي كنتم على
حالكم ذلك لزارتكم الملائكة في بيوتكم ولو لم تذنبوا لجاء الله بخلق
جديد كى يذنبوا فيغفر لهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت يا رسول الله مم خلق الخلق
قال ‏"‏ من الماء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا الجنة ما بناؤها قال ‏"‏ لبنة من فضة
ولبنة من ذهب وملاطها المسك الأذفر وحصباؤها اللؤلؤ والياقوت وتربتها
الزعفران من يدخلها ينعم ولا يبأس ويخلد ولا يموت لا تبلى ثيابهم ولا
يفنى شبابهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ثلاثة لا ترد دعوتهم الإمام العادل
والصائم حين يفطر ودعوة المظلوم يرفعها فوق الغمام وتفتح لها أبواب
السماء ويقول الرب عز وجل وعزتي لأنصرنك ولو بعد حين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو
عيسى هذا حديث ليس إسناده بذاك القوي وليس هو عندي بمتصل وقد روي هذا
الحديث بإسناد آخر عن أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated: "We said: 'O Messenger of
Allah! What is wrong with us that when we are with you our hearts
are softened and we feel free of desire for this world, and we are
of the people of the Hereafter. But when we depart from you and
socialize with our families and our children, we do not recognize
ourselves(i.e., we are changed persons)?' So the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) said: 'If you were to be in that condition when you depart
from me, the angels would have surely visited you in your houses.
And if you did not sin, Allah would surely have brought anew
creation that they may sin, so that then He may forgive them.'"He
said: "I said: 'O Messenger of Allah! From what was the creation
created?' He said: 'From water.' We said: 'Paradise, what is it
constructed of?' He said,'Bricks of silver and bricks of gold. Its
mortar is musk of a strong fragrance, and its pebbles are pearls
and rubies, and its earth is saffron. Whoever enters it shall live
and shall not suffer, and shall feel joy and shall not die, nor
shall their clothes wear out, nor shall their youth come to an
end.' Then he said: 'Three persons , their supplication is not
rejected: The just ruler, the fasting person when he breaks his
fast, and the supplication of the wronged person. It is raised up
above the clouds, and the gates of Heaven are opened up for it, and
the Lord, Blessed and Exalted says: I shall surely come to your
aid, even if after a time.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
