<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32646</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2722</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of Paradise - كتاب صفة الجنة
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 30423, 20167, 11163, 11020, 32</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، وأحمد بن عبدة الضبي البصري، قالا حدثنا
عبد العزيز بن محمد، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن عطاء بن يسار، عن معاذ بن
جبل، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من صام رمضان وصلى
الصلوات وحج البيت لا أدري أذكر الزكاة أم لا إلا كان حقا على الله أن
يغفر له إن هاجر في سبيل الله أو مكث بأرضه التي ولد بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
معاذ ألا أخبر بهذا الناس فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ذر
الناس يعملون فإن في الجنة مائة درجة ما بين كل درجتين كما بين السماء
والأرض والفردوس أعلى الجنة وأوسطها وفوق ذلك عرش الرحمن ومنها تفجر
أنهار الجنة فإذا سألتم الله فسلوه الفردوس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هكذا
روي هذا الحديث عن هشام بن سعد عن زيد بن أسلم عن عطاء بن يسار عن
معاذ بن جبل وهذا عندي أصح من حديث همام عن زيد بن أسلم عن عطاء بن
يسار عن عبادة بن الصامت ‏.‏ وعطاء لم يدرك معاذ بن جبل ومعاذ قديم
الموت مات في خلافة عمر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mu'adh bin Jabal narrated that the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) said: "Whoever fasts Ramadan, performs the Salat, performs
hajj to the House"- I do not know whether he mentioned Zakat or
not- "except tat it is binding on Allah that He forgive him,
whether he emigrated in the cause of Allah, or remained in his land
in which he was born." Mu'adh said: "Should I not inform the people
of this?" the Messenger of Allah said, "Leave the people to do
deeds, for verily in Paradise there are a hundred levels, what is
between every two levels is like what is between the heavens and
the earth. Al-Firdaus is the highet of Paradise and its most
expansive, and above that is the Throne of Ar-Rahman(the Most
Merciful), and from it the rivers of Paradise are made to flow
forth. So when you ask Allah, ask Him for
Al-Firdaus."</english-text>
</hadith>
