<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32679</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2755</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of Paradise - كتاب صفة الجنة
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20167, 10606, 11884, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن محمد، عن العلاء بن
عبد الرحمن، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ يجمع الله الناس يوم القيامة في صعيد واحد ثم يطلع عليهم رب
العالمين فيقول ألا يتبع كل إنسان ما كانوا يعبدونه ‏.‏ فيمثل لصاحب
الصليب صليبه ولصاحب التصاوير تصاويره ولصاحب النار ناره فيتبعون ما
كانوا يعبدون ويبقى المسلمون فيطلع عليهم رب العالمين فيقول ألا
تتبعون الناس فيقولون نعوذ بالله منك نعوذ بالله منك الله ربنا هذا
مكاننا حتى نرى ربنا ‏.‏ وهو يأمرهم ويثبتهم ثم يتوارى ثم يطلع فيقول
ألا تتبعون الناس فيقولون نعوذ بالله منك نعوذ بالله منك الله ربنا
وهذا مكاننا حتى نرى ربنا ‏.‏ وهو يأمرهم ويثبتهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا وهل
نراه يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ وهل تضارون في رؤية القمر ليلة البدر ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا لا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنكم لا تضارون في رؤيته تلك
الساعة ثم يتوارى ثم يطلع فيعرفهم نفسه ثم يقول أنا ربكم فاتبعوني ‏.‏
فيقوم المسلمون ويوضع الصراط فيمرون عليه مثل جياد الخيل والركاب
وقولهم عليه سلم سلم ‏.‏ ويبقى أهل النار فيطرح منهم فيها فوج ثم يقال
هل امتلأت فتقول هل من مزيد ‏.‏ ثم يطرح فيها فوج فيقال هل امتلأت ‏.‏
فتقول هل من مزيد ‏.‏ حتى إذا أوعبوا فيها وضع الرحمن قدمه فيها وأزوي
بعضها إلى بعض ثم قال قط قالت قط قط فإذا أدخل الله أهل الجنة الجنة
وأهل النار النار قال أتي بالموت ملببا فيوقف على السور الذي بين أهل
الجنة وأهل النار ثم يقال يا أهل الجنة ‏.‏ فيطلعون خائفين ثم يقال يا
أهل النار ‏.‏ فيطلعون مستبشرين يرجون الشفاعة فيقال لأهل الجنة وأهل
النار هل تعرفون هذا فيقولون هؤلاء وهؤلاء قد عرفناه هو الموت الذي
وكل بنا ‏.‏ فيضجع فيذبح ذبحا على السور الذي بين الجنة والنار ثم
يقال يا أهل الجنة خلود لا موت ويا أهل النار خلود لا موت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ - وقد روي عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم روايات كثيرة مثل هذا ما يذكر فيه أمر الرؤية أن الناس يرون ربهم
وذكر القدم وما أشبه هذه الأشياء والمذهب في هذا عند أهل العلم من
الأئمة مثل سفيان الثوري ومالك بن أنس وابن المبارك وابن عيينة ووكيع
وغيرهم أنهم رووا هذه الأشياء ثم قالوا تروى هذه الأحاديث ونؤمن بها
ولا يقال كيف وهذا الذي اختاره أهل الحديث أن تروى هذه الأشياء كما
جاءت ويؤمن بها ولا تفسر ولا تتوهم ولا يقال كيف وهذا أمر أهل العلم
الذي اختاروه وذهبوا إليه ‏.‏ ومعنى قوله في الحديث ‏"‏ فيعرفهم نفسه
‏"‏ ‏.‏ يعني يتجلى لهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated that the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) said: "Allah will gather mankind on the Day of Resurrection
on a single plane, then the Lord of the Worlds will come to them
and say: 'Let every person follow what they used to worship.' SO to
the worshipper of the cross, his cross shall be symbolized to him,
and to the worshipper of images his images, and to the worshipper
of fire his fire. They will follow what they used to worship, and
the Muslims will remain. Then the Lord of the Worlds will come to
them and say: 'Do you not follow the people?' So they will say: 'We
seek refuge in Allah from you, we seek refuge in Allah from you,
Allah is our Lord, and we shall remain here until we see our Lord.'
And He orders them and makes them firm.'"Thy said: "And you will
see Him, O Messenger of Allah?" He said: "Are you harmed in seeing
the moon on the night of a full moon?" They said: "No, O Messenger
of Allah." He said: "So you will not be harmed in seeing Him at
that hour. Then He will conceal Himself, then He will come, and He
will make them recognize Him, then He will say: "I am your Lord, so
follow Me." So the Muslims will arise and the Sirat shall be
placed, and they shall be placed, and they shall pass by it the
like of excellent horses and camels and their statement upon it
shall be, "Grant them safety, grant them safety." And the people of
Fire shall remain, then a party of them shall be cast down into it,
and it shall be said (to the Fire): 'Have you become full?' So it
shall say: Is there more? Then a party of them shall be cast down
into it, and it shall be said: 'Have you become full?' So it shall
say: Is there more? Until when they are all included into it,
Ar-Rahman (the Most-Merciful) shall place His foot in it and its
sides shall be all brought together, then He will say: 'Enough.' It
will say 'Enough, enough.' So when Allah, the Exalted, has admitted
the people of Paradise into Paradise and the people of Fire into
Fire"- [He said:]- "Death shall be brought in by the collar and
stood on the wall that is between the people of Paradise and the
people of the Fire, then it will be said: 'O people of Paradise!'
They will come near, afraid. Then it will be said: 'O people of the
Fire!' They will come rejoicing, hoping for intercession. Then it
will be said to the people of Paradise and the people of the Fire:
'Do you recognize this?' So they will-both of them-say: 'We
recognize it. It is Death which was given charge of us,' so it will
be laid down and slaughtered upon the wall [the one that is between
Paradise and the Fire], then it will be said: 'O people of
Paradise! Everlasting life without death!' And 'O people of the
Fire! Everlasting life without death!'"</english-text>
</hadith>
