<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32682</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>38</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2758</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on the description of Paradise - كتاب صفة الجنة
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20337, 11220, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كريب، حدثنا عبدة بن سليمان، عن محمد بن عمرو،
حدثنا أبو سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ لما خلق الله الجنة والنار أرسل جبريل إلى الجنة فقال انظر إليها
وإلى ما أعددت لأهلها فيها قال فجاءها ونظر إليها وإلى ما أعد الله
لأهلها فيها قال فرجع إليه قال فوعزتك لا يسمع بها أحد إلا دخلها ‏.‏
فأمر بها فحفت بالمكاره فقال ارجع إليها فانظر إلى ما أعددت لأهلها
فيها قال فرجع إليها فإذا هي قد حفت بالمكاره فرجع إليه فقال وعزتك
لقد خفت أن لا يدخلها أحد ‏.‏ قال اذهب إلى النار فانظر إليها وإلى ما
أعددت لأهلها فيها ‏.‏ فإذا هي يركب بعضها بعضا فرجع إليه فقال وعزتك
لا يسمع بها أحد فيدخلها ‏.‏ فأمر بها فحفت بالشهوات فقال ارجع إليها
‏.‏ فرجع إليها فقال وعزتك لقد خشيت أن لا ينجو منها أحد إلا دخلها
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated that the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) said: "When Allah created Paradise and the Fire, He sent
Jibril to Paradise , saying: 'Look at it and at what I have
prepared in it for its inhabitants.'" He (s.a.w) said: "So he came
to it and looked at it, and at what Allah had prepared in it. He
(Jibril) said: 'Indeed, by your Might, none shall hear of it except
that he shall enter it.' Then He gave the order for it to be
surrounded with hardships. He said: 'Return to it and look at it,
and at what I have prepared in it for its inhabitants.'" He (s.a.w)
said: "So he returned to it and found it surrounded with hardships.
He returned to Him and said: 'Indeed, by your Might, I fear that
none shall enter it.' He (s.a.w) said: 'Go to the Fire and look at
it and at what I have prepared in it for its inhabitants.' So he
found it, one part of it riding the other. So he returned to Him
and said: 'Indeed, by your Might, none shall hear of it and then
enter it.' So He gave the order for it to be surrounded with
desires, then He said: 'Return to it.,' so he (Jibril) returned to
it, then he said: 'Indeed, by Your Might, I fear that none shall be
saved from it except that he shall enter it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
