<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32727</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>39</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2803</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on the Description of Hellfire - كتاب صفة جهنم عن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>38265, 20025, 26012, 11113, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سويد بن نصر، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا رشدين بن
سعد، حدثني ابن أنعم، عن أبي عثمان، أنه حدثه عن أبي هريرة، عن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن رجلين ممن دخل النار اشتد صياحهما
فقال الرب عز وجل أخرجوهما ‏.‏ فلما أخرجا قال لهما لأى شيء اشتد
صياحكما قالا فعلنا ذلك لترحمنا ‏.‏ قال إن رحمتي لكما أن تنطلقا
فتلقيا أنفسكما حيث كنتما من النار ‏.‏ فينطلقان فيلقي أحدهما نفسه
فيجعلها عليه بردا وسلاما ويقوم الآخر فلا يلقي نفسه فيقول له الرب عز
وجل ما منعك أن تلقي نفسك كما ألقى صاحبك فيقول يا رب إني لأرجو أن لا
تعيدني فيها بعد ما أخرجتني ‏.‏ فيقول له الرب لك رجاؤك ‏.‏ فيدخلان
جميعا الجنة برحمة الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى إسناد هذا الحديث ضعيف
لأنه عن رشدين بن سعد ‏.‏ ورشدين بن سعد هو ضعيف عند أهل الحديث عن
ابن أنعم وهو الإفريقي والإفريقي ضعيف عند أهل الحديث
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated that the Messenger of Allah
(s.a.w) said: "Indeed two men among those who entered the Fire will
be screaming violently. So the Lord, Blessed and Exalted, will say:
'Take them out.' Then when they are taken out He will say: 'What
caused you to scream so violently?' They will say: 'We did that so
You would have mercy on us.' He will say: 'My mercy for you is that
you both go and throw yourselves where you were in the Fire.' So
they will go. One of them will throw himself in, and He will make
it cool and peaceful for him. And the other will stand there and
not throw himself in, so the Lord, Mighty and Majestic, will say to
him: 'What prevented you from throwing yourself in as your
companion did?' He will say: 'O Lord! I hope that you will not
return me to it aftrr You have taken me out.' So the Lord, Blessed
and Exalted, will say to him: 'For you is what you hoped for,' and
so they will both enter Paradise together by the mercy of
Allah."</english-text>
</hadith>
