<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>32738</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2610</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book on Faith - كتاب الإيمان عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20032, 11303, 11432, 11316</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عمار الحسين بن حريث الخزاعي، أخبرنا وكيع، عن
كهمس بن الحسن، عن عبد الله بن بريدة، عن يحيى بن يعمر، قال أول من
تكلم في القدر معبد الجهني قال فخرجت أنا وحميد بن عبد الرحمن الحميري
حتى أتينا المدينة فقلنا لو لقينا رجلا من أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فسألناه عما أحدث هؤلاء القوم ‏.‏ قال فلقيناه يعني عبد الله بن
عمر وهو خارج من المسجد قال فاكتنفته أنا وصاحبي قال فظننت أن صاحبي
سيكل الكلام إلى فقلت يا أبا عبد الرحمن إن قوما يقرءون القرآن
ويتقفرون العلم ويزعمون أن لا قدر وأن الأمر أنف قال فإذا لقيت أولئك
فأخبرهم أني منهم بريء وأنهم مني برآء والذي يحلف به عبد الله لو أن
أحدهم أنفق مثل أحد ذهبا ما قبل ذلك منه حتى يؤمن بالقدر خيره وشره
‏.‏ قال ثم أنشأ يحدث فقال قال عمر بن الخطاب كنا عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فجاء رجل شديد بياض الثياب شديد سواد الشعر لا يرى
عليه أثر السفر ولا يعرفه منا أحد حتى أتى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فألزق ركبته بركبته ثم قال يا محمد ما الإيمان قال ‏"‏ أن تؤمن بالله
وملائكته وكتبه ورسله واليوم الآخر والقدر خيره وشره ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فما
الإسلام قال ‏"‏ شهادة أن لا إله إلا الله وأن محمدا عبده ورسوله
وإقام الصلاة وإيتاء الزكاة وحج البيت وصوم رمضان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فما
الإحسان قال ‏"‏ أن تعبد الله كأنك تراه فإنك إن لم تكن تراه فإنه
يراك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال في كل ذلك يقول له صدقت ‏.‏ قال فتعجبنا منه يسأله
ويصدقه ‏.‏ قال فمتى الساعة قال ‏"‏ ما المسئول عنها بأعلم من السائل
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فما أمارتها قال أن تلد الأمة ربتها وأن ترى الحفاة
العراة العالة أصحاب الشاء يتطاولون في البنيان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عمر
فلقيني النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بعد ذلك بثلاث فقال ‏"‏ يا عمر هل
تدري من السائل ذاك جبريل أتاكم يعلمكم معالم دينكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حدثنا
أحمد بن محمد، أخبرنا ابن المبارك، أخبرنا كهمس بن الحسن، بهذا
الإسناد نحوه ‏.‏ حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا معاذ بن معاذ، عن كهمس،
بهذا الإسناد نحوه بمعناه ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن طلحة بن عبيد الله وأنس بن
مالك وأبي هريرة ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح قد روي من غير
وجه نحو هذا عن عمر ‏.‏ وقد روي هذا الحديث عن ابن عمر عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم والصحيح هو ابن عمر عن عمر عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abdullah bin Buraidah from Yahya bin Ya'mur
who said: "The first person to speak about Al-Qadar was Ma'bad
Al-Juhani." He said: "Humaid bin Abdur-Rahman Al-Himyari and I went
out until we reached Al-Madinah, and we said: 'If we could only
meet someone among the companions of the Prophet (ﷺ) so we could
ask him about what those people have innovated." [He said:] "So we
met him - meaning Abdullah bin 'Umar - while he was leaving the
Masjid." [He said:] "My companion and I were on either side of
him." [He said:] I thought my companion was going to leave the
speaking to me so I said: "O Abu Abdur-Rahman! There is a group of
people who recite the Qur'an and seek knowledge, and they claim
there is no Al-Qadar, and that the affair is left to chance.' He
said: "Whenever you meet those people, then tell them that I am not
of them and they are not of me. By the One Whom Abdullah swears by!
If one of them were to spend gold the like of Uhud (mountain) in
charity, it would not be accepted from him until he believes in
Al-Qadar; the good of it and the bad of it.'" He said: "Then he
began to narrate, he said: "'Umar bin Al-Khattab said: "We were
with the Messenger of Allah when a man came with extremely white
garments, and extremely black hair. He had no appearance of
traveling visible on him, yet none of us recognized him. He came
until he reached the Prophet (ﷺ). He put his knees up against his
knees, and then said: "O Muhammad! What is Iman?' He said 'To
believe in Allah, His Angels, His, Books, His Messengers, the Day
of Judgement, and Al-Qadar, the good of it and the bad of it.' He
said: 'Then what is Islam?' He said: 'Testifying to La Ilaha
Illallah, and that Muhammad is His servant and Messenger,
establishing the Salat, giving the Zakat, performing Hajj to the
House, and fasting (the month of) Ramadan.' He said: 'Then what is
Ihsan?' He said 'That (is) you worship Allah as if you see Him, and
although you do not see Him, He certainly sees you.' He said: 'For
all of those he replied to him: 'You have told the truth.'" He
said: "So we were amazed at him, he would ask, and then tell him
that he is telling the truth. He said: 'Then when is the Hour?' He
(ﷺ) said: 'The one being asked knows no more than the questioner.'
He said: 'Then what are its signs?' He said: 'That the slave woman
gives birth to her master, and that the naked, poor, and
bare-footed shepherds rival each other in the height of the
buildings.'" 'Umar said: 'Then the Prophet (ﷺ) met me three days
after that and said: 'O 'Umar! Do you know who the questioner was?
It was Jibril. He came to teach you about the matters of your
religion.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
