<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33023</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3115</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on The Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20167, 10606, 11884, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن محمد، عن العلاء بن
عبد الرحمن، عن أبيه، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
خرج على أبى بن كعب فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا أبى ‏"‏
‏.‏ وهو يصلي فالتفت أبى ولم يجبه وصلى أبى فخفف ثم انصرف إلى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال السلام عليك يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعليك السلام ما منعك يا أبى أن تجيبني
إذ دعوتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال يا رسول الله إني كنت في الصلاة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
أفلم تجد فيما أوحى الله إلى أن ‏(‏استجيبوا لله وللرسول إذا دعاكم
لما يحييكم ‏)‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال بلى ولا أعود إن شاء الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تحب
أن أعلمك سورة لم ينزل في التوراة ولا في الإنجيل ولا في الزبور ولا
في الفرقان مثلها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كيف تقرأ في الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقرأ أم القرآن
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده ما أنزلت في
التوراة ولا في الإنجيل ولا في الزبور ولا في الفرقان مثلها وإنها سبع
من المثاني والقرآن العظيم الذي أعطيته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن أنس بن مالك وفيه عن أبي سعيد بن المعلى
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: that the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) came out to Ubayy bin Ka'b, and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: "O Ubayy!" And he was performing Salat, so Ubayy turned
around but he did not respond to him, so Ubayy finished his Salat
quickly. Then he turned to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said:
'As-Salamu 'Alaikum, O Messenger of Allah!' The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) said: 'Wa 'Alaikum As-Salam - what prevented you from
responding to me when I called you Ubayy?' He said: 'O Messenger of
Allah! I was performing Salat.' So he said: 'Do you not find among
what Allah revealed to me: Respond to Allah and to the Messenger
when they call you to what gives you life?' He said: 'Of course, I
shall not repeat that, if Allah wills.' He said: 'Would you like
for me to teach you a Surah the likes of which has neither been
revealed in the Tawrah, nor the Injil, nor the Zabur, nor in the
entire Qur'an?' He said: "Yes, O Messenger of Allah!' The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'What do you recite in your Salat?' He said: 'I
recite Umm Al-Qur'an.' So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'By the
One in Whose Hand is my soul! The like of it has neither been
revealed in the Tawrah, nor the Injil nor the Zabur, nor in the
Furqan. It is the seven oft-repeated, and the Magnificent Qur'an
which I was given.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
