<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33055</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3147</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on The Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>34188, 30103, 20167, 11201, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا إسماعيل بن أبي أويس،
حدثنا عبد العزيز بن محمد، عن عبيد الله بن عمر، عن ثابت البناني، عن
أنس بن مالك، قال كان رجل من الأنصار يؤمهم في مسجد قباء فكان كلما
افتتح سورة يقرأ لهم في الصلاة فقرأ بها افتتح ب ‏(‏قل هو الله أحد
‏)‏ حتى يفرغ منها ثم يقرأ بسورة أخرى معها وكان يصنع ذلك في كل ركعة
فكلمه أصحابه فقالوا إنك تقرأ بهذه السورة ثم لا ترى أنها تجزيك حتى
تقرأ بسورة أخرى فإما أن تقرأ بها وإما أن تدعها وتقرأ بسورة أخرى ‏.‏
قال ما أنا بتاركها إن أحببتم أن أؤمكم بها فعلت وإن كرهتم تركتكم ‏.‏
وكانوا يرونه أفضلهم وكرهوا أن يؤمهم غيره فلما أتاهم النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم أخبروه الخبر فقال ‏"‏ يا فلان ما يمنعك مما يأمر به أصحابك
وما يحملك أن تقرأ هذه السورة في كل ركعة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال يا رسول الله
إني أحبها ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن حبها أدخلك
الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب صحيح من هذا الوجه من
حديث عبيد الله بن عمر عن ثابت ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: "There was a man from the
Ansar who led them (in Salat) at Masjid Quba. Every time he was to
recite a Surah for them during Salat, he would begin by reciting
Qul Huwa Allahu Ahad until he finished, then he would recite
another Surah with it. He did that in each Rak'ah. His companions
talked to him and said: 'You recite this Surah. You should either
recite it or leave it and recite another Surah.'" He said: "I shall
not leave it, if you would like me to lead you with it then I shall
do so, and if you do not like it then I shall leave you." And they
considered him the best among them, and they did not like the idea
of someone else leading them. So when the Prophet (ﷺ) came to them
they informed him about what had happened and he (ﷺ) said: "O
so-and-so! What prevents you from doing what your companions told
you to do, why do recite this Surah in every Rak'ah" He said: "O
Messenger of Allah! Indeed I love it." So the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) said: "Your love for it shall have you admitted into
Paradise."</english-text>
</hadith>
