<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33083</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3174</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on The Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن
عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 20675, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا الليث، عن معاوية بن صالح، عن عبد
الله بن أبي قيس، هو رجل بصري قال سألت عائشة عن وتر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم كيف كان يوتر من أول الليل أو من آخره فقالت كل ذلك قد
كان يصنع ربما أوتر من أول الليل وربما أوتر من آخره ‏.‏ فقلت الحمد
لله الذي جعل في الأمر سعة فقلت كيف كانت قراءته أكان يسر بالقراءة أم
يجهر قالت كل ذلك قد كان يفعل قد كان ربما أسر وربما جهر قال فقلت
الحمد لله الذي جعل في الأمر سعة قلت فكيف كان يصنع في الجنابة أكان
يغتسل قبل أن ينام أو ينام قبل أن يغتسل قالت كل ذلك قد كان يفعل
فربما اغتسل فنام وربما توضأ فنام قلت الحمد لله الذي جعل في الأمر
سعة ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب من هذا الوجه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Abdullah bin Abi Qais [A man from
Al-Basrah]: "I asked 'Aishah about the Witr of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ), how would he perform Witr, was it during the first part
of the night or the end of it? She said: 'All of that. Sometimes he
would perform Witr during the first part of the night, and
sometimes he would perform Witr during the end of it.' So I said:
'All praise is due to Allah who made the matter accommodating.' I
said: 'How was his recitation, was he quiet with recitations or
loud?' She said: 'He would do all of that. Sometimes he would
recite quietly and sometimes aloud.' I said: 'All praise is due to
Allah who made the matter accommodating. He said: 'I said: 'How
would he deal with sexual impurity? Would he perform Ghusl prior to
sleeping or would he sleep prior to Ghusl?' She said: 'He would do
all of that. Sometimes he would perform Ghusl then sleep, and
sometimes he would perform Wudu and then sleep.' I said: 'Allah
praise is due to Allah who made the matter
accommodating.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
