<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33104</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>46</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3195</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Recitation - كتاب القراءات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 20121, 20115, 11013, 10511, 2201,
3</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي الخلال، وغير، واحد، قالوا حدثنا عبد
الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن الزهري، عن عروة بن الزبير، عن المسور بن
مخرمة، وعبد الرحمن بن عبد القاري، أخبراه أنهما، سمعا عمر بن الخطاب،
يقول مررت بهشام بن حكيم بن حزام وهو يقرأ سورة الفرقان في حياة رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فاستمعت قراءته فإذا هو يقرأ على حروف كثيرة
لم يقرئنيها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فكدت أساوره في الصلاة
فنظرته حتى سلم فلما سلم لببته بردائه فقلت من أقرأك هذه السورة التي
سمعتك تقرؤها فقال أقرأنيها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏.‏ قلت
له كذبت والله إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لهو أقرأني هذه السورة
التي تقرؤها ‏.‏ فانطلقت أقوده إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا
رسول الله إني سمعت هذا يقرأ سورة الفرقان على حروف لم تقرئنيها وأنت
أقرأتني سورة الفرقان ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرسله يا
عمر اقرأ يا هشام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقرأ القراءة التي سمعته فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هكذا أنزلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ اقرأ يا عمر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقرأت القراءة التي أقرأني النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هكذا أنزلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن هذا القرآن أنزل على سبعة
أحرف فاقرءوا ما تيسر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وقد روى مالك
بن أنس عن الزهري بهذا الإسناد نحوه إلا أنه لم يذكر فيه المسور بن
مخرمة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Umar bin Al-Khattab: "I passed by Hisham
bin Hakim bin Hizam while he was reciting Surat Al-Furqan during
the lifetime of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). I listened to his
recitation and noticed that he recited it in several different
ways, which the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had not taught me. I was
about to jump over him during his Salat, but waited until he said
the Salam. When he had said the Salam, I strangled him with his
upper-garment and said: 'Who taught you this Surah which I heard
you reciting?' He said: 'The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) taught it to
me.' I said to him: 'You lie! By Allah! The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
taught me this Surah which you were reciting.' I dragged him to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: 'O Messenger of Allah! I heard
this one reciting Surat Al-Furqan in a manner different from how
you taught me, and you taught me Surat Al-Furqan.' The Prophet (ﷺ)
said: 'Release him O 'Umar! Recite O Hisham.' So he recited it for
him as I had heard him reciting. Then the Prophet (ﷺ) said to me:
'This is how it was revealed.' Then the Prophet (ﷺ) said to me,
'Recite O 'Umar.' So I recited the recitation which the Prophet (ﷺ)
taught me. The Prophet (ﷺ) said: 'This is how it was revealed.'
Then the Prophet (ﷺ) said 'Indeed this Qur'an was revealed in seven
modes, so recite of it what is easier for you.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
