<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33152</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3243</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 20193, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثني سليمان بن حرب، حدثنا حماد بن
سلمة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، قال كانت اليهود إذا حاضت امرأة منهم لم
يواكلوها ولم يشاربوها ولم يجامعوها في البيوت فسئل النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم عن ذلك فأنزل الله تعالى ‏:‏ ‏(‏يسألونك عن المحيض قل هو
أذى ‏)‏ فأمرهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يواكلوهن ويشاربوهن
وأن يكونوا معهن في البيوت وأن يفعلوا كل شيء ما خلا النكاح فقالت
اليهود ما يريد أن يدع شيئا من أمرنا إلا خالفنا فيه ‏.‏ قال فجاء
عباد بن بشر وأسيد بن حضير إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبراه
بذلك وقالا يا رسول الله أفلا ننكحهن في المحيض فتمعر وجه رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى ظننا أنه قد غضب عليهما فقاما فاستقبلتهما
هدية من لبن فأرسل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في آثارهما فسقاهما
فعلمنا أنه لم يغضب عليهما ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: "When the women among the Jews
menstruated, they would not eat with them, nor drink with them, nor
mingle with them in their homes. The Prophet (ﷺ) was asked about
that, so Allah, Blessed and Most High, revealed: "They ask you
about menstruation. Say It is a Adha (harmful matter) (2:222).' So
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) told them to eat with them, drink with
them and to remain in the house with them, and to do everything
besides intercourse with them. The Jews said: 'He does not want to
leave any matter of ours without opposing us in it.'" He said:
"Then 'Abbad bin Bishr and Usaid bin Hudair came to the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) to inform him about that. They said: 'O Messenger of
Allah! Should we not (then) have intercourse with them during their
menstruation?' The face of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) changed
color, until they thought that he was angry with them. So they
left, and afterwards the Prophet (ﷺ) was given some milk as a gift,
so he sent some of it to them to drink. Then they knew that he was
not angry with them."</english-text>
</hadith>
