<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33216</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3307</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 399,
49</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم بن سعد، عن
أبيه، عن صالح بن كيسان، عن ابن شهاب، حدثني سهل بن سعد، قال رأيت
مروان بن الحكم جالسا في المسجد فأقبلت حتى جلست إلى جنبه فأخبرنا أن
زيد بن ثابت أخبره أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أملى عليه لا يستوي
القاعدون من المؤمنين والمجاهدون في سبيل الله قال فجاءه ابن أم مكتوم
وهو يمليها على فقال يا رسول الله والله لو أستطيع الجهاد لجاهدت وكان
رجلا أعمى ‏.‏ فأنزل الله على رسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم وفخذه على
فخذي فثقلت حتى همت ترض فخذي ثم سري عنه فأنزل الله عليه ‏:‏ ‏(‏ غير
أولي الضرر ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ هكذا روى غير
واحد عن الزهري عن سهل بن سعد نحو هذا ‏.‏ وروى معمر عن الزهري هذا
الحديث عن قبيصة بن ذؤيب عن زيد بن ثابت ‏.‏ وفي هذا الحديث رواية رجل
من أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن رجل من التابعين رواه سهل بن
سعد الأنصاري عن مروان بن الحكم ومروان لم يسمع من النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم وهو من التابعين ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa'd As-Sa'idi: "I saw Marwan bin
Al-Hakam sitting in the Masjid, so I went over to him until I sat
next to him. He informed us that Zaid bin Thabit informed him, that
the Prophet (ﷺ) dictated: 'Not equal among the believers are those
who sit and the Mujahidin in the cause of Allah.' He said: 'So Ibn
Umm Maktum came and he was dictating to me that he said: "O
Messenger of Allah! By Allah! If I were capable of Jihad then I
would participate in Jihad.' And he was a blind a man. So Allah
revealed to His Messenger (ﷺ) - while his thigh was against my
thigh - and it became so heavy that I was worried it was about to
fracture my thigh. Then he was relieved of it, so Allah had
revealed to him: Except those who are disabled."</english-text>
</hadith>
