<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33245</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3336</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 11107, 11164, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن أحمد بن أبي شعيب الحراني، حدثنا محمد بن
سلمة الحراني، حدثنا محمد بن إسحاق، عن أبي النضر، عن باذان، مولى أم
هانئ عن ابن عباس، عن تميم الداري، في هذه الآية ‏:‏ ‏(‏ يا أيها
الذين آمنوا شهادة بينكم إذا حضر أحدكم الموت ‏)‏ قال برئ منها الناس
غيري وغير عدي بن بداء وكانا نصرانيين يختلفان إلى الشام قبل الإسلام
فأتيا الشام لتجارتهما وقدم عليهما مولى لبني سهم يقال له بديل بن أبي
مريم بتجارة ومعه جام من فضة يريد به الملك وهو عظم تجارته فمرض فأوصى
إليهما وأمرهما أن يبلغا ما ترك أهله قال تميم فلما مات أخذنا ذلك
الجام فبعناه بألف درهم ثم اقتسمناه أنا وعدي بن بداء فلما قدمنا إلى
أهله دفعنا إليهم ما كان معنا وفقدوا الجام فسألونا عنه فقلنا ما ترك
غير هذا وما دفع إلينا غيره قال تميم فلما أسلمت بعد قدوم رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم المدينة تأثمت من ذلك فأتيت أهله فأخبرتهم الخبر
وأديت إليهم خمسمائة درهم وأخبرتهم أن عند صاحبي مثلها فأتوا به رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسألهم البينة فلم يجدوا فأمرهم أن يستحلفوه
بما يعظم به على أهل دينه فحلف فأنزل الله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ يا أيها الذين
آمنوا شهادة بينكم إذا حضر أحدكم الموت ‏)‏ إلى قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ أو
يخافوا أن ترد أيمان بعد أيمانهم ‏)‏ ‏.‏ فقام عمرو بن العاص ورجل آخر
فحلفا فنزعت الخمسمائة درهم من عدي بن بداء ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
غريب وليس إسناده بصحيح ‏.‏ وأبو النضر الذي روى عنه محمد بن إسحاق
هذا الحديث هو عندي محمد بن السائب الكلبي يكنى أبا النضر وقد تركه
أهل الحديث وهو صاحب التفسير سمعت محمد بن إسماعيل يقول محمد بن
السائب الكلبي يكنى أبا النضر ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى ولا نعرف لسالم أبي
النضر المدني رواية عن أبي صالح مولى أم هانئ وقد روي عن ابن عباس شيء
من هذا على الاختصار من غير هذا الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: from Tamim Ad-Dari, regarding
this Ayah: O you who believe! When death approaches any of you then
take the testimony (5:106). He said: "The people are innocent of
it, other than myself and 'Adi bin Badda.' We were Christians who
used to frequent Ash-Sham before Islam." They went to Ash-Sham for
their business, and they were approached by a freed slave of Banu
Sahm, who was called Budail bin Abi Maryam, with some trade. He had
a bowl they wanted made of silver, but he wanted a great deal for
it. Then he became ill, and willed it to them, and he commissioned
them to deliver what was left to his family. Tamim said: "When he
died, we took that bowl and we sold it for one-thousand Dirham.
Then 'Adi bin Badda and I divided it. When we went to his family to
give them what was with us, they searched for the bowl and asked
about it. We said: 'He did not leave behind other than this, nor
did he give us other than this.'" Tamim said: "When I accepted
Islam, after the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had arrived in Al-Madinah,
I felt guilty about that, so I went to his family, and informed
them about what had happened. I gave them fifty-thousand Dirham and
told them my companion had the same. They took him to the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) but he asked them for their proof, which they did not
have, so he ordered them, to have him to take an oath in accordance
with whatever the people of his religion revered, so he took the
oath. Then Allah revealed: 'O you who believe! When death
approaches any of you then take the testimony...' up to His saying:
'Or else they would fear that oaths will be admitted after their
oaths (5:106).'" So 'Amr bin Al-'As and another man stood to take
an oath, and the fifty-thousand Dirham was taken from 'Adi bin
Badda.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
