<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33256</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3347</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30242, 20411, 11585, 11052, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن منيع، حدثنا إسحاق بن يوسف الأزرق، حدثنا
داود بن أبي هند، عن الشعبي، عن مسروق، قال كنت متكئا عند عائشة فقالت
يا أبا عائشة ثلاث من تكلم بواحدة منهن فقد أعظم على الله الفرية من
زعم أن محمدا رأى ربه فقد أعظم الفرية على الله والله يقول ‏:‏ ‏(‏ لا
تدركه الأبصار وهو يدرك الأبصار وهو اللطيف الخبير ‏)‏ ، ‏(‏ ما كان
لبشر أن يكلمه الله إلا وحيا أو من وراء حجاب ‏)‏ وكنت متكئا فجلست
فقلت يا أم المؤمنين أنظريني ولا تعجليني أليس يقول الله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ ولقد
رآه نزلة أخرى ‏)‏، ‏(‏ ولقد رآه بالأفق المبين ‏)‏ قالت أنا والله
أول من سأل عن هذا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إنما ذاك
جبريل ما رأيته في الصورة التي خلق فيها غير هاتين المرتين رأيته
منهبطا من السماء سادا عظم خلقه ما بين السماء والأرض ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ومن زعم
أن محمدا كتم شيئا مما أنزل الله عليه فقد أعظم الفرية على الله يقول
الله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ يا أيها الرسول بلغ ما أنزل إليك من ربك ‏)‏ ومن زعم أنه
يعلم ما في غد فقد أعظم الفرية على الله والله يقول ‏:‏ ‏(‏قل لا يعلم
من في السموات والأرض الغيب إلا الله ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
حسن صحيح ومسروق بن الأجدع يكنى أبا عائشة وهو مسروق بن عبد الرحمن
وهكذا كان اسمه في الديوان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Masruq: "I was reclining in the presence of
'Aishah when she said: 'O Abu 'Aishah! There are three things,
whoever speaks of one of them, then he has uttered one of the worst
lies against Allah. Whoever claims that Muhammad saw his Lord. Then
he has uttered one the worst lies against Allah, Allah says: No
vision can grasp Him, but His grasp is over all vision, and He is
the Most Subtle, Well-Acquainted with all things (6:103). It is not
for any human being that Allah should speak to him unless (it be)
by revelation or from behind a veil (42:91).' I was reclining so I
sat up an said: 'O Mother of the Believers! Take your time with me
and do not be hasty with me! Did Allah Most High not say: And
indeed he saw him at a second descent (53:13). (And) 'And indeed he
saw him in the clear horizon (81:23).' She said 'By Allah! I was
the first who asked the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) about this. He said:
"That was only Jibril. I did not see him in the appearance he was
created in except for these two times. I saw him descending from
the heavens, and due to his tremendous size he filled what was
between the heavens and the earth." "And whoever claimed that
Muhammad hid anything that Allah revealed to him, then he uttered
one of the worst lies against Allah. Allah says: O Messenger!
Proclaim what has been sent down to you from your Lord (5:67)."
"And whoever claimed that he (ﷺ) knew what would be tomorrow, then
he has uttered one of the worst lies against Allah. Allah says:
Say: 'None in the heavens and in the earth knows the unseen but
Allah (27:65).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
