<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33280</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3371</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>34188, 30252, 20431, 20655, 11069, 11725,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا سعيد بن سليمان، حدثنا
عباد بن العوام، حدثنا سفيان بن حسين، عن الحكم بن عتيبة، عن مقسم، عن
ابن عباس، قال بعث النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أبا بكر وأمره أن ينادي
بهؤلاء الكلمات ثم أتبعه عليا فبينا أبو بكر في بعض الطريق إذ سمع
رغاء ناقة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم القصواء فخرج أبو بكر فزعا
فظن أنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فإذا هو علي فدفع إليه كتاب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأمر عليا أن ينادي بهؤلاء الكلمات
فانطلقا فحجا فقام علي أيام التشريق فنادى ذمة الله ورسوله بريئة من
كل مشرك فسيحوا في الأرض أربعة أشهر ولا يحجن بعد العام مشرك ولا
يطوفن بالبيت عريان ولا يدخل الجنة إلا مؤمن وكان علي ينادي فإذا عيي
قام أبو بكر فنادى بها ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وهذا حديث حسن غريب من هذا
الوجه من حديث ابن عباس ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
dispatched Abu Bakr ordering him to announce these statements. Then
'Ali followed him. When Abu Bakr was at a particular road, he heard
the heavy breathing of Al-Qiswa, the she camel of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ), so Abu Bakr appeared frightened because he thought that
it was the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). When he saw that it was 'Ali, he
gave him the letter of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), and told 'Ali to
announce the statements. So he left to perform Hajj. During the day
of At-Tashriq 'Ali stood to announce: 'The protection of Allah and
His Messenger is removed from every idolater. So travel in the land
for four months. There is to be no idolater performing Hajj after
this year, nor may anyone perform Tawaf around the House while
naked. None shall enter Paradise but a believer.' 'Ali was making
the announcement, so when he became exhausted Abu Bakr would
announce it."</english-text>
</hadith>
