<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33312</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3403</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 20472, 25246, 11524, 579, 1040</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن، أخبرنا يزيد بن هارون،
أخبرنا قيس بن الربيع، عن عثمان بن عبد الله بن موهب، عن موسى بن
طلحة، عن أبي اليسر، قال أتتني امرأة تبتاع تمرا فقلت إن في البيت
تمرا أطيب منه ‏.‏ فدخلت معي في البيت فأهويت إليها فقبلتها فأتيت أبا
بكر فذكرت ذلك له قال استر على نفسك وتب ولا تخبر أحدا ‏.‏ فلم أصبر
فأتيت عمر فذكرت ذلك له فقال استر على نفسك وتب ولا تخبر أحدا ‏.‏ فلم
أصبر فأتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك له ‏.‏ فقال له
‏"‏ أخلفت غازيا في سبيل الله في أهله بمثل هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى تمنى أنه
لم يكن أسلم إلا تلك الساعة حتى ظن أنه من أهل النار ‏.‏ قال وأطرق
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم طويلا حتى أوحى الله إليه ‏:‏ ‏(‏أقم
الصلاة طرفى النهار وزلفا من الليل ‏)‏ إلى قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ذكرى للذاكرين
‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو اليسر فأتيته فقرأها على رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال أصحابه يا رسول الله ألهذا خاصة أم للناس عامة قال ‏"‏ بل
للناس عامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح غريب ‏.‏ وقيس بن
الربيع ضعفه وكيع وغيره وأبو اليسر هو كعب بن عمرو ‏.‏ قال وروى شريك
عن عثمان بن عبد الله هذا الحديث مثل رواية قيس بن الربيع ‏.‏ قال وفي
الباب عن أبي أمامة وواثلة بن الأسقع وأنس بن مالك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Musa bin Talhah: that Abu Al-Yasar said: "A
woman came to me selling dates. I said to her: 'There are better
dates than these in the house.' So she entered the house with me. I
had an urge for her so I began kissing her. I went to Abu Bakr and
mentioned that to him, so he said: 'Cover what you have done,
repent, do not inform any one, and never do it again.' So I went to
'Umar and mentioned that to him. He said: 'Cover what you have
done, repent, do not inform any one, and never do it again.' Then I
went to the Prophet (ﷺ) and mentioned it to him." He said: 'Is this
how you take care of the wife of someone who is away fighting in
Allah's cause?" Such that he had wished he had not accepted Islam
until that very time, and he thought that he must be one of the
people of the Fire." He said: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) bowed his
head for a long time, until Allah revealed to him: And perform the
Salat, at the two ends of the day and in some hours of the night.
Verily, the good deeds remove the evil deeds. That is a reminder
for the mindful (11:114). Abu Al-Yasar said: "So I went to him and
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) recited it for me. A companion of his
said: "O Messenger of Allah! Is this specific, or is it for the
people in general?" He said: "Rather it is for the people in
general."</english-text>
</hadith>
