<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33369</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3460</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30277, 20291, 20714, 11013, 11002, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمود بن غيلان، حدثنا النضر بن شميل، أخبرنا صالح
بن أبي الأخضر، عن الزهري، عن سعيد بن المسيب، عن أبي هريرة، قال لما
قفل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من خيبر أسرى ليلة حتى أدركه الكرى
أناخ فعرس ثم قال ‏"‏ يا بلال اكلأ لنا الليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فصلى بلال
ثم تساند إلى راحلته مستقبل الفجر فغلبته عيناه فنام فلم يستيقظ أحد
منهم وكان أولهم استيقاظا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أى
بلال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال بلال بأبي أنت يا رسول الله أخذ بنفسي الذي أخذ
بنفسك ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اقتادوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم
أناخ فتوضأ فأقام الصلاة ثم صلى مثل صلاته للوقت في تمكث ثم قال ‏:‏
‏(‏وأقم الصلاة لذكري ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث غير محفوظ رواه غير واحد
من الحفاظ عن الزهري عن سعيد بن المسيب أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
ولم يذكروا فيه عن أبي هريرة ‏.‏ وصالح بن أبي الأخضر يضعف في الحديث
ضعفه يحيى بن سعيد القطان وغيره من قبل حفظه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: "While the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) was returning from Khaibar he traveled during the night until
he became sleepy and he sat down to rest. Then he said: 'O Bilal!
Stand guard for us for the night.'" He said: 'So Bilal performed
Salat, then he leaned against his mount facing the direction of
(dawn awaiting) Fajr. His eyes overcame him until he slept, and not
one of them awoke. The first of them to awaken was the Prophet (ﷺ)
who said: 'O Bilal!' Bilal said: 'May my father be ransomed for you
O Messenger of Allah! I was overtaken just as you were overtaken.'
So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'Move out!' Then he kneeled to
perform Wudu and to announce the standing for the Salat, then he
performed Salat the same as he would when not traveling. Then he
said: 'And establish the Salat for My rememberance
(20:14).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
