<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33373</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3464</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30277, 20032, 20298, 20547, 20020, 11655, 11050,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمود بن غيلان، حدثنا وكيع، ووهب بن جرير، وأبو
داود قالوا حدثنا شعبة، عن المغيرة بن النعمان، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن
ابن عباس، قال قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالموعظة فقال ‏"‏ يا
أيها الناس إنكم محشورون إلى الله عراة غرلا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قرأ ‏:‏ ‏(‏
كما بدأنا أول خلق نعيده وعدا علينا ‏)‏ إلى آخر الآية قال ‏"‏ أول من
يكسى يوم القيامة إبراهيم وإنه سيؤتى برجال من أمتي فيؤخذ بهم ذات
الشمال فأقول رب أصحابي ‏.‏ فيقال إنك لا تدري ما أحدثوا بعدك ‏.‏
فأقول كما قال العبد الصالح ‏(‏ وكنت عليهم شهيدا ما دمت فيهم فلما
توفيتني كنت أنت الرقيب عليهم وأنت على كل شيء شهيد * إن تعذبهم فإنهم
عبادك وإن تغفر لهم فإنك أنت العزيز الحكيم ‏)‏ فيقال هؤلاء لم يزالوا
مرتدين على أعقابهم منذ فارقتهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
stood to deliver a Khutbah, he said: 'O you people! You will be
gathered before Allah naked and uncircumcised.' Then he recited:
'As We began the first creation, We shall repeat it...' until the
end of the Ayah (21:104). He said: 'The first to be clothed on the
Day of Resurrection is Ibrahim. Indeed some men from my Ummah will
be brought and taken from the left side, so I will say: "My Lord!
My followers!" It will be said: "Indeed you do not know what they
innovated after you.' So I shall say as the righteous slave said:
'And I was a witness over them while I dwelt among them, but when
You took me up, You were the Watcher over them. If You punish them,
they are your slaves, and if You forgive them...' [until the end
of] the Ayah (5:117 &amp; 118) I shall be told: 'These people have
not ceased turning on their heels as apostates ever since you
parted from them.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
