<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33376</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3467</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20031, 11019, 11016, 123</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، حدثنا هشام بن
أبي عبد الله، عن قتادة، عن الحسن، عن عمران بن حصين، قال كنا مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في سفر فتفاوت بين أصحابه في السير فرفع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صوته بهاتين الآيتين أيها الناس اتقوا
ربكم إن زلزلة الساعة شيء عظيم ‏)‏ إلى قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ إن عذاب الله
شديد ‏)‏ فلما سمع ذلك أصحابه حثوا المطي وعرفوا أنه عند قول يقوله
فقال ‏"‏ هل تدرون أى يوم ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ ذاك يوم ينادي الله فيه آدم فيناديه ربه فيقول يا آدم ابعث بعث
النار ‏.‏ فيقول يا رب وما بعث النار فيقول من كل ألف تسعمائة وتسعة
وتسعون إلى النار وواحد في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فيئس القوم حتى ما أبدوا
بضاحكة فلما رأى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الذي بأصحابه قال ‏"‏
اعملوا وأبشروا فوالذي نفس محمد بيده إنكم لمع خليقتين ما كانتا مع
شيء إلا كثرتاه يأجوج ومأجوج ومن مات من بني آدم وبني إبليس ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال فسري عن القوم بعض الذي يجدون ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اعملوا وأبشروا فوالذي
نفس محمد بيده ما أنتم في الناس إلا كالشامة في جنب البعير أو كالرقمة
في ذراع الدابة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Imran bin Husain: "We were with the Prophet
(ﷺ) on a journey when some of his Companions fell behind. So the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) raised his voice reciting these two Ayat: "O
mankind! Have Taqwa of your Lord! Verily the earthquake of the hour
is a terrible thing..." up to His saying: but Allah's torment is
severe (21:1 &amp; 2)." When his Companions heard that, they
hastened to catch up with him, since they knew that he had
something to say. He (ﷺ) said: 'Do you know what Day this is? That
is the Day when Adam will be called. His Lord will call him and
say: O Adam, send forth those who are to be sent to the Fire. He
will say: O Lord! How many are to be sent to the Fire? He will say:
From every one-thousand there are nine-hundred and ninety-nine for
the Fire and one for Paradise. So the people despaired as if they
would not smile again. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) saw the
state of his Companions, he said: 'Strive hard and receive the good
news. By the One in Whose Hand is the soul of Muhammad, you will be
counted with two creations who are immense in numbers; Ya'juj and
Ma'juj, and those who have died among the progeny of Adam and the
progeny of Iblis.'" He said: "So some of the people's grief went
away, and he (ﷺ) said: 'Strive hard and receive the good news. By
the One in Whose Hand is the soul of Muhammad! Among mankind, you
are but like the mole on the flank of a camel, or a mark on the
foreleg of a beast.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
