<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33375</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3466</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20005, 11016, 123</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، حدثنا سفيان بن عيينة، عن ابن جدعان،
عن الحسن، عن عمران بن حصين، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لما نزلت
‏:‏ ‏(‏ يا أيها الناس اتقوا ربكم إن زلزلة الساعة شيء عظيم ‏)‏ إلى
قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ولكن عذاب الله شديد ‏)‏ قال أنزلت عليه هذه وهو في سفر
فقال ‏"‏ أتدرون أى يوم ذلك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ ذلك يوم يقول الله لآدم ابعث بعث النار فقال يا رب وما بعث النار
قال تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعون إلى النار وواحد إلى الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فأنشأ المسلمون يبكون فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قاربوا
وسددوا فإنها لم تكن نبوة قط إلا كان بين يديها جاهلية قال فيؤخذ
العدد من الجاهلية فإن تمت وإلا كملت من المنافقين وما مثلكم والأمم
إلا كمثل الرقمة في ذراع الدابة أو كالشامة في جنب البعير ثم قال إني
لأرجو أن تكونوا ربع أهل الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكبروا ثم قال ‏"‏ إني لأرجو
أن تكونوا ثلث أهل الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكبروا ثم قال ‏"‏ إني لأرجو أن
تكونوا نصف أهل الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكبروا قال ولا أدري قال الثلثين أم لا
‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن صحيح وقد روي من غير وجه عن عمران بن حصين عن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Imran bin Husain: when (the following) was
revealed: "O mankind! Have Taqwa of your Lord! Verily the
earthquake of the hour is a terrible thing..." up to His saying:
"But Allah's torment is severe...(22:1 &amp; 2)" - he said: "These
Ayat were revealed while he (ﷺ) was on a journey and he said: 'Do
you know what Day this is?' So they said: 'Allah and His Messenger
know better.' He said: 'That is the day when Allah says to Adam:
Send forth those who are to be sent to the Fire. So he says: O
Lord! How many are to be sent? He says: Nine-hundred and
ninety-nine in the Fire, and one to Paradise. He said: "So the
Muslims started crying. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
'Close your ranks and be straight forward, for there was never any
Prophethood but there was a time of ignorance just before his
advent, so the number will be taken from that time of ignorance,
and if that is not enough, it will be made up of the hypocrites.
The parable of you and the other nations is that you are like a
mark on the foreleg of an animal, or a mole on the flank of a
camel.' Then he said: 'I hope that you will be a quarter of the
people of Paradise.' They said: Allahu Akbar. Then he said: 'I hope
that you will be a third of the people of Paradise.' They said:
Allahu Akbar. Then he said: 'I hope that you will be half of the
people of Paradise.' They said: Allahu Akbar." He said: "I do not
know if he said two thirds or not."</english-text>
</hadith>
