<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33396</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3487</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 30464, 20445, 11368, 579, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثنا زكريا بن عدي، حدثنا عبيد الله
بن عمرو الرقي، عن عبد الملك بن عمير، عن موسى بن طلحة، عن أبي هريرة،
قال لما نزلت ‏:‏ ‏(‏ وأنذر عشيرتك الأقربين ‏)‏ جمع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قريشا فخص وعم فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر قريش أنقذوا أنفسكم من
النار فإني لا أملك لكم من الله ضرا ولا نفعا يا معشر بني عبد مناف
أنقذوا أنفسكم من النار فإني لا أملك لكم من الله ضرا ولا نفعا يا
معشر بني قصى أنقذوا أنفسكم من النار فإني لا أملك لكم ضرا ولا نفعا
يا معشر بني عبد المطلب أنقذوا أنفسكم من النار فإني لا أملك لكم ضرا
ولا نفعا يا فاطمة بنت محمد أنقذي نفسك من النار فإني لا أملك لك ضرا
ولا نفعا إن لك رحما سأبلها ببلالها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
حسن صحيح غريب من هذا الوجه يعرف من حديث موسى بن طلحة
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Hurairah: "When (the following) was
revealed: 'And warn your tribe of near kindred (26:214)' the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gathered the (families) of the Quraish
(calling them) one and all, he said: 'O people of the Quraish!
Ransom yourselves from the Fire! I have no power to prevent harm or
bring benefit to you before Allah! O people of Banu 'Abd Manaf!
Ransom yourselves from the Fire! I have no power to prevent harm or
bring benefit to you before Allah! O people of Banu Qusayy! Ransom
yourselves from the Fire! I have no power to prevent harm or bring
benefit to you! O people of Banu 'Abdul-Muttalib! Ransom yourselves
from the Fire! I have no power to prevent harm or bring benefit to
you! O Fatimah bint Muhammad! Ransom yourself from the Fire! I have
no power to prevent harm or bring benefit to you before Allah! All
you have is the womb, and the kind relations that shall come of
it."</english-text>
</hadith>
