<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33411</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3502</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20005, 11395, 11368, 10792, 11052</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، حدثنا سفيان، عن مطرف بن طريف، وعبد
الملك، وهو ابن أبجر سمعا الشعبي، يقول سمعت المغيرة بن شعبة، على
المنبر يرفعه إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إن موسى عليه
السلام سأل ربه فقال أى رب أى أهل الجنة أدنى منزلة قال رجل يأتي بعد
ما يدخل أهل الجنة الجنة فيقال له ادخل الجنة ‏.‏ فيقول كيف أدخل وقد
نزلوا منازلهم وأخذوا أخذاتهم ‏.‏ قال فيقال له أترضى أن يكون لك ما
كان لملك من ملوك الدنيا فيقول نعم أى رب قد رضيت ‏.‏ فيقال له فإن لك
هذا ومثله ومثله ومثله فيقول رضيت أى رب ‏.‏ فيقال له فإن لك هذا
وعشرة أمثاله فيقول رضيت أى رب ‏.‏ فيقال له فإن لك مع هذا ما اشتهت
نفسك ولذت عينك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وروى
بعضهم هذا الحديث عن الشعبي عن المغيرة ولم يرفعه والمرفوع أصح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ash-Sha'bi: "While he was on the Minbar, I
heard Al-Mughirah bin Shu'bah saying - and he attributed it to the
Prophet (ﷺ) - 'Indeed Musa [peace be upon him] asked his Lord: "O
Lord! Who is the lowest in rank among the people of Paradise?" He
said: "A man who comes after the people of Paradise have been
admitted to Paradise, and he is told to enter. He says: 'How can I
enter when they have gotten all of their abodes, and all that is to
be had?'" He said: "So it is said to him: 'Would you accept if you
were to have what a king in the world?' He says: 'Yes, O Lord! I
accept.' So it is said to him: 'Then for you is this and its like,
and its like again, and its like again.' So he says: 'I accept, O
Lord!' So it is said to him: 'Then for you is this and ten the like
thereof.' So he says: 'I accept, O Lord!' So it is said: 'Indeed
you shall have this, and whatever your soul desires, and whatever
delights your eyes.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
