<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33406</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3497</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30325, 20389, 20405, 20012, 14069, 11050</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسين بن حريث، حدثنا معاوية بن عمرو، عن أبي
إسحاق الفزاري، عن سفيان الثوري، عن حبيب بن أبي عمرة، عن سعيد بن
جبير، عن ابن عباس، في قول الله تعالى ‏:‏ ‏(‏ الم * غلبت الروم * في
أدنى الأرض ‏)‏ قال غلبت وغلبت كان المشركون يحبون أن يظهر أهل فارس
على الروم لأنهم وإياهم أهل أوثان وكان المسلمون يحبون أن يظهر الروم
على فارس لأنهم أهل كتاب فذكروه لأبي بكر فذكره أبو بكر لرسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أما إنهم سيغلبون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذكره أبو بكر
لهم فقالوا اجعل بيننا وبينك أجلا فإن ظهرنا كان لنا كذا وكذا وإن
ظهرتم كان لكم كذا وكذا فجعل أجل خمس سنين فلم يظهروا فذكروا ذلك
للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ألا جعلته إلى دون - قال أراه
العشر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سعيد والبضع ما دون العشر قال ثم ظهرت الروم بعد
‏.‏ قال فذلك قوله تعالى ‏:‏ ‏(‏ الم * غلبت الروم ‏)‏ إلى قوله ‏:‏
‏(‏يفرح المؤمنون * بنصر الله ينصر من يشاء ‏)‏ قال سفيان سمعت أنهم
ظهروا عليهم يوم بدر ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح غريب إنما
نعرفه من حديث سفيان الثوري عن حبيب بن أبي عمرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa'eed bin Jubair: from Ibn 'Abbas,
regarding the saying of Allah, Most High: Alif Lam Mim. The Romans
have been defeated. In the nearest land (30:1-3)" he said:
"Ghulibat wa Ghalabat (defeated and then victorious)." He said:
"The idolaters wanted the Persians to be victorious over the Romans
because they too were people who worshiped idols, while the Muslims
wanted the Romans to be victorious over the Persians because they
were people of the Book. This was mentioned to Abu Bakr, so Abu
Bakr mentioned that to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and he said:
'They will certainly prevail.' Abu Bakr mentioned that to them, and
they said: 'Make a wager between us and you; if we win, we shall
get this and that, and if you win, you shall get this or that.' He
made the term five years, but they (the Romans) were not
victorious. They mentioned that to the Prophet (ﷺ) and he said:
"Why did you not make it less (than)" - He (one of the narrators
said): I think he said: "ten?" He said: Sa'eed said: "Al-Bid' is
what is less than then" - he said: "Afterwards the Romans have been
victorious." He said: "That is what Allah Most High said: 'Alif Lam
Mim. The Romans have been defeated' up to His saying: 'And on the
day, the believers will rejoice - with the help of Allah. He helps
whom He wills (30:1-5).' Sufyan said: "I heard that they were
victorious over them on the Day of Badr."</english-text>
</hadith>
