<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33414</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3505</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30304, 20025, 20236, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن محمد، حدثنا عبد الله بن المبارك، أخبرنا
سليمان بن المغيرة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، قال قال عمي أنس بن النضر سميت
به لم يشهد بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فكبر عليه فقال أول
مشهد شهده رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غبت عنه أما والله لئن أراني
الله مشهدا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليرين الله ما أصنع ‏.‏
قال فهاب أن يقول غيرها فشهد مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم أحد
من العام القابل فاستقبله سعد بن معاذ فقال يا أبا عمرو أين قال واها
لريح الجنة أجدها دون أحد فقاتل حتى قتل فوجد في جسده بضع وثمانون من
بين ضربة وطعنة ورمية فقالت عمتي الربيع بنت النضر فما عرفت أخي إلا
ببنانه ‏.‏ ونزلت هذه الآية ‏:‏ ‏(‏رجال صدقوا ما عاهدوا الله عليه
فمنهم من قضى نحبه ومنهم من ينتظر وما بدلوا تبديلا ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو
عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: "My paternal uncle Anas bin An-Nadr -
after whom I was named - did not participate in the battle of Badr
with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). This distressed him and he said:
'I was absent from the first battle which the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) attended. By Allah! If Allah gives me the opportunity to
participate in another battle along with the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ), then Allah will see what I will do!'" He said: "He did not
want to say more than that. A year later, he attended the battle of
Uhud, where he saw Sa'd bin Mu'adh and said: 'O Abu 'Amr where are
you going?' He said: 'I long for the fragrance of Paradise and I
have found it near the mountains of Uhud.' He fought them until he
was killed. They found more than eighty wounds on his body, be they
from blows of a sword, puncture wounds, or arrows. My paternal aunt
Ar-Ruba'i bin An-Nadr said: 'I could not recognize my brother
except by his finger tips.' And this Ayah was revealed: 'Among the
believers are men who have been true to their covenant with Allah;
of them some have fulfilled their vow, and some of them are still
waiting, but they have never changed in the least
(33:23).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
