<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33430</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3521</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 20229, 18598, 11044, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثنا روح، عن عبد الحميد بن بهرام،
عن شهر بن حوشب، قال قال ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما نهي رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم عن أصناف النساء إلا ما كان من المؤمنات المهاجرات قال
‏:‏ ‏(‏ لا يحل لك النساء من بعد ولا أن تبدل بهن من أزواج ولو أعجبك
حسنهن إلا ما ملكت يمينك ‏)‏ فأحل الله فتياتكم المؤمنات وامرأة مؤمنة
إن وهبت نفسها للنبي وحرم كل ذات دين غير الإسلام ثم قال ‏:‏ ‏(‏ومن
يكفر بالإيمان فقد حبط عمله وهو في الآخرة من الخاسرين ‏)‏ وقال ‏:‏
‏(‏ يا أيها النبي إنا أحللنا لك أزواجك اللاتي آتيت أجورهن وما ملكت
يمينك مما أفاء الله عليك ‏)‏ إلى قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ خالصة لك من دون
المؤمنين ‏)‏ وحرم ما سوى ذلك من أصناف النساء ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا
حديث حسن إنما نعرفه من حديث عبد الحميد بن بهرام ‏.‏ قال سمعت أحمد
بن الحسن يقول قال أحمد بن حنبل لا بأس بحديث عبد الحميد بن بهرام عن
شهر بن حوشب ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: "All types of women were
prohibited for the Messenger of ALlah (ﷺ) except for the believing
women among those who emigrated. (Allah) said: 'It is not lawful
for you (to marry other) women after this, nor to change them for
other wives even though their beauty attracts you, except those
whom your right hand possesses (33:52). - And Allah made your
believing girls lawful 'And a believing woman if she offers herself
to the Prophet (33:50)' and He made every woman of a religion other
than Islam unlawful." Then He said: "And whoever disbelieves in
faith then fruitless is his work; and in the Hereafter he will be
among the losers (5:5)." And he said: "Verily We have made lawful
to you your wives, to whom you have paid their due, and those whom
your right hands possess - whom Allah has given you" up to His
saying: "A privilege to only you, not for the (rest of) the
believers (33:50)." He made the other types of women
unlawful."</english-text>
</hadith>
