<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33439</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3530</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20246, 20115, 11013, 11045, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي الجهضمي، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، حدثنا
معمر، عن الزهري، عن علي بن حسين، عن ابن عباس، قال بينما رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم جالس في نفر من أصحابه إذ رمي بنجم فاستنار فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما كنتم تقولون لمثل هذا في
الجاهلية إذا رأيتموه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا كنا نقول يموت عظيم أو يولد عظيم
‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فإنه لا يرمى به لموت أحد
ولا لحياته ولكن ربنا عز وجل إذا قضى أمرا سبح له حملة العرش ثم سبح
أهل السماء الذين يلونهم ثم الذين يلونهم حتى يبلغ التسبيح إلى هذه
السماء ثم سأل أهل السماء السادسة أهل السماء السابعة ماذا قال ربكم
قال فيخبرونهم ثم يستخبر أهل كل سماء حتى يبلغ الخبر أهل السماء
الدنيا وتختطف الشياطين السمع فيرمون فيقذفونها إلى أوليائهم فما
جاءوا به على وجهه فهو حق ولكنهم يحرفون ويزيدون ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى
هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: "We were with the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ), while he was sitting with a group of his Companions,
when they saw a glowing shooting star. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'When you saw the likes of this during Jahiliyyah, what would
you say about it?' They said: 'We would say that a great man died,
or that a great man has been born.' The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'It is not shot due to the death of anyone, nor his coming
into life. Rather when our Lord [Blessed is His Name and Most High]
decrees a matter, He is glorified by the bearers of the Throne.
Then He is glorified by the inhabitants who are below them, then
those below them, until such glorification reaches this Heaven.
Then the inhabitants of the sixth Heaven ask the inhabitants of the
seventh Heaven: "What did your Lord say?" He said: 'So they inform
them; then the inhabitants of each Heaven seek the information,
until the news is conveyed to the inhabitants of the Heavens of the
earth. The Shayatin try to overhear so they are shot at, so they
cast it down to their friends. Whatever they came with is true, as
it is, but they distort it and add to it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
