<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33450</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3541</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30417, 30553, 20121, 20115, 11015, 11047,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سلمة بن شبيب، وعبد بن حميد، قالا حدثنا عبد
الرزاق، عن معمر، عن أيوب، عن أبي قلابة، عن ابن عباس، قال قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أتاني الليلة ربي تبارك وتعالى في أحسن
صورة قال أحسبه قال في المنام فقال يا محمد هل تدري فيم يختصم الملأ
الأعلى قال قلت لا ‏.‏ قال فوضع يده بين كتفى حتى وجدت بردها بين ثديى
أو قال في نحري فعلمت ما في السموات وما في الأرض قال يا محمد هل تدري
فيم يختصم الملأ الأعلى قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال في الكفارات ‏.‏ والكفارات
المكث في المساجد بعد الصلوات والمشى على الأقدام إلى الجماعات وإسباغ
الوضوء في المكاره ومن فعل ذلك عاش بخير ومات بخير وكان من خطيئته
كيوم ولدته أمه وقال يا محمد إذا صليت فقل اللهم إني أسألك فعل
الخيرات وترك المنكرات وحب المساكين وإذا أردت بعبادك فتنة فاقبضني
إليك غير مفتون قال والدرجات إفشاء السلام وإطعام الطعام والصلاة
بالليل والناس نيام ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Qilabah: from Ibn 'Abbas that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: "During the night, my Lord, Blessed is
He, and Most High, came to me in the best of appearances." He (one
of the narrators) said - I think he said it was during a dream -
"So he said: 'O Muhammad! Do you know in what the most exalted
group busy themselves with?'" He said: "I said: 'No.'" He said: "So
He placed His Hand between my shoulders, until I sensed its
coolness between my breast." - or he said: "on my throat, so I knew
what was in the heavens, and what was in the earth. He said: 'O
Muhammad! Do you know in what the most exalted group busy
themselves with?' I said: 'Yes, in the acts that atone: and the
acts that atone are; lingering in the Masjid after the Salat,
walking on the feet to the congregation, Isbagh Al-Wudu, in
difficulty, and whoever does that, he lives in goodness and dies
upon goodness, and his wrongs shall be like that of the day his
mother bore him.' He said: 'O Muhammad! When you have performed
Salat then say: 'O Allah! Indeed I ask of You, the doing of good
deeds, avoiding the evil deeds, and loving the poor. And when you
have willed Fitnah for your slave, then take me to You, without
making me suffer from Fitnah.'" He [the Prophet (ﷺ)] said: "And the
acts that raise ranks are spreading the Salam, feeding others, and
Salat during the night, while the people are
sleeping."</english-text>
</hadith>
