<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33451</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3542</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20287, 20295, 11019, 11047, 18248,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا معاذ بن هشام، حدثني أبي، عن
قتادة، عن أبي قلابة، عن خالد بن اللجلاج، عن ابن عباس، عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أتاني ربي في أحسن صورة فقال يا محمد قلت لبيك
ربي وسعديك قال فيم يختصم الملأ الأعلى قلت ربي لا أدري فوضع يده بين
كتفى فوجدت بردها بين ثديى فعلمت ما بين المشرق والمغرب قال يا محمد
‏.‏ فقلت لبيك رب وسعديك قال فيم يختصم الملأ الأعلى قلت في الدرجات
والكفارات وفي نقل الأقدام إلى الجماعات وإسباغ الوضوء في المكروهات
وانتظار الصلاة بعد الصلاة ومن يحافظ عليهن عاش بخير ومات بخير وكان
من ذنوبه كيوم ولدته أمه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن غريب من هذا الوجه
‏.‏ قال وفي الباب عن معاذ بن جبل وعبد الرحمن بن عائش عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: that the Prophet (ﷺ) said: "My
Lord, Blessed is He and Most High, came to me in the best of
appearances. So he said: 'O Muhammad!' I said: 'Here I am O my
Lord! And I am at Your service.' He said: 'What is it that the most
exalted group busy themselves with?' I said: '[Lord] I do not
know.' So He placed His Hand between my shoulders, until I sensed
its coolness between my breast, so I knew what was in between the
east and the west. He said: 'O Muhammad!' I said: 'Here I am O my
Lord! And I am at Your service.' He said: 'What is it that the most
exalted group busy themselves with?' I said: 'In the acts that
raise ranks and the acts that atone, and in recording the footsteps
to the congregation, Isbagh Al-Wudu in difficulties, and awaiting
the Salat after the Salat. And whoever preserves them, he shall
live in goodness and die upon goodness, and his sins shall be like
that on the day upon which his mother bore him.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
