<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33448</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3539</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30277, 30553, 20355, 20012, 11060, 11449, 11050,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمود بن غيلان، وعبد بن حميد، - المعنى واحد قالا
حدثنا أبو أحمد، حدثنا سفيان، عن الأعمش، عن يحيى، قال عبد هو ابن
عباد عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس، قال مرض أبو طالب فجاءته قريش
وجاءه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وعند أبي طالب مجلس رجل فقام أبو جهل
كى يمنعه وشكوه إلى أبي طالب فقال يا ابن أخي ما تريد من قومك قال ‏"‏
إني أريد منهم كلمة واحدة تدين لهم بها العرب وتؤدي إليهم العجم
الجزية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كلمة واحدة قال ‏"‏ كلمة واحدة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ يا
عم قولوا لا إله إلا الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا‏:‏ إلها واحدا‏؟‏ ‏(‏ ما
سمعنا بهذا في الملة الآخرة إن هذا إلا اختلاق ‏)‏ قال فنزل فيهم
القرآن ‏:‏ ‏(‏ص* والقرآن ذي الذكر * بل الذين كفروا في عزة وشقاق ‏)‏
إلى قوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ما سمعنا بهذا في الملة الآخرة إن هذا إلا اختلاق ‏)‏
‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Abbas: "Abu Talib fell ill, so the
Quraish went to see him, and the Prophet (ﷺ) went to see him. There
was a gathering there with Abu Talib, so Abu Jahl stood up enraged,
to prevent him (the Prophet (ﷺ) from entering)." He said: "He
complained to Abu Talib. So he (Abu Talib) said: 'O my nephew! What
is it that you want from your people?' He said: 'I only want one
word from them, for which, if they were to say it, then the Arabs
will become their followers, and the non-Arabs will pay Jizyah to
them.' He said: 'One word?' He replied: 'One word.' So he said: 'O
uncle! Let them say La Ilaha Illallah' so they replied: 'One God?
We have not heard (the like) of this in the religion of these later
days. This is nothing but an invention.'" He said: "So the
(following) was revealed in the Qur'an about them: 'Sad. By the
Qur'an full of reminding. Those who disbelieve are in false pride
and opposition...' up to His saying: 'We have not heard (the like)
of this in the religion of these later days. This is nothing but an
invention (38:1-7).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
