<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33470</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3561</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 20267</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثنا عمرو بن عاصم، حدثنا عبيد الله
بن الوازع، حدثني شيخ، من بني مرة قال قدمت الكوفة فأخبرت عن بلال بن
أبي بردة، فقلت إن فيه لمعتبرا فأتيته وهو محبوس في داره التي قد كان
بنى قال وإذا كل شيء منه قد تغير من العذاب والضرب وإذا هو في قشاش
فقلت الحمد لله يا بلال لقد رأيتك وأنت تمر بنا تمسك بأنفك من غير
غبار وأنت في حالك هذا اليوم فقال ممن أنت فقلت من بني مرة بن عباد
‏.‏ فقال ألا أحدثك حديثا عسى الله أن ينفعك به قلت هات ‏.‏ قال حدثني
أبي أبو بردة عن أبيه أبي موسى أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ لا يصيب عبدا نكبة فما فوقها أو دونها إلا بذنب وما يعفو الله عنه
أكثر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وقرأ ‏:‏ ‏(‏وما أصابكم من مصيبة فبما كسبت أيديكم
ويعفو عن كثير ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث غريب لا نعرفه إلا من
هذا الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah bin Al-Wazi': "A Shaikh from
Banu Murrah narrated to me, he said: 'I arrived in Al-Kufah and was
informed about Bilal bin Abi Burdah so I said: "Indeed there is a
lesson in him" so I went to him while he was imprisoned in his
home, which he had built.' He said: 'After everything that had
happened to him he had changed due to the punishment and the
beatings, and now he was living in isolation. So I said: "All
praise is due to Allah O Bilal! I have seen you passing you by us
holding your nose, and it was not from the dust! And today you are
in this state.' So he said: 'Where are you from?' I said: 'From
Banu Murrah bin 'Abbad.' So he said: 'Shall I not narrate a Hadith
to you, perhaps Allah will benefit you by it?' I said: 'Go ahead.'
He said: 'My father, Abu Burdah narrated from his father Abu Musa,
that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: "No worshiper suffers a
calamity nor what is worse than that or less, except due to a sin,
and what Allah pardons as a result of it is more." He (Abu Musa)
said: "And he recited: And whatever misfortune befalls you, it is
because of what your hands have earned (42:30)."</english-text>
</hadith>
