<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33472</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3563</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30277, 20196, 20020, 11060, 11067, 11392,
11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمود بن غيلان، حدثنا عبد الملك بن إبراهيم
الجدي، حدثنا شعبة، عن الأعمش، ومنصور، سمعا أبا الضحى، يحدث عن
مسروق، قال جاء رجل إلى عبد الله فقال إن قاصا يقص يقول إنه يخرج من
الأرض الدخان فيأخذ بمسامع الكفار ويأخذ المؤمن كهيئة الزكام قال فغضب
وكان متكئا فجلس ثم قال إذا سئل أحدكم عما يعلم فليقل به قال منصور
فليخبر به وإذا سئل عما لا يعلم فليقل الله أعلم فإن من علم الرجل إذا
سئل عما لا يعلم أن يقول الله أعلم فإن الله تعالى قال لنبيه ‏:‏
‏(‏قل ما أسألكم عليه من أجر وما أنا من المتكلفين ‏)‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ إن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لما رأى قريشا استعصوا عليه قال ‏"‏
اللهم أعني عليهم بسبع كسبع يوسف ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأخذتهم سنة فأحصت كل شيء
حتى أكلوا الجلود والميتة وقال أحدهما العظام قال وجعل يخرج من الأرض
كهيئة الدخان قال فأتاه أبو سفيان قال إن قومك قد هلكوا فادع الله لهم
‏.‏ قال فهذا لقوله ‏:‏ ‏(‏ يوم تأتي السماء بدخان مبين * يغشى الناس
هذا عذاب أليم ‏)‏ ‏.‏ قال منصور هذا لقوله ‏(‏ ربنا اكشف عنا العذاب
إنا مؤمنون ‏)‏ فهل يكشف عذاب الآخرة قال مضى البطشة واللزام الدخان
وقال أحدهما القمر وقال الآخر الروم ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى واللزام يعني
يوم بدر ‏.‏ قال وهذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Masruq: "A man came to 'Abdullah and said:
'A story teller has said that a smoke will appear from the earth,
taking the hearing of disbelievers and manifesting as a cold for
the believers.'" He became angry, and since he was reclining, he
sat up then said: 'When one of you is asked about something he
knows, then let him speak accordingly' - Mansur (one of the
narrators) narrated it as: "Then let him inform of it" - "And when
asked about what he does not know, then let him say: "Allah knows
best." For indeed, it is part of a man's knowledge, that when he is
asked about something he does not know, he says: "Allah knows
best." For verily Allah, Most High said to His Prophet: Say: "No
wage do I ask of you for this, nor am I one of the pretenders
(38:86)." When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) saw that the Quraish were
behaving stubbornly with him, he said: "O Allah! Assist me against
them with seven (years of famine) like the seven of Yusuf." So He
punished them with drought making everything barren, until they ate
skins and carcasses" - one of them said: "bones." He said: 'And it
appeared that smoke was coming out of the earth. So Abu Sufyan came
to him and said: "Verily your people are being destroyed, so
supplicate to Allah for them." He said: "So this is about His
saying: 'The Day when the sky will bring forth a visible smoke,
covering the people, this is a painful torment (44:10 &amp; 11).'"
Mansur narrated it as: "So this is about His saying: Our Lord!
Remove the torment from us, really we shall become believers
(44:12)." - "So shall the punishment be removed from them in the
Hereafter? Al-Batshah (humiliated defeat in Badr), Al-Lizam
(disbeliever captives from Badr), the smoke," - one of them said:
"The moon" the other said: "The Romans have all
passed."</english-text>
</hadith>
