<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33498</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3589</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20005, 10820, 11052</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، حدثنا سفيان، عن مجالد، عن الشعبي،
قال لقي ابن عباس كعبا بعرفة فسأله عن شيء، فكبر حتى جاوبته الجبال
فقال ابن عباس إنا بنو هاشم ‏.‏ فقال كعب إن الله قسم رؤيته وكلامه
بين محمد وموسى فكلم موسى مرتين ورآه محمد مرتين ‏.‏ قال مسروق فدخلت
على عائشة فقلت هل رأى محمد ربه فقالت لقد تكلمت بشيء قف له شعري قلت
رويدا ثم قرأت ‏:‏ ‏(‏لقد رأى من آيات ربه الكبرى ‏)‏ قالت أين يذهب
بك إنما هو جبريل من أخبرك أن محمدا رأى ربه أو كتم شيئا مما أمر به
أو يعلم الخمس التي قال الله تعالى ‏:‏ ‏(‏ إن الله عنده علم الساعة
وينزل الغيث ‏)‏ فقد أعظم الفرية ولكنه رأى جبريل لم يره في صورته إلا
مرتين مرة عند سدرة المنتهى ومرة في جياد له ستمائة جناح قد سد الأفق
‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وقد روى داود بن أبي هند عن الشعبي عن مسروق عن
عائشة عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم نحو هذا الحديث وحديث داود أقصر من
حديث مجالد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ash-Sha'bi: "Ibn 'Abbas met Ka'b at Arafat,
so he asked him about something and he kept on saying the Takbir
until it reverberated off of the mountains. So Ibn 'Abbas (finally)
said: 'We are Banu Hashim.' So Ka'b said: 'Indeed Allah divided His
being seen and His speaking between Muhammad and Musa. He spoke to
Musa two times, and Muhammad saw Him two times.' Masruq said: 'I
entered upon 'Aishah and asked her if Muhammad saw his Lord.' She
said: 'You have said something that makes my hair stand on end.' I
said: 'Take it easy.' Then I recited: Indeed he saw of the great
signs of his Lord (53:18). So she said: 'What do you mean by that?
That is only Jibra'il. Whoever informed you that Muhammad saw his
Lord, or that (ﷺ) concealed something he was ordered with, or he
knew of the five things about which Allah, [Most High] said: Verily
Allah, with Him is the knowledge of the Hour, He sends down the
rain (31:34) - then he has fabricated the worst lie. Rather he (ﷺ)
saw Jibra'il, but he did not see him in his (real) image except two
times. One time at Sidrat Al-Muntaha and one time in Jiyad, he had
six-hundred wings which filled the horizon.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
