<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33540</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3631</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20005, 11081, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، حدثنا سفيان، عن عمرو بن دينار، سمع
جابر بن عبد الله، يقول كنا في غزاة قال سفيان يرون أنها غزوة بني
المصطلق فكسع رجل من المهاجرين رجلا من الأنصار فقال المهاجري يا
للمهاجرين وقال الأنصاري يا للأنصار فسمع ذلك النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ما بال دعوى الجاهلية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا رجل من المهاجرين
كسع رجلا من الأنصار فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ دعوها
فإنها منتنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فسمع ذلك عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول فقال أوقد
فعلوها والله ‏(‏لئن رجعنا إلى المدينة ليخرجن الأعز منها الأذل ‏)‏
فقال عمر يا رسول الله دعني أضرب عنق هذا المنافق ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ دعه لا يتحدث الناس أن محمدا يقتل أصحابه ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وقال غير عمرو فقال له ابنه عبد الله بن عبد الله والله لا تنقلب حتى
تقر أنك الذليل ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم العزيز ‏.‏ ففعل ‏.‏
قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sufyan narrated from Amr bin Dinar that he heard
Jabir bin Abdullah sayin: “We were in a battle” – Sufyan said:
“They say in was the battle of Banu Mustaliq” – “Aman from the
Muhajirin kicked a man from the Ansar. The man from the Muhajirin
said: ‘O Muhajirin!’ the man from the Ansar said: ‘O Ansar!’ The
Prophet heard that and said: ‘What is this evil call of Jahliyyah?’
They said: ‘A man from the Muhajirin kicked a man from the Ansar.’
So the Prophet said: ‘Leave that, for it is offensive.’ Abdullah
bin Ubayy bin Salul heard that and said: ‘Did they really do that?
By Allah! If we return to Al-Madinah indeed the more honorable will
expel therefrom the meaner.’ Umar said: ‘Allow me to chop off the
head of this hypocrite O Messenger of Allah!’ The Prophet said:
‘Leave him, I do not want the people to say that Muhammad kills his
Companios.’” Someone other than Amr said: “So his son, Abdullah bin
Abdullah, said: ‘By Allah! You shall not return until you say that
you are the mean and that the Messenger of Allah is the honorable.’
So he did so.”</english-text>
</hadith>
