<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33550</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3641</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30553, 20296, 20469, 11419, 11050, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد بن حميد، حدثني أبو الوليد، حدثنا أبو عوانة،
عن أبي بشر، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس، رضى الله عنهما قال ما قرأ
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على الجن ولا رآهم انطلق رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم في طائفة من أصحابه عامدين إلى سوق عكاظ وقد حيل بين
الشياطين وبين خبر السماء وأرسلت عليهم الشهب فرجعت الشياطين إلى
قومهم فقالوا ما لكم قالوا حيل بيننا وبين خبر السماء وأرسلت علينا
الشهب ‏.‏ فقالوا ما حال بيننا وبين خبر السماء إلا من أمر حدث
فاضربوا مشارق الأرض ومغاربها فانظروا ما هذا الذي حال بينكم وبين خبر
السماء قال فانطلقوا يضربون مشارق الأرض ومغاربها يبتغون ما هذا الذي
حال بينهم وبين خبر السماء فانصرف أولئك النفر الذين توجهوا إلى نحو
تهامة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو بنخلة عامدا إلى سوق عكاظ
وهو يصلي بأصحابه صلاة الفجر فلما سمعوا القرآن استمعوا له فقالوا هذا
والله الذي حال بينكم وبين خبر السماء ‏.‏ قال فهنالك رجعوا إلى قومهم
فقالوا يا قومنا ‏:‏ ‏(‏ إنا سمعنا قرآنا عجبا * يهدي إلى الرشد فآمنا
به ولن نشرك بربنا أحدا ‏)‏ فأنزل الله على نبيه ‏:‏ ‏(‏ قل أوحي إلى
أنه استمع ‏)‏ وإنما أوحي إليه قول الجن ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Abbas [may Allah be pleased with them] said: the
Messenger of Allah did not recite for the jinns nor did he see
them. The Messenger of Allah went out with a group of his
Companions towards the Ukaz market. Something had been intervening
between the Shayatin and the news from the heavens, and shooting
stars has been sent upon them, so the Shayatin returned to their
people and they said to them: ‘What is wrong with you?’ They
replied: ‘Something has been intervening between us and the news of
the heavens except that something has happened. So travel east and
west in the earth and look for what is it that intervenes between
you an between the news of the heavens.’” He said: “So they went
traveling east and west on the earth, seeking whatever it was that
had been intervening between them and the news of the heavens. A
group of those who were traveling towards Tihamah headed in the
direction of the Messenger of Allah, while he was at Nakhlah,
enroute to the Ukaz market. He was performing Salat Al-Fajr with
his Companions. When they heard the Quran they listened to it, and
they said: ‘By Allah! This is what has been intervening between us
and the news of the heavens.’” He said: “Then they returned to
their people and said: ‘O our people! Verily we heard a wonderful
Recitation! It guides to the Right Path, and we have believed
therein, and we shall never join anything with our Lord.’ So Allah,
Blessed is He and Most High, revealed to His Prophet: Say: ‘It has
been revealed to me that a group of the jinn listened.’ So the
saying of the jinns was only revealed to him.”</english-text>
</hadith>
