<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33555</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3646</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30421, 20005, 10820, 11052, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي عمر، حدثنا سفيان، عن مجالد، عن الشعبي،
عن جابر بن عبد الله، قال قال ناس من اليهود لأناس من أصحاب النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم هل يعلم نبيكم كم عدد خزنة جهنم قالوا لا ندري حتى
نسأل نبينا ‏.‏ فجاء رجل إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا محمد
غلب أصحابك اليوم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وبم غلبوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سألهم يهود هل
يعلم نبيكم كم عدد خزنة جهنم قال ‏"‏ فما قالوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قالوا لا
ندري حتى نسأل نبينا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أفغلب قوم سئلوا عما لا يعلمون
فقالوا لا نعلم حتى نسأل نبينا لكنهم قد سألوا نبيهم فقالوا أرنا الله
جهرة على بأعداء الله إني سائلهم عن تربة الجنة وهي الدرمك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فلما جاءوا قالوا يا أبا القاسم كم عدد خزنة جهنم قال ‏"‏ هكذا وهكذا
‏"‏ ‏.‏ في مرة عشرة وفي مرة تسع ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال لهم النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما تربة الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فسكتوا هنيهة ثم قالوا
خبزة يا أبا القاسم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ الخبز
من الدرمك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث غريب إنما نعرفه من هذا الوجه من حديث
مجالد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Jabir [bin Abdullah] said: “Some people from the Jews
said to some people among the Companions of the Prophet: ‘Does your
Prophet know how many keepers are there in Jahannam?’ They said:
‘We do not know until we ask our Prophet and said: ‘O Muhammad!
Your Companions were defeated today.’ He said: ‘In what were they
defeated?’ He said: ‘Some Jews asked them if their Prophet knew how
many keepers are there in Jahannam.’ He said: ‘So what did they
say?’ He said: ‘They said: “We do not know until we ask our
Prophet.” He said: ‘Are a people defeated who are asked about
something that they do not know, merely because they said, “We do
not know until we ask our Prophet?” Rather, there (people) did ask
their Prophet, they said: “Show us Allah plainly.” I should ask the
enemies of Allah about the Darmak.’ So when they came to him they
said: ‘O Abul-Qasim! How many keepers are there in Jahannum?’ He
said: ‘This and that many.’ One time ten, and one time nine. They
said: ‘Yes.’ He said to them: ‘What is the dirt of Paradise?’” He
said: “They were silent for a while, then they said: ‘Is it bread O
Abul-Qasim?’ So the Prophet said: ‘The bread is made of
Ad-Darmak.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
