<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33582</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3673</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30277, 20547, 20564, 14434</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمود بن غيلان، حدثنا أبو داود الطيالسي، حدثنا
القاسم بن الفضل الحداني، عن يوسف بن سعد، قال قام رجل إلى الحسن بن
علي بعد ما بايع معاوية فقال سودت وجوه المؤمنين ‏.‏ أو يا مسود وجوه
المؤمنين ‏.‏ فقال لا تؤنبني رحمك الله فإن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
أري بني أمية على منبره فساءه ذلك فنزلت ‏:‏ ‏(‏ إنا أعطيناك الكوثر
‏)‏ يا محمد يعني نهرا في الجنة ونزلت ‏:‏ ‏(‏ إنا أنزلناه في ليلة
القدر * وما أدراك ما ليلة القدر * ليلة القدر خير من ألف شهر ‏)‏
يملكها بعدك بنو أمية يا محمد ‏.‏ قال القاسم فعددناها فإذا هي ألف
شهر لا يزيد يوم ولا ينقص ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث غريب لا نعرفه
إلا من هذا الوجه من حديث القاسم بن الفضل ‏.‏ وقد قيل عن القاسم بن
الفضل عن يوسف بن مازن ‏.‏ والقاسم بن الفضل الحداني هو ثقة وثقه يحيى
بن سعيد وعبد الرحمن بن مهدي ويوسف بن سعد رجل مجهول ولا نعرف هذا
الحديث على هذا اللفظ إلا من هذا الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Qasim bin Al-Fadl Al-Huddani narrated from Yusuf
bin Sa’d, who said: “A man stood up in front of Al-Hasan bin Ali,
after he pledged to Mu’awiyah, so he said: ‘You have made fools of
the believers.’ – or: ‘O you who has made fools of the believers’ –
So he said: ‘Do not scold me so, may Allah have mercy upon you, for
indeed the Prophet had a dream in which he saw Banu Umayyah upon
his Minbar. That distressed him, so (the following) was revealed:
Verily We have granted you Al-Kauthar (O Muhammad) meaning a river
in Paradise, and (the following) was revealed: ‘Verily We have sent
it down on the Night of Al-Qadr. And what will make you know what
the Night of Al-Qadr is? The Night of Al-Qadr is better than a
thousand months, in which Banu Umayyah rules after you O Muhammad.”
Al-Qasim said: “So we counted them, and found that they were
one-thousand months, not a day more nor less.”</english-text>
</hadith>
