<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33603</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3694</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Tafsir - كتاب تفسير القرآن عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20553, 11834, 11168, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا صفوان بن عيسى، حدثنا الحارث
بن عبد الرحمن بن أبي ذباب، عن سعيد بن أبي سعيد المقبري، عن أبي
هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لما خلق الله آدم
ونفخ فيه الروح عطس فقال الحمد لله فحمد الله بإذنه فقال له ربه يرحمك
الله يا آدم اذهب إلى أولئك الملائكة إلى ملإ منهم جلوس فقل السلام
عليكم ‏.‏ قالوا وعليك السلام ورحمة الله ‏.‏ ثم رجع إلى ربه فقال إن
هذه تحيتك وتحية بنيك بينهم ‏.‏ فقال الله له ويداه مقبوضتان اختر
أيهما شئت قال اخترت يمين ربي وكلتا يدى ربي يمين مباركة ‏.‏ ثم بسطها
فإذا فيها آدم وذريته فقال أى رب ما هؤلاء فقال هؤلاء ذريتك فإذا كل
إنسان مكتوب عمره بين عينيه فإذا فيهم رجل أضوؤهم أو من أضوئهم ‏.‏
قال يا رب من هذا قال هذا ابنك داود قد كتبت له عمر أربعين سنة ‏.‏
قال يا رب زده في عمره ‏.‏ قال ذاك الذي كتبت له ‏.‏ قال أى رب فإني
قد جعلت له من عمري ستين سنة قال أنت وذاك ‏.‏ قال ثم أسكن الجنة ما
شاء الله ثم أهبط منها فكان آدم يعد لنفسه ‏.‏ قال فأتاه ملك الموت
فقال له آدم قد عجلت قد كتب لي ألف سنة ‏.‏ قال بلى ولكنك جعلت لابنك
داود ستين سنة فجحد فجحدت ذريته ونسي فنسيت ذريته ‏.‏ قال فمن يومئذ
أمر بالكتاب والشهود ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب من هذا
الوجه ‏.‏ وقد روي من غير وجه عن أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم من رواية زيد بن أسلم عن أبي صالح عن أبي هريرة عن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hurairah narrated that the Messenger of Allah
said: “When Allah created Adam, He breathed the soul into him, then
he sneezed and said: ‘All praise is due to Allah.’ So he praised
Allah by His permission. Then His Lord said to him: ‘May Allah have
mercy upon you O Adam. Go to those angels – to that gathering of
them sitting – so say: “As-Salamu Alaikas-Salamu, Wa Rahmatullah’
Then he returned to his Lord, He said: ‘This is your greeting and
the greeting of your children among each other.’ Then Allah said to
him – while His Two Hands were closed – ‘Choose which of them you
wish.’ He said: ‘I chose the right My Lord and both of the Hands of
my Lord are right, blessed.’ Then He extended it, and there was
Adam and his offspring in it.’ So he said: ‘What are these O my
Lord?’ He said: ‘These are your offspring?’ Each one of them had
his age written between his eyes. But among them there was a man
who was the most illuminating of them – or among the most
illuminated of them. He said: ‘O Lord! Who is this?’ He said: ‘This
is your son Dawud, I wrote forty years for him.’ He said: ‘O Lord!
Add to his age.’ He said: ‘That is what I have written for him.’ He
said: ‘O Lord! Give him sixty of my years.’ He said: ‘So you shall
have it.’” He said: “Then, he resided in Paradise as long as Allah
willed, then he was cast from it, so Adam was counting for
himself.” He said: “So the Angel of death came to him, and Adam
said to him: ‘You are hasty, one-thousand years were written for
me.’ He said: ‘Of course! But you gave sixty years to your son
Dawud.’ So he rejected, and his offspring rejected, and he forgot,
and his offspring forgot.” He said: “So ever since that day, what
is written and witnessed has been decreed.”</english-text>
</hadith>
