<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33625</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3390</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>35047, 20028, 10755, 10887, 20395, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سفيان بن وكيع، حدثنا جرير، عن الحسن بن عبيد
الله، عن إبراهيم بن سويد، عن عبد الرحمن بن يزيد، عن عبد الله، قال
كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا أمسى قال ‏"‏ أمسينا وأمسى الملك
لله والحمد لله ولا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له أراه قال فيها له
الملك وله الحمد وهو على كل شيء قدير أسألك خير ما في هذه الليلة وخير
ما بعدها وأعوذ بك من شر هذه الليلة وشر ما بعدها وأعوذ بك من الكسل
وسوء الكبر وأعوذ بك من عذاب النار وعذاب القبر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا أصبح قال
ذلك أيضا ‏"‏ أصبحنا وأصبح الملك لله والحمد لله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث
حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وقد رواه شعبة بهذا الإسناد عن ابن مسعود لم يرفعه
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah said: “When he reached the evening, the
Prophet used to say, ‘We have reached the evening, and the Dominion
has reached the evening, while belonging to Allah. And all praise
belongs to Allah. None has the right to be worshipped but Allah,
alone, without partner. (Amsaina Wa Amsal-Mulkullah,
Wal-Hamdullilah, Wa La Ilaha Illallah, Wahdahu La Sharika Lahu)’ –
I think he said [in it]: - ‘To Him belongs the Dominion, and to Him
is the praise, and He is capable of all things. I ask You for the
good that is in this night, and the good of what is after it, and I
seek refuge in You from the evil of this night, and the evil of
what is after it, and I seek refuge in You from laziness and
helpless old age. And I seek refuge in You from the punishment of
the Fire and the punishment of the grave (Lahul-Mulku Wa
Lahul-Hamdu, Wa Huwa Ala Kulli Shai’in Qadir. Asa’luka Khaira Ma Fi
Hadhihil-Lailah, Wa Khaira Ma Ba’daha, Wa A’udhu Bika min Sharri
hadhihil-lailati wa sharri ma ba'diha, Wa A’udhu Bika Minal-Kasali
Wa Su’il-Kibar, Wa A’udhu Bika Min Adhabin-Nari Wa Adhabil-Qabr).
And when he reached the morning, while belonging to Allah. And all
praise belongs to Allah (Asbahna Wa Asbahal-Mulkullah,
Wal-Hamdulillah)’”</english-text>
</hadith>
