<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33628</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3393</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30325, 20165, 22171, 389</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسين بن حريث، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي حازم، عن
كثير بن زيد، عن عثمان بن ربيعة، عن شداد بن أوس، رضى الله عنه أن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال له ‏"‏ ألا أدلك على سيد الاستغفار
اللهم أنت ربي لا إله إلا أنت خلقتني وأنا عبدك وأنا على عهدك ووعدك
ما استطعت أعوذ بك من شر ما صنعت وأبوء إليك بنعمتك على وأعترف بذنوبي
فاغفر لي ذنوبي إنه لا يغفر الذنوب إلا أنت ‏.‏ لا يقولها أحدكم حين
يمسي فيأتي عليه قدر قبل أن يصبح إلا وجبت له الجنة ولا يقولها حين
يصبح فيأتي عليه قدر قبل أن يمسي إلا وجبت له الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وفي
الباب عن أبي هريرة وابن عمر وابن مسعود وابن أبزى وبريدة رضى الله
عنهم ‏.‏ قال وهذا حديث حسن غريب ‏.‏ وعبد العزيز بن أبي حازم هو ابن
أبي حازم الزاهد ‏.‏ وقد روي هذا الحديث من غير هذا الوجه عن شداد بن
أوس رضى الله عنه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Shaddad bin Aws narrated that: The Prophet said to
him: “Should I not direct you to the chief of supplications for
forgiveness? ‘O Allah, You are my Lord, there is none worthy of
worship except You, You created me and I am Your slave. I am
adhering to Your covenant and Your promise as much as I am able to,
I seek refuge in You from the evil of what I have done. I admit to
You your blessings upon me, and I admit to me sins. So forgive me,
for there is none who can forgive sins except You (Allahumma Anta
Rabbi La Ilaha Illa Anta Khalaqtani Wa Ana `Abduka Wa Ana `Ala
`Ahdika Wa Wa’dika Ma-stata’tu. A’udhu Bika Min Sharri Ma Sana’tu
Wa Abu'u ilayka Bini’matika Alayya Wa A’tarifu Bidhunubi Faghfirli
Dhunubi Innahu La Yaghfirudh-Dhunuba Illa Ant).’ None of you says
it when he reaches the evening, and a decree comes upon him before
he reaches morning, except that Paradise becomes obligatory upon
him. And none says it when he reaches the morning, and a decree
comes upon him before he reaches evening, except that Paradise
becomes obligatory for him.”</english-text>
</hadith>
