<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33645</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3410</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30242, 20208, 11068, 19867, 29</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن منيع، حدثنا إسماعيل ابن علية، حدثنا عطاء
بن السائب، عن أبيه، عن عبد الله بن عمرو، رضى الله عنهما قال قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خلتان لا يحصيهما رجل مسلم إلا دخل
الجنة ألا وهما يسير ومن يعمل بهما قليل يسبح الله في دبر كل صلاة
عشرا ويحمده عشرا ويكبره عشرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأنا رأيت رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يعقدها بيده قال ‏"‏ فتلك خمسون ومائة باللسان وألف
وخمسمائة في الميزان وإذا أخذت مضجعك تسبحه وتكبره وتحمده مائة فتلك
مائة باللسان وألف في الميزان فأيكم يعمل في اليوم والليلة ألفين
وخمسمائة سيئة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا وكيف لا يحصيها قال ‏"‏ يأتي أحدكم
الشيطان وهو في صلاته فيقول اذكر كذا اذكر كذا ‏.‏ حتى ينفتل فلعله أن
لا يفعل ويأتيه وهو في مضجعه فلا يزال ينومه حتى ينام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا
حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وقد روى شعبة والثوري عن عطاء بن السائب هذا الحديث
‏.‏ وروى الأعمش هذا الحديث عن عطاء بن السائب مختصرا ‏.‏ وفي الباب
عن زيد بن ثابت وأنس وابن عباس رضى الله عنهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah bin `Amr [may Allah be pleased with both of
them] said: “The Messenger of Allah said: ‘There are two
characteristics over which a Muslim man does not guard, except that
he enters Paradise. And indeed, they are easy, and those who act
upon them are few: He glorifies Allah at the end of every prayer
ten times (saying Subhan Allah) and praises Him ten times saying
(Al-Hamdullilah) and extols His greatness ten times (saying Allahu
Akbar).’”He said: “And I have seen the Messenger of Allah counting
them with his hand. He said: ‘So this is one hundred and fifty with
the tongue, and one thousand and five hundred on the Scale. When
you go to bed, you glorify Him, extol His greatness, and praise Him
a hundred times, so this is one hundred with the tongue and one
thousand on the Scale. Which of you perform two thousand and five
hundred evil deeds in a single day and night?’ They said: ‘How
could we not guard over them?’ He said: ‘Shaitan comes to one of
you when he is in his Salat and says: “Remember such and such,
remember such and such” until he turns perhaps he will not do it.
And he comes to him and he is lying down and makes him sleepy until
he falls asleep.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
