<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33656</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3421</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30450, 20027, 10628, 11197, 11199, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الملك بن أبي الشوارب، حدثنا يوسف بن
الماجشون، حدثني أبي، عن عبد الرحمن الأعرج، عن عبيد الله بن أبي
رافع، عن علي بن أبي طالب، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان إذا
قام إلى الصلاة قال ‏"‏ وجهت وجهي للذي فطر السموات والأرض حنيفا وما
أنا من المشركين إن صلاتي ونسكي ومحياى ومماتي لله رب العالمين لا
شريك له وبذلك أمرت وأنا من المسلمين اللهم أنت الملك لا إله إلا أنت
أنت ربي وأنا عبدك ظلمت نفسي واعترفت بذنبي فاغفر لي ذنوبي جميعا إنه
لا يغفر الذنوب إلا أنت واهدني لأحسن الأخلاق لا يهدي لأحسنها إلا أنت
واصرف عني سيئها إنه لا يصرف عني سيئها إلا أنت آمنت بك تباركت
وتعاليت أستغفرك وأتوب إليك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا ركع قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك ركعت
وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت خشع لك سمعي وبصري ومخي وعظامي وعصبي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا
رفع رأسه قال ‏"‏ اللهم ربنا لك الحمد ملء السموات والأرضين وملء ما
بينهما وملء ما شئت من شيء بعد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا سجد قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك
سجدت وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت سجد وجهي للذي خلقه فصوره وشق سمعه وبصره
فتبارك الله أحسن الخالقين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم يكون آخر ما يقول بين التشهد
والسلام ‏"‏ اللهم اغفر لي ما قدمت وما أخرت وما أسررت وما أعلنت وما
أنت أعلم به مني أنت المقدم وأنت المؤخر لا إله إلا أنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ali bin Abi Talib narrated that whenever the
Messenger of Allah would stand for Salat, he would say: “I have
directed my face towards the One who created the Heavens and the
earth, as a Hanif, andI am not of the idolaters. Indeed, my Salat,
my sacrifice, my living, and my dying is for Allah, the Lord of all
that exists, there is no partner for Him, and with this have I been
ordered, and I among the Muslims. O Allah, You are the King, there
is none worthy of worship except You. You are My Lord, and I am
Your slave, I have wronged myself, and I admit to my sin, so
forgive me all my sins, verily, there is none who forgives sins but
You. And guide me to the best of the manners, none guides to the
best of them except You, and turn the evil of them away from me,
[verily,] none can turn the evil of them away from me except You. I
have believed in You. Blessed are You and Exalted are You, I seek
Your forgiveness and I repent to you (Wajjahtu Wajhi Lilladhi
Fataras-Samawati Wal-Arda Hanifan Wa Ma Ana Min Al-Mushrikin, Inna
Salati Wa Nusuki Wa Mahyaya Wa Mamati Lillahi Rabbil-Alamin, La
Sharika Lahu Wa Bidhalika Umirtu Wa Ana Min Al-Muslimin. Allahumma
Antal-Maliku La Ilaha Illa Ant, Anta Rabbi, Wa Ana Abduka Zalamtu
Nafsi Wa’taraftu Bidhanbi Faghfirli Dhunubi Jami’an, Innahu La
Yaghfir Adh-Dhunuba Illa Ant. Wahdini Li-Ahsanil-Akhlaqi La Yahdi
Li-Ahsaniha Illa Ant. Wasrif Anni Sayyi’aha [Innahu] La Yasrifu
Anni Sayyi’aha Illa Ant. Amantu Bika Tabarakta Wa Ta’alaita
Astaghfiruka Wa Atubu Ilaik).” And when he would bow in Ruku, he
would say: “O Allah, to You I have bowed, and in You I believe, and
to You have I submitted. My hearing, my sight, my brain, my bones
and my sinew are humbled to you (Allahumma Laka Raka’tu Wa Bika
Amantu Wa Laka Aslamtu Khasha’a Laka Sam’I Wa Basari Wa Mukhkhi Wa
Azmi, Wa Asabi)” Then when he would raise his head, he would say:
“O Allah, our Lord, to You is praise the fill of the Heavens and
the earths and the fill of whatever You will of things. (Allahumma
Rabbana Lakal-Hamdu Mil’as-Samawati Wal-Ardina Wa Ma Bainahuma, Wa
Mil’a Ma Shi’ta Min Shai).” Then, when he prostrated, he would say:
“O Allah, to You have I prostrated, and in You have I believed, and
to You have I submitted, my face has prostrated to the One Who
created it and fashioned it, and gave it its hearing and its sight.
So Blessed is Allah, the Best of creators (Allahumma Laka Sajadtu
Wa Bika Amantu Wa Laka Aslamtu, Sajada Wajhi Lilladhi Khalaqahu Wa
Suwwarahu Wa Shaqqa Sam’ahu Wa Basarahu Fatabarak Allahu
Ahsanul-Khaliqin).” Then the last of what he would say between
At-Tashah-hud and As-Salam would be: “O Allah, forgive me what I
have done before and after, and what I have hidden and what I have
done openly, and what You know more of it than I, You are the One
who sends forth and the One who delays, there is none worthy of
worship except You. (Allahummaghfirli Ma Qaddamtu Wa Ma Akhkhartu
Wa Ma Asrartu Wa Ma A’lantu Wa Ma Anta A’lamu Bihi Minni
Antal-Muqaddimu Wa Antal-Mu’akhkhiru, La Ilaha Illa
Ant).”</english-text>
</hadith>
