<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33653</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3418</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20280, 30112, 20001, 11263, 11053, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الأنصاري، حدثنا معن، حدثنا مالك بن أنس، عن أبي
الزبير، عن طاوس، عن عبد الله بن عباس، رضى الله عنهما أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم كان إذا قام إلى الصلاة من جوف الليل يقول ‏"‏
اللهم لك الحمد أنت نور السموات والأرض ولك الحمد أنت قيام السموات
والأرض ولك الحمد أنت رب السموات والأرض ومن فيهن أنت الحق ووعدك الحق
ولقاؤك حق والجنة حق والنار حق والساعة حق اللهم لك أسلمت وبك آمنت
وعليك توكلت وإليك أنبت وبك خاصمت وإليك حاكمت فاغفر لي ما قدمت وما
أخرت وما أسررت وما أعلنت أنت إلهي لا إله إلا أنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا
حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ وقد روي من غير وجه عن ابن عباس عن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abdullah bin Abbas [may Allah be pleased with them]
narrated, : that when the Messenger of Allah would stand for prayer
during the middle of the night, he would say: “O Allah, to You is
the Praise, You are the Light of the heavens and the earth, and to
You is the Praise, You are the Sustainer of the heavens and the
earth, and To You is the praise, You are the Lord of the heaves and
the earth, and those in them, You are the truth, and Your Promise
is the truth, and Your meeting is true, and Paradise is true, and
the Fire is true, and the Hour is true, O Allah, to You have I
submitted, and in You have I believed , and in You have I relied,
and to You have I turned, and by You have I argued, and to You have
I referred for judgment. So forgive me what I have done before and
after, and that which I have hidden and that which I have done
openly. You are my Diety, no has the right to be worshipped but You
(Allahumma Lakal-Hamd, Anta Nurus-Samawati Wal-Ard, Wa Lakal-Hamd,
Anta Qayyamus-Samawati Wal-Ard, Wa Lakal-Hamd, Anta Rabbus-Samawati
Wal-Ard, Wa Man Fihim, Antal-Haqq, Wa Wa’dukal-Haqq, Wa Liqa’uka
Haqq, Was-Sa’atu Haqq. Allahumma Laka Aslamtu Wa Bika Khasamtu Wa
Ilaika Hakamtu, Faghfirli Ma Qaddamtu Wa Ma Akhartu, Wa Ma Asrartu
Wa Ma A’lantu, Anta Ilahi La Ilaha Illa Ant).”</english-text>
</hadith>
