<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33658</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3423</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30115, 30584, 20509, 11106, 11187, 11197, 11199,
5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن علي الخلال، حدثنا سليمان بن داود
الهاشمي، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن أبي الزناد، عن موسى بن عقبة، عن عبد
الله بن الفضل، عن عبد الرحمن الأعرج، عن عبيد الله بن أبي رافع، عن
علي بن أبي طالب، عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه كان إذا قام
إلى الصلاة المكتوبة رفع يديه حذو منكبيه ويصنع ذلك أيضا إذا قضى
قراءته وأراد أن يركع ويصنعها إذا رفع رأسه من الركوع ولا يرفع يديه
في شيء من صلاته وهو قاعد وإذا قام من سجدتين رفع يديه كذلك فكبر
ويقول حين يفتتح الصلاة بعد التكبير ‏"‏ وجهت وجهي للذي فطر السموات
والأرض حنيفا وما أنا من المشركين إن صلاتي ونسكي ومحياى ومماتي لله
رب العالمين لا شريك له وبذلك أمرت وأنا من المسلمين اللهم أنت الملك
لا إله إلا أنت سبحانك أنت ربي وأنا عبدك ظلمت نفسي واعترفت بذنبي
فاغفر لي ذنوبي جميعا إنه لا يغفر الذنوب إلا أنت واهدني لأحسن
الأخلاق لا يهدي لأحسنها إلا أنت واصرف عني سيئها لا يصرف عني سيئها
إلا أنت لبيك وسعديك وأنا بك وإليك ولا منجا منك ولا ملجأ إلا إليك
أستغفرك وأتوب إليك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم يقرأ فإذا ركع كان كلامه في ركوعه أن
يقول ‏"‏ اللهم لك ركعت وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت وأنت ربي خشع سمعي وبصري
ومخي وعظمي لله رب العالمين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فإذا رفع رأسه من الركوع قال ‏"‏
سمع الله لمن حمده ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم يتبعها ‏"‏ اللهم ربنا ولك الحمد ملء
السموات والأرض وملء ما شئت من شيء بعد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وإذا سجد قال في سجوده
‏"‏ اللهم لك سجدت وبك آمنت ولك أسلمت وأنت ربي سجد وجهي للذي خلقه
وشق سمعه وبصره تبارك الله أحسن الخالقين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ويقول عند انصرافه
من الصلاة ‏"‏ اللهم اغفر لي ما قدمت وما أخرت وما أسررت وما أعلنت
أنت إلهي لا إله إلا أنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏ والعمل
على هذا عند الشافعي وبعض أصحابنا ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى وأحمد لا يراه
وقال بعض أهل العلم من أهل الكوفة وغيرهم يقول هذا في صلاة التطوع ولا
يقوله في المكتوبة ‏.‏ سمعت أبا إسماعيل الترمذي محمد بن إسماعيل بن
يوسف يقول سمعت سليمان بن داود الهاشمي يقول وذكر هذا الحديث فقال هذا
عندنا مثل حديث الزهري عن سالم عن أبيه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ali bin Abi Talib narrated that : when the Messenger
of Allah would stand for the obligatory prayer, he would raise his
hands to the level of his shoulder, and he would do this [also]
when he finished his recitation and intended to bow, and he would
do it when he raised his head from Ruku, and he would not raise his
hands in any of his prayers while he was seated. When he would rise
from the two prostrations, he would likewise raise his hands, and
say the Takbir, and when he opened his Salat after the Takbir, he
would say: “I have directed my face towards the One who has created
the heavens and the earth, as a Hanif, and I am not of the
idolaters. Indeed, my Salat, my sacrifice, my living, my dying, is
for Allah, the Lord of all that exists, without partner, and with
this have I been ordered and I am of the Muslims. O Allah, You are
the King, there is none worthy of worship except You. Glorified are
You, You are My Lord, and I am Your slave, I have wronged myself
and I admit to my sin, so forgive me all my sins, verily, there is
none who forgives sins but You, and guide me to the best of
manners, none guides to the best of them except You, and turn away
from me the evil of them, none can turn away from me the evil of
them, none turns away from me the evil of them except You, I am
here in Your obedience and aiding Your cause, and I am reliant upon
You and ever-turning towards You, [and] there is no refuge from You
nor hiding place from You except (going) to You, I seek Your
forgiveness, and I repent to you (Wajjahtu Wajhi Lilladhi
Fataras-Samawati Wal-Arda Hanifan Wa Ma Ana Min Al-Mushrikin, Inna
Salati Wa Nusuki Wa Mahyaya Wa Mamati Lillahi Rabbil-Alamin, La
Sharika Lahu Wa Bidhalika Umirtu Wa Ana Min Al-Muslimin. Allahumma
Antal-Maliku La Ilaha Illa Anta Subhanaka, Anta Rabbi, Wa Ana
Abduka Zalamtu Nafsi Wa’taraftu Bidhanbi Faghfirli Dhanbi Jami’an,
Innahu La Yaghfir udh-Dhunuba Illa Ant. Wahdini Li-Ahsanil-Akhlaqi
La Yahdi Li-Ahsaniha Illa Ant. Wasrif Anni Sayyi’aha Illa Ant.
Labaika Wa Sa’daika Wa Ana Bika Wa Ilaika, [Wa] La Manja Minka Wa
La Milja Illa Ilaik, Astaghfiruka Wa Atubu Ilaik).” Then he would
recite, then when he would bow, his speech in his Ruku, would be to
say: “O Allah, to You have I bowed, and in You have I believed, and
to You have I submitted (in Islam), and You are my Lord. My
hearing, my sight, my brain and my bones are humbled to Allah, the
Lord of the Worlds all that exists (Allahumma Laka Raka’tu Wa Bika
Amantu Wa Laka Aslamtu Wa Anta Rabbi, Khasha’a Sam’I Wa Basari Wa
Mukhkhi Wa Azmi Lillahi, Rabbil-Alamin).” Then, when he raised his
head from Ruku he would say: “Allah hears the one who praises him
(Sami Allahu Liman Hamidah).” Then he would follow it with: “O
Allah, our Lord, to You is praise filling the heavens and the earth
and filling whatever You wish of things afterward (Allahumma Rabban
Lakal-Hamdu Mil’as-Samawati Wal-Ardi Wa Mil’a Ma Shi’ta Min Shai’in
Ba’d).” Then, when he would prostrated he would say in his
prostration: “O Allah, to You have I prostrated, and in You have I
believed, and to You have I submitted (in Islam), and You are my
Lord, my face has prostrated to the One that created it, and grated
its hearing and sight, Blessed is Allah, the Best of Creators
(Allahumma Laka Sajadtu Wa Bika Amantu Wa Laka Aslamtu, Wa Anta
Rabbi, Sajada WAjhi Lilladhi Khalaqahu Wa Shaqqa Sam’ahu Wa
Basarahu, Tabarak Allahu Ahsanul-Khaliqin).” When he was finished
with his Salat, we would say: “O Allah, forgive me what I have
done, before and after, and what I have hidden, and what I have
done openly, and You are my Deity, there is none worthy of worship
except You (Allahummaghfirli Ma Qaddamtu Wa Ma Akhkhartu Wa Ma
Asrartu Wa Ma A’lantu, Wa Anta Ilahi, La Ilaha Illa
Ant).”</english-text>
</hadith>
