<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33681</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3446</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20327, 11049, 11376</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا أبو الأحوص، عن أبي إسحاق، عن علي بن
ربيعة، قال شهدت عليا أتي بدابة ليركبها فلما وضع رجله في الركاب قال
بسم الله ثلاثا فلما استوى على ظهرها قال الحمد لله ثم قال ‏:‏ ‏(‏
سبحان الذي سخر لنا هذا وما كنا له مقرنين * وإنا إلى ربنا لمنقلبون
‏)‏ ثم قال الحمد لله ثلاثا والله أكبر ثلاثا سبحانك إني قد ظلمت نفسي
فاغفر لي فإنه لا يغفر الذنوب إلا أنت ‏.‏ ثم ضحك ‏.‏ فقلت من أى شيء
ضحكت يا أمير المؤمنين قال رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صنع كما
صنعت ثم ضحك فقلت من أى شيء ضحكت يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ إن ربك ليعجب
من عبده إذا قال رب اغفر لي ذنوبي إنه لا يغفر الذنوب غيرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال وفي الباب عن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن صحيح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ali bin Rabi’ah said: “I witnessed Ali having an
animal brought to him to ride. When he placed his foot in the
stirrup he said: ‘In the Name of Allah,’ (Bismillah) [three times].
So then, once he had ascended upon its back, he said: ‘All praise
is due to Allah.’ (Al-Hamdulillah) then he said: Glory is to Him
Who has subjected this to us, and we were not able to do it. And,
surely, to our Lord are we returning (Subhan Alladhi Sakh-khara
Lana Hadha Wa Ma Kunna Lahu Muqrinin. Wa Inna Ila Rabbina
Lamunqalibun). Then he said: ‘All praise is due to Allah
(Al-Hamdulillah)’ – three times – and ‘Allah is the Greatest
(Allahu Akbar)’ – three times – ‘Glory is to You, indeed I have
wronged myself, so forgive me, for indeed none forgives sins except
You (Subhanaka Inni Qad Zalamtu Nafsi Faghfirli Fa-Innahu La
Yaghfirudh-Dhunuba Illa Ant).’ Then he laughed. So I said: ‘O
Commander of the Believer! What caused you to laugh?’ He said: ‘I
saw the Messenger of Allah do as I did, then he (pbuh) laughed, so
I said, ‘What cause you to laugh?’ He said: ‘Indeed, your Lord if
very pleased with His worshipper when he says: “O my Lord, forgive
me my sins, indeed, no one other than You forgives
sins.”</english-text>
</hadith>
