<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33730</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3495</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>35158, 20337, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هارون بن إسحاق الهمداني، حدثنا عبدة بن سليمان،
عن هشام بن عروة، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، قالت كان رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يدعو بهؤلاء الكلمات ‏"‏ اللهم إني أعوذ بك من فتنة النار
وعذاب النار وعذاب القبر وفتنة القبر ومن شر فتنة الغنى ومن شر فتنة
الفقر ومن شر فتنة المسيح الدجال اللهم اغسل خطاياى بماء الثلج والبرد
وأنق قلبي من الخطايا كما أنقيت الثوب الأبيض من الدنس وباعد بيني
وبين خطاياى كما باعدت بين المشرق والمغرب اللهم إني أعوذ بك من الكسل
والهرم والمأثم والمغرم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال هذا حديث حسن صحيح
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Aishah narrated that the Messenger of Allah used to
supplicate with these words: “O Allah, indeed, I seek refuge in You
from the trial of the Fire, and the punishment of the Fire, and the
punishment of the grave, and the trial of the grave, and from the
evil of the trial of the grave, and from the evil of the trials of
riches, and from the evils of the trials of poverty, and from the
evil of the trial of the false Masih. O Allah, wash my sins with
water of ice and hail, and clease my heart of sins, as You cleansed
a white garment of filth, and distance me and my sins as You
distanced between the east and the west. O Allah, indeed, I seek
refuge in You from laziness, senility, sin and debt. (Allahumma
Inni A’udhu Bika Min Fitnatin-Nar, Wa Adhabin-Nar, Wa Adhabil-Qabr,
Wa Fitnatil-Qabr. Wa Min Sharri Fitnatil-Ghina, Wa Min Sharri
Fitnatil-Faqr, Wa Min Sharri Fitnatil-Masihid-Dajjal.
Allahummaghsil Khatayaya Bi-Ma’ith-Thalji Wal-Bardi, Wa Anqi Qalbi
Minal-Khataya Kama Anqaitath-Thawbal-Abyada Minad-Danas, Wa Ba’id
Baini Wa Baina Khatayaya Kama Ba’adta Bainal-Mashriqi Wal Maghrib,
Allahumma Inni A’udhu Bika Min Al-Kasali Wal-Harami Wal-Ma’atham
Wal-Maghram).”</english-text>
</hadith>
