<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33805</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3570</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Supplication - كتاب الدعوات عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30292, 30587, 20733, 11070, 11029, 11023,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن الحسن، حدثنا سليمان بن عبد الرحمن
الدمشقي، حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا ابن جريج، عن عطاء بن أبي رباح،
وعكرمة، مولى ابن عباس عن ابن عباس، أنه قال بينما نحن عند رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ جاءه علي بن أبي طالب فقال بأبي أنت وأمي تفلت
هذا القرآن من صدري فما أجدني أقدر عليه ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا أبا الحسن أفلا أعلمك كلمات ينفعك الله بهن
وينفع بهن من علمته ويثبت ما تعلمت في صدرك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أجل يا رسول
الله فعلمني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إذا كان ليلة الجمعة فإن استطعت أن تقوم في
ثلث الليل الآخر فإنها ساعة مشهودة والدعاء فيها مستجاب وقد قال أخي
يعقوب لبنيه ‏:‏ ‏(‏سوف أستغفر لكم ربي ‏)‏ يقول حتى تأتي ليلة الجمعة
فإن لم تستطع فقم في وسطها فإن لم تستطع فقم في أولها فصل أربع ركعات
تقرأ في الركعة الأولى بفاتحة الكتاب وسورة يس وفي الركعة الثانية
بفاتحة الكتاب و‏(‏ حم ‏)‏ الدخان وفي الركعة الثالثة بفاتحة الكتاب
والم تنزيل السجدة وفي الركعة الرابعة بفاتحة الكتاب وتبارك المفصل
فإذا فرغت من التشهد فاحمد الله وأحسن الثناء على الله وصل على وأحسن
وعلى سائر النبيين واستغفر للمؤمنين والمؤمنات ولإخوانك الذين سبقوك
بالإيمان ثم قل في آخر ذلك اللهم ارحمني بترك المعاصي أبدا ما أبقيتني
وارحمني أن أتكلف ما لا يعنيني وارزقني حسن النظر فيما يرضيك عني
اللهم بديع السموات والأرض ذا الجلال والإكرام والعزة التي لا ترام
أسألك يا الله يا رحمن بجلالك ونور وجهك أن تلزم قلبي حفظ كتابك كما
علمتني وارزقني أن أتلوه على النحو الذي يرضيك عني اللهم بديع السموات
والأرض ذا الجلال والإكرام والعزة التي لا ترام أسألك يا الله يا رحمن
بجلالك ونور وجهك أن تنور بكتابك بصري وأن تطلق به لساني وأن تفرج به
عن قلبي وأن تشرح به صدري وأن تغسل به بدني لأنه لا يعينني على الحق
غيرك ولا يؤتيه إلا أنت ولا حول ولا قوة إلا بالله العلي العظيم يا
أبا الحسن تفعل ذلك ثلاث جمع أو خمس أو سبع تجاب بإذن الله والذي
بعثني بالحق ما أخطأ مؤمنا قط ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال عبد الله بن عباس فوالله ما
لبث علي إلا خمسا أو سبعا حتى جاء علي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في مثل ذلك المجلس فقال يا رسول الله إني كنت فيما خلا لا آخذ إلا
أربع آيات أو نحوهن وإذا قرأتهن على نفسي تفلتن وأنا أتعلم اليوم
أربعين آية أو نحوها وإذا قرأتها على نفسي فكأنما كتاب الله بين عينى
ولقد كنت أسمع الحديث فإذا رددته تفلت وأنا اليوم أسمع الأحاديث فإذا
تحدثت بها لم أخرم منها حرفا ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم عند ذلك ‏"‏ مؤمن ورب الكعبة يا أبا الحسن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى
هذا حديث حسن غريب لا نعرفه إلا من حديث الوليد بن مسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ikrimah, the freed slave of Ibn Abbas, narrated that:
Ibn Abbas said: “We were with the Messenger of Allah (S) when Ali
bin Abi Talib came to him, and he said: ‘May my father and mother
be ransomed for you! This Quran has suddenly left my heart, and I
do not find myself capable of it.’ So the Messenger of Allah (A)
said to him: ‘O Abul-Hasan! Should I not teach you words that Allah
shall benefit you with, and benefit whomever you teach, and they
will make whatever you have learned in your chest firm?’ He said:
‘Of course, O Messenger of Allah (S), so teach me.’ He said: ‘When
it is the night of (before) Friday, then if you are able to stand
in the last third of the night, then verily it is a witnessed hour,
and supplication is answered in it. And my brother Ya’qub (AS) did
say to his sons: I shall seek forgiveness for you from my Lord. He
said: “Until the night of Friday comes.” So if you are not able,
then stand in the middle of it, and if you are not able then stand
in the first of it. And pray four Rak’ah. Recite Fatihatul-Kitab
(the Opening of the Book) and Surat Ya-Sin in the first Rakah, and
Fatihatul-Kitab and Ha-Min Ad-Dukhan in the second Rakah, and
Fatihatul-Kitab and Alif Lam Mim Tanzil As-Sajdah in the third
Rakah, and Fatihatul-Kitab and Tabarak Al-Mufassal in the fourth
Rakah. So when you have finished with the Tasha-hud, then praise
Allah and mention Allah’s greatness in an excellent manner, and
send Salat upon me - and be excellent in it - and upon the rest of
the Prophet. And seek forgiveness for the believing women, and for
your brothers who have preceded you in faith. Then say in the end
of that: “O Allah, have mercy on me by abandonment of sins forever,
so long as You keep me remaining. And have mercy on me from taking
upon myself what does not concern me, and provide me good sight for
what will make You pleased with me. O Allah, Originator of the
heavens and the earth, Possessor of glory, and generosity, and
honor that is not exceeded. I ask you, O Allah, O Rahman, by Your
glory and the light of Your Face, to make my heart constant in
remembering Your Book as You taught me, and grant me that I recite
it in the manner that will make You pleased with me. O Allah,
Originator of the heavens and the earth, Possessor of glory, and
generosity, and honor that is not exceeded. I ask you, O Allah, O
Rahman, by Your glory and the light of Your Face, to enlighten me
sight with Your Book, and make my tongue free with it, and to
relieve my heart with it, and to expand my chest with it, and to
wash my body with it. For indeed, none aids me upon the truth other
than You, and none gives it except You, and there is no might or
power except by Allah, the High, the Magnificent. (Allahummarhamni
Bitarkil-Ma’asi Abadan Ma Abqaitani, Warhamni An Atakallafa Ma La
Ya’nini, Warzuqni Husnan-Nazari Fi Ma Yurdika Anni. Allahumma
Badi’as Samawati Wal-Ardi Dhal-Jalali Wal-Ikrami Wal-Izzatil-lat La
Turamu As’aluka Ya Allahu Ya Rahmanu Bi-Jalalika Wa Nuri Wajhika An
Tulzima Qalbi Hifza Kitabika Kama Allamtani Warzuqni An Atluwahu
Alan-Nahwil-ladhi Yurdika Anni. Allahumma Badi’as Samawati Wal Ardi
Dhal-Jalali Wal-Ikrami Wal Izzati-llahi La Turamu As’aluka Ya
Allahu, Ya Rahmanu Bi-Jalalika Wa Nuri Wajhika An Tunawwira
Bi-Kitabika Basari, Wa An Tufarrija Bihi Sadri, Wa An Taghsila Bihi
Badani, Fa’innahu La Yu’inuni Alal-Haqqi Ghairuka Wa La Yu’tihi
Illa Anta Wa La Hawla Wa La Quwwata Illa Billahil-Alil-Azim).” O
Abul-Hasan! So do this three Fridays, or five, or seven, you will
be answered - by the will of Allah - by the One Who sent me with
the Truth, it has not failed a believer once.’”Abdullah bin abbas
said: “So, by Allah, ali did not wait but five or seven until [Ali]
came to the Messenger of Allah in a gathering similar to that and
said: ‘O Messenger of Allah, indeed I was [a man] in the time that
passed, who used to not take except four Ayat or about that much,
so when I would recite them to myself they would suddenly depart
from me, and today I learn forty Ayat or about that much, and when
I recite them to myself, then it is as if the Book of Allah is
before my eyes. I used to hear a Hadith and when I would repeat it,
it would suddenly depart from me, and today I hear Ahadith, and
when I report them, I do not err in a single letter.’ So the
Messenger of Allah said at that point: ‘A believer, by the Lord of
the Ka’bah, O Abul-Hasan.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
