<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33865</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3980</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30264, 10846, 11900, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الفضل بن سهل أبو العباس الأعرج البغدادي، حدثنا
عبد الرحمن بن غزوان أبو نوح، أخبرنا يونس بن أبي إسحاق، عن أبي بكر
بن أبي موسى، عن أبيه، قال خرج أبو طالب إلى الشام وخرج معه النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم في أشياخ من قريش فلما أشرفوا على الراهب هبطوا فحلوا
رحالهم فخرج إليهم الراهب وكانوا قبل ذلك يمرون به فلا يخرج إليهم ولا
يلتفت ‏.‏ قال فهم يحلون رحالهم فجعل يتخللهم الراهب حتى جاء فأخذ بيد
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال هذا سيد العالمين هذا رسول رب
العالمين يبعثه الله رحمة للعالمين ‏.‏ فقال له أشياخ من قريش ما علمك
فقال إنكم حين أشرفتم من العقبة لم يبق شجر ولا حجر إلا خر ساجدا ولا
يسجدان إلا لنبي وإني أعرفه بخاتم النبوة أسفل من غضروف كتفه مثل
التفاحة ‏.‏ ثم رجع فصنع لهم طعاما فلما أتاهم به وكان هو في رعية
الإبل قال أرسلوا إليه فأقبل وعليه غمامة تظله فلما دنا من القوم
وجدهم قد سبقوه إلى فىء الشجرة فلما جلس مال فىء الشجرة عليه فقال
انظروا إلى فىء الشجرة مال عليه ‏.‏ قال فبينما هو قائم عليهم وهو
يناشدهم أن لا يذهبوا به إلى الروم فإن الروم إذا رأوه عرفوه بالصفة
فيقتلونه فالتفت فإذا بسبعة قد أقبلوا من الروم فاستقبلهم فقال ما جاء
بكم قالوا جئنا أن هذا النبي خارج في هذا الشهر فلم يبق طريق إلا بعث
إليه بأناس وإنا قد أخبرنا خبره بعثنا إلى طريقك هذا فقال هل خلفكم
أحد هو خير منكم قالوا إنما أخبرنا خبره بطريقك هذا ‏.‏ قال أفرأيتم
أمرا أراد الله أن يقضيه هل يستطيع أحد من الناس رده قالوا لا ‏.‏ قال
فبايعوه وأقاموا معه قال أنشدكم الله أيكم وليه قالوا أبو طالب فلم
يزل يناشده حتى رده أبو طالب وبعث معه أبو بكر بلالا وزوده الراهب من
الكعك والزيت ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب لا نعرفه إلا من هذا
الوجه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari: "Abu Talib departed to
Ash-Sham, and the Prophet (ﷺ) left with him, along with some older
men from the Quraish. When they came across the monk they stopped
there and began setting up their camp, and the monk came out to
them. Before that they used to pass by him and he wouldn't come out
nor pay attention to them." He said: "They were setting up their
camp when the monk was walking amidst them, until he came and took
the hand of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). Then he said: 'This is the
master of the men and jinn, this is the Messenger of the Lord of
the worlds. Allah will raise him as a mercy to the men and jinn.'
So some of the older people from the Quraish said: 'What do you
know?' He said: 'When you people came along from the road, not a
rock nor a tree was left, except that it prostrated, and they do
not prostrate except for a Prophet. And I can recognize him by the
seal of the Prophethood which is below his shoulder blade, like an
apple.' Then he went back, and made them some food, and when he
brought it to them, he [the Prophet (ﷺ)] was tending to the camels.
So he said: 'Send for him.' So he came, and there was a cloud over
him that was shading him. When he came close to the people, he
found that they had beaten him to the tree's shade. So when he sat
down, the shade of the tree leaned towards him. He (the monk) said:
'Look at the shade of the tree leaning towards him.'" He said: "So
while he was standing over them, telling them not to take him to
Rome with him - because if the Romans were to see him, they would
recognize him by his description, and they would kill him - he
turned, and there were seven people who had come from Rome. So he
faced them and said: 'Why have you come?' They said: 'We came
because this Prophet is going to appear during this month, and
there isn't a road left except that people have been sent to it,
and we have been informed of him, and we have been send to this
road of yours.' So he said: 'Is there anyone better than you behind
you?' They said: 'We only have news of him from this road of
yours.' He said: 'Do you think that if there is a matter which
Allah wishes to bring about, there is anyone among the people who
can turn it away?' They said: 'No.'" He said: "So they gave him
their pledge, and they stayed with him. And he said: 'I ask you by
Allah, which of you is his guardian?' They said: 'Abu Talib.' So he
kept adjuring him until Abu Talib returned him (back to Makkah) and
he sent Abu Bakr and Bilal with him. And the monk gave him
provisions of Ka'k (a type of bread) and olive oil."</english-text>
</hadith>
