<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33875</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3990</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30410, 30112, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن موسى الأنصاري، حدثنا معن، قال عرضت على
مالك بن أنس عن إسحاق بن عبد الله بن أبي طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك،
يقول قال أبو طلحة لأم سليم لقد سمعت صوت، رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم - يعني ضعيفا - أعرف فيه الجوع فهل عندك من شيء فقالت نعم ‏.‏
فأخرجت أقراصا من شعير ثم أخرجت خمارا لها فلفت الخبز ببعضه ثم دسته
في يدي وردتني ببعضه ثم أرسلتني إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
فذهبت به إليه فوجدت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جالسا في المسجد
ومعه الناس قال فقمت عليهم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
أرسلك أبو طلحة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ بطعام ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقلت نعم
‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمن معه ‏"‏ قوموا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فانطلقوا فانطلقت بين أيديهم حتى جئت أبا طلحة فأخبرته فقال أبو طلحة
يا أم سليم قد جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس معه وليس
عندنا ما نطعمهم ‏.‏ قالت أم سليم الله ورسوله أعلم ‏.‏ قال فانطلق
أبو طلحة حتى لقي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأقبل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وأبو طلحة معه حتى دخلا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ هلمي يا أم سليم ما عندك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتت بذلك الخبز فأمر به
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ففت وعصرت أم سليم عكة لها فآدمته ثم
قال فيه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله أن يقول ثم قال ‏"‏
ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا ثم قال ‏"‏
ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا فأكل القوم
كلهم وشبعوا والقوم سبعون أو ثمانون رجلا ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: "Abu Talhah said to Umm
Sulaim: 'I heard the voice of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sounding
weak and I sensed some hunger in it. Do you have anything? She
said: 'Yes.' So she got some loaves of wheat bread, then she took
out a Khimar of hers, and put the bread in it. Then she put it
under my arm, and wrapped my upper body with part of it, and she
sent me to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)." He said: "So I brought it
to him, and I found the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sitting in the
Masjid, and there were people with him. So I stood among them, and
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'Has Abu Talhah sent you?' I said:
'Yes.' He said: 'With food?' I said: 'Yes.' So the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said to those with him: 'Stand up.'" So they left, and I
left in front of them, until I came to Abu Talhah, and I told him
(that they were coming). Abu Talhah said: 'O Umm Sulaim! The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) is coming with people, and we don't have
anything to feed them.' Umm Sulaim said: 'Allah and His Messenger
know best.'" He said: "So Abu Talhah departed until he met up with
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah came, while Abu
Talhah was with him, until they entered, when the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said: 'Come O Umm Sulaim! What do you have?' So she
brought him that bread, and he (ﷺ) ordered that it be broken into
pieces. Umm Sulaim poured some butter from an oil-skin upon them,
then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) recited whatever Allah willed for
him to say over it. Then he said: 'Let ten come.' So ten were
admitted, and they ate until they were full, and then they left.
Then he said: 'Let ten come.' So ten were admitted, and they ate
until they were full, and they left. Then he said: 'Let ten come.'
So ten were admitted, and they ate until they were full, and there
were seventy or eighty men."</english-text>
</hadith>
