<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33884</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3999</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20347, 12391, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو جعفر، محمد بن الحسين بن أبي حليمة من قصر
الأحنف وأحمد بن عبدة الضبي وعلي بن حجر المعنى واحد قالوا حدثنا عيسى
بن يونس، حدثنا عمر بن عبد الله، مولى غفرة حدثني إبراهيم بن محمد، من
ولد علي بن أبي طالب قال كان علي رضى الله عنه إذا وصف النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال لم يكن بالطويل الممغط ولا بالقصير المتردد وكان ربعة
من القوم ولم يكن بالجعد القطط ولا بالسبط كان جعدا رجلا ولم يكن
بالمطهم ولا بالمكلثم وكان في الوجه تدوير أبيض مشرب أدعج العينين
أهدب الأشفار جليل المشاش والكتد أجرد ذو مسربة شثن الكفين والقدمين
إذا مشى تقلع كأنما يمشي في صبب وإذا التفت التفت معا بين كتفيه خاتم
النبوة وهو خاتم النبيين أجود الناس كفا وأشرحهم صدرا وأصدق الناس
لهجة وألينهم عريكة وأكرمهم عشرة من رآه بديهة هابه ومن خالطه معرفة
أحبه يقول ناعته لم أر قبله ولا بعده مثله ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث
حسن غريب ليس إسناده بمتصل ‏.‏ قال أبو جعفر سمعت الأصمعي يقول في
تفسيره صفة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم الممغط الذاهب طولا ‏.‏ وسمعت
أعرابيا يقول تمغط في نشابة أى مدها مدا شديدا ‏.‏ وأما المتردد
فالداخل بعضه في بعض قصرا وأما القطط فالشديد الجعودة والرجل الذي في
شعره حجونة قليلا وأما المطهم فالبادن الكثير اللحم وأما المكلثم
فالمدور الوجه ‏.‏ وأما المشرب فهو الذي في بياضه حمرة والأدعج الشديد
سواد العين والأهدب الطويل الأشفار والكتد مجتمع الكتفين وهو الكاهل
والمسربة هو الشعر الدقيق الذي هو كأنه قضيب من الصدر إلى السرة ‏.‏
والشثن الغليظ الأصابع من الكفين والقدمين والتقلع أن يمشي بقوة
والصبب الحدور يقول انحدرنا في صبوب وصبب وقوله جليل المشاش يريد رءوس
المناكب والعشيرة الصحبة والعشير الصاحب والبديهة المفاجأة يقال بدهته
بأمر أى فجأته ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibrahim bin Muhammad, one of the offspring
of 'Ali bin Abi Talib: said: "When 'Ali [may Allah be pleased with
him] described the Prophet (ﷺ) he would say: 'He was not extremely
tall (Mummaghit), nor was he extremely short (Mutaraddid), and he
was of medium height in relation to the people. The wave of his
hair was not completely curly (Qatat), nor straight, but it was in
between. He did not have a large head, nor a small head
(Mukaltham), his face was round and a blended-white color
(Mushrab), his eyes were dark black (Ad'aj), his eye-lashes were
long (Ahdab). He was big-boned and broad shouldered (Al-Katad), his
body hair was well-placed, and he had a Masrubah, his hands and
feet were thick (Shathn). When he walked he walked briskly
(Taqalla'), he leaned forward as if he was walking on a decline
(Sabab). And if he turned his head, his body turned as well,
between his two shoulders was the seal of Prophethood, and he was
the seal of the Prophets. He was the most generous of people [in
hand, and the most big-hearted of them] in breast. He was the most
truthful of people in speech, the softest of them in nature, and
the most noble of them in his relations ('Ishrah). Whoever saw him
for the first time (Badihah) would fear him, and whoever got to
know him, loved him. The one who tried to describe him would have
to say: 'I have not seen before him or after him anyone who
resembles him (ﷺ).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
