<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33949</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4064</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 30346, 30024, 11340, 11049, 11359</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن، أخبرنا عبد الله بن جعفر
الرقي، حدثنا عبيد الله بن عمرو، عن زيد، هو ابن أبي أنيسة عن أبي
إسحاق، عن أبي عبد الرحمن السلمي، قال لما حصر عثمان أشرف عليهم فوق
داره ثم قال أذكركم بالله هل تعلمون أن حراء حين انتفض قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اثبت حراء فليس عليك إلا نبي أو صديق أو شهيد
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال أذكركم بالله هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال في جيش العسرة ‏"‏ من ينفق نفقة متقبلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
والناس مجهدون معسرون فجهزت ذلك الجيش قالوا نعم ‏.‏ ثم قال أذكركم
بالله هل تعلمون أن بئر رومة لم يكن يشرب منها أحد إلا بثمن فابتعتها
فجعلتها للغني والفقير وابن السبيل قالوا اللهم نعم وأشياء عددها ‏.‏
هذا حديث حسن صحيح غريب من هذا الوجه من حديث أبي عبد الرحمن السلمي
عن عثمان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu 'Abdur-Rahman As-Sulami: "When 'Uthman
was besieged, he looked out over them from atop his house and said:
'I remind you by Allah. Do you know that when (mount) Hira shook,
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: "Be firm O Hira! For there is none
upon you except a Prophet, a Siddiq, and a martyr?"' They said:
'Yes.' He said: 'I remind you by Allah! Do you know that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said, about the army of distress
(Al-'Usrah): "Who will spend something which shall be accepted (by
Allah)?" And the people were struggling during difficult times, so
I prepared that army?' They said: 'Yes.' Then he said: 'I remind
you by Allah. Do you know that no one drank from the well of Rumah
but have to pay for it, then I bought it and made it for the rich,
the poor, and the wayfarer?' They said: 'O Allah! Yes!'" And he
listed other things. This Hadith is Hasan Sahih Gharib from this
route; as a narration of Abu 'Abdur-Rahman As-Sulami from
'Uthman.</english-text>
</hadith>
