<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33950</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4065</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20547, 24168, 10622</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا أبو داود، حدثنا السكن بن
المغيرة، ويكنى أبا محمد، مولى لآل عثمان حدثنا الوليد بن أبي هشام،
عن فرقد أبي طلحة، عن عبد الرحمن بن خباب، قال شهدت النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم وهو يحث على جيش العسرة فقام عثمان بن عفان فقال يا رسول
الله على مائة بعير بأحلاسها وأقتابها في سبيل الله ‏.‏ ثم حض على
الجيش فقام عثمان بن عفان فقال يا رسول الله على مائتا بعير بأحلاسها
وأقتابها في سبيل الله ‏.‏ ثم حض على الجيش فقام عثمان بن عفان فقال
يا رسول الله لله على ثلاثمائة بعير بأحلاسها وأقتابها في سبيل الله
‏.‏ فأنا رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينزل عن المنبر وهو يقول
‏"‏ ما على عثمان ما عمل بعد هذه ما على عثمان ما عمل بعد هذه ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث غريب من هذا الوجه لا نعرفه إلا من حديث السكن
بن المغيرة ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن عبد الرحمن بن سمرة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Abdur-Rahman bin Khabbab: "I witnessed the
Prophet (ﷺ) while he was exhorting support for the 'army of
distress.' 'Uthman bin 'Affan stood and said: 'O Messenger of
Allah! I will take the responsibility of one-hundred camels,
including their saddles and water-skins, in the path of Allah.'
Then he [(ﷺ) again] urged support for the army. So 'Uthman [bin
'Affan] stood and said: 'O Messenger of Allah! I will take the
responsibility of two-hundred camels, including their saddles and
water-skins, in the path of Allah.' Then he [(ﷺ) again] urged
support for the army. So 'Uthman bin 'Affan stood and said: '[O
Messenger of Allah] I will take the responsibility of three-hundred
camels, including their saddles and water-skins, in the path of
Allah.' So I saw the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) descend from the Minbar
while he was saying: 'It does not matter what 'Uthman does after
this, it does not matter what 'Uthman does after
this.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
