<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33956</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4071</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20469, 11524</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا صالح بن عبد الله، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن عثمان بن
عبد الله بن موهب، أن رجلا، من أهل مصر حج البيت فرأى قوما جلوسا فقال
من هؤلاء قالوا قريش ‏.‏ قال فمن هذا الشيخ قالوا ابن عمر ‏.‏ فأتاه
فقال إني سائلك عن شيء فحدثني أنشدك الله بحرمة هذا البيت أتعلم أن
عثمان فر يوم أحد قال نعم ‏.‏ قال أتعلم أنه تغيب عن بيعة الرضوان فلم
يشهدها قال نعم ‏.‏ قال أتعلم أنه تغيب يوم بدر فلم يشهد قال نعم ‏.‏
قال الله أكبر ‏.‏ فقال له ابن عمر تعال أبين لك ما سألت عنه أما
فراره يوم أحد فأشهد أن الله قد عفا عنه وغفر له وأما تغيبه يوم بدر
فإنه كانت عنده - أو تحته - ابنة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لك أجر رجل شهد بدرا وسهمه ‏"‏
‏.‏ وأمره أن يخلف عليها وكانت عليلة وأما تغيبه عن بيعة الرضوان فلو
كان أحد أعز ببطن مكة من عثمان لبعثه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
مكان عثمان بعث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عثمان إلى مكة وكانت
بيعة الرضوان بعد ما ذهب عثمان إلى مكة قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بيده اليمنى ‏"‏ هذه يد عثمان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وضرب بها على يده
فقال ‏"‏ هذه لعثمان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال له اذهب بهذا الآن معك ‏.‏ قال أبو
عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Uthman bin 'Abdullah bin Mawhab: "A man
among the people of Egypt performed Hajj to the House, and saw a
group sitting, so he said: 'Who are these?' They said: 'The
Quraish.' He said: 'So who is this old man?' They said: 'Ibn
'Umar.' So he went to him and said: 'I will ask you about
something, so inform me. I ask you by Allah! By the sanctity of
this House! Do you know that 'Uthman fled on the Day of (the battle
of) Uhud?' He said: 'Yes.' He said: 'Do you know that he was absent
from the Pledge of Ar-Ridwan, that he did not witness it?' He said:
'Yes.' He said: 'Do you know that he was absent on the Day of (the
battle of) Badr and did not participate in it?' He said: 'Yes.' So
he said: 'Allah is Great' So Ibn 'Umar said to him: 'Come, so I can
clarify to you what you have asked about. As for his fleeing on the
Day of (the battle of) Uhud, then I bear witness that Allah has
pardoned him and forgiven him. As for his being absent on the Day
of (the battle of) Badr, then he was married to the daughter of the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to him:
"You have the reward of a man who participated in (the battle of)
Badr, and his share (spoils of war)." [And he ordered him to stay
behind with her, as she was ill]. As for his being absent from the
Pledge of Ar-Ridwan, then if there was anyone more revered in
Makkah than 'Uthman, then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) would have
sent him instead of 'Uthman. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sent
'Uthman [to Makkah], and the Pledge of Ar-Ridwan was after 'Uthman
had departed for Makkah." He said: "So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said with his right hand: "This is the hand of 'Uthman," and he put
it upon his own hand, and said: "This is for 'Uthman."' He said to
him: "Go now, and take this (clarification) with
you."</english-text>
</hadith>
