<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33953</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4068</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 30585, 20232, 18, 20232, 24486,
10673</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن، وعباس بن محمد الدوري،
وغير، واحد المعنى، واحد، قالوا حدثنا سعيد بن عامر قال عبد الله
أخبرنا سعيد بن عامر عن يحيى بن أبي الحجاج المنقري عن أبي مسعود
الجريري عن ثمامة بن حزن القشيري قال شهدت الدار حين أشرف عليهم عثمان
فقال ائتوني بصاحبيكم اللذين ألباكم على ‏.‏ قال فجيء بهما فكأنهما
جملان أو كأنهما حماران ‏.‏ قال فأشرف عليهم عثمان فقال أنشدكم بالله
والإسلام هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قدم المدينة وليس
بها ماء يستعذب غير بئر رومة فقال رسول الله ‏"‏ من يشتري بئر رومة
فيجعل دلوه مع دلاء المسلمين بخير له منها في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاشتريتها
من صلب مالي فأنتم اليوم تمنعوني أن أشرب منها حتى أشرب من ماء البحر
‏.‏ قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال أنشدكم بالله والإسلام هل تعلمون أن
المسجد ضاق بأهله فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من يشتري
بقعة آل فلان فيزيدها في المسجد بخير له منها في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فاشتريتها من صلب مالي فأنتم اليوم تمنعوني أن أصلي فيها ركعتين ‏.‏
قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال أنشدكم بالله والإسلام هل تعلمون أني جهزت
جيش العسرة من مالي قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ ثم قال أنشدكم بالله والإسلام
هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان على ثبير مكة ومعه أبو
بكر وعمر وأنا فتحرك الجبل حتى تساقطت حجارته بالحضيض قال فركضه برجله
وقال ‏"‏ اسكن ثبير فإنما عليك نبي وصديق وشهيدان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا اللهم
نعم ‏.‏ قال الله أكبر شهدوا لي ورب الكعبة أني شهيد ثلاثا ‏.‏ قال
أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن ‏.‏ وقد روي من غير وجه عن عثمان
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Thumamah bin Hazn Al-Qushairi: "I was
present at the house when 'Uthman appeared above them saying:
'Bring me your two companions who have gathered you against me.'"
He said: "So they were brought as if they were two camels, or as if
they were two donkeys." He said: "'Uthman appeared above them and
said: 'I ask you by Allah and Islam! Do you know that the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) came to Al-Madinah and there was no water in it that
was sweet except the well of Rumah, so the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'Who will purchase this well of Rumah and place his bucket
alongside the buckets of the Muslims, in exchange for better than
that in Paradise?' So I bought it with the core of my wealth, and
today you prevent me from drinking from it, so that I would have to
drink from the water of the sea?' They said: 'O Allah! Yes!' He
said: 'I ask you by Allah and Islam! Do you know that the Masjid,
was insufficient for its people, so the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'Who will purchase the land of the family of so-and-so, and
add it to the Masjid in exchange for better than that in Paradise?'
So I bought it with the core of my wealth, and today you prevent me
from praying two Rak'ah in it?' They said: 'O Allah! Yes.' He said:
'I ask you by Allah and Islam! Do you know that I prepared the
'army of distress' from my wealth?' They said: 'O Allah! Yes!' Then
he said: 'I ask you by Allah and Islam! Do you know that the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was on (mount) Thabir of Makkah, and with
him was Abu Bakr, and 'Umar, and myself. The mountain began shaking
until its rocks fell to the bottom.' He said: 'So he (ﷺ) stomped it
with his foot and said: "Be still O Thabir! For there is none upon
except a Prophet, a Siddiq and two martyrs?"' They said: 'O Allah!
Yes!' He said: 'Allah is Great! Bear witness by the Lord of the
Ka'bah that I am a martyr!' - three times."</english-text>
</hadith>
