<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33960</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4075</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30423, 20022, 11015, 11113, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عبدة الضبي، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن أيوب،
عن أبي عثمان النهدي، عن أبي موسى الأشعري، قال انطلقت مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فدخل حائطا للأنصار فقضى حاجته فقال لي ‏"‏ يا أبا
موسى أملك على الباب فلا يدخلن على أحد إلا بإذن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاء رجل
يضرب الباب فقلت من هذا فقال أبو بكر ‏.‏ فقلت يا رسول الله هذا أبو
بكر يستأذن ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ائذن له وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فدخل وبشرته
بالجنة وجاء رجل آخر فضرب الباب فقلت من هذا فقال عمر ‏.‏ فقلت يا
رسول الله هذا عمر يستأذن ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ افتح له وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ففتحت الباب ودخل وبشرته بالجنة فجاء رجل آخر فضرب الباب فقلت من هذا
قال عثمان ‏.‏ فقلت يا رسول الله هذا عثمان يستأذن ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ افتح
له وبشره بالجنة على بلوى تصيبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن
صحيح ‏.‏ وقد روي من غير وجه عن أبي عثمان النهدي ‏.‏ وفي الباب عن
جابر وابن عمر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa Al-Ash'ari: "I went with the
Prophet (ﷺ) and he entered a garden of the Ansar, and he relieved
himself. He said to me: 'O Abu Musa! Watch the gate for me, and do
not let anyone enter except with permission.' Then a man came and
knocked at the gate, so I said: 'Who is it?' He said: 'Abu Bakr.'
So I said: 'O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)! It is Abu Bakr asking
permission?' He said: 'Give him permission and give him the glad
tidings of Paradise.' So he entered, and I gave him the glad
tidings of Paradise. Another man came and knocked at the gate. I
said: 'Who is it?' He said: "'Umar.' So I said: 'O Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ)! It is 'Umar asking permission?' He said: 'Open it for
him, and give him the glad tidings of Paradise.' I opened [the
gate], he entered, and I gave him the glad tidings of Paradise.
Then another man knocked at the gate. I said: 'Who is it?' So he
said: ''Uthman.' I said: 'O Messenger of Allah! It is 'Uthman
asking permission.' He said: 'Open it for him, and give him the
glad tidings of Paradise due to a calamity that will befall
him.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
