<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33965</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4080</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>35047, 11858, 11067, 11334</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سفيان بن وكيع، حدثنا أبي، عن شريك، عن منصور، عن
ربعي بن حراش، حدثنا علي بن أبي طالب، بالرحبة قال لما كان يوم
الحديبية خرج إلينا ناس من المشركين فيهم سهيل بن عمرو وأناس من رؤساء
المشركين فقالوا يا رسول الله خرج إليك ناس من أبنائنا وإخواننا
وأرقائنا وليس لهم فقه في الدين وإنما خرجوا فرارا من أموالنا وضياعنا
فارددهم إلينا ‏.‏ ‏"‏ فإن لم يكن لهم فقه في الدين سنفقههم ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا معشر قريش لتنتهن أو ليبعثن
الله عليكم من يضرب رقابكم بالسيف على الدين قد امتحن الله قلبه على
الإيمان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا من هو يا رسول الله فقال له أبو بكر من هو يا
رسول الله وقال عمر من هو يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ هو خاصف النعل ‏"‏ ‏.‏
وكان أعطى عليا نعله يخصفها ثم التفت إلينا علي فقال إن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من كذب على متعمدا فليتبوأ مقعده من النار ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن صحيح غريب لا نعرفه إلا من حديث ربعي
عن علي ‏.‏ قال وسمعت الجارود يقول سمعت وكيعا يقول لم يكذب ربعي بن
حراش في الإسلام كذبة ‏.‏ وأخبرني محمد بن إسماعيل عن عبد الله بن أبي
الأسود قال سمعت عبد الرحمن بن مهدي يقول منصور بن المعتمر أثبت أهل
الكوفة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Rib'i bin Hirash: "At Ar-Rahbah, 'Ali
narrated us: 'On the Day of (the Pledge of) Hudaibiyah, some people
from the idolaters came out to us. Among them was Suhail bin 'Amr,
and some people among the heads of the idolaters. They said: "O
Messenger of Allah! People among our fathers, brothers, and slaves
have come to you, and they have no knowledge of the religion,
rather they came fleeing from our wealth and property, so return
them to us. If they do not have knowledge of the religion, then we
will teach them." So the Prophet (ﷺ) said: "O people of Quraish,
you will desist, or Allah will send upon you one who will chop your
necks with the sword over the religion. Allah has tested their
hearts regarding faith." They said: "Who is he O Messenger of
Allah?" Abu Bakr said to him: "Who is he O Messenger of Allah?"
'Umar said to him: "Who is he O Messenger of Allah?" He said: "He
is the one repairing the sandals." - And he had given 'Ali his
sandals to repair them. - He said: "Then 'Ali turned to us and
said: 'Indeed the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: "Whoever lies upon
me intentionally, then let him take his seat in the
Fire."</english-text>
</hadith>
