<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>33962</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4077</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20532, 11319, 11305, 123</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا جعفر بن سليمان الضبعي، عن يزيد
الرشك، عن مطرف بن عبد الله، عن عمران بن حصين، قال بعث رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم جيشا واستعمل عليهم علي بن أبي طالب فمضى في السرية
فأصاب جارية فأنكروا عليه وتعاقد أربعة من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقالوا إذا لقينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرناه بما
صنع علي وكان المسلمون إذا رجعوا من السفر بدءوا برسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فسلموا عليه ثم انصرفوا إلى رحالهم فلما قدمت السرية سلموا
على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقام أحد الأربعة فقال يا رسول الله ألم
تر إلى علي بن أبي طالب صنع كذا وكذا ‏.‏ فأعرض عنه رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ثم قام الثاني فقال مثل مقالته فأعرض عنه ثم قام إليه
الثالث فقال مثل مقالته فأعرض عنه ثم قام الرابع فقال مثل ما قالوا
فأقبل إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والغضب يعرف في وجهه فقال
‏"‏ ما تريدون من علي ما تريدون من علي ما تريدون من علي إن عليا مني
وأنا منه وهو ولي كل مؤمن بعدي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن
غريب لا نعرفه إلا من حديث جعفر بن سليمان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Imran bin Husain: that the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) dispatched an army and he put 'Ali bin Abi Talib in
charge of it. He left on the expedition and he entered upon a
female slave. So four of the Companions of the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) scolded him, and they made a pact saying: "[If] we meet the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) we will inform him of what 'Ali did." When
the Muslims returned from the journey, they would begin with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and give him Salam, then they would go to
their homes. So when the expedition arrived, they gave Salam to the
Prophet (ﷺ), and one of the four stood saying: "O Messenger of
Allah! Do you see that 'Ali bin Abi Talib did such and such." The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) turned away from him. Then the second one
stood and said as he said, and he turned away from him. Then the
third stood before him, and said as he said, and he turned away
from him. Then the fourth stood and said as they had said. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) faced him, and the anger was visible on his
face, he said: "What do you want from 'Ali?! What do you want from
'Ali?! Indeed 'Ali is from me, and I am from him, and he is the
ally of every believer after me."</english-text>
</hadith>
