<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>34093</id>
<source>Jami' al-Tirmidhi</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4208</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Virtues - كتاب المناقب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30025, 30296, 20672, 11107, 11213</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن الدارمي، أخبرنا أحمد بن
سعيد الحراني، حدثني محمد بن سلمة الحراني، عن محمد بن إسحاق، عن محمد
بن إبراهيم، عن مالك بن أبي عامر، قال جاء رجل إلى طلحة بن عبيد الله
فقال يا أبا محمد أرأيت هذا اليماني يعني أبا هريرة هو أعلم بحديث
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منكم نسمع منه ما لا نسمع منكم أو يقول
على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما لم يقل ‏.‏ قال أما أن يكون سمع
من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما لم نسمع فلا أشك إلا أنه سمع من
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما لم نسمع وذاك أنه كان مسكينا لا شىء
له ضيفا لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده مع يد رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وكنا نحن أهل بيوتات وغنى وكنا نأتي رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم طرفى النهار فلا نشك إلا أنه سمع من رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ما لم نسمع ولا نجد أحدا فيه خير يقول على رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ما لم يقل ‏.‏ قال أبو عيسى هذا حديث حسن غريب لا
نعرفه إلا من حديث محمد بن إسحاق ‏.‏ وقد رواه يونس بن بكير وغيره عن
محمد بن إسحاق ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Malik bin Abi 'Amir: "A man came to Talhah
bin 'Ubaidullah and said: 'O Abu Muhammad, do you see this Yemeni -
meaning: Abu Hurairah - is he more knowledgeable of Ahadith of the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) than you? We hear from him what we do not
hear from you, or does he attribute to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
what he did not say?' He said: 'As for his having heard from the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) what we did not hear from him, then that is
because he was poor, having nothing, a guest of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ), his hand was in the hand of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).
And we used to be people of houses and wealth, and we used to come
to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) at the two ends of the day. I do not
doubt that he heard from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) what we did not
hear, and you will not find anyone in whom there is good
attributing to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) what he did not
say.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
