<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40082</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>82</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Purification - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>11213, 20212, 11071, 11052, 11373, 166, 11035,
166</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن إبراهيم البصري، عن بشر بن المفضل، عن
ابن عون، عن عامر الشعبي، عن عروة بن المغيرة، عن المغيرة، وعن محمد
بن سيرين، عن رجل، حتى رده إلى المغيرة - قال ابن عون ولا أحفظ حديث
ذا من حديث ذا - أن المغيرة قال كنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في سفر فقرع ظهري بعصا كانت معه فعدل وعدلت معه حتى أتى كذا وكذا من
الأرض فأناخ ثم انطلق ‏.‏ قال فذهب حتى توارى عني ثم جاء فقال ‏"‏
أمعك ماء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ومعي سطيحة لي فأتيته بها فأفرغت عليه فغسل يديه
ووجهه وذهب ليغسل ذراعيه وعليه جبة شامية ضيقة الكمين فأخرج يده من
تحت الجبة فغسل وجهه وذراعيه وذكر من ناصيته شيئا وعمامته شيئا - قال
ابن عون لا أحفظ كما أريد ثم مسح على خفيه - ثم قال ‏"‏ حاجتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قلت يا رسول الله ليست لي حاجة فجئنا وقد أم الناس عبد الرحمن بن عوف
وقد صلى بهم ركعة من صلاة الصبح فذهبت لأوذنه فنهاني فصلينا ما أدركنا
وقضينا ما سبقنا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Mughirah said: "We were with the Prophet (ﷺ) on a
journey, and he tapped me on the back with a stick he had with him,
then he turned off (route) and I turned off with him until he came
to such and such an area. Then he made his camel stop and went away
until he disappeared from me, then he came back and said: 'Do you
have water with you?' I had a water skin with me, so I brought it
out and poured it for him. He washed his hands and face and began
to wash his arms, but he was wearing a Syrian Jubbah[1] that had
narrow sleeves, so he brought his arms out from beneath the Jubbah
and washed his hands and arms, and wiped his forelock a little and
his turban a little." - Ibn 'Awn said: "I cannot remember it well -
then he wiped over his Khuffs." Then he said: 'What do you need?' I
said: 'O Messenger of Allah, I do not need anything.' Then we came
and 'Abdur-Rahman bin 'Awf was leading the people in Salah, and he
had led them in one Rak'ah of the Subh (Fajr) prayer. I wanted to
tell him that the Prophet (ﷺ) had arrived but he did not let me, so
we prayed what we had caught up with and made up what we had
missed.'"[1] It is a type of cloak.</english-text>
</hadith>
