<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40309</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>1</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>309</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Purification - كتاب الطهارة</chapter>
<chain-index>30185, 30463, 20593, 11049, 11382</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا أحمد بن عثمان بن حكيم، قال حدثنا خالد، - يعني
ابن مخلد - قال حدثنا علي، - وهو ابن صالح - عن أبي إسحاق، عن عمرو بن
ميمون، قال حدثنا عبد الله، في بيت المال قال كان رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يصلي عند البيت وملأ من قريش جلوس وقد نحروا جزورا فقال
بعضهم أيكم يأخذ هذا الفرث بدمه ثم يمهله حتى يضع وجهه ساجدا فيضعه -
يعني - على ظهره قال عبد الله فانبعث أشقاها فأخذ الفرث فذهب به ثم
أمهله فلما خر ساجدا وضعه على ظهره فأخبرت فاطمة بنت رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وهي جارية فجاءت تسعى فأخذته من ظهره فلما فرغ من
صلاته قال ‏"‏ اللهم عليك بقريش ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث مرات ‏"‏ اللهم عليك
بأبي جهل بن هشام وشيبة بن ربيعة وعتبة بن ربيعة وعقبة بن أبي معيط
‏"‏ ‏.‏ حتى عد سبعة من قريش ‏.‏ قال عبد الله فوالذي أنزل عليه
الكتاب لقد رأيتهم صرعى يوم بدر في قليب واحد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Amr bin Maimun said: "Abdullah
told us: 'The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was praying at the House (the
Ka'bah) and a group of the nobles of Quraish were sitting there.
They had just slaughtered a camel and one of them said: "Which of
you will take these stomach contents with the blood and wait until
he prostrates, then put them on his back?" 'Abdullah said: 'The one
who was most doomed got up and took the stomach contents, then went
and waited until he prostrated himself, and put it on his back.
Fatimah, the daughter of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), who was a
young girl, was told about that, and she came running and took it
off his back. When he had finished praying he said: "O Allah!
Punish the Quraish," three times, "O Allah, punish Abu Jahl bin
Hisham, Shaibah bin Rabi'ah, 'Utbah bin Rabi'ah, 'Uqbah bin Abi
Mu'ait" until he had listed seven men from Quraish.' 'Abdullah
said: 'By the One Who revealed the Book to him, I saw them dead on
the day of Badr (their corpses) in a single dry
well.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
