<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40370</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>369</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Menstruation and Istihadah - كتاب الحيض
والاستحاضة</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20193, 20021, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال أنبأنا سليمان بن حرب، قال
حدثنا حماد بن سلمة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، قال كانت اليهود إذا حاضت
المرأة منهم لم يؤاكلوهن ولا يشاربوهن ولا يجامعوهن في البيوت فسألوا
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ ويسألونك عن المحيض
قل هو أذى ‏}‏ الآية فأمرهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يؤاكلوهن
ويشاربوهن ويجامعوهن في البيوت وأن يصنعوا بهن كل شىء ما خلا الجماع
‏.‏ فقالت اليهود ما يدع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شيئا من أمرنا
إلا خالفنا ‏.‏ فقام أسيد بن حضير وعباد بن بشر فأخبرا رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قالا أنجامعهن في المحيض فتمعر رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم تمعرا شديدا حتى ظننا أنه قد غضب فقاما فاستقبل رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم هدية لبن فبعث في آثارهما فردهما فسقاهما فعرف أنه
لم يغضب عليهما ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Anas said: "When one of their
womenfolk menstruated, the Jews would not eat or drink with them,
or mix with them in their houses. They (the Companions) asked the
Prophet of Allah (ﷺ) about that, and Allah, the Mighty and Sublime,
revealed the Ayah: They ask you concerning menstruation. Say: "That
is an Adha (a harmful thing).[2] So the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
commanded them to eat and drink with them (menstruating women) and
to mix them in their houses, and to do everything with them except
intercourse. The Jews said: 'The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) does not
leave anything of our affairs except he goes against it.' Usaid bin
Hudair and 'Abbad bin Bishr went and told the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) and they said: 'Should we have intercourse with them when they
are menstruating?' The expression of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
changed greatly until we thought he was angry with them, and they
left. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) received a gift of milk, so
he sent someone to bring them back and he gave them some to drink,
so we knew that he was not angry with them."[1] Al-Baqarah 2:222[2]
Al-Baqarah 2:222</english-text>
</hadith>
