<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40523</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>524</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Times (of Prayer) - كتاب
المواقيت</chapter>
<chain-index>38434, 20462, 20012, 11374, 10916, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني عمرو بن هشام، قال حدثنا مخلد بن يزيد، عن سفيان
الثوري، عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن أبيه، قال جاء رجل
إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسأله عن وقت الصلاة فقال ‏"‏ أقم
معنا هذين اليومين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأمر بلالا فأقام عند الفجر فصلى الفجر ثم
أمره حين زالت الشمس فصلى الظهر ثم أمره حين رأى الشمس بيضاء فأقام
العصر ثم أمره حين وقع حاجب الشمس فأقام المغرب ثم أمره حين غاب الشفق
فأقام العشاء ثم أمره من الغد فنور بالفجر ثم أبرد بالظهر وأنعم أن
يبرد ثم صلى العصر والشمس بيضاء وأخر عن ذلك ثم صلى المغرب قبل أن
يغيب الشفق ثم أمره فأقام العشاء حين ذهب ثلث الليل فصلاها ثم قال ‏"‏
أين السائل عن وقت الصلاة وقت صلاتكم ما بين ما رأيتم ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Sulaiman bin Buraidah that his
father said: "A man came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and asked
him about the times of prayer. He said: 'Stay with us for these two
days.' Then he told Bilal to say the Iqamah at dawn and he prayed
Fajr. Then he told him to do that when the sun had passed its
zenith and he prayed Zuhr. Then he told him to do that when the sun
was still bright, and he said the Iqamah for 'Asr. Then he told him
to do that when the last part of the sun had dissapeared, and he
said the Iqamah for Maghrib. Then he told him to do that when the
twilight had disappeared and he said the Iqamah for 'Isha'. The
following day, he prayed Fajr when there was light, then he delayed
Zuhr until it was cooler, and waited until it was much cooler
before praying 'Asr but the sun was still clear, so he prayed 'Asr
later than on the first day. Then he prayed Maghrib before the
twilight disappeared. Then he told him to say the Iqamah for 'Isha'
when one-third of the night had passed, and he prayed, then he
said: 'Where is the one who was asking about the times of prayer?
The times of your prayer are between the times you have
seen.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
