<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40527</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>528</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Times (of Prayer) - كتاب
المواقيت</chapter>
<chain-index>30149, 38022, 20547, 10745</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبدة بن عبد الله، وأحمد بن سليمان، - واللفظ له
- قالا حدثنا أبو داود، عن بدر بن عثمان، قال إملاء على حدثنا أبو بكر
بن أبي موسى، عن أبيه، قال أتى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم سائل يسأله
عن مواقيت الصلاة فلم يرد عليه شيئا فأمر بلالا فأقام بالفجر حين انشق
ثم أمره فأقام بالظهر حين زالت الشمس والقائل يقول انتصف النهار وهو
أعلم ثم أمره فأقام بالعصر والشمس مرتفعة ثم أمره فأقام بالمغرب حين
غربت الشمس ثم أمره فأقام بالعشاء حين غاب الشفق ثم أخر الفجر من الغد
حين انصرف والقائل يقول طلعت الشمس ثم أخر الظهر إلى قريب من وقت
العصر بالأمس ثم أخر العصر حتى انصرف والقائل يقول احمرت الشمس ثم أخر
المغرب حتى كان عند سقوط الشفق ثم أخر العشاء إلى ثلث الليل ثم قال
‏"‏ الوقت فيما بين هذين ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Bakr bin Abi Musa narrated that his father said:
"A man came to the Prophet (ﷺ) asking him about the times of
prayer, and he did not answer him. He told Bilal to say the Iqamah
at dawn broke, then he told him to say the Iqamah for Zuhr when the
sun had passed its zenith and a person would say: 'It is the middle
of the day,' but he (the Prophet (ﷺ)) knew better. Then he told him
to say the Iqamah for 'Asr when the sun was still high. Then he
told him to say the Iqamah for Maghrib when the sun had set. Then
he told him to say the Iqamah for 'Isha' when the twilight had
dissapeared. Then the next day he told him to say the Iqamah for
Fajr, at a time such that when after he had finished one would say:
'The sun has risen.' Then he delayed Zuhr until it was nearly the
time of 'Asr compared to the day before. Then he delayed 'Asr, to a
time such that when he finished one would say: 'The su has turned
red.' Then he delayed Maghrib until the twilight was about to
disappear. Then he delayed 'Isha' until one-third of the night had
passed. Then he said: 'The time (for prayer) is between these
times.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
