<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40578</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>579</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Times (of Prayer) - كتاب
المواقيت</chapter>
<chain-index>38433, 20404, 20023, 20675, 4002</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمرو بن منصور، قال أنبأنا آدم بن أبي إياس، قال
حدثنا الليث بن سعد، قال حدثنا معاوية بن صالح، قال أخبرني أبو يحيى،
سليم بن عامر وضمرة بن حبيب وأبو طلحة نعيم بن زياد قالوا سمعنا أبا
أمامة الباهلي، يقول سمعت عمرو بن عبسة، يقول قلت يا رسول الله هل من
ساعة أقرب من الأخرى أو هل من ساعة يبتغى ذكرها قال ‏"‏ نعم إن أقرب
ما يكون الرب عز وجل من العبد جوف الليل الآخر فإن استطعت أن تكون ممن
يذكر الله عز وجل في تلك الساعة فكن فإن الصلاة محضورة مشهودة إلى
طلوع الشمس فإنها تطلع بين قرنى الشيطان وهي ساعة صلاة الكفار فدع
الصلاة حتى ترتفع قيد رمح ويذهب شعاعها ثم الصلاة محضورة مشهودة حتى
تعتدل الشمس اعتدال الرمح بنصف النهار فإنها ساعة تفتح فيها أبواب
جهنم وتسجر فدع الصلاة حتى يفيء الفىء ثم الصلاة محضورة مشهودة حتى
تغيب الشمس فإنها تغيب بين قرنى شيطان وهي صلاة الكفار ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Yahya Sulaim bin 'Amir, Damrah bin Habib and Abu
Talhah Nu'aim bin Ziyad said: "We heard Abu Umamah Al-Bahili say:
'I heard 'Amrah bin 'Abasah say: I said: 'O Messenger of Allah, is
there any moment which brings one close to Allah than another, or
any moment that should be sought out for remembering Allah? He
said: 'Yes, the closest that the Lord is to His slave is in the
last part of the night, so if you can be among those who remember
Allah at that time, then do so. For prayer is attended and
witnessed (by the angels) until the sun rises, then it rises
between the two horns of the Shaitan, that is the time when the
disbelievers pray, so do not pray until the sun had risen to the
height of a spear and its rays have disappeared. Then prayer is
attended and witness (by the angels) until the sun is directly
overhead at midday, and that is the time when the gates of Hell are
opened and it is stoked up. So do not pray until the shadows
appear. Then prayer is attended and witnessed (by angels) until the
sun sets, and it sets between the horns of a Shaitan, and that is
the time when the disbelievers pray.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
