<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40594</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>595</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Times (of Prayer) - كتاب
المواقيت</chapter>
<chain-index>30448, 20304, 11011</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الله بن بزيع، قال حدثنا يزيد بن
زريع، قال حدثنا كثير بن قاروندا، قال سألت سالم بن عبد الله عن صلاة،
أبيه في السفر وسألناه هل كان يجمع بين شىء من صلاته في سفره فذكر أن
صفية بنت أبي عبيد كانت تحته فكتبت إليه وهو في زراعة له أني في آخر
يوم من أيام الدنيا وأول يوم من الآخرة ‏.‏ فركب فأسرع السير إليها
حتى إذا حانت صلاة الظهر قال له المؤذن الصلاة يا أبا عبد الرحمن ‏.‏
فلم يلتفت حتى إذا كان بين الصلاتين نزل فقال أقم فإذا سلمت فأقم ‏.‏
فصلى ثم ركب حتى غابت الشمس قال له المؤذن الصلاة ‏.‏ فقال كفعلك في
صلاة الظهر والعصر ‏.‏ ثم سار حتى إذا اشتبكت النجوم نزل ثم قال
للمؤذن أقم فإذا سلمت فأقم ‏.‏ فصلى ثم انصرف فالتفت إلينا فقال قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إذا حضر أحدكم الأمر الذي يخاف فوته
فليصل هذه الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Kathir bin Qarawanda said: "I asked Salim bin
'Abdullah about how his father prayed when traveling. We asked him:
'Did he combine any of his prayers when traveling?' He said that
Safiyyah bint Abi 'Ubaid was married to him, and she wrote to him,
when he was at some farmland of his, saying: 'This is the last of
my days in this world, and the first day of the Hereafter." [1] He
rode quickly to go to her, and when the time for Zuhr came, the
Mu'adhdhin said to him: "The prayer, O Abu 'Abdur-Rahman!" But he
paid no attention to him until it was between the time for the two
prayers, then he stopped and said: "Say the Iqamah and when I say
the Taslim, say the Iqamah." Then he rode on again, and when the
sun set the Mu'adhdhin said to him; "The prayer!" He said: "Do as
you did for Zuhr and 'Asr." When the stars had appeared, he stopped
and said to the Mu'adhdhin: "Say the Iqamah and when I say the
Taslim, say the Iqamah." He prayed, then when he had finished he
turned to us and said: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'If any
one of you has an urgent need that he fears he may miss, let him
pray like this.'"[1] Meaning that she was dying.</english-text>
</hadith>
