<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40603</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>604</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Times (of Prayer) - كتاب
المواقيت</chapter>
<chain-index>38366, 11011</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبدة بن عبد الرحيم، قال حدثنا ابن شميل، قال
حدثنا كثير بن قاروندا، قال سألنا سالم بن عبد الله عن الصلاة، في
السفر فقلنا أكان عبد الله يجمع بين شىء من الصلوات في السفر فقال لا
إلا بجمع ثم أتيته فقال كانت عنده صفية فأرسلت إليه أني في آخر يوم من
الدنيا وأول يوم من الآخرة ‏.‏ فركب وأنا معه فأسرع السير حتى حانت
الصلاة فقال له المؤذن الصلاة يا أبا عبد الرحمن ‏.‏ فسار حتى إذا كان
بين الصلاتين نزل فقال للمؤذن أقم فإذا سلمت من الظهر فأقم مكانك ‏.‏
فأقام فصلى الظهر ركعتين ثم سلم ثم أقام مكانه فصلى العصر ركعتين ثم
ركب فأسرع السير حتى غابت الشمس فقال له المؤذن الصلاة يا أبا عبد
الرحمن ‏.‏ فقال كفعلك الأول ‏.‏ فسار حتى إذا اشتبكت النجوم نزل فقال
أقم فإذا سلمت فأقم ‏.‏ فصلى المغرب ثلاثا ثم أقام مكانه فصلى العشاء
الآخرة ثم سلم واحدة تلقاء وجهه ثم قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إذا حضر أحدكم أمر يخشى فوته فليصل هذه الصلاة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Kathir bin Qarawanda said: "We asked Salim bin
'Abdullah about prayer while traveling. We said: 'Did 'Abdullah
combine any of his prayer while traveling?' He said: 'No, except at
Jam'.'[1] Then he paused, and said: 'Safiyyah was married to him,
and she sent word to him that she was in her last day in this world
and the first day in the Hereafter. So he ride off in a hurry, and
I was with him. The time for prayer came and the Mu'adhdhin said to
him: 'The prayer, O Abu 'Abdur-Rahman! But he kept going until it
was between the time for the two prayer. Then he stopped and said
to the Mu'adhdhin: "Say the Iqamah, and when I say the Taslim at
the end of Zuhr, say the Iqamah (again) straight away." So he said
the Iqamah and he prayed Zuhr, two Rak'ahs, then he said the Iqamah
(again) straight away, and he prayed 'Asr, two Rak'ahs. Then he
rode off quickly until the sun set and the Mu'adhdhin said to him:
"The prayer, O Abu 'Abdur-Rahman!" He said: "Do what you did
before." He rode on until the starts appeared, then he stopped and
said: "Say the Iqamah, then when I say the Taslim, say the Iqamah.
So he said the Iqamah and he prayed Maghrib, three Rak'ahs, then he
said the Iqamah (again) straight away and he prayed 'Isha', then he
said one Taslim, turning his face. Then he said: "The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) said: 'If any one of you has urgent need that he fears he
may miss, let him pray like this.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
