<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40639</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>640</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Adhan (The Call to Prayer) - كتاب
الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>38070, 20219, 11070, 2416</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إبراهيم بن الحسن، قال حدثنا حجاج، عن ابن جريج،
عن عثمان بن السائب، قال أخبرني أبي وأم عبد الملك بن أبي محذورة، عن
أبي محذورة، قال لما خرج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من حنين خرجت
عاشر عشرة من أهل مكة نطلبهم فسمعناهم يؤذنون بالصلاة فقمنا نؤذن
نستهزئ بهم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد سمعت في هؤلاء
تأذين إنسان حسن الصوت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأرسل إلينا فأذنا رجل رجل وكنت آخرهم
فقال حين أذنت ‏"‏ تعال ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأجلسني بين يديه فمسح على ناصيتي
وبرك على ثلاث مرات ثم قال ‏"‏ اذهب فأذن عند البيت الحرام ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قلت كيف يا رسول الله فعلمني كما تؤذنون الآن بها ‏"‏ الله أكبر الله
أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا
الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن لا إله
إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن
محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة حى على الصلاة حى على الفلاح حى على
الفلاح الصلاة خير من النوم الصلاة خير من النوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ في الأولى من
الصبح قال وعلمني الإقامة مرتين ‏"‏ الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر
الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن
محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة حى على الصلاة
حى على الفلاح حى على الفلاح قد قامت الصلاة قد قامت الصلاة الله أكبر
الله أكبر لا إله إلا الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن جريج أخبرني عثمان هذا
الخبر كله عن أبيه وعن أم عبد الملك بن أبي محذورة أنهما سمعا ذلك من
أبي محذورة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Mahdhurah said: "When the
Messenger of Allah left Hunain, I was the tenth of a group of ten
of the people of Makkah who were trying to catch up with them. We
heard them calling the Adhan for the prayer and we started to
repeat the Adhan, mocking them. The Messenger of Allah said, 'I
heard among these people the Adhan of one who has a beautiful
voice.' He sent for us, and we recited the Adhan one by one, and I
was the last of them. When I said the Adhan, he said: 'Come here.'
He sat me down in front of him and rubbed my forelock and blessed
me three times, then he said, 'Go and give the Adhan at the sacred
House.' I said: 'How, O Messenger of Allah?' He taught me as you
say the Adhan now: 'Allahu Akbar, Allahu akbar, Allahu Akbar,
Allahu Akbar; Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah, Ashhadu an la ilaha
illallah; Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah, Ashhadu anna
Muhammadan Rasulallah, Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah, Ashhadu an la
ilaha illallah; Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah, Ashhadu anna
Muhammadan Rasulallah; Hayya 'alas-salah, Hayya 'ala-salah; Hayya
'alal-falah Hayya 'alal-falah; as-salatu khairun min
an-nawm;as-salatu khairun min an-nawm; (Allah is the Greatest,Allah
is the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest; I
bear witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah, I
bear witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah; I
bear witness that Muhammad is the Messenger Allah,I bear witness
that Muhammad is the Messenger Allah; I bear witness that there is
none worthy of worship except Allah, I bear witness that there is
none worthy of worship except Allah; I bear witness that Muhammad
is the Messenger of Allah, I bear witness that Muhammad is the
Messenger of Allah; Come to prayer, come to prayer; come to
prosperity, come to prosperity; prayer is better than sleep, prayer
is better than sleep)' - in the first (Adhan) for As-Subh (Fajr).
And he taught me the Iqamah saying each phrase twice: 'Allahu
Akbar, Allahu Akbar, (Allahu Akbar, Allahu Akbar), Ashhadu an la
ilaha illallah, Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah; Ashhadu anna
Muhammadan Rasulallah, Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah; Hayya
'alas-salah, Hayya 'alas-salah; Hayya 'alal-falah, Hayya
'alal-falah; qad qamatis-salah, qad qamati-salah, Allahu Akbar,
Allahu Akbar La ilaha illallah (Allah is the Greatest, Allah is the
Greatest, (Allah is the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest); I bear
witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah, I bear
witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah ; I bear
witness that Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah, I bear witness
that Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah; Come to prayer, come to
prayer; come to prosperity, come to prosperity; the prayer is about
to begin, the prayer is about to begin, Allah is the Greatest,Allah
is the Greatest; there is none worthy of worship except
Allah)."(One of the narrators) Ibn Juraij said:''Uthmin narrated
this whole reportto me from his father and from Umm'Abdul-Malik bin
Abi Mahafirah,and (said that) they heard that fromAbu
Mahdhurah.</english-text>
</hadith>
