<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40638</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>7</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>639</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Adhan (The Call to Prayer) - كتاب
الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>38070, 20219, 11070, 19832, 11253</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إبراهيم بن الحسن، ويوسف بن سعيد، - واللفظ له -
قالا حدثنا حجاج، عن ابن جريج، قال حدثني عبد العزيز بن عبد الملك بن
أبي محذورة، أن عبد الله بن محيريز، أخبره - وكان، يتيما في حجر أبي
محذورة حتى جهزه إلى الشام - قال قلت لأبي محذورة إني خارج إلى الشام
وأخشى أن أسأل عن تأذينك فأخبرني أن أبا محذورة قال له خرجت في نفر
فكنا ببعض طريق حنين مقفل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من حنين
فلقينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في بعض الطريق فأذن مؤذن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالصلاة عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فسمعنا صوت المؤذن ونحن عنه متنكبون فظللنا نحكيه ونهزأ به فسمع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الصوت فأرسل إلينا حتى وقفنا بين يديه فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أيكم الذي سمعت صوته قد ارتفع ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأشار القوم إلى وصدقوا فأرسلهم كلهم وحبسني فقال ‏"‏ قم فأذن
بالصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقمت فألقى على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم التأذين
هو بنفسه قال ‏"‏ قل الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن
لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله
أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ارجع فامدد صوتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ قل أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد
أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة حى على
الصلاة حى على الفلاح حى على الفلاح الله أكبر الله أكبر لا إله إلا
الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم دعاني حين قضيت التأذين فأعطاني صرة فيها شىء من فضة
فقلت يا رسول الله مرني بالتأذين بمكة ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ قد أمرتك به ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقدمت على عتاب بن أسيد عامل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بمكة
فأذنت معه بالصلاة عن أمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Abdul-'Aziz bin 'Abdul-Malik bin Abu Mahdhurah
narrated that 'Abdullah bin Muhairiz - who was an orphan under the
care of Abu Mahdhurah until he prepared him to go to Ash-Sham -
informed him: he said: "I said to Abu Mahdhurah: 'I am going to
Ash-Sham and I am afraid that I will be asked about how you say the
Adhan."'He told me that Abu Mahdhurah said to him, I went out with
a group of people and we were somewhere on the road to Hunain when
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was coming back from Hunain. The
Messenger of Allah met us somewhere on the road and the Muadhdhin
of the Messenger of Allah called the Adhan for prayer in the
presence of the Messenger of Allah. We heard the voice of the
Muadh'dhin and we were careless about it (the Adhan), so we started
yelling, immitating and mocking it. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
heard us, so he sent some people who brought us to stand infront of
him. He said, 'Who is the one whose voice I heard so loud?' The
people all pointed to me, and they were telling the truth. He sent
them all away, but kept me there and said to me: 'Stand up and call
the Adhan for the Prayer.' I stood up and the Messenger of Allah
taught me the Adhan himself. He Said, 'Say: 'Allahu Akbar, Allahu
akbar, Allahu Akbar, Allahu Akbar; Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah,
Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah; Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah,
Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah (Allah is the Greatest,Allah is
the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest; I bear
witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah, I bear
witness that there is none worthy of worship except Allah; I bear
witness that Muhammad is the Messenger Allah,I bear witness that
Muhammad is the Messenger Allah).' Then he said: 'Then repeat and
say in a loud voice:Ashhadu an la ilaha illallah, Ashhadu an la
ilaha illallah; Ashhadu anna Muhammadan Rasulallah, Ashhadu anna
Muhammadan Rasulallah; Hayya 'alas-salah, Hayya 'ala-salah; Hayya
'alal-falah Hayya 'alal-falah; Allahu Akbar, Allahu Akbar; La ilaha
ill-Allah (I bear witness that there is none worthy of worship
except Allah, I bear witness that there is none worthy of worship
except Allah; I bear witness that Muhammad is the Messenger of
Allah, I bear witness that Muhammad is the Messenger of Allah; Come
to prayer, come to prayer; come to prosperity, come to prosperity;
Allah is the Greatest, Allah is the Greatest; there is none worthy
of worship except Allah).' Then he called me when I had finished
saying the Adhan, and hegave me a bundle in which there wassome
silver. I said: 'O Messenger of Allah, let me be the one doing the
Adhan in Makkah.' He said: 'I command you to do so.' Then I came to
'Attab bin Asid who was the governor of the Messenger of Allah in
Makkah, and I called theAdhan for prayer with him upon the orders
of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)."</english-text>
</hadith>
