<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40701</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>694</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Masjids - كتاب المساجد</chapter>
<chain-index>38462, 30373, 20459, 11013, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا كثير بن عبيد، قال حدثنا محمد بن حرب، عن
الزبيدي، عن الزهري، عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، وأبي عبد الله الأغر،
مولى الجهنيين وكانا من أصحاب أبي هريرة أنهما سمعا أبا هريرة يقول
صلاة في مسجد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أفضل من ألف صلاة فيما
سواه من المساجد إلا المسجد الحرام فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
آخر الأنبياء ومسجده آخر المساجد ‏.‏ قال أبو سلمة وأبو عبد الله لم
نشك أن أبا هريرة كان يقول عن حديث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فمنعنا أن نستثبت أبا هريرة في ذلك الحديث حتى إذا توفي أبو هريرة
ذكرنا ذلك وتلاومنا أن لا نكون كلمنا أبا هريرة في ذلك حتى يسنده إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إن كان سمعه منه فبينا نحن على ذلك
جالسنا عبد الله بن إبراهيم بن قارظ فذكرنا ذلك الحديث والذي فرطنا
فيه من نص أبي هريرة فقال لنا عبد الله بن إبراهيم أشهد أني سمعت أبا
هريرة يقول قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فإني آخر الأنبياء
وإنه آخر المساجد ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Salamah bin 'Abdur-Rahman
and Abu 'Abdullah Al-Agharr, the freed slave of the Juhanis -
better of whom were companions of Abu Hurairah - that they heard
Abu Hurairah say: "One prayer in the Masjid of the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) is better than one thousand prayers offered in other
mosques, except Al-Masjid Al-Haram, for the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
was the last of the prophets and his Masjid was the last of the
Masjids." Abu Salamah and Abu 'Abdullah said: "We do not doubt that
Abu Hurairah was speaking on the basis of the Hadith of the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), but we could not verify that Hadith with
Abu Hurairah before he died. Then we remembered that and we blamed
one another for not having spoken to Abu Hurairah about that, so
that he could attribute it to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) if he had
indeed heard it from him. While we were arguing, we went and sat
down with 'Abdullah bin Ibrahim bin Qariz, and we told him about
the Hadith and how we had been negligent in not checking it with
Abu Hurairah. 'Abdullah bin Ibrahim said to us: 'I bear witness
that I heard Abu Hurairah say: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: I
am the last of the prophets and it is the last of the
Masjids.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
