<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40746</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>739</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Masjids - كتاب المساجد</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20185, 19235</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا يعقوب بن عبد الرحمن، قال حدثني
أبو حازم بن دينار، أن رجالا، أتوا سهل بن سعد الساعدي وقد امتروا في
المنبر مم عوده فسألوه عن ذلك فقال والله إني لأعرف مم هو ولقد رأيته
أول يوم وضع وأول يوم جلس عليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أرسل
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى فلانة امرأة قد سماها سهل ‏"‏ أن
مري غلامك النجار أن يعمل لي أعوادا أجلس عليهن إذا كلمت الناس ‏"‏
‏.‏ فأمرته فعملها من طرفاء الغابة ثم جاء بها فأرسلت إلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فأمر بها فوضعت ها هنا ثم رأيت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم رقي فصلى عليها وكبر وهو عليها ثم ركع وهو عليها ثم نزل
القهقرى فسجد في أصل المنبر ثم عاد فلما فرغ أقبل على الناس فقال ‏"‏
يا أيها الناس إنما صنعت هذا لتأتموا بي ولتعلموا صلاتي ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Hazim bin Dinar narrated that some men came to
Sahl bin Sa'd As-Sa'idi. They were wondering what kind of wood the
Minbar was made of, so they asked him about that. He said: "By
Allah, I know what it is made of. I saw it the first day it was set
up and the first day the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sat on it. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) sent word to so-and-so" - a woman whose name
Sahl mentioned - "telling her: 'Tell your carpenter slave to make
me something of wood that I can sit on when I speak to the people.'
So she told him, and he made it from tamarisk wood from Al-Ghabah
(a place near Al-Madinah). Then he brought it and it was sent to
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), who commanded that it be set up here.
Then I saw the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) ascend it and praying on it,
and saying the Takbir while he was on top of it, then he bowed when
he was on top of it, then he came down backward and prostrated at
the base of the Minbar, then he went back. When he had finished he
turned to face the people and said: 'O people, I only did this so
that you can follow me in prayer and learn how I
pray.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
