<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40800</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>793</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Leading the Prayer (Al-Imamah) - كتاب
الإمامة</chapter>
<chain-index>30423, 20022, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا أحمد بن عبدة، عن حماد بن زيد، ثم ذكر كلمة
معناها قال حدثنا أبو حازم، قال سهل بن سعد كان قتال بين بني عمرو بن
عوف فبلغ ذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى الظهر ثم أتاهم ليصلح
بينهم ثم قال لبلال ‏"‏ يا بلال إذا حضر العصر ولم آت فمر أبا بكر
فليصل بالناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما حضرت أذن بلال ثم أقام فقال لأبي بكر رضى
الله عنه تقدم ‏.‏ فتقدم أبو بكر فدخل في الصلاة ثم جاء رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فجعل يشق الناس حتى قام خلف أبي بكر وصفح القوم وكان
أبو بكر إذا دخل في الصلاة لم يلتفت فلما رأى أبو بكر التصفيح لا يمسك
عنه التفت فأومأ إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بيده فحمد الله عز
وجل على قول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم له امضه ثم مشى أبو بكر
القهقرى على عقبيه فتأخر فلما رأى ذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
تقدم فصلى بالناس فلما قضى صلاته قال ‏"‏ يا أبا بكر ما منعك إذ أومأت
إليك أن لا تكون مضيت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال لم يكن لابن أبي قحافة أن يؤم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وقال للناس ‏"‏ إذا نابكم شىء فليسبح
الرجال وليصفح النساء ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Sahl bin Sa'd said: "There was some fighting among
Banu 'Amr bin 'Ad, and news of that reached the Prophet (ﷺ). He
prayed Zuhr, then he went to them to reconcile between them. Then
he said to Bilal: '0 Bilal, if the time for Asr comes and I have
not come back, then tell Abu Bakr to lead the people in prayer.'
When thetime (for Asr) came, Bilil called the A&amp;Bn, then the
Iqimh, then he said to Abu Bakr: 'Go forward. So Abu Bakr went
forward and started to pray. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came
and started passing through the rows of people until he stood
behind Abu Bakr, and the people clapped. Abu Bakr was such that
whenever he started praying, he would never glance sideways, but
when he noticed that the clapping persisted he turned around. The
Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) gestured to him to carry on praying. Abu Bakr
praised Allah the Mighty and Sublime for the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
having told him to continue. Then Abu Bakr moved backward on his
heels, and when the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) saw that, he came foiward
and led the people in prayer. When he completed the prayer he said:
'0Abu Bakr, when I gestured to you, what kept you from continuing
(to lead the people)?' He said: 'It does not befit the son of Abu
Quhafah to lead the Messenger of Alliah (ﷺ) in prayer.' And he (the
Prophet) said to the people: 'If you notice something (during the
prayer), men should say Subhan Allah and women should
clap."'</english-text>
</hadith>
