<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>40944</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>937</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Commencement of the Prayer - كتاب
الافتتاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 36017, 30234, 20001, 11013, 10511, 3195,
3</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، والحارث بن مسكين، قراءة عليه وأنا
أسمع، - واللفظ له - عن ابن القاسم، قال حدثني مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عروة بن الزبير، عن عبد الرحمن بن عبد القاري، قال سمعت عمر بن
الخطاب، - رضى الله عنه - يقول سمعت هشام بن حكيم، يقرأ سورة الفرقان
على غير ما أقرؤها عليه وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أقرأنيها
فكدت أن أعجل عليه ثم أمهلته حتى انصرف ثم لببته بردائه فجئت به إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا رسول الله إني سمعت هذا يقرأ
سورة الفرقان على غير ما أقرأتنيها ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ اقرأ ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقرأ القراءة التي سمعته يقرأ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هكذا أنزلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال لي ‏"‏ اقرأ ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقرأت فقال ‏"‏ هكذا أنزلت إن هذا القرآن أنزل على سبعة أحرف ‏{‏
فاقرءوا ما تيسر منه ‏}‏ ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that AbdurRahman bin Abdul-Qari said:
"I heard Umar bin Al-Khattab, may Allah be pleased with him, say:
'I heard Hisham bin Hakim bin Hizam reciting Surat Al-Furqan, in a
way that I had not been taught, and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had
taught me. I was about to interrupt him (in his prayer), but I left
him alone until he had finished. Then I grabbed him by his garment
and brought him to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and said: 'O
Messenger of Allah, I heard this man reciting Surat Al-Furqan in a
way that you did not teach me.' The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to
him: 'Recite.' So he recited it in the way that I had heard him
recite. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'It was revealed like
this.' Then he said to me: 'Recite.' So I recited it and he said:
'It was revealed like this. This Quran has been revealed in seven
different modes, so recite as much of the Quran as may be easy for
you.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
