<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41060</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1053</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of The At-Tatbiq (Clasping One's Hands Together)
- كتاب التطبيق</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20374, 10616, 11710, 325, 323</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا بكر بن مضر، عن ابن عجلان، عن
علي بن يحيى الزرقي، عن أبيه، عن عمه، رفاعة بن رافع وكان بدريا قال
كنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ دخل رجل المسجد فصلى ورسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يرمقه ولا يشعر ثم انصرف فأتى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فسلم عليه فرد عليه السلام ثم قال ‏"‏ ارجع فصل فإنك
لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال لا أدري في الثانية أو في الثالثة قال والذي أنزل
عليك الكتاب لقد جهدت فعلمني وأرني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إذا أردت الصلاة فتوضأ
فأحسن الوضوء ثم قم فاستقبل القبلة ثم كبر ثم اقرأ ثم اركع حتى تطمئن
راكعا ثم ارفع حتى تعتدل قائما ثم اسجد حتى تطمئن ساجدا ثم ارفع رأسك
حتى تطمئن قاعدا ثم اسجد حتى تطمئن ساجدا فإذا صنعت ذلك فقد قضيت
صلاتك وما انتقصت من ذلك فإنما تنقصه من صلاتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Rifa'ah bin Rafi'- who had been
present at Badr- said: "We were with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
when a man entered the Masjid and prayed. The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) watched him without him realizing, then he finished, came to
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and greeted him with salam. He returned
the salam and said: "Go back and pray, for you have not prayed.'"
He (the narrator) said: "I do not know if it was the second or
third time,- "(the man) said: 'By the One Who revealed the Book to
you, I have tried my best. Teach me and show me.' He said: 'When
you want to pray, perform wudu' and do it well, then stand up and
face the qiblah. Then say the takbir, then recite, then bow until
you are at ease in bowing. Then stand up until you are standing up
straight. Then prostrate until you are at ease in prostration, then
raise your head until you are at ease in sitting, then prostrate
until you are at ease in prostration. If you do that then you will
have done your prayer properly, and whatever you failed to do
properly is going to detract from your prayer."</english-text>
</hadith>
