<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41143</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1136</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of The At-Tatbiq (Clasping One's Hands Together)
- كتاب التطبيق</chapter>
<chain-index>11447, 11151, 422, 323</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الله بن يزيد المقرئ أبو يحيى، بمكة
- وهو بصري - قال حدثنا أبي قال، حدثنا همام، قال حدثنا إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي طلحة، أن علي بن يحيى بن خلاد بن مالك بن رافع بن مالك،
حدثه عن أبيه، عن عمه، رفاعة بن رافع قال بينما رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم جالس ونحن حوله إذ دخل رجل فأتى القبلة فصلى فلما قضى صلاته
جاء فسلم على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وعلى القوم فقال له رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعليك اذهب فصل فإنك لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذهب
فصلى فجعل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يرمق صلاته ولا يدري ما يعيب
منها فلما قضى صلاته جاء فسلم على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وعلى
القوم فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وعليك اذهب فصل فإنك
لم تصل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأعادها مرتين أو ثلاثا فقال الرجل يا رسول الله ما
عبت من صلاتي فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنها لم تتم صلاة
أحدكم حتى يسبغ الوضوء كما أمره الله عز وجل فيغسل وجهه ويديه إلى
المرفقين ويمسح برأسه ورجليه إلى الكعبين ثم يكبر الله عز وجل ويحمده
ويمجده ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال همام وسمعته يقول ‏"‏ ويحمد الله ويمجده ويكبره
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فكلاهما قد سمعته يقول قال ‏"‏ ويقرأ ما تيسر من القرآن
مما علمه الله وأذن له فيه ثم يكبر ويركع حتى تطمئن مفاصله وتسترخي ثم
يقول سمع الله لمن حمده ثم يستوي قائما حتى يقيم صلبه ثم يكبر ويسجد
حتى يمكن وجهه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وقد سمعته يقول ‏"‏ جبهته حتى تطمئن مفاصله
وتسترخي ويكبر فيرفع حتى يستوي قاعدا على مقعدته ويقيم صلبه ثم يكبر
فيسجد حتى يمكن وجهه ويسترخي فإذا لم يفعل هكذا لم تتم صلاته ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Rifa'ah bin Rafi' said: "While
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was sitting with us around him, a man
came in, turned towards the Qiblah and prayed. When he had finished
his prayer, he came and greeted the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and the
people with Salam. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to him: 'And
also to you. Go and pray, for you have not prayed.' So he went and
prayed, and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) started watching him, and he
(the man) did not know what was wrong with it. When he had finished
the prayer, he came and greeted the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and the
people with salam. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said to him: 'And
also to you. Go and pray, for you have not prayed.' He repeated it
two or three times, then the man said: 'O Messenger of Allah, what
is wrong with my prayer?' The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'The
prayer of any of you is not complete unless he performs wudu
properly as enjoined by Allah, the Mighty and Sublime. So he should
wash his face, his arms up to the elbows, and wipe his head, and
(wash) his feet up to the ankles. Then he should magnify Allah
(SWT) and praise Him and glorify Him.'" - (One of the narrators)
Hammam said: "I heard him say: 'He should praise Allah and glorify
Him and magnify Him." He said: "I heard both of them." -"He (the
Prophet (ﷺ)) said: 'He should recite whatever is easy for him of
the Quran that Allah has taught him and permitted him in it (the
prayer). Then he should say the Takbir and bow until his joints
settle and he is relaxed. Then he should say: 'Sami Allahu liman
hamidah (Allah hears the one who praises Him)' and stand up
straight until his backbone is straight (and at ease). Then he
should say Takbir and prostrate until he has placed his face firmly
on the ground." "I heard him say: his forehead, until his joints
settle and he is relaxed. Then he should say the Takbir and sit up
until his backbone is straight (and at ease). Then he should
prostrate until he has placed his face firmly on the ground and he
is relaxed. If he does not do that then he has not completed his
prayer."</english-text>
</hadith>
