<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41179</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1172</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of The At-Tatbiq (Clasping One's Hands Together)
- كتاب التطبيق</chapter>
<chain-index>11062, 11065, 11019, 11320</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبيد الله بن سعيد أبو قدامة السرخسي، قال حدثنا
يحيى بن سعيد، قال حدثنا هشام، قال حدثني قتادة، عن يونس بن جبير، عن
حطان بن عبد الله، أن الأشعري، قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
خطبنا فعلمنا سنتنا وبين لنا صلاتنا فقال ‏"‏ أقيموا صفوفكم ثم ليؤمكم
أحدكم فإذا كبر فكبروا وإذا قال ‏{‏ ولا الضالين ‏}‏ فقولوا آمين
يجبكم الله وإذا كبر الإمام وركع فكبروا واركعوا فإن الإمام يركع
قبلكم ويرفع قبلكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فتلك
بتلك وإذا قال سمع الله لمن حمده فقولوا ربنا لك الحمد يسمع الله لكم
فإن الله عز وجل قال على لسان نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم سمع الله لمن
حمده ثم إذا كبر الإمام وسجد فكبروا واسجدوا فإن الإمام يسجد قبلكم
ويرفع قبلكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فتلك بتلك
فإذا كان عند القعدة فليكن من أول قول أحدكم أن يقول التحيات الطيبات
الصلوات لله السلام عليك أيها النبي ورحمة الله وبركاته السلام علينا
وعلى عباد الله الصالحين أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله وأشهد أن محمدا عبده
ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Hittan bin 'Abdullah that
Al-Ash'ari said: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) addressed us and
taught us our Sunnahs and our prayer. He said: 'Make your rows
straight, then let one of you lead the others. When he says the
takbir, then say the takbir; when he says: "Wa lad-dallin" then say
"Amin" and Allah (SWT) will answer you. When the Imam says the
takbir and bows, then say the takbir and bow, for the Imam bows
before you and stands up before you.' The Prophet of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'This makes up for that. When he says: 'Sami Allahu liman
hamidah (Allah hears the one who praises Him), say: "Rabbana wa
lakal-hamd (Our Lord, to You be praise)," Allah (SWT) will hear
you, for indeed Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, has said on the
tongue of His Prophet (ﷺ): "Allah hears the one who praises Him."
Then when the Imam says the takbir and prostrates, say the takbir
and prostrate, for the Imam prostrates before you and rises before
you.' The Prophet of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'This makes up for that. Then
when you are sitting, let the first thing that any one of you says
be: At-tahiyyatu lillahi was-salawatu wat-tayyibat, as-salamu
'alaika ayyuhan-Nabiyyu wa rahmatAllahi wa baraktuhu. As-salamu
'alaina wa 'ala 'ibad illahis-salihin, ashahdu an la illaha
ill-Allah wa ashhadu anna Muhammadan 'abduhu wa rasuluhu (Allah
compliments, prayers and pure words are due to Allah. Peace be upon
you, O Prophet, and the mercy of Allah (SWT) and his blessings.
Peace be upon us and upon the righteous slaves of Allah (SWT). I
bear witness that none has the right to be worshipped except Allah
and I bear witness that Muhammad is His slave and
Messenger)."</english-text>
</hadith>
