<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41190</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1183</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Forgetfulness (In Prayer) - كتاب
السهو</chapter>
<chain-index>30448, 20246, 11201, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الله بن بزيع، قال حدثنا عبد الأعلى
بن عبد الأعلى، قال حدثنا عبيد الله، - وهو ابن عمر - عن أبي حازم، عن
سهل بن سعد، قال انطلق رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلح بين بني
عمرو بن عوف فحضرت الصلاة فجاء المؤذن إلى أبي بكر فأمره أن يجمع
الناس ويؤمهم فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرق الصفوف حتى قام
في الصف المقدم وصفح الناس بأبي بكر ليؤذنوه برسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وكان أبو بكر لا يلتفت في الصلاة فلما أكثروا علم أنه قد نابهم
شىء في صلاتهم فالتفت فإذا هو برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأومأ
إليه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أى كما أنت فرفع أبو بكر يديه فحمد
الله وأثنى عليه لقول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم رجع القهقرى
وتقدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى فلما انصرف قال لأبي بكر ‏"‏
ما منعك إذ أومأت إليك أن تصلي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر رضى الله عنه ما
كان ينبغي لابن أبي قحافة أن يؤم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ ثم
قال للناس ‏"‏ ما بالكم صفحتم إنما التصفيح للنساء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏
إذا نابكم شىء في صلاتكم فسبحوا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Sahl bin Sa'd said: "The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) set out to bring about reconciliation among
Banu 'Amr bin 'Awf. The time for prayer came, and the Mu'adhdhin
went to Abu Bakr to tell him to gather the people and lead them in
prayer. Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came and passed though the
rows until he stood in the first row. The people started clapping
to let Abu Bakr know that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had come. Abu
Bakr never used to turn around when he prayed, but when they
clapped consistently he realized something must have happened while
they were praying. So he turned around and saw the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) gestured to him to stay where
he was. Abu Bakr raised his hands and praised and thanked Allah
(SWT) for what the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) had said. Then, he moved
backwards, and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) went forward and prayed.
When he finished, he said to Abu Bakr: 'What stopped you from
continuing to pray when I gestured to you?' Abu Bakr, may Allah
(SWT) be pleased with him, said: 'It was not appropriate for the
son of Abu Quhafah to lead the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) in prayer.'
Then he said to the people: 'Why did you clap?' Clapping is for
women.' Then he said: 'If you notice something when you are
praying, say "SubhanAllah.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
