<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41225</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1218</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Forgetfulness (In Prayer) - كتاب
السهو</chapter>
<chain-index>30313, 30388, 20024, 11449, 11229, 11020,
5300</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن منصور، قال حدثنا محمد بن يوسف، قال
حدثنا الأوزاعي، قال حدثني يحيى بن أبي كثير، عن هلال بن أبي ميمونة،
قال حدثني عطاء بن يسار، عن معاوية بن الحكم السلمي، قال قلت يا رسول
الله إنا حديث عهد بجاهلية فجاء الله بالإسلام وإن رجالا منا يتطيرون
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ذاك شىء يجدونه في صدورهم فلا يصدنهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ورجال منا
يأتون الكهان ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فلا تأتوهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله ورجال
منا يخطون ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ كان نبي من الأنبياء يخط فمن وافق خطه فذاك ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال وبينا أنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في الصلاة إذ عطس
رجل من القوم فقلت يرحمك الله فحدقني القوم بأبصارهم فقلت واثكل أمياه
ما لكم تنظرون إلى قال فضرب القوم بأيديهم على أفخاذهم فلما رأيتهم
يسكتوني لكني سكت فلما انصرف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دعاني بأبي
وأمي هو ما ضربني ولا كهرني ولا سبني ما رأيت معلما قبله ولا بعده
أحسن تعليما منه قال ‏"‏ إن صلاتنا هذه لا يصلح فيها شىء من كلام
الناس إنما هو التسبيح والتكبير وتلاوة القرآن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ثم اطلعت
إلى غنيمة لي ترعاها جارية لي في قبل أحد والجوانية وإني اطلعت فوجدت
الذئب قد ذهب منها بشاة وأنا رجل من بني آدم آسف كما يأسفون فصككتها
صكة ثم انصرفت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته فعظم ذلك على
فقلت يا رسول الله أفلا أعتقها قال ‏"‏ ادعها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال لها رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أين الله عز وجل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت في السماء
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فمن أنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت أنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إنها مؤمنة فاعتقها ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Mu'awiyah bin Al-Hakam As-Sulami
said: "I said: 'O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), we were recently in a
state of ignorance, then Allah (SWT) brought Islam. Some men among
us follow omens.' He said: 'That is something that they find in
their own hearts; it should not deter them from going ahead.' I
said: 'And some men among us go to fortune tellers.' He said: 'Do
not go to them.' He said: 'Some men among us draw lines.' He said:
'One of the Prophets used to draw lines. So whoever is in accord
with his drawing of lines, then so it is.'" He said: "While I was
praying with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), a man sneezed and I said:
'Yarhamuk-Allah (May Allah have mercy on you).' The people glared
at me and I said: 'May my mother be bereft of me, why are you
looking at me?' The people struck their hands against their thighs,
and when I saw that they were telling me to be quiet, I fell
silent. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) finished, he called me. May
my father and mother be ransomed for him, he neither did hit me nor
rebuke me nor revile me. I have never seen a better teacher than
him, before or after. He said: 'This prayer of ours is not the
place for ordinary human speech, rather it is glorification and
magnification of Allah (SWT), and reciting Qur'an.' Then I went out
to a flock of sheep of mine that was tended by a slave woman of
mine beside Uhud and Al-Jawwaniyyah, and I found that the wolf had
taken one of the sheep. I am a man from the sons of Adam and I get
upset as they get upset. So I slapped her. Then I came to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and told him what happened. He regarded that
as a serious action on my part. I said: 'O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ),
should I set her free?' He said: 'Call her.' The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) said to her: 'Where is Allah (SWT), the Mighty and Sublime?'
She said: 'Above the heavens.' He said: 'And who am I?' She said:
'The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).' He said: 'She is a believer, set her
free.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
