<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41287</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1280</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Forgetfulness (In Prayer) - كتاب
السهو</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20031, 11065, 11019, 30170, 20031, 11065,
11019, 11320</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن بشار، قال حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، عن هشام،
عن قتادة، ح وأنبأنا محمد بن المثنى، قال حدثنا يحيى، قال حدثنا هشام،
قال حدثنا قتادة، عن يونس بن جبير، عن حطان بن عبد الله، أن الأشعري،
قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خطبنا فعلمنا سنتنا وبين لنا
صلاتنا فقال ‏"‏ إذا قمتم إلى الصلاة فأقيموا صفوفكم ثم ليؤمكم أحدكم
فإذا كبر فكبروا وإذا قال ‏{‏ ولا الضالين ‏}‏ فقولوا آمين يجبكم الله
ثم إذا كبر وركع فكبروا واركعوا فإن الإمام يركع قبلكم ويرفع قبلكم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فتلك بتلك وإذا قال سمع
الله لمن حمده فقولوا اللهم ربنا لك الحمد فإن الله عز وجل قال على
لسان نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم سمع الله لمن حمده ثم إذا كبر وسجد
فكبروا واسجدوا فإن الإمام يسجد قبلكم ويرفع قبلكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نبي
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فتلك بتلك وإذا كان عند القعدة فليكن من
قول أحدكم أن يقول التحيات الطيبات الصلوات لله السلام عليك أيها
النبي ورحمة الله وبركاته السلام علينا وعلى عباد الله الصالحين أشهد
أن لا إله إلا الله وأشهد أن محمدا عبده ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Hittan bin 'Abdullah that
Al-Ash'ari said: "The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) addressed us and
taught us our Sunnahs and our prayer. He said: 'When you stand for
the prayer, make your rows straight, then let one of you lead the
others. When he says the takbir, then say the takbir; when he says
: "Wa lad-dallin" then say "Amin" and Allah (SWT) will answer you.
Then when he says the takbir and bows, then say the takbir and bow,
for the Imam bows before you and stands up before you.' The Prophet
of Allah (ﷺ) said: "This makes up for that. When he says: 'Sami'
Allahu liman hamidah (Allah hears the one who praises Him),' say:
'Allahumma, Rabbana wa lakal-hamd (O Allah, our Lord, to You be
praise),' Allah will hear you, for indeed Allah (SWT), the Mighty
and Sublime, has said on the tongue of His Prophet: "Allah hears
the one who praises Him." Then when he says the takbir and
prostrates, say the takbir and prostrate, for the Imam prostrates
before you and rises before you.' The Prophet of Allah (ﷺ) said:
'This makes up for that. Then when you are sitting, let the
following be among what one of you says: At-tahiyyatu lillahi
wasalawatu wat-tayibaat, as-salamu 'alaika ayah-Nabiyyu wa
rahmatAllahi wa baraktuhu. As-salamu 'alaina a 'ala ibad
illahis-salihin, ashadu an la ilaha ill Allah, wa ashhadu anna
Muhammadan 'abduhu wa rasuluhu. (All compliments, prayers and pure
words are due to Allah. Peace be upon you O Prophet, and the mercy
of Allah and His blessings. Peace be upon us and upon the righteous
slaves of Allah. I bear witness that that none has the right to be
worshipped except Allah, and I bear witness that Muhammad is His
slave and messenger.)"</english-text>
</hadith>
