<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41313</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1306</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Forgetfulness (In Prayer) - كتاب
السهو</chapter>
<chain-index>20587, 11313, 11609</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبيد الله بن سعد بن إبراهيم بن سعد، قال حدثنا
عمي، قال حدثنا شريك، عن أبي هاشم الواسطي، عن أبي مجلز، عن قيس بن
عباد، قال صلى عمار بن ياسر بالقوم صلاة أخفها فكأنهم أنكروها فقال
ألم أتم الركوع والسجود قالوا بلى ‏.‏ قال أما إني دعوت فيها بدعاء
كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يدعو به ‏"‏ اللهم بعلمك الغيب وقدرتك
على الخلق أحيني ما علمت الحياة خيرا لي وتوفني إذا علمت الوفاة خيرا
لي وأسألك خشيتك في الغيب والشهادة وكلمة الإخلاص في الرضا والغضب
وأسألك نعيما لا ينفد وقرة عين لا تنقطع وأسألك الرضاء بالقضاء وبرد
العيش بعد الموت ولذة النظر إلى وجهك والشوق إلى لقائك وأعوذ بك من
ضراء مضرة وفتنة مضلة اللهم زينا بزينة الإيمان واجعلنا هداة مهتدين
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Qais bin 'Ubad said: "Ammar bin
Yasir led the people in prayer and he made the prayer short. It was
as if they disliked that, so he said: 'Did I not do bowing and
prostration properly?' They said: 'Yes.' He said: 'And I said a
supplication that the Prophet (ﷺ) used to say:Allahumma bi
'ilmikal-ghaiba wa qudratika 'alal-khalqi ahini ma 'alimtal-hayata
khairan li, wa tawaffani idha 'alimtal-wafata khairan li. Allahumma
as'aluka khashyataka fil-ghaibi wash-shahadati wa as'aluka
kalimatul-aqua fir-rida'i wal ghadab, wa as'alukal-qasda fil faqr
wal-ghina, wa as'aluka na'iman la yanfadu wa as'aluka qurrata ainan
la tanqati'u wa as'alukar-rida'i ba'dal-qada'i wa as'aluka bardal
'aishi ba'dal-mawti, wa as'aluka ladhatan-nazari ila wajhika
wash-shawqa ila liqa'ika fi fitnatin mudillatin, Allahumma zayyina
dizinatil-imani waj'alna hudatan muhtadin (O Allah, by Your
knowledge of the unseen and Your power over creation, keep me alive
so long as You know that living is good for me and cause me to die
when You know that death is better for me. O Allah, cause me to
fear You in secret and in public. I ask You to make me true in
speech in times of pleasure and of anger. I ask You to make me
moderate in times of wealth and poverty. And I ask You for
everlasting delight and joy that will never cease. I ask You to
make me pleased with that which You have decreed and for an easy
life after death. I ask You for the sweetness of looking upon Your
face and a longing to meet You in a manner that does not entail a
calamity that will bring about harm or a trial that will cause
deviation. O Allah, beautify us with the adornment of faith and
make us among those who guide and are rightly
guided."</english-text>
</hadith>
