<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41355</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1348</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Forgetfulness (In Prayer) - كتاب
السهو</chapter>
<chain-index>30459, 20022, 11068, 19867, 29</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا يحيى بن حبيب بن عربي، قال حدثنا حماد، عن عطاء
بن السائب، عن أبيه، عن عبد الله بن عمرو، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خلتان لا يحصيهما رجل مسلم إلا دخل الجنة وهما يسير ومن
يعمل بهما قليل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
الصلوات الخمس يسبح أحدكم في دبر كل صلاة عشرا ويحمد عشرا ويكبر عشرا
فهي خمسون ومائة في اللسان وألف وخمسمائة في الميزان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأنا
رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعقدهن بيده ‏"‏ وإذا أوى أحدكم
إلى فراشه أو مضجعه سبح ثلاثا وثلاثين وحمد ثلاثا وثلاثين وكبر أربعا
وثلاثين فهي مائة على اللسان وألف في الميزان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فأيكم يعمل في كل يوم وليلة ألفين
وخمسمائة سيئة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يا رسول الله وكيف لا نحصيهما فقال ‏"‏ إن
الشيطان يأتي أحدكم وهو في صلاته فيقول اذكر كذا اذكر كذا ويأتيه عند
منامه فينيمه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abdullah in 'Umar said: "The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: 'There are two qualities which no
Muslim person attains but he will enter Paradise, and they are
easy, but those who do them are few.' The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: 'The five daily prayers: After each prayer one of you
glorifies Allah (SWT) ten times and praises Him ten times and
magnifies him ten times, which makes one hundred and fifty on the
tongue and one thousand five hundred in the balance.' And I saw the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) counting them on his hands. 'And when one of
you retires to his bed he says the tasbih thirty-three times and
the tahmid thirty-three times and the takbir thirty-four times,
that is one hundred on the tongue and one thousand in the balance.'
The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: "So which of you does two thousand
five hundred bad deeds in a day and a night?" It was said: "O
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), how can a person not persist in doing
that?" He said: "The Shaitan comes to one of you when he is praying
and says: 'Remember such and such, remember such and such," or he
comes to him when he is in bed and makes him fall
asleep."</english-text>
</hadith>
