<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41440</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>14</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>Grade</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Jumu'ah (Friday Prayer) - كتاب
الجمعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20374, 11234, 11213, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا بكر، - يعني ابن مضر - عن ابن
الهاد، عن محمد بن إبراهيم، عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، عن أبي هريرة،
قال أتيت الطور فوجدت ثم كعبا فمكثت أنا وهو يوما أحدثه عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ويحدثني عن التوراة فقلت له قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خير يوم طلعت فيه الشمس يوم الجمعة فيه خلق آدم
وفيه أهبط وفيه تيب عليه وفيه قبض وفيه تقوم الساعة ما على الأرض من
دابة إلا وهي تصبح يوم الجمعة مصيخة حتى تطلع الشمس شفقا من الساعة
إلا ابن آدم وفيه ساعة لا يصادفها مؤمن وهو في الصلاة يسأل الله فيها
شيئا إلا أعطاه إياه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال كعب ذلك يوم في كل سنة ‏.‏ فقلت بل
هي في كل جمعة ‏.‏ فقرأ كعب التوراة ثم قال صدق رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم هو في كل جمعة ‏.‏ فخرجت فلقيت بصرة بن أبي بصرة الغفاري
فقال من أين جئت قلت من الطور ‏.‏ قال لو لقيتك من قبل أن تأتيه لم
تأته ‏.‏ قلت له ولم قال إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول
‏"‏ لا تعمل المطي إلا إلى ثلاثة مساجد المسجد الحرام ومسجدي ومسجد
بيت المقدس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلقيت عبد الله بن سلام فقلت لو رأيتني خرجت إلى
الطور فلقيت كعبا فمكثت أنا وهو يوما أحدثه عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ويحدثني عن التوراة فقلت له قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ خير يوم طلعت فيه الشمس يوم الجمعة فيه خلق آدم وفيه أهبط
وفيه تيب عليه وفيه قبض وفيه تقوم الساعة ما على الأرض من دابة إلا
وهي تصبح يوم الجمعة مصيخة حتى تطلع الشمس شفقا من الساعة إلا ابن آدم
وفيه ساعة لا يصادفها عبد مؤمن وهو في الصلاة يسأل الله شيئا إلا
أعطاه إياه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كعب ذلك يوم في كل سنة ‏.‏ فقال عبد الله بن
سلام كذب كعب ‏.‏ قلت ثم قرأ كعب فقال صدق رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم هو في كل جمعة ‏.‏ فقال عبد الله صدق كعب إني لأعلم تلك الساعة
فقلت يا أخي حدثني بها ‏.‏ قال هي آخر ساعة من يوم الجمعة قبل أن تغيب
الشمس فقلت أليس قد سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ لا
يصادفها مؤمن وهو في الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وليست تلك الساعة صلاة قال أليس
قد سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ من صلى وجلس ينتظر
الصلاة لم يزل في صلاته حتى تأتيه الصلاة التي تلاقيها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت
بلى ‏.‏ قال فهو كذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Hurairah said: "I went out
to At-Tur and met Ka'b. He and I spent a day together, when I
narrated things to him from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and he
narrated things to me from the Tawrah. I said to him: The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) said: The best day on which the sun rises is Friday.
On this day, Adam was created, on this day he was sent down, on it
repentance was accepted, on this day he died, and on this day the
Hour will begin. There is no living creature on Earth that does not
listen out from Friday morning until the sun rises, fearing the
onset of the Hour, except the son of Adam. On (Friday) there is an
hour in which, if a believer prays and asks Allah (SWT) for
something, He will give it to him. Ka'b said: Is than one day in
every year? I said: No, it is every Friday.' Then Ka'b read in the
Tawrah and said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) spoke the truth; it is
every Friday. Then I went out and met Basrah bin Abi Basrah
Al-Ghifari. He said: From where have you come? I said: From At-Tur.
He said: If I had met you before you went there, you would not have
gone. I said to him: Why? He said: I heard the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) say: Do not travel especially to visit a masjid except three:
Al Masjid Al Haram (in Makkah), my masjid (in Al-Madinah) and the
Masjid of Bait Al-Maqdis (in Jerusalem). Then I met 'Abdullah bin
Salam and said: 'If you had only seen me, I went to At-Tur and met
Ka'b, and he and I spent the day together, when I narrated things
to him from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and he narrated things to me
from the Tawrah. I said to him: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
The best day on which the sun rises is Friday. On this day, Adam
was created, on this day he was sent down, on it repentance was
accepted, on this day he died, and on this day the Hour will begin.
There is no living creature on Earth that does not listen out from
Friday morning until the sun rises, fearing the onset of the Hour,
except the son of Adam. On (Friday) there is an hour in which, if a
believer prays and asks Allah (SWT) for something, He will give it
to him. Ka'b said: That is one day in every year. 'Abdullah bin
Salam said: Ka'b is not telling the truth. I said: Then Ka'b read
(in the Tawrah) and said: The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) spoke the
truth; it is every Friday. 'Abdullah said: Ka'b spoke the truth; I
know when that time is. I said: O my brother, tell me about it. He
said: It is the last hour of Friday, before the sun sets. I said:
Did you hear the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: If a believer prays,
but that is not a time for prayer. He said: Did you not hear the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: Whoever prays and sits waiting for the
(next) prayer, is in a state of prayer until the next prayer comes?
I said: Of course. He said: That is what it is."</english-text>
</hadith>
