<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41486</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1476</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30153, 20031, 11062, 11455</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمرو بن علي، قال حدثنا يحيى بن سعيد، قال حدثنا
يحيى بن سعيد، - هو الأنصاري - قال سمعت عمرة، قالت سمعت عائشة، تقول
جاءتني يهودية تسألني فقالت أعاذك الله من عذاب القبر ‏‏.‏‏ فلما جاء
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قلت يا رسول الله أيعذب الناس في القبور
فقال عائذا بالله فركب مركبا - يعني - وانخسفت الشمس فكنت بين الحجر
مع نسوة فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من مركبه فأتى مصلاه فصلى
بالناس فقام فأطال القيام ثم ركع فأطال الركوع ثم رفع رأسه فأطال
القيام ثم ركع فأطال الركوع ثم رفع رأسه فأطال القيام ثم سجد فأطال
السجود ثم قام قياما أيسر من قيامه الأول ثم ركع أيسر من ركوعه الأول
ثم رفع رأسه فقام أيسر من قيامه الأول ثم ركع أيسر من ركوعه الأول ثم
رفع رأسه فقام أيسر من قيامه الأول فكانت أربع ركعات وأربع سجدات
وانجلت الشمس فقال ‏‏"‏‏ إنكم تفتنون في القبور كفتنة الدجال ‏‏"‏‏
‏‏.‏‏ قالت عائشة فسمعته بعد ذلك يتعوذ من عذاب القبر
‏‏.‏‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Amrah said: "I heard Aishah say: 'A Jewish woman came
to me begging, and said: May Allah grant you protection from the
torment of the grave.' When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came, I
said: 'O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), will people be tormented in their
graves?' He sought refuge with Allah (SWT) and climbed onto his
mount. The sun became eclipsed while I was between the apartments
with some women. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came from his mount and
came to his prayer place, and led the people in prayer.He stood for
a long time, then he bowed for a long time, then he raised his head
and stood for a long time, then he bowed for a long time, then he
raised his head and stood for a long time, then he prostrated for a
long time. Then he stood for a shorter time than in the first
(rak'ah), then he bowed for a shorter time than the first, then he
raised his head and stood for a shorter time than the first, then
he bowed for a shorter time than the first, then he raised his head
and stood for a shorter time than the first, so he bowed four times
and prostrated four times, and the eclipse ended. He said: "You
will be tried in your graves like the trial of the Dajjal.' Aishah
said: 'I heard him after that seeking refuge with Allah from the
torment of the grave.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
