<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41480</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1470</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>20184, 20208, 11070, 11029, 11259</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، قال حدثنا ابن علية، قال
أخبرني ابن جريج، عن عطاء، قال سمعت عبيد بن عمير، يحدث قال حدثني من،
أصدق فظننت أنه يريد عائشة أنها قالت كسفت الشمس على عهد رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقام بالناس قياما شديدا يقوم بالناس ثم يركع ثم
يقوم ثم يركع ثم يقوم ثم يركع فركع ركعتين في كل ركعة ثلاث ركعات ركع
الثالثة ثم سجد حتى إن رجالا يومئذ يغشى عليهم حتى إن سجال الماء لتصب
عليهم مما قام بهم يقول إذا ركع ‏‏"‏‏ الله أكبر ‏‏"‏‏ ‏‏.‏‏ وإذا رفع
رأسه ‏‏"‏‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ‏‏"‏‏ ‏‏.‏‏ فلم ينصرف حتى تجلت الشمس
فقام فحمد الله وأثنى عليه وقال ‏‏"‏‏ إن الشمس والقمر لا ينكسفان
لموت أحد ولا لحياته ولكن آيتان من آيات الله يخوفكم بهما فإذا كسفا
فافزعوا إلى ذكر الله عز وجل حتى ينجليا ‏‏"‏‏ ‏‏.‏‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Ata said: "I heard Ubaid bin Umair say:'Someone whom
I trust'- and I think he meant Aishah- told me: There was an
eclipse of the sun during the time of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).
He led the people in prayer and stood for a very long time, then he
bowed, then he stood, then he bowed, then he stood, then he bowed.
He prayed two rak'ahs, bowing three times in each rak'ah. After
bowing for the third time he prostrated for a long time. Some men
fainted on that day and had to be revived by having buckets of
water thrown over them, because of having stood for so log. When he
bowed, he said: Allahu Akbar, and when he raised his head, he said:
Sami' Allahu lima hamidah.He did not finish until the eclipse had
ended. Then he stood and praised and glorified Allah (SWT) and
said: The sun and moon do not eclipse for the death or birth of
anyone, but they are two of the signs of Allah (SWT) with which He
strikes fear unto you. If they are eclipsed then turn to the
remembrance of Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, until it (the
eclipse) is over.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
