<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41503</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1493</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 30234, 20001, 11163, 11020, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، قال حدثنا ابن القاسم، عن مالك،
قال حدثني زيد بن أسلم، عن عطاء بن يسار، عن عبد الله بن عباس، قال
خسفت الشمس فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس معه فقام قياما
طويلا قرأ نحوا من سورة البقرة - قال - ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا ثم رفع
فقام قياما طويلا وهو دون القيام الأول ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون
الركوع الأول ثم سجد ثم قام قياما طويلا وهو دون القيام الأول ثم ركع
ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع الأول ثم رفع فقام قياما طويلا وهو دون
القيام الأول ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع الأول ثم سجد ثم
انصرف وقد تجلت الشمس فقال ‏"‏ إن الشمس والقمر آيتان من آيات الله لا
يخسفان لموت أحد ولا لحياته فإذا رأيتم ذلك فاذكروا الله عز وجل ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله رأيناك تناولت شيئا في مقامك هذا ثم رأيناك
تكعكعت ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إني رأيت الجنة أو أريت الجنة فتناولت منها عنقودا
ولو أخذته لأكلتم منه ما بقيت الدنيا ورأيت النار فلم أر كاليوم منظرا
قط ورأيت أكثر أهلها النساء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لم يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏
بكفرهن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قيل يكفرن بالله قال ‏"‏ يكفرن العشير ويكفرن الإحسان
لو أحسنت إلى إحداهن الدهر ثم رأت منك شيئا قالت ما رأيت منك خيرا قط
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Abdullah bin Abbas said: "There
was an eclipse of the sun and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) prayed and
the people with him. He stood for long time reciting something like
Surah Al-Baqarah, then he raised (his head) and stood for a long
time, then he raised (his head) and stood for a long time which was
shorter than the first time. Then he bowed for a long time, which
was shorter than the first time, then he prostrated. Then he got up
and stood for a long time, which was shorter than the first time,
then he bowed for a long time, which was shorter than the first
time, then he raised (his head) and stood for a long time, which
was shorter than the first time. Then he bowed for a long time,
which was shorter than the first time, then he prostrated, then he
finished (his prayer) and the sun had been clear. He said: 'The sun
and the moon are two of the signs of Allah (SWT) and they do not
become eclipsed for the death or birth of anyone. If you see that
then remember Allah (SWT) the Mighty and Sublime.' They said: 'O
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), we saw you stretching out your hand when
you were standing, then we saw you moving backward. He said: 'I saw
Paradise-or it was shown to me- and I reached out to a take a bunch
of its fruits. If I ha taken it you would have eaten from it for as
long as this world lasts. And I saw Hell and I have never seen
anything like it, and I saw that most of its inhabitants are
women.' They said: "Why, O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)? He said:
'Because of their ingratitude.' It was said: 'Are they ungrateful
to Allah?' He said: 'They are ungrateful to their husbands and they
are ungrateful for kind treatment. If you are kind to one of them
for a lifetime, then she sees (one) bad thing from you, she will
say: I have never seen anything good from you.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
