<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41528</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1518</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Praying for Rain (Al-Istisqa') - كتاب
الاستسقاء</chapter>
<chain-index>20387, 20155, 20587, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا علي بن حجر، قال حدثنا إسماعيل بن جعفر، قال
حدثنا شريك بن عبد الله، عن أنس بن مالك، أن رجلا، دخل المسجد ورسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائم يخطب فاستقبل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قائما وقال يا رسول الله هلكت الأموال وانقطعت السبل فادع الله
أن يغيثنا ‏.‏ فرفع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يديه ثم قال ‏"‏
اللهم أغثنا اللهم أغثنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أنس ولا والله ما نرى في السماء
من سحابة ولا قزعة وما بيننا وبين سلع من بيت ولا دار فطلعت سحابة مثل
الترس فلما توسطت السماء انتشرت وأمطرت ‏.‏ قال أنس ولا والله ما
رأينا الشمس سبتا ‏.‏ قال ثم دخل رجل من ذلك الباب في الجمعة المقبلة
ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائم يخطب فاستقبله قائما فقال يا رسول
الله صلى الله وسلم عليك هلكت الأموال وانقطعت السبل فادع الله أن
يمسكها عنا ‏.‏ فرفع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يديه فقال ‏"‏
اللهم حوالينا ولا علينا اللهم على الآكام والظراب وبطون الأودية
ومنابت الشجر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأقلعت وخرجنا نمشي في الشمس ‏.‏ قال شريك
سألت أنسا أهو الرجل الأول قال لا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Anas bin Malik that: A man
entered the masjid when the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was standing and
delivering the Khutbah. He turned to face the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) standing and said: 'O Messenger of Allah, our wealth has been
destroyed and the routes have been cut off. Pray to Allah (SWT) to
send us rain.' The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) raised his hands then
said: "O Allah, send us rain." Anas said: "By Allah, we had not
seen even a wisp of a cloud in the sky and there were no houses or
buildings between us and (the mountain of ) Sal'. Then a cloud like
a shield appeared, and when it reached the middle of the sky it
spread and it began to rain." Anas said: "By Allah, we did not see
the sun for a week. Then a man entered through that door on the
following Friday, when the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) was standing and
delivering the Khutbah. He turned to face him standing and said: 'O
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), may Allah (SWT) send blessings upon you.
Our wealth has been destroyed and the routes have been cut off.
Pray to Allah (SWT) to withold (the rain) from us.' The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) raised his hands and said: 'O Allah, around us and not
on us.; O Allah, on the hills and mountains, the bottoms of the
valleys and where the trees grow.' Then it stopped raining and we
went out walking in the sun." Sharik said: 'I asked Anas: 'Was he
the same man?' He said: 'No.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
