<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41527</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>17</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1517</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Praying for Rain (Al-Istisqa') - كتاب
الاستسقاء</chapter>
<chain-index>30449, 20288, 11201, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الأعلى، قال حدثنا المعتمر، قال سمعت
عبيد الله بن عمر، - وهو العمري - عن ثابت، عن أنس، قال كان النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم يخطب يوم الجمعة فقام إليه الناس فصاحوا فقالوا يا نبي
الله قحطت المطر وهلكت البهائم فادع الله أن يسقينا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اللهم
اسقنا اللهم اسقنا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وايم الله ما نرى في السماء قزعة من
سحاب - قال - فأنشأت سحابة فانتشرت ثم إنها أمطرت ونزل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فصلى وانصرف الناس فلم تزل تمطر إلى يوم الجمعة الأخرى
فلما قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يخطب صاحوا إليه فقالوا يا نبي
الله تهدمت البيوت وتقطعت السبل فادع الله أن يحبسها عنا ‏.‏ فتبسم
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقال ‏"‏ اللهم حوالينا ولا علينا ‏"‏
‏.‏ فتقشعت عن المدينة فجعلت تمطر حولها وما تمطر بالمدينة قطرة فنظرت
إلى المدينة وإنها لفي مثل الإكليل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Thabit that Anas said: "The
Prophet (ﷺ) was delivering the Khutbah one Friday when the people
stood up and shouted: 'O Prophet of Allah! There has been no rain
and the animals have died. Pray to Allah (SWT) to send us rain.' He
said: 'O Allah, send us rain; O Allah, send us rain.' By Allah
(SWT), we could not see even a wisp of a cloud in the sky, then a
cloud appeared and grew, and it rained. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
came down and prayed, and the people departed, and it continued to
rain until the following Friday. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
stood up to deliver the Khutbah, they called out to him and said:
'O Prophet of Allah, the houses are destroyed and the routes are
cut off. Pray to Allah to take it away from us.' The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) smiled and said: 'O Allah, around us and not on us!' Then
is dispersed from Al-Madinah and rain fell around Al-Madinah but
not a single drop fell on Al-Madinah. I looked, and it was in
something like a ring."</english-text>
</hadith>
