<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41559</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>18</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1549</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Fear Prayer - كتاب صلاة الخوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 30160, 20278, 20020, 11067, 11028</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن المثنى، ومحمد بن بشار، عن محمد، قال
حدثنا شعبة، عن منصور، قال سمعت مجاهدا، يحدث عن أبي عياش الزرقي، قال
شعبة كتب به إلى وقرأته عليه وسمعته منه يحدث ولكني حفظته قال ابن
بشار في حديثه حفظي من الكتاب أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كان مصاف
العدو بعسفان وعلى المشركين خالد بن الوليد فصلى بهم النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم الظهر قال المشركون إن لهم صلاة بعد هذه هي أحب إليهم من
أموالهم وأبنائهم فصلى بهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم العصر فصفهم
صفين خلفه فركع بهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جميعا فلما رفعوا
رءوسهم سجد بالصف الذي يليه وقام الآخرون فلما رفعوا رءوسهم من السجود
سجد الصف المؤخر بركوعهم مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم تأخر
الصف المقدم وتقدم الصف المؤخر فقام كل واحد منهم في مقام صاحبه ثم
ركع بهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جميعا فلما رفعوا رءوسهم من
الركوع سجد الصف الذي يليه وقام الآخرون فلما فرغوا من سجودهم سجد
الآخرون ثم سلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عليهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Shu'bah narrated from Mansur who said: "I heard
Mujahid narrating from Abu Ayyash Az-Zuraqi"- Shu'bah said: "He had
written it for me, and I read it before him, and I heard him
narrating it; rather, I even memorized it." Ibn Bashshar said: "I
memorized it from the book"- "The Prophet (ﷺ) was drawing up ranks
facing the enemy in 'Usfan when the idolaters were led by Khalid
bin Al-Walid. The Prophet (ﷺ) led them in praying Zuhr. The
idolaters said: 'They have a prayer after this that is dearer to
them than their wealth and sons.' Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
led them in praying 'Asr. He divided them into two rows, behind
him. He led them all in bowing, then when they raised their heads
he led the row that was closest to him in prostrating, while the
others remained standing. When they raised their heads from
prostration, the second row prostrated, as they had already bowed
with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). Then the front row moved forward,
so each of them took the place of his companion. Then the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ) led them all in bowing, then when they raised their
heads from bowing, the row that was closest to him prostrated while
the others remained standing, then when they had finished
prostrating, the others prostrated, then the Prophet (ﷺ) said the
taslim for all of them together.</english-text>
</hadith>
