<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41560</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>18</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1550</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Fear Prayer - كتاب صلاة الخوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30153, 20251, 11067, 11028</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمرو بن علي، قال حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الصمد،
قال حدثنا منصور، عن مجاهد، عن أبي عياش الزرقي، قال كنا مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بعسفان فصلى بنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
صلاة الظهر وعلى المشركين يومئذ خالد بن الوليد فقال المشركون لقد
أصبنا منهم غرة ولقد أصبنا منهم غفلة ‏.‏ فنزلت - يعني صلاة الخوف -
بين الظهر والعصر فصلى بنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاة العصر
ففرقنا فرقتين فرقة تصلي مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وفرقة يحرسونه
فكبر بالذين يلونه والذين يحرسونهم ثم ركع فركع هؤلاء وأولئك جميعا ثم
سجد الذين يلونه وتأخر هؤلاء والذين يلونه وتقدم الآخرون فسجدوا ثم
قام فركع بهم جميعا الثانية بالذين يلونه وبالذين يحرسونه ثم سجد
بالذين يلونه ثم تأخروا فقاموا في مصاف أصحابهم وتقدم الآخرون فسجدوا
ثم سلم عليهم فكانت لكلهم ركعتان ركعتان مع إمامهم وصلى مرة بأرض بني
سليم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu 'Ayyash Al-Zuraqi said: "We
were with the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) in 'Usfan and the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) led us in praying Zuhr. The idolaters were led that day
by Khalid bin Al-Walid, and the idolaters said: 'We have caught
them unawares.' Then the fear prayer was revealed between Zuhr and
'Asr. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) led us in praying 'Asr and divided
us into two groups, a group that prayed with the Prophet (ﷺ) and a
group that guarded him. He said takbir with those who were closest
to him and those who were guarding them, then he bowed and both
groups bowed with him. Then those who were closest to him
prostrated. Then they moved back and the others moved forward and
prostrated. Then he stood and led them all in bowing, those who
were closest to him and those who were guarding him. Then he led
those who were closest to him in prostrating, then they moved back
and took the place of their companions and the others came forward
and prostrated. Then he said the taslim so each group had prayed
two rak'ahs with their imam. And he offered the fear prayer once in
the land of Banu Sulaym."</english-text>
</hadith>
