<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41629</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1619</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Qiyam Al-Lail (The Night Prayer) and Voluntary
Prayers During the Day - كتاب قيام الليل وتطوع النهار</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20005, 11053, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة بن سعيد، قال حدثنا سفيان، عن الأحول، -
يعني سليمان بن أبي مسلم - عن طاوس، عن ابن عباس، قال كان النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم إذا قام من الليل يتهجد قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك الحمد أنت
نور السموات والأرض ومن فيهن ولك الحمد أنت قيام السموات والأرض ومن
فيهن ولك الحمد أنت ملك السموات والأرض ومن فيهن ولك الحمد أنت حق
ووعدك حق والجنة حق والنار حق والساعة حق والنبيون حق ومحمد حق لك
أسلمت وعليك توكلت وبك آمنت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم ذكر قتيبة كلمة معناها ‏"‏ وبك
خاصمت وإليك حاكمت اغفر لي ما قدمت وما أخرت وما أعلنت أنت المقدم
وأنت المؤخر لا إله إلا أنت ولا حول ولا قوة إلا بالله ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Ibn 'Abbas said: "When the
Prophet (ﷺ) got up at night to pray Tahajjud, he said: Allahumma,
lakal-hamdu anta nurus-samawati wal-ardi wa man fihinna wa
lakal-hamdu anta qayyamus-samawati wal ardi wa man fihinna wa
lakal-hamdu, anta haqqun wa wa'duka haqqun wal jannatu haqqun
wan-nuru haqqun wan-nabiyyuna haqqun wa Muhammadan haqqun, laka
aslant wa 'alaika tawakkaltu wa bika amant. ( O Allah, to You be
praise, You are the Light of the heavens and earth and whoever is
in them. To You be praise, You are the Sustainer of the Heavens and
the earth and whoever is in them. To You be praise, You are the
Sovereign of the heavens and earth and whoever is in them. To You
be praise; You are True, Your promise is true, Paradise is true,
Hell is true, the Hour is true, the Prophets are true and Muhammad
is true. To You have I submitted, in You I put my trust and in You
I have believed.'" Then (one of the narrators) Qutaibah mentioned
some words the meaning of which was: "Wa bika khasamtu wa ilaika
hakamtu, ighfirli ma quadrate wa ma akhkhartu wa ma a'lantu
antal-muqaddimu wa antal-mu'khkhir, la ilaha illa anta wa la hawla
wa la quwwata illa billah (And with Your help I argue [with my
opponents, the non-believers], and I take You as a judge [to judge
between us]. Forgive me my past and future sins and those that I
commit openly. You are the One who puts [some people] back and
bring [others] forward. There is no God but You and there is no
power and no strength except with Allah).'"</english-text>
</hadith>
