<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41630</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1620</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Qiyam Al-Lail (The Night Prayer) and Voluntary
Prayers During the Day - كتاب قيام الليل وتطوع النهار</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 30234, 20001, 11223, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، قال أنبأنا ابن القاسم، عن مالك،
قال حدثني مخرمة بن سليمان، عن كريب، أن عبد الله بن عباس، أخبره أنه،
بات عند ميمونة أم المؤمنين - وهي خالته - فاضطجع في عرض الوسادة
واضطجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأهله في طولها فنام رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى إذا انتصف الليل أو قبله قليلا أو بعده قليلا
استيقظ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجلس يمسح النوم عن وجهه بيده ثم
قرأ العشر الآيات الخواتيم من سورة آل عمران ثم قام إلى شن معلقة
فتوضأ منها فأحسن وضوءه ثم قام يصلي قال عبد الله بن عباس فقمت فصنعت
مثل ما صنع ثم ذهبت فقمت إلى جنبه فوضع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يده اليمنى على رأسي وأخذ بأذني اليمنى يفتلها فصلى ركعتين ثم ركعتين
ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم أوتر ثم اضطجع حتى جاءه
المؤذن فصلى ركعتين خفيفتين ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Kuraib that 'Abdullah bin 'Abbas
told him: He slept at the house of Maimunah the wife of the Prophet
(ﷺ), who was his maternal aunt. He said: "I laid down across the
mattress an the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and his wife lay along it.
The Prophet (ﷺ) slept until midnight, or a little before or a
little after. The Prophet (ﷺ) woke up and began to rub the sleep
from his face with his hand. Then he recited the last ten verses of
Surah Al Imran. Then he got up and went to a water skin that was
hanging up and performed wudu from it, and he performed wudu well,
then he stood up and prayed." Abdullah bin 'Abbas said: "I stood up
and did what he had done, then I went and stood beside him. The
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) put his right hand on my neck, and took old
of my right hand and tweaked it. Then he prayed two rak'ahs, then
two rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs, then two rak'ahs,
then two rak'ahs, then he prayed witr.Then he lay down until the
Mu'adhdhin came to him and he prayed two brief
rak'ahs."</english-text>
</hadith>
