<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41636</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1626</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Qiyam Al-Lail (The Night Prayer) and Voluntary
Prayers During the Day - كتاب قيام الليل وتطوع النهار</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 20029, 20475, 11013, 10561</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، قال أنبأنا ابن وهب، عن يونس، عن
ابن شهاب، قال حدثني حميد بن عبد الرحمن بن عوف، أن رجلا، من أصحاب
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال قلت وأنا في سفر مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم والله لأرقبن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لصلاة حتى أرى
فعله فلما صلى صلاة العشاء - وهي العتمة - اضطجع هويا من الليل ثم
استيقظ فنظر في الأفق فقال ‏{‏ ربنا ما خلقت هذا باطلا ‏}‏ حتى بلغ
‏{‏ إنك لا تخلف الميعاد ‏}‏ ‏.‏ ثم أهوى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إلى فراشه فاستل منه سواكا ثم أفرغ في قدح من إداوة عنده ماء
فاستن ثم قام فصلى حتى قلت قد صلى قدر ما نام ثم اضطجع حتى قلت قد نام
قدر ما صلى ثم استيقظ ففعل كما فعل أول مرة وقال مثل ما قال ففعل رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثلاث مرات قبل الفجر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Ibn Shihaab said: "Humaid bin
Abdur-Rahman bin 'Awf told me that a man from among the companions
of the Prophet (ﷺ) said: 'I said, when I was on a journey with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ): By Allah (SWT), I am going to watch the
prayer of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and see what he does. When he
prayed 'Isha, he lay down for a long time. Then he woke up and
looked toward the horizon and said: "Our Lord! You have not created
(all) this without purpose" until he reached: "for You never break
(Your) Promise." Then the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) reached across his
bed and took a siwak from it, then he poured water from a vessel
and cleaned his teeth. Then he stood and prayed until I said: He
has prayed for as long as he has slept. Then he lay down until I
said: He has slept as long as he prayed. Then he woke up and did
the same as he had done the first time and said the same as he had
said. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) did that three times before
Fajr.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
