<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41674</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>20</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1664</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Qiyam Al-Lail (The Night Prayer) and Voluntary
Prayers During the Day - كتاب قيام الليل وتطوع النهار</chapter>
<chain-index>38181, 20331, 11060, 11344, 10824, 11354,
145</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا الحسين بن منصور، قال حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير،
قال حدثنا الأعمش، عن سعد بن عبيدة، عن المستورد بن الأحنف، عن صلة بن
زفر، عن حذيفة، قال صليت مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ليلة فافتتح
البقرة فقلت يركع عند المائة فمضى فقلت يركع عند المائتين فمضى فقلت
يصلي بها في ركعة فمضى فافتتح النساء فقرأها ثم افتتح آل عمران فقرأها
يقرأ مترسلا إذا مر بآية فيها تسبيح سبح وإذا مر بسؤال سأل وإذا مر
بتعوذ تعوذ ثم ركع فقال ‏"‏ سبحان ربي العظيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكان ركوعه نحوا
من قيامه ثم رفع رأسه فقال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكان قيامه
قريبا من ركوعه ثم سجد فجعل يقول ‏"‏ سبحان ربي الأعلى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكان
سجوده قريبا من ركوعه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Hudhaifah said: "I prayed with
the Prophet (ﷺ) one night. He started to recite Al-Baqarah and I
thought, 'he will bow when he reaches one hundred,' but he carried
on. I thought, 'he is going to recite the whole surah in one
rak'ah,' but he carried on. He started to recite An-Nisa' and
recited (the whole surah), then he started to recite Al Imran and
recited (the whole surah), reciting slowly. When he reached a verse
that spoke of glorifying Allah (SWT), he glorified Him. When he
reached a verse that spoke of supplication, he made supplication.
When he reached a verse that spoke of seeking refuge with Allah, he
sought refuge with Him. Then he bowed and said: 'Subhana
Rabbiyal-Azim.(Glory be to my Lord Almighty)', and he bowed for
almost as long as he had stood. Then he raised his head and said:
'Sami Allahu liman hamidah (Allah hears those who praise Him)', and
he stood for almost as long as he had bowed. Then he prostrated and
started to say: Subhana Rabbiyal-'Ala (Glory be to my Lord Most
High),' and he prostrated for almost as long as he had
bowed.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
