<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>41856</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1846</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Funerals - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>1730</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عتبة بن عبد الله بن عتبة، قال قرأت على مالك عن
عبد الله بن عبد الله بن جبر بن عتيك، أن عتيك بن الحارث، وهو جد عبد
الله بن عبد الله أبو أمه أخبره أن جبر بن عتيك أخبره أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم جاء يعود عبد الله بن ثابت فوجده قد غلب عليه فصاح به
فلم يجبه فاسترجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقال ‏"‏ قد غلبنا
عليك أبا الربيع ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصحن النساء وبكين فجعل ابن عتيك يسكتهن فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ دعهن فإذا وجب فلا تبكين باكية ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا وما الوجوب يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ الموت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت ابنته
إن كنت لأرجو أن تكون شهيدا قد كنت قضيت جهازك ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فإن الله عز وجل قد أوقع أجره عليه على قدر نيته
وما تعدون الشهادة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا القتل في سبيل الله عز وجل ‏.‏ قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ الشهادة سبع سوى القتل في سبيل الله
عز وجل المطعون شهيد والمبطون شهيد والغريق شهيد وصاحب الهدم شهيد
وصاحب ذات الجنب شهيد وصاحب الحرق شهيد والمرأة تموت بجمع شهيدة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Jabir bin 'Abdullah bin 'Atik
that 'Atik bin Al-Harith who was the grandfather of 'Abdullah bin
'Abdullah, his mother's fathr told him that the Jabir bin "Atik
told him that: the Prophet came to visit 'Abdullah bin Thabit (when
he was sick) and found him very close to death. He called out to
him and he did not respond, so the Messenger of Allah said: "Truly,
to Allah we belong and truly, to Him we shall return," and said:
"We wanted you to live but we were overtaken by the decree of
Allah, O Abu Ar-Rabi." The women screamed and wept, and Ibn "Atik
started telling them to quiet. The Messenger of Allah said: "Leave
them; when the inevitable comes, no one should weep." They said:
"What is the inevitable, O Messenger of Allah?" He said: "Death."
His daughter said: "I had hoped that you would become a martyr, for
you had prepared yourself for it." The Messenger of Allah said:
"Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, has rewarded him according to his
intention. What do you think martyrdom is?" They said: "Being
killed for the sake of Allah." The Messenger of Allah said:
"Martyrdom is of seven types besides being killed for the sake of
Allah. The one who dies of the plague is a martyr; the one who is
crushed by a falling building is a martyr; the one who is crusheds
by a falling building is a martyr; the one who dies of pleurisy is
a martyr; the one who dies of pleurisy is a martyr; the one who is
burned to death is a martyr, and the woman who dies in pregnancy is
a martyr."</english-text>
</hadith>
