<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42102</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>22</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2091</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>30172, 20443, 20236, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن معمر، قال حدثنا أبو عامر العقدي، قال
حدثنا سليمان بن المغيرة، عن ثابت، عن أنس، قال نهينا في القرآن أن
نسأل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن شىء فكان يعجبنا أن يجيء الرجل
العاقل من أهل البادية فيسأله فجاء رجل من أهل البادية فقال يا محمد
أتانا رسولك فأخبرنا أنك تزعم أن الله عز وجل أرسلك قال ‏"‏ صدق ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فمن خلق السماء قال ‏"‏ الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فمن خلق الأرض قال
‏"‏ الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فمن نصب فيها الجبال قال ‏"‏ الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فمن جعل فيها المنافع قال ‏"‏ الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالذي خلق السماء
والأرض ونصب فيها الجبال وجعل فيها المنافع آلله أرسلك قال ‏"‏ نعم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وزعم رسولك أن علينا خمس صلوات في كل يوم وليلة قال ‏"‏
صدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالذي أرسلك آلله أمرك بهذا قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
وزعم رسولك أن علينا زكاة أموالنا قال ‏"‏ صدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالذي
أرسلك آلله أمرك بهذا قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وزعم رسولك أن علينا
صوم شهر رمضان في كل سنة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ صدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالذي أرسلك
آلله أمرك بهذا قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وزعم رسولك أن علينا الحج من
استطاع إليه سبيلا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ صدق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فبالذي أرسلك آلله
أمرك بهذا قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فوالذي بعثك بالحق لا أزيدن عليهن
شيئا ولا أنقص ‏.‏ فلما ولى قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لئن صدق
ليدخلن الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Anas said: "We were forbidden in
the Quran to ask the Prophet about anything not imperative, so we
liked it when a wise man from among the people of the desert came
and asked him. A man from among the desert people came and said: 'O
Muhammad, your messenger came to us and told us that you say that
Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, has sent you.' He said: 'He spoke
the trought." He said: "Who created the heavens?' He said: Allah.
He said: 'Who created the Earth? He said: Allah. He said: 'Who set
up the mountains in it?' He said: 'Allah.' He said: Who created
beneficial things in them?' He said; 'Allah.' He said: 'By the One
Who created the heavens and the Earth, and set up the mountains
therein, and created beneficial things in them has Allah sent you?'
He said: 'Yes.' He said; 'Your messenger said that we have to offer
five prayers each day and night.' He said: 'He spoke the truth.' He
said: 'By the One Who sent you, has Allah commanded you to do
this?' he said: 'Yes.' He said: 'Your messenger said that we have
to pay Zakah on our wealth.' He said: 'He spoke the truth.' He
said: 'By the One Who sent you, has Allah commanded you to do
this?' He said: 'Yes.' He said; 'Your messenger said that we have
to fast the month of Ramadan each year.' He said: 'He spoke the
truth . He said: 'By the One Who sent You, has Allah commanded you
to do this?' He said: 'yes .' He said: 'Your messenger said that we
have to perform Hajj, those who can afford it.' He said: 'He spoke
the truth.' He said: 'By the One Who sent you, has Allah commanded
you to do this?' he said: 'yes. He said: 'By the One Who sent you
with the truth, I will not do more that this or less.' When he
left, the Prophet, said: 'If he is sincere, he will certainly
center paradise."'</english-text>
</hadith>
