<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42143</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>22</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2132</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fasting - كتاب الصيام</chapter>
<chain-index>30258, 20385, 11176, 11013, 11200, 38433, 30330,
20428, 11013, 11200, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبيد الله بن سعد بن إبراهيم، قال حدثنا عمي، قال
حدثني أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن أبي
ثور، حدثه ح، وأخبرنا عمرو بن منصور، قال حدثنا الحكم بن نافع، قال
أنبأنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن أبي
ثور، عن ابن عباس، قال لم أزل حريصا أن أسأل عمر بن الخطاب عن
المرأتين من أزواج رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اللتين قال الله لهما
‏{‏ إن تتوبا إلى الله فقد صغت قلوبكما ‏}‏ وساق الحديث وقال فيه
فاعتزل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نساءه من أجل ذلك الحديث حين
أفشته حفصة إلى عائشة تسعا وعشرين ليلة ‏.‏ قالت عائشة وكان قال ‏"‏
ما أنا بداخل عليهن شهرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ من شدة موجدته عليهن حين حدثه الله
عز وجل حديثهن فلما مضت تسع وعشرون ليلة دخل على عائشة فبدأ بها فقالت
له عائشة إنك قد كنت آليت يا رسول الله أن لا تدخل علينا شهرا وإنا
أصبحنا من تسع وعشرين ليلة نعدها عددا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ الشهر تسع وعشرون ليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Ibn 'Abbas said: "I was very
keen to ask 'Umar bin Al-Khattab about the two wives of the
Messenger of Allah to whom Allah said: If you two turn in
repentance to Allah, (it will be better for you), your hearts are
indeed so inclined." And he quoted the Hadith. He said concerning
it:' "The from his wives for twenty-nine days because of that, when
Hafsah had made her disclosure to Aishah. He had said: 'I will not
enter upon them for a month,' because he was so upset with them
when Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, informed him of what they had
said. When twenty-nine days had passed, he entered upon 'Aishah, so
he started with her. Aishah, said to him: 'O Messenger of Allah,
you swore not to enter upon us for a month, and now twenty-nine
days have passed; we have been counting them.' The Messenger of
Allah said; 'The month is twenty-nine days."'</english-text>
</hadith>
