<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42589</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2578</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakah - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30480, 20327, 20016, 11366, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا هناد بن السري، عن أبي الأحوص، عن سعيد بن مسروق،
عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي نعم، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال بعث علي وهو
باليمن بذهيبة بتربتها إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقسمها رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بين أربعة نفر الأقرع بن حابس الحنظلي وعيينة
بن بدر الفزاري وعلقمة بن علاثة العامري ثم أحد بني كلاب وزيد الطائي
ثم أحد بني نبهان فغضبت قريش وقال مرة أخرى صناديد قريش فقالوا تعطي
صناديد نجد وتدعنا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إنما فعلت ذلك لأتألفهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاء
رجل كث اللحية مشرف الوجنتين غائر العينين ناتئ الجبين محلوق الرأس
فقال اتق الله يا محمد ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فمن يطع الله عز وجل إن عصيته
أيأمنني على أهل الأرض ولا تأمنوني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم أدبر الرجل فاستأذن رجل
من القوم في قتله يرون أنه خالد بن الوليد فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن من ضئضئ هذا قوما يقرءون القرآن لا يجاوز حناجرهم
يقتلون أهل الإسلام ويدعون أهل الأوثان يمرقون من الإسلام كما يمرق
السهم من الرمية لئن أدركتهم لأقتلنهم قتل عاد ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Sa'eed Al-Khudri said: "When
he was in Yemen, Ali sent a piece of gold that was still mixed with
sediment to the Messenger of Allah, and the Messenger of Allah
distributed it among four people: Al-Aqra' bin Habis Al-Hanzali,
'Uyaynah bin Badr Al-Fazari, 'Alqamah bin 'Ulathah Al- 'Amiri, who
was from Banu Kilab and Zaid Al-Ta'I who was from Banu Nabhan. The
Quraish" - he said one time: became angry and said: 'You give to
the chiefs of Najdand that, so as to soften their hearts toward
Islam.' Then a man with a thick beard, prominent cheeks, and a
shaven head came and said: 'Fear Allah. O Muhammad! He said: 'Who
would obey Allah if I disobeyed Him? (Is it fair that) He has
entrusted me with all the people of the Earth but you do not trust
me?' Then the man went away, and a man from among the people, whom
they (the narrators) think was Khalid bin Al-Walid, asked for
permission to kill him. The Messenger of Allah said: 'Among the
offspring of this man will be some people who will recite the
Qur'an but it will not go any further than their throats. They will
kill the Muslims but leave the idol worshippers alone, and they
will passes through Islam as an arrow passes through the body of
the target. If I live to see them. I will kill them all, as the
people of 'Ad were killed."'</english-text>
</hadith>
