<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42592</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2581</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakah - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30249, 20208, 20295, 11449, 11229, 11020,
38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني زياد بن أيوب، قال حدثنا إسماعيل ابن علية، قال
أخبرني هشام، قال حدثني يحيى بن أبي كثير، قال حدثني هلال، عن عطاء بن
يسار، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال جلس رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على
المنبر وجلسنا حوله فقال ‏"‏ إنما أخاف عليكم من بعدي ما يفتح لكم من
زهرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذكر الدنيا وزينتها فقال رجل أويأتي الخير بالشر فسكت
عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقيل له ما شأنك تكلم رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ولا يكلمك ‏.‏ قال ورأينا أنه ينزل عليه فأفاق يمسح
الرحضاء وقال ‏"‏ أشاهد السائل إنه لا يأتي الخير بالشر وإن مما ينبت
الربيع يقتل أو يلم إلا آكلة الخضر فإنها أكلت حتى إذا امتدت خاصرتاها
استقبلت عين الشمس فثلطت ثم بالت ثم رتعت وإن هذا المال خضرة حلوة
ونعم صاحب المسلم هو إن أعطى منه اليتيم والمسكين وابن السبيل وإن
الذي يأخذه بغير حقه كالذي يأكل ولا يشبع ويكون عليه شهيدا يوم
القيامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Sa'eed Al-Khudri said: "The
Messenger of Allah sat on the Minbar, and we sat around him. He
said: 'What I fear most for you after I am gone is the (worldly)
delights that will come to you.' And he spoke of this world and its
attractions. A man said: 'Can good bring forth evil? 'The Messenger
of Allah remained silent and it was said to him (that man): 'What
is the matter with you? You speak to the Messenger of Allah when he
does not speak to you? We noticed that he was receiving Revelation.
Then he recovered and wiped off his sweat and said: I know what the
questioner meant: he means that good never brings forth evil. But
some of that which grows in the spring kills the animals or makes
them sick, unless they eat Al-Khadir (kind of plant): if they eat
their fill or it then turn to face the sun and then defecate and
urinate and start to graze again. This wealth is fresh and sweet.
Blessed is the wealth of a Muslim from which he gives to a Muslim
from which he gives to orphans, the poor and wayfarers. The one who
takes it unlawfully is like the one who eats but is never
satisfied, and who eats but is never satisfied, and it will be a
witness against him on the Day of Resurrection."'</english-text>
</hadith>
