<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42594</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2583</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakah - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30126, 20278, 20020, 11060, 11353, 20377</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا بشر بن خالد، قال حدثنا غندر، عن شعبة، عن
سليمان، عن أبي وائل، عن عمرو بن الحارث، عن زينب، امرأة عبد الله
قالت قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم للنساء ‏"‏ تصدقن ولو من حليكن
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت وكان عبد الله خفيف ذات اليد فقالت له أيسعني أن أضع
صدقتي فيك وفي بني أخ لي يتامى فقال عبد الله سلي عن ذلك رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قالت فأتيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فإذا على
بابه امرأة من الأنصار يقال لها زينب تسأل عما أسأل عنه فخرج إلينا
بلال فقلنا له انطلق إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسله عن ذلك
ولا تخبره من نحن ‏.‏ فانطلق إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
‏"‏ من هما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال زينب ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أى الزيانب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال زينب
امرأة عبد الله وزينب الأنصارية قال ‏"‏ نعم لهما أجران أجر القرابة
وأجر الصدقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Zainab, the wife of 'Abdullah,
said: "The Messenger of Allah said to women: 'Give charity, even
from women: 'Give charity, even from your jewelry. 'Abdullah was
not a wealthy man and she said to him: 'Can I spend my charity on
you and on my brother's children who are orphans? 'Abdullah said:
'Ask the Messenger of Allah about that.' She said: So I went to the
Messenger of Allah, and at his door I found a woman from among the
Ansar who was also called Zainab, and she was asking about the same
matter as I was. Bilal came out to us and we said to him: Go to the
Messenger of Allah and ask him about that, but do not tell him who
we are. He went to the Messenger of Allah and he said:' Who are
they?' He said: Zainab.' He said: 'Which Zainab?" He said: 'Zainab
Al-Ansariyyah.' Abdullah and Zainab Al-Ansariyyah.' He said: 'Yes,
they will have two rewards, the reward for upholding the ties of
kinship and the reward dfor giving charity."'</english-text>
</hadith>
