<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42607</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2596</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Zakah - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>36017, 30234, 20001, 11163, 11020</chain-index>
<arabic-text>قال الحارث بن مسكين قراءة عليه وأنا أسمع، عن ابن
القاسم، قال أنبأنا مالك، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن عطاء بن يسار، عن رجل،
من بني أسد قال نزلت أنا وأهلي، ببقيع الغرقد فقالت لي أهلي اذهب إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسله لنا شيئا نأكله ‏.‏ فذهبت إلى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فوجدت عنده رجلا يسأله ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ لا أجد ما أعطيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فولى الرجل عنه وهو مغضب
وهو يقول لعمري إنك لتعطي من شئت ‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إنه ليغضب على أن لا أجد ما أعطيه من سأل منكم وله أوقية أو
عدلها فقد سأل إلحافا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال الأسدي فقلت للقحة لنا خير من أوقية
- والأوقية أربعون درهما - فرجعت ولم أسأله فقدم على رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم بعد ذلك شعير وزبيب فقسم لنا منه حتى أغنانا الله عز
وجل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Ata'bin Yasar that a man from
Banu Asad said: "My wife and I stopped at Baqi Al-Gharqad, and my
wife said to me: 'Go to the Messenger of Allah and ask him to give
us something to eat. ' So I went to the Messenger of Allah and
found a man with him asking him (for something), and the Messenger
of Allah was saying: 'I do not have anything to give to you.' The
man turned away angrily, saying: 'You only give to those you want.
'The Messenger of Allah said: 'He is angry with me because I did
not have anything to give him. Whoever asks of you and he has an
Uqiyah or its equivalent, then he has been too demanding in
asking."' Al-Asadi said: I said: 'Our milch-camel is worth more
than an Uqiyah, 'and an Uqiyah is forty Dirhams. "So I went back
and did not ask him for anything. Then the Messenger of Allah got
some barley and raisins after that, and he gave us a share of them,
until Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, made us independent of
means."</english-text>
</hadith>
