<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42730</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2719</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20028, 11067, 11353</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال أنبأنا جرير، عن منصور، عن
أبي وائل، قال قال الصبى بن معبد كنت أعرابيا نصرانيا فأسلمت فكنت
حريصا على الجهاد فوجدت الحج والعمرة مكتوبين على فأتيت رجلا من
عشيرتي يقال له هذيم بن عبد الله فسألته فقال اجمعهما ثم اذبح ما
استيسر من الهدى فأهللت بهما فلما أتيت العذيب لقيني سلمان بن ربيعة
وزيد بن صوحان وأنا أهل بهما فقال أحدهما للآخر ما هذا بأفقه من بعيره
‏.‏ فأتيت عمر فقلت يا أمير المؤمنين إني أسلمت وأنا حريص على الجهاد
وإني وجدت الحج والعمرة مكتوبين على فأتيت هذيم بن عبد الله فقلت يا
هناه إني وجدت الحج والعمرة مكتوبين على ‏.‏ فقال اجمعهما ثم اذبح ما
استيسر من الهدى فأهللت بهما فلما أتينا العذيب لقيني سلمان بن ربيعة
وزيد بن صوحان فقال أحدهما للآخر ما هذا بأفقه من بعيره ‏.‏ فقال عمر
هديت لسنة نبيك صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Wail said: "As-subai bin
Mabad said: 'I was a Christian Bedouin, then I became Muslim. I was
keen to go for Jihad but I learned that Hajj and "Umrah had been
enjoined on me, I went to a man of my clan who was called Huraim
bin 'Abdullah and asked him, and he said: "Put them together, then
slaughter whatever you can of the Hadi, so I entered Ihram for
bother together, and when I came to al-'Udhaib, I was met by Salman
bin Rabiah and Zaid bin Suhan, while I was uttering the Talbiyah
for bothe. One of them said to the other: "He does not understand
more than his camel!: I came to 'Umar and said: "O Commander of the
Believers! I have become Muslim and I am keen to go for Jihad, but
I learned that Hajj and "Umrah were enjoined on me, so I went to
Huraim bin 'Abdullah and said: "Hey you! I have learned that Hajj,
and 'Umrah have been enjoined on me. He said: 'Put them together
then slaughter whatever you can of the Jade' so I entered Ihram for
both together, and when I came to Al-Udhaib I was met by Salman bin
Rabiah and Zaid bin Suhan, and one of them said to the other: 'He
does not understand more than his camel,''' 'Umar said: "You have
been guided to the Sunnah of your Prophet</english-text>
</hadith>
