<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42749</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2738</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20033, 20012, 11046, 3680, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن المثنى، عن عبد الرحمن، قال حدثنا سفيان،
عن قيس، وهو ابن مسلم عن طارق بن شهاب، عن أبي موسى، قال قدمت على
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو بالبطحاء فقال ‏"‏ بما أهللت ‏"‏
‏.‏ قلت أهللت بإهلال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل سقت من
هدى ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فطف بالبيت وبالصفا والمروة ثم حل ‏"‏
‏.‏ فطفت بالبيت وبالصفا والمروة ثم أتيت امرأة من قومي فمشطتني وغسلت
رأسي فكنت أفتي الناس بذلك في إمارة أبي بكر وإمارة عمر وإني لقائم
بالموسم إذ جاءني رجل فقال إنك لا تدري ما أحدث أمير المؤمنين في شأن
النسك ‏.‏ قلت يا أيها الناس من كنا أفتيناه بشىء فليتئد فإن أمير
المؤمنين قادم عليكم فائتموا به فلما قدم قلت يا أمير المؤمنين ما هذا
الذي أحدثت في شأن النسك قال إن نأخذ بكتاب الله عز وجل فإن الله عز
وجل قال ‏{‏ وأتموا الحج والعمرة لله ‏}‏ وإن نأخذ بسنة نبينا صلى
الله عليه وسلم فإن نبينا صلى الله عليه وسلم لم يحل حتى نحر الهدى
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Musa said: "I came to the
Messenger of Allah when he was in Al-Batha', and he said: 'For what
have you entered Ihram?' I said: 'I have entered Ihram for that for
which the Proper had entered Ihram,' He said: 'Have you brought a
hadi (sacrifical animal)?' I said: 'No.' He said: 'Then
circumambulate the House and (perform Sa) between As-Safa and
Al-Marwah, then exit Ihram, so I circumambulated the House and
(performed Sa i) between As-Safa and Al-Marwah, then went to a
woman of my people and she combed and washed my hair, I used to
issue Fatwas to the people based on that, during the Khilafah of
Abu Bakr and 'Umar. Then one day during Hajj season a man came to
me and said: 'You do not know what the commander of the Believers
has introduced concerning the rites. I said: O people, whoever
heard our heard our Fatwa, let him not rush to follow it, for the
commander of the Believers! Is coming to you, and you should follow
him. When he came, I said: O Commander of the Believers! What is
this that you have introduced concerning the rites? He said: If we
follow the Book of Allah, then Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, says:
'And complete the Hajj and 'Umrah for Allah. And if we follow the
sunnah of our Prophet then our Prophet did not exit Ihram until he
had slaughtered the Hadi (sacrificial animal)
(sahih)</english-text>
</hadith>
