<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42753</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2742</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30449, 20423, 20020, 11386, 3680</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الأعلى، قال حدثنا خالد، قال حدثنا
شعبة، قال أخبرني قيس بن مسلم، قال سمعت طارق بن شهاب، قال قال أبو
موسى أقبلت من اليمن والنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم منيخ بالبطحاء حيث حج
فقال ‏"‏ أحججت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ كيف قلت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قلت
لبيك بإهلال كإهلال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ فطف بالبيت
وبالصفا والمروة وأحل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلت ثم أتيت امرأة ففلت رأسي فجعلت
أفتي الناس بذلك حتى كان في خلافة عمر فقال له رجل يا أبا موسى رويدك
بعض فتياك فإنك لا تدري ما أحدث أمير المؤمنين في النسك بعدك ‏.‏ قال
أبو موسى يا أيها الناس من كنا أفتيناه فليتئد فإن أمير المؤمنين قادم
عليكم فائتموا به ‏.‏ وقال عمر إن نأخذ بكتاب الله فإنه يأمرنا
بالتمام وإن نأخذ بسنة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فإن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم لم يحل حتى بلغ الهدى محله ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Abu Musa said: "I came from Yemen and the Prophet had
stopped in Al-Batha at the time to Hajj. He asked: 'Have you
performed Hajj?' I said: 'Yes, He said: 'What did you say?' I said;
'Labbaika bi ihlal ka ihlal in-nabiy (Here I am (O Allah, entering
Ihram for that for which the Prophet entered Ihram). He said
'Circumambulate the House and (perform Sa) between As-Safa and
Al-Marwah, and exit Ihram.' Then I went to a woman who combed my
hair. I started to issue Fatwas to the people based on that. Then
during the Khilafah of 'Umar, a man said to me: 'O abu Musa,
withhold some of our Fatwas from us, for you do not know what the
Commander of the Believers has introduced into the rites after
you.''' Abu Musa said: "O people, O people, whoever heard our
Fatwa,let him not rush to follow it, for the Commander of the
Believers is coming to your and you should follow him.: 'Umar said:
"If we follow the Book of Allah, then indeed He commands us to
complete Hajj and 'Umrah, and the Messenger of Allah did not exit
Ihram until the Hadi had reached its place."</english-text>
</hadith>
