<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42774</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2763</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11263, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا الليث، عن أبي الزبير، عن جابر
بن عبد الله، قال أقبلنا مهلين مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بحج
مفرد وأقبلت عائشة مهلة بعمرة حتى إذا كنا بسرف عركت حتى إذا قدمنا
طفنا بالكعبة وبالصفا والمروة فأمرنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن
يحل منا من لم يكن معه هدى قال فقلنا حل ماذا قال ‏"‏ الحل كله ‏"‏
‏.‏ فواقعنا النساء وتطيبنا بالطيب ولبسنا ثيابنا وليس بيننا وبين
عرفة إلا أربع ليال ثم أهللنا يوم التروية ثم دخل رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم على عائشة فوجدها تبكي فقال ‏"‏ ما شأنك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت شأني
أني قد حضت وقد حل الناس ولم أحلل ولم أطف بالبيت والناس يذهبون إلى
الحج الآن ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إن هذا أمر كتبه الله على بنات آدم فاغتسلي ثم
أهلي بالحج ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلت ‏.‏ ووقفت المواقف حتى إذا طهرت طافت
بالكعبة وبالصفا والمروة ثم قال ‏"‏ قد حللت من حجتك وعمرتك جميعا ‏"‏
‏.‏ فقالت يا رسول الله إني أجد في نفسي أني لم أطف بالبيت حتى حججت
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاذهب بها يا عبد الرحمن فأعمرها من التنعيم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وذلك
ليلة الحصبة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Jabir bin 'Abdullah said: "We
came in Ihram with the Messenger of Allah for Hajj alone (Mufrad),
and 'Aishah came in Ihram for 'Umrah. Then, whe we were in Sarif
her menses started. When we came, we circumambulated the Ka'bah and
(performed Sa'i) between As-safa and Al-Marwah. Then, the Messenger
of Allah commanded those of us who did not have a Hadi to exit
Ihram. We said: 'Exit Ihram to what degree?' He said" 'Completely.'
So we had intercourse with out, wives put on perfume, and wore only
four nights away from 'Arafat. The, we entered Ihram on the day of
At-Tarwiyah. The Messenger of Allah entered upon 'Aishah and found
here weeping. He said: 'What is the matter with you?' She said: 'I
have got my menses and the people exited Ihram, but I did not exit
Ihram or did I circumambulate the House, and the people are going
for Hajj now.' He said: 'This is something that Allah ahs decreed
for the daughters of Adam. Perform Ghusl, then begin the Talbiyah
for Hajj.' So she did that and did all the rituals. Then, when she
became pure, she circumambulated the House and (Performed Sa'i)
between As-Safa and Al-Marwah. Then, he said: 'You have exited
Ihram from your Hajj and your 'Umrah at the same time." She said:
'O Messenger of Allah, I feel upset because I only circumambulated
the House during my Hajj.' He said: 'Take here, O 'Abdullah, to
perform 'Umrah from At-Tan'im.' And that was on the night of
Al-Hasbah (the twelfth night of Dhul-Hijjah)."</english-text>
</hadith>
