<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42775</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2764</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 36017, 30234, 20001, 11013, 10511,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، والحارث بن مسكين، قراءة عليه وأنا
أسمع، - واللفظ له - عن ابن القاسم، قال حدثني مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة، قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في حجة الوداع فأهللنا بعمرة ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ من كان معه هدى فليهلل بالحج مع العمرة ثم لا يحل حتى يحل
منهما جميعا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقدمت مكة وأنا حائض فلم أطف بالبيت ولا بين
الصفا والمروة فشكوت ذلك إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏
انقضي رأسك وامتشطي وأهلي بالحج ودعي العمرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعلت فلما قضيت
الحج أرسلني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مع عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر
إلى التنعيم فاعتمرت قال ‏"‏ هذه مكان عمرتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فطاف الذين أهلوا
بالعمرة بالبيت وبين الصفا والمروة ثم حلوا ثم طافوا طوافا آخر بعد أن
رجعوا من منى لحجهم وأما الذين جمعوا الحج والعمرة فإنما طافوا طوافا
واحدا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Aishah said: "We set out with
the Messenger of Allah for the Farewell Pligrimage and we entered
Ihram for 'Umrah, then the Messenger of Allah said: 'Whoever has a
Hadi with him, let him enter Ihram for both Hajj and 'Umrah, then
do not exit Ihram until he exits Ihram for them both.' I came to
Makkah and I had my menses, so I did not circumambulate the House
or (Perform Sa'i) between As-Safa and Al-Marwah. I complained about
that to the Messenger of Allah and he said: 'Undo your hair, and
comb it, and enter Ihram for Hajj, and leave 'Umrah.' When I had
completed Hajj, the Messenger of Allah sent me with 'Abdur-Rahman
bin Abi Bakr to At-Tan'im, and I performed 'Umrah. He said: 'This
is the place of your 'Umrah.' Then those who had entered Ihram for
'Umar circumambulated the House and (performed Sa'i) between
As-Safa and Al-Marwah. Then they exited Ihram, then they performed
Tawaf again, after they came back from Mina for their Hajj. As for
those who combined Hajj and 'Umrah, they only performed one
Tawaf."</english-text>
</hadith>
