<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>42986</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2974</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20428, 20023, 11234, 10898, 11442, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن عبد الله بن، ‏{‏ عبد ‏}‏ الحكم عن شعيب،
قال أنبأنا الليث، عن ابن الهاد، عن جعفر بن محمد، عن أبيه، عن جابر،
قال طاف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالبيت سبعا رمل منها ثلاثا
ومشى أربعا ثم قام عند المقام فصلى ركعتين وقرأ ‏{‏ واتخذوا من مقام
إبراهيم مصلى ‏}‏ ورفع صوته يسمع الناس ثم انصرف فاستلم ثم ذهب فقال
‏"‏ نبدأ بما بدأ الله به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فبدأ بالصفا فرقي عليها حتى بدا له
البيت وقال ثلاث مرات ‏"‏ لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له له الملك
وله الحمد يحيي ويميت وهو على كل شىء قدير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكبر الله وحمده ثم
دعا بما قدر له ثم نزل ماشيا حتى تصوبت قدماه في بطن المسيل فسعى حتى
صعدت قدماه ثم مشى حتى أتى المروة فصعد فيها ثم بدا له البيت فقال ‏"‏
لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له له الملك وله الحمد وهو على كل شىء
قدير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ذلك ثلاث مرات ثم ذكر الله وسبحه وحمده ثم دعا عليها
بما شاء الله فعل هذا حتى فرغ من الطواف ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Jabir said: "The Messenger of
Allah circumambulated the House seven times, walking rapidly in
three circuits and walking (at a normal pace)b in three. Then he
stood at the Maqam (place) of Ibrahim as a place of prayer, raising
his voice so that the people could hear. Then he went and touched
the Black Stone and went (to perform Sai) and said: 'We will start
with that with which Allah started.' So he started with As-Safa,
climbing up until he could see the House and he said three times:
''La ilaha illallah, Wahdahu la sharika lah, lahul-mulku wa
lahul-hamdu, yuhyi wa yumitu, wa huwaala kulli shayin qadir (There
is none worthy of worship except Allah alone with no partner or
associate, His is the dominion and to Him be praise, He gives life
and death, and He has power over all things).' Then exclaimed
Allah's greatness and praised Him, then he supplicated as much as
was decreed for him. Then he came down walking, until he reached
level ground at the bottom of the valley. Then he hastened until
the ground began to rise. Then he walked until he came to Al-Marwah
and climbed up it, and when he could see the house he said: 'La
ilaha illallah, Wahdahu la sharika lah, lahul-mulku wa lahul-hamdu,
yuhyi wa yumitu, wa huwaala kulli shayin qadir (There is none
worthy of worship except Allah alone with no partner or associate,
His is the dominion and to Him be praise, He gives life and death,
and He has power over all things).' He said that three times, then
he remembered Allah, and glorified and praised Him, then he
supplicated there for as long as Allah willed. And he did that
until he had finished Sai."</english-text>
</hadith>
