<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43005</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2993</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Hajj - كتاب مناسك الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 11070, 10644, 11263, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال قرأت على أبي قرة موسى بن
طارق عن ابن جريج، قال حدثني عبد الله بن عثمان بن خثيم، عن أبي
الزبير، عن جابر، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حين رجع من عمرة
الجعرانة بعث أبا بكر على الحج فأقبلنا معه حتى إذا كان بالعرج ثوب
بالصبح ثم استوى ليكبر فسمع الرغوة خلف ظهره فوقف على التكبير فقال
هذه رغوة ناقة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الجدعاء لقد بدا لرسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في الحج فلعله أن يكون رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فنصلي معه فإذا علي عليها فقال له أبو بكر أمير أم رسول قال
لا بل رسول أرسلني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ببراءة أقرؤها على
الناس في مواقف الحج ‏.‏ فقدمنا مكة فلما كان قبل التروية بيوم قام
أبو بكر رضى الله عنه فخطب الناس فحدثهم عن مناسكهم حتى إذا فرغ قام
علي رضى الله عنه فقرأ على الناس براءة حتى ختمها ثم خرجنا معه حتى
إذا كان يوم عرفة قام أبو بكر فخطب الناس فحدثهم عن مناسكهم حتى إذا
فرغ قام علي فقرأ على الناس براءة حتى ختمها ثم كان يوم النحر فأفضنا
فلما رجع أبو بكر خطب الناس فحدثهم عن إفاضتهم وعن نحرهم وعن مناسكهم
فلما فرغ قام علي فقرأ على الناس براءة حتى ختمها فلما كان يوم النفر
الأول قام أبو بكر فخطب الناس فحدثهم كيف ينفرون وكيف يرمون فعلمهم
مناسكهم فلما فرغ قام علي فقرأ براءة على الناس حتى ختمها ‏.‏ قال أبو
عبد الرحمن بن خثيم ليس بالقوي في الحديث وإنما أخرجت هذا لئلا يجعل
ابن جريج عن أبي الزبير وما كتبناه إلا عن إسحاق بن إبراهيم ويحيى بن
سعيد القطان لم يترك حديث ابن خثيم ولا عبد الرحمن إلا أن علي بن
المديني قال ابن خثيم منكر الحديث وكأن علي بن المديني خلق للحديث
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Jabir that: when the Prophet
came back from the Umrah of Al-Jirranah, he sent Abu Bakr to lead
the Hajj. We wnet the him until, when he was in Al-Urj, the Iqamah
for Subh was said, and he stood up to say the Takbir while he heard
the grunting of a camel behind him, and he did not say the Takbir.
He said: "This is the grunting of the camel of the Messenger of
Allah has had second thoughts about the Hajj, and may be he is
here, and we will pray with him." But it was 'Ali on the camel. Abu
Bakr said to him: "(Have you come) as a leader or as messenger?" He
said: "No, as a messenger, sent by the Messenger of Allah with a
declaration of innocence to recite it to the people in the stations
of Hajj. So we came to makkah and one day before the day of
At-Tarwiyah Abu Bakr, may Allah be pleased with him, stood up and
addressed the people telling them about their rituals. When he
finished, Ali, may Allah be pleased with him, stood up and recited
the declaration of innocence to the people until he finished it.
Then we went out with hm and on the day of Arafat. Abu Bakr stood
up and addressed people, telling them about rituals. When he
finished, Ali, may Allah be pleased with him, stood up and recited
the declaration of innocence to the people until he finished it.
Then on the day of Sacrifice, we departed (Ifadah) and when Abu
Bakr came back, eh addressed the people, telling them about their
departure (Ifadah), sacrifice and rituals. When he finished, Ali,
may Allah be pleased with him, stood up and recited the declaration
of innocence to the people until he finished it. On the first day
of An-Nafr (The 12th of Dhul-Hijjah), Abu Bakr stood up and
addressed the people, telling them how to offer their sacrifice and
how to stone the Jamrat, and teaching them their rituals. When he
had finished, "Ali, may Allah be pleased with him, stood up and
recited the declaration of innocence to the people until he
finished it. (Daif)Abu Abdur-Rahman (An-Nasai) said: Ibn Khuthaim
is not strong in Hadith, and I only narrated this so it would not
be considered to be from Ibn Juraij from Abu Az-Zubai. And we did
not write it except from Ishaq bin Rahuyah bin Ibrahm. And yahya
bin Saeed Al-Qattan did not abandon the narrations of Ibn Khuthaim,
or dod Abdur-Rahamn. However, Ali bin Al-Madini said: "Ibn Khuthaim
is Munkar in Hadith," and Ali bin Al-Madini is more knowledgeable
of Hadith.</english-text>
</hadith>
