<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43236</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3224</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20158, 20436, 20160, 11062, 11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن نصر، قال حدثنا أيوب بن سليمان بن بلال،
قال حدثني أبو بكر بن أبي أويس، عن سليمان بن بلال، قال قال يحيى -
يعني ابن سعيد - وأخبرني ابن شهاب، قال حدثني عروة بن الزبير، وابن
عبد الله بن ربيعة، عن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأم سلمة
زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن أبا حذيفة بن عتبة بن ربيعة بن عبد
شمس - وكان ممن شهد بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - تبنى
سالما وهو مولى لامرأة من الأنصار كما تبنى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم زيد بن حارثة وأنكح أبو حذيفة بن عتبة سالما ابنة أخيه هند ابنة
الوليد بن عتبة بن ربيعة وكانت هند بنت الوليد بن عتبة من المهاجرات
الأول وهي يومئذ من أفضل أيامى قريش فلما أنزل الله عز وجل في زيد بن
حارثة ‏{‏ ادعوهم لآبائهم هو أقسط عند الله ‏}‏ رد كل أحد ينتمي من
أولئك إلى أبيه فإن لم يكن يعلم أبوه رد إلى مواليه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Aishah: It was narrated from 'Aishah the
wife of the Prophet, and Umm Salamah the wife of the Prophet that
Abu Hudhaifah bin 'Utbah bin Rabi'ah bin Abd Shams --who was one of
those who had been present at Badr with the Messenger of Allah--
adopted Salim --who was the freed slave of an Ansari woman-- as the
Messenger of Allah had adopted Zaid bin Harithah. Abu Hudhaifah bin
'Utbah married Salim to his brother's daughter Hind bint Al-Walid
bin 'Utbah bin Rabi'ah. Hind bint Al-Walid bin 'Utbah was one of
the first Muhajir women, and at that time she was one of the best
single women of the Quraish. When Allah, the Mighty and Sublime,
revealed the following concerning Zaid bin Harithah: "Call them by
(the names of) their fathers, that is more just with Allah. But if
you know not their fathers' (names, call them) your brothers in
Faith and Mawalikum (your freed slaves).' Each of them went back to
being called after his father, and if a person's father was
unknown, he was named after his former masters.</english-text>
</hadith>
