<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43249</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3237</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>36587, 20250, 20258, 11278, 11432, 224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني عبد الرحمن بن محمد بن سلام، قال حدثنا عبد الصمد
بن عبد الوارث، قال سمعت أبي قال، حدثنا حسين المعلم، قال حدثني عبد
الله بن بريدة، قال حدثني عامر بن شراحيل الشعبي، أنه سمع فاطمة بنت
قيس، - وكانت من المهاجرات الأول - قالت خطبني عبد الرحمن بن عوف في
نفر من أصحاب محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم وخطبني رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم على مولاه أسامة بن زيد وقد كنت حدثت أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ‏"‏ من أحبني فليحب أسامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما كلمني رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قلت أمري بيدك فأنكحني من شئت ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ انطلقي إلى
أم شريك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وأم شريك امرأة غنية من الأنصار عظيمة النفقة في سبيل
الله عز وجل ينزل عليها الضيفان فقلت سأفعل ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لا تفعلي فإن
أم شريك كثيرة الضيفان فإني أكره أن يسقط عنك خمارك أو ينكشف الثوب عن
ساقيك فيرى القوم منك بعض ما تكرهين ولكن انتقلي إلى ابن عمك عبد الله
بن عمرو بن أم مكتوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وهو رجل من بني فهر فانتقلت إليه ‏.‏
مختصر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Amir bin Shurahbil Ash-Sha'bi: 'Amir bin
Shurahbil Ash-Sha'bi narrated that he heard Fatimah bint Qais--who
was one of the first Muhajir women-- say: 'Abdur-Rahman bin 'Awf
proposed marriage to me, along with others of the Companions of
Muhammad. And the Messenger of Allah proposed that I marry his
freed slave, Usamah bin Zaid. I was told that the Messenger of
Allah had said: 'Whoever loves me, let him love Usamah.' When the
Messenger of Allah spoke to me I said: 'My affairs are in your
hands; marry me to whomever you wish.' He said: 'Go to Umm Sharik.'
Umm Sharik was a rich Ansari woman who used to spend a great deal
in the cause of Allah, and she always had a lot of guests. I said:
'I will do that.' He said: 'Do not do that, for Umm Sharik has a
lot of guests, and I would not like your Khimar to fall off, or
your shins to become uncovered, and the people to see something of
you that you do not want them to see. Rather go to your cousin (son
of your paternal uncle) 'Abdullah bin 'Amr bin Umm Maktum, who is a
man of Banu Fihr.' So I went to him."</english-text>
</hadith>
