<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43257</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3245</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 36017, 30234, 20001, 1945, 10567,
224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، والحارث بن مسكين، قراءة عليه وأنا
أسمع، - واللفظ لمحمد - عن ابن القاسم، عن مالك، عن عبد الله بن يزيد،
عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، عن فاطمة بنت قيس، أن أبا عمرو بن حفص،
طلقها البتة وهو غائب فأرسل إليها وكيله بشعير فسخطته ‏.‏ فقال والله
ما لك علينا من شىء ‏.‏ فجاءت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك
له فقال ‏"‏ ليس لك نفقة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأمرها أن تعتد في بيت أم شريك ثم
قال ‏"‏ تلك امرأة يغشاها أصحابي فاعتدي عند ابن أم مكتوم فإنه رجل
أعمى تضعين ثيابك فإذا حللت فآذنيني ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فلما حللت ذكرت له
أن معاوية بن أبي سفيان وأبا جهم خطباني فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أما أبو جهم فلا يضع عصاه عن عاتقه وأما معاوية فصعلوك لا
مال له ولكن انكحي أسامة بن زيد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكرهته ثم قال ‏"‏ انكحي
أسامة بن زيد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فنكحته فجعل الله عز وجل فيه خيرا واغتبطت به
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Fatimah bint Qais that Abu 'Amr
bin Hafs issued a final divorce to her while he was absent. His
deputy sent some barley to her but she did not like it. He said:
"By Allah, you have no rights over us." She went to the Messenger
of Allah and told him about that, and he said: "You have no right
to maintenance." He told her to observe her 'Iddah in the house of
Umm Sharik, then he said: "She is a woman whose house is frequented
by my Companions. Observe your 'Iddah in the house of Ibn Umm
Maktum, for he is a blind man and you can take off your garment.
And when your 'Iddah is over, let me know." She said: "When my
'Iddah was over I told him that Mu'awiyah bin Abi Sufyan and Abu
Jahm had proposed marriage to me. The Messenger of Allah said: 'As
for Abu Jahm, his stick never leaves his shoulder, and as for
Mu'awiyah he is a poor man who has no wealth. Rather you should
marry Usamah bin Zaid.' I did not like the idea, then he said:
'Marry Usamah bin Zaid.' So I married him and Allah created a lot
of good in him, and others felt jealous of my good
fortune."</english-text>
</hadith>
