<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43265</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3253</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 11048, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا ابن أبي الموال، عن محمد بن
المنكدر، عن جابر بن عبد الله، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يعلمنا الاستخارة في الأمور كلها كما يعلمنا السورة من القرآن يقول
‏"‏ إذا هم أحدكم بالأمر فليركع ركعتين من غير الفريضة ثم يقول اللهم
إني أستخيرك بعلمك وأستعينك بقدرتك وأسألك من فضلك العظيم فإنك تقدر
ولا أقدر وتعلم ولا أعلم وأنت علام الغيوب اللهم إن كنت تعلم أن هذا
الأمر خير لي في ديني ومعاشي وعاقبة أمري - أو قال في عاجل أمري وآجله
- فاقدره لي ويسره لي ثم بارك لي فيه وإن كنت تعلم أن هذا الأمر شر لي
في ديني ومعاشي وعاقبة أمري - أو قال في عاجل أمري وآجله - فاصرفه عني
واصرفني عنه واقدر لي الخير حيث كان ثم أرضني به - قال - ويسمي حاجته
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Jabir bin 'Abdullah said: "The
Messenger of Allah used to teach his Companions to perform
Istikharah in all matters, just as he used to teach them Surahs
from the Qur'an. He said: 'If any one of you is deliberating about
a decision he has to make, then let him pray two Rak'ahs of
non-obligatory prayer, then say: Allahumma inni astakhiruka bi
'ilmika wa astaqdiruka bi qudratika wa as'aluka min fadlika, fa
innaka taqdiru wa la aqdir, wa ta'lamu wa la a'lam, wa anta 'allam
al-ghuyub. Allahumma in kunta ta'lamu anna hadhal-amra khayrun li
fi dini wa ma'ashi wa aqibati amri faqdurhu li wa yassirhu li
thumma barik li fihi. Allahumma, wa in kunta ta'lamu annahu sharrun
li fi dini wa ma'ashi wa 'aqibati amri fasrifhu 'anni wasrifni
'anhu waqdur li al-khayr haythu kana, thumma radini bihi. (O Allah,
I seek Your guidance (in making a choice) by virtue of Your
knowledge, and I seek ability by virtue of Your power, and I ask
You of Your great bounty. You have power, I have none. And You
know, I know not. You are the Knower of hidden things. O Allah, if
in Your knowledge, this matter (then it should be mentioned by
name) is good for me in my religion, my livelihood and my affairs
(or: both in this world and in the Hereafter), then ordain it for
me, make it easy for me, and bless it for me. And if in Your
knowledge it is bad for me and for my religion, my livelihood and
my affairs (or: for me both in this world and the next), then turn
it away from me and turn me away from it, and ordain for me the
good wherever it may be and make me pleased with
it.)"</english-text>
</hadith>
