<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43351</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3339</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20184, 11349, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا يعقوب، عن أبي حازم، عن سهل بن
سعد، أن امرأة، جاءت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت يا رسول الله
جئت لأهب نفسي لك ‏.‏ فنظر إليها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصعد
النظر إليها وصوبه ثم طأطأ رأسه فلما رأت المرأة أنه لم يقض فيها شيئا
جلست فقام رجل من أصحابه فقال أى رسول الله إن لم يكن لك بها حاجة
فزوجنيها ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل عندك من شىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال لا والله ما وجدت
شيئا ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ انظر ولو خاتما من حديد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع فقال
لا والله يا رسول الله ولا خاتما من حديد ولكن هذا إزاري - قال سهل ما
له رداء - فلها نصفه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما
تصنع بإزارك إن لبسته لم يكن عليها منه شىء وإن لبسته لم يكن عليك منه
شىء ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجلس الرجل حتى طال مجلسه ثم قام فرآه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم موليا فأمر به فدعي فلما جاء قال ‏"‏ ماذا معك من القرآن
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال معي سورة كذا وسورة كذا ‏.‏ عددها ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ هل تقرؤهن
عن ظهر قلب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ملكتكها بما معك من القرآن
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Sahl bin Sa'd that a woman came
to the Messenger of Allah and said: "O Messenger of Allah, I have
come to offer myself to you (in marriage)." The Messenger of Allah
looked her up and down then lowered his head. When the woman saw
that he was not saying anything about her, she sat down. A man
among his Companions stood up and said: "O Messenger of Allah, if
you do not want to marry her, then marry me to her." He said: "Do
you have anything?" He said: "No, by Allah, I do not have
anything." He said: "Look, even if it is only an iron ring." He
went, then he came back and said: "No, by Allah, O Messenger of
Allah, not even an iron ring, but this is my Izar (lower garment)"
- Sahl said: "He did not have a Rida' (upper garment)" - "she can
have half of it." The Messenger of Allah said: "What could she do
with your Izar? If you wear it, she will not have any of it, and if
she wears it, you will not have any of it." The man sat down for a
long time, then he got up, and the Messenger of Allah saw him
leaving, so he ordered that he be called back. When he came, he
said: "What do you know of the Qur'an?" He said: "I know Surah
such-and-such, and Surah such-and-such," and listed them. He said:
"Can you recite them by heart?" He said: "Yes." He said: "Then I
marry you to her on the basis of what you know of the
Qur'an."</english-text>
</hadith>
