<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43366</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3354</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>20320, 11067, 11051, 11017, 11054</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبد الله بن محمد بن عبد الرحمن، قال حدثنا أبو
سعيد عبد الرحمن بن عبد الله، عن زائدة بن قدامة، عن منصور، عن
إبراهيم، عن علقمة، والأسود، قالا أتي عبد الله في رجل تزوج امرأة ولم
يفرض لها فتوفي قبل أن يدخل بها فقال عبد الله سلوا هل تجدون فيها
أثرا قالوا يا أبا عبد الرحمن ما نجد فيها يعني أثرا ‏.‏ قال أقول
برأيي فإن كان صوابا فمن الله لها كمهر نسائها لا وكس ولا شطط ولها
الميراث وعليها العدة فقام رجل من أشجع فقال في مثل هذا قضى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فينا في امرأة يقال لها بروع بنت واشق تزوجت رجلا
فمات قبل أن يدخل بها فقضى لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بمثل
صداق نسائها ولها الميراث وعليها العدة ‏.‏ فرفع عبد الله يديه وكبر
‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الرحمن لا أعلم أحدا قال في هذا الحديث الأسود غير
زائدة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Alqamah and Al-Aswad said: "A
man was brought to 'Abdullah who had married a woman without naming
a dowry for her, then he died before consummating the marriage with
her. 'Abdullah said: 'Ask whether they can find any report about
that.' They said: 'O Abu 'Abdur-Rahman, we cannot find any report
about that.' He said: 'I will say what I think, and if it is
correct then it is from Allah. She should have a dowry like that of
her peers and no less, with no injustice, and she may inherit from
him, and she has to observe the 'Iddah.' A man from Ashja' stood up
and said: "The Messenger of Allah passed a similar judgment among
us concerning a woman called Birwa' bint Washiq. She married a man
who died before consummating the marriage with her, and the
Messenger of Allah ruled that she should be given a dowry like that
of her peers, and she could inherit, and she had to observe the
'Iddah.' 'Abdullah raised his hands and said the
Takbir."</english-text>
</hadith>
