<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43392</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3380</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Marriage - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30249, 20208, 11295, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا زياد بن أيوب، قال حدثنا إسماعيل ابن علية، قال
حدثنا عبد العزيز بن صهيب، عن أنس، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
غزا خيبر فصلينا عندها الغداة بغلس فركب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وركب أبو طلحة وأنا رديف أبي طلحة فأخذ نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في زقاق خيبر وإن ركبتي لتمس فخذ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وإني
لأرى بياض فخذ نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما دخل القرية قال ‏"‏
الله أكبر خربت خيبر إنا إذا نزلنا بساحة قوم فساء صباح المنذرين ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالها ثلاث مرات قال وخرج القوم إلى أعمالهم - قال عبد العزيز -
فقالوا محمد - قال عبد العزيز وقال بعض أصحابنا والخميس - وأصبناها
عنوة فجمع السبى فجاء دحية فقال يا نبي الله أعطني جارية من السبى ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ اذهب فخذ جارية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأخذ صفية بنت حيى فجاء رجل إلى النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا نبي الله أعطيت دحية صفية بنت حيى سيدة
قريظة والنضير ما تصلح إلا لك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ادعوه بها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجاء بها
فلما نظر إليها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ خذ جارية من السبى
غيرها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وإن نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أعتقها وتزوجها
‏.‏ فقال له ثابت يا أبا حمزة ما أصدقها قال نفسها أعتقها وتزوجها -
قال - حتى إذا كان بالطريق جهزتها له أم سليم فأهدتها إليه من الليل
فأصبح عروسا قال ‏"‏ من كان عنده شىء فليجئ به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال وبسط نطعا
فجعل الرجل يجيء بالأقط وجعل الرجل يجيء بالتمر وجعل الرجل يجيء
بالسمن فحاسوا حيسة فكانت وليمة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Anas: "The Messenger of Allah
invaded Khaibar and we prayed Al-Ghadah (Fajr) there (early in the
morning) when it was still dark. Then the Prophet rode and Abu
Talha rode, and I was riding behind Abu Talha. The Prophet of Allah
passed through the lane of Khaibar quickly, and my knee was
touching the thigh of the Messenger of Allah, and I could see the
whiteness of the thigh of the Prophet. When he entered the town he
said: 'Allahu Akbar, Khaibar is destroyed! Whenever we approach a
(hostile) nation to fight, evil will be the morning for those who
have been warned.' He said this three times. The people came out
for their work." (One of the narrators) 'Abdul-'Aziz said: "They
said: 'Muhammad (has come)!'" 'Abdul-'Aziz said: "Some of our
companions said: 'With his army.'" "We conquered Khaibar and
gathered the captives. Dihyah came and said: 'O Prophet of Allah,
give me a slave girl from among the captives.' He said: 'Go and
take a slave girl.' He took Safiyyah bint Huyayy. Then a man came
to the Prophet and said: 'O Messenger of Allah, you gave Dihyah
Safiyyah bint Huyayy, and she is the chief mistress of Quraizah and
An-Nadir, and she is fit for no one but you.' He said: 'Call him to
bring her.' When the Prophet saw her, he said: 'Take any other
slave girl from among the captives.'" He said: "The Prophet of
Allah set her free and married her." (One of the narrators) Thabit
said to him: "O Abu Hamzah, what dowry did he give her?" He (Anas)
said: "Herself; he set her free and married her." He said: "While
on the road, Umm Sulaim fitted her out and presented her to him in
the night, and the following morning he was a bridegroom. He said:
'Whoever has anything, let him bring it.' He spread out a leather
cloth and men came with cottage cheese, dates, and ghee, and they
made Hais, and that was the Walimah (wedding feast) of the
Messenger of Allah."</english-text>
</hadith>
