<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43463</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3451</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20028, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال أنبأنا جرير، عن هشام بن
عروة، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، قالت كاتبت بريرة على نفسها بتسع أواق في كل
سنة بأوقية فأتت عائشة تستعينها فقالت لا إلا أن يشاءوا أن أعدها لهم
عدة واحدة ويكون الولاء لي ‏.‏ فذهبت بريرة فكلمت في ذلك أهلها فأبوا
عليها إلا أن يكون الولاء لهم فجاءت إلى عائشة وجاء رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم عند ذلك فقالت لها ما قال أهلها فقالت لاها الله إذا
إلا أن يكون الولاء لي ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما
هذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالت يا رسول الله إن بريرة أتتني تستعين بي على كتابتها
فقلت لا إلا أن يشاءوا أن أعدها لهم عدة واحدة ويكون الولاء لي فذكرت
ذلك لأهلها فأبوا عليها إلا أن يكون الولاء لهم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ابتاعيها واشترطي لهم الولاء فإن الولاء لمن
أعتق ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قام فخطب الناس فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ ما
بال أقوام يشترطون شروطا ليست في كتاب الله عز وجل يقولون أعتق فلانا
والولاء لي كتاب الله عز وجل أحق وشرط الله أوثق وكل شرط ليس في كتاب
الله فهو باطل وإن كان مائة شرط ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فخيرها رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم من زوجها وكان عبدا فاختارت نفسها ‏.‏ قال عروة فلو كان حرا
ما خيرها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Aishah said: "Barirah made a
contract that she would be freed in return for nine Awaq, one
Uqiyyah to be paid each year." She came to 'Aishah asking for help
and she said: "No, not unless they agree to accept the sum in one
payment, and that the Wala' will go to me." Barirah went and spoke
to her masters but they insisted that the Wala' should be for them.
She came to 'Aishah and the Messenger of Allah came, and she told
her what her masters had said. She said: "No, by Allah, not unless
Wala' is to me." The Messenger of Allah said: "What is this?" She
said: "O Messenger of Allah, Barirah came to me and asked me to
help her with her contract of manumission, and I said no, not
unless they agree to accept the sum in one payment, and that the
Wala' will be for me. She mentioned that to her masters and they
insisted that the Wala' should be for them." The Messenger of Allah
said: "Buy her, and stipulate that the Wala' is for the one who
sets the slave free." Then he stood up and addressed the people and
said: "What is the matter with people who stipulate conditions that
are not in the Book of Allah, the Mighty and Sublime? They say: 'I
set so-and-so free but the Wala' will be to me.' Every condition
that is not in the Book of Allah, the Mighty and Sublime, is a
false condition, even if there are a hundred conditions." And the
Messenger of Allah gave her the choice with regard to her husband
who was still a slave, and she chose herself. 'Urwah said: "If he
had been free the Messenger of Allah would not have given her the
choice."</english-text>
</hadith>
