<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43482</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3470</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30412, 20023, 11062, 10530, 10535, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عيسى بن حماد، قال أنبأنا الليث، عن يحيى بن
سعيد، عن عبد الرحمن بن القاسم، عن القاسم بن محمد، عن ابن عباس، أنه
قال ذكر التلاعن عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال عاصم بن عدي
في ذلك قولا ثم انصرف فأتاه رجل من قومه يشكو إليه أنه وجد مع امرأته
رجلا قال عاصم ما ابتليت بهذا إلا بقولي فذهب به إلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأخبره بالذي وجد عليه امرأته وكان ذلك الرجل مصفرا
قليل اللحم سبط الشعر وكان الذي ادعى عليه أنه وجده عند أهله آدم خدلا
كثير اللحم ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اللهم بين ‏"‏
‏.‏ فوضعت شبيها بالرجل الذي ذكر زوجها أنه وجده عندها فلاعن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بينهما ‏.‏ فقال رجل لابن عباس في المجلس أهي
التي قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو رجمت أحدا بغير بينة
رجمت هذه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ابن عباس لا تلك امرأة كانت تظهر في الإسلام
الشر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Ibn 'Abbas said: "Mention of
Li'an was made in the presence of the Messenger of Allah and 'Asim
bin 'Adiyy said something about that, then he went away. A man from
among his people came to him, complaining that he had found a man
with his wife. 'Asim said: 'I was only put to this test because of
what I said.' He took him to the Messenger of Allah and told him of
the situation in which he found his wife. That man was pale and
slim with straight hair, and the one whom he claimed to have found
with his wife was dark and well-built. The Messenger of Allah said:
'O Allah, make it clear to me.' Then she gave birth to a child who
resembled the one whom her husband said he had found with her. So
the Messenger of Allah conducted the procedure of Li'an between
them." A man in the gathering said to Ibn 'Abbas: "Was she the one
of whom the Messenger of Allah said: 'If I were to have stoned
anyone without evidence I would have stoned this one?'" Ibn 'Abbas
said: "No, that was a woman who used to do mischief even after
becoming Muslim."</english-text>
</hadith>
