<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43532</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3520</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>38462, 30373, 20459, 11013, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا كثير بن عبيد، قال حدثنا محمد بن حرب، عن
الزبيدي، عن الزهري، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، أن عبد الله بن عتبة،
كتب إلى عمر بن عبد الله بن الأرقم الزهري أن ادخل، على سبيعة بنت
الحارث الأسلمية فاسألها عما أفتاها به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في حملها ‏.‏ قال فدخل عليها عمر بن عبد الله فسألها فأخبرته أنها
كانت تحت سعد ابن خولة - وكان من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
ممن شهد بدرا - فتوفي عنها في حجة الوداع فولدت قبل أن تمضي لها أربعة
أشهر وعشرا من وفاة زوجها فلما تعلت من نفاسها دخل عليها أبو السنابل
- رجل من بني عبد الدار - فرآها متجملة فقال لعلك تريدين النكاح قبل
أن تمر عليك أربعة أشهر وعشرا ‏.‏ قالت فلما سمعت ذلك من أبي السنابل
جئت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فحدثته حديثي ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد حللت حين وضعت حملك ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Ubaidullah bin 'Abdullah that
'Abdullah bin 'Utbah wrote to 'Umar bin 'Abdullah bin Al-Arqam
Az-Zuhri, telling him: "Go to Subai'ah bint Al-Harith
Al-Aslamiyyah, and ask her about the ruling of the Messenger of
Allah concerning her pregnancy." He said: "So 'Umar bin 'Abdullah
went to her and asked her. She told him that she was married to
Sa'd bin Khawlah, who was one of the Companions of the Messenger of
Allah who had been present at Badr. He died during the Farewell
Pilgrimage, and she gave birth before four months and ten days had
passed since her husband's death. When her Nifas ended, Abu
As-Sanabil -a man from Banu 'Abd Ad-Dar- went to her and saw that
she had adorned herself. He said: 'Perhaps you want to get married
before four months and ten days has passed?' She said: 'When I
heard that from Abu As-Sanabil, I went to the Messenger of Allah
and told him my story. The Messenger of Allah said: 'It is
permissible for you to marry when you gave birth.''"</english-text>
</hadith>
