<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43566</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3552</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>38429, 28388, 20428, 11013, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمرو بن عثمان بن سعيد بن كثير بن دينار، قال
حدثنا أبي، عن شعيب، قال قال الزهري أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن
عتبة، أن عبد الله بن عمرو بن عثمان، طلق ابنة سعيد بن زيد - وأمها
حمنة بنت قيس - البتة فأمرتها خالتها فاطمة بنت قيس بالانتقال من بيت
عبد الله بن عمرو وسمع بذلك، مروان فأرسل إليها فأمرها أن ترجع إلى
مسكنها حتى تنقضي عدتها فأرسلت إليه تخبره أن خالتها فاطمة أفتتها
بذلك وأخبرتها أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أفتاها بالانتقال حين
طلقها أبو عمرو بن حفص المخزومي فأرسل مروان قبيصة بن ذؤيب إلى فاطمة
فسألها عن ذلك فزعمت أنها كانت تحت أبي عمرو لما أمر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم علي بن أبي طالب على اليمن خرج معه فأرسل إليها
بتطليقة وهي بقية طلاقها فأمر لها الحارث بن هشام وعياش بن أبي ربيعة
بنفقتها فأرسلت إلى الحارث وعياش تسألهما النفقة التي أمر لها بها
زوجها فقالا والله ما لها علينا نفقة إلا أن تكون حاملا وما لها أن
تسكن في مسكننا إلا بإذننا ‏.‏ فزعمت فاطمة أنها أتت رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك له فصدقهما قالت فقلت أين أنتقل يا رسول
الله فقال ‏"‏ انتقلي عند ابن أم مكتوم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وهو الأعمى الذي عاتبه
الله عز وجل في كتابه فانتقلت عنده فكنت أضع ثيابي عنده حتى أنكحها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم زعمت أسامة بن زيد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Ubaidullah bin 'Abdullah bin 'Utbah narrated that
'Abdullah bin 'Amr bin 'Uthman divorced the daughter of Sa'eed bin
Zaid -whose mother was Hamnah bint Qais- irrevocably. Her maternal
aunt Fatimah bint Qais told her to move from the house of 'Abdullah
bin 'Amr. Marwan heard of that, so he sent word to her, telling her
to go back to her home until her 'Iddah was over. She sent a word
to him telling him that her maternal aunt Fatimah had issued a
Fatwa to that effect, and she told her that the Messenger of Allah
had issued a Fatwa to her, telling her to move when Abu 'Amr bin
Hafs Al-Makhzumi divorced her. Marwan sent Qabisah bin Dhu'aib to
Fatimah to ask her about that. She said that she had been married
to Abu 'Amr when the Messenger of Allah appointed 'Ali bin Abi
Talib as governor of Yemen, and he went out with him, then he sent
word to her divorcing her, and that was the final divorce for her.
He told her to ask Al-Harith bin Hisham and 'Ayyash for her
provisions that her husband had allocated for her. They said: "By
Allah, she is not entitled to any provision. So, she sent to
Al-Harith bin Hisham and 'Ayyash asking them for the provisions
from us unless she is pregnant, and she has no right to live in our
house unless we permit her." Fatimah said that she went to the
Messenger of Allah and told him about that and he said that they
had told the truth. She said: "I said: 'Where shall I move to, O
Messenger of Allah?' He said: 'Move to the house of Ibn Umm Maktum'
-who was the blind man, concerning whom Allah rebuked him in His
Book. I moved to his house, and I used to take off my outer
garments." Then the Messenger of Allah married her to Usamah bin
Zaid.</english-text>
</hadith>
