<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43568</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3554</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 30555, 20648, 19950, 11023</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زكريا بن يحيى، قال حدثنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال
حدثنا علي بن الحسين بن واقد، قال حدثني أبي قال، حدثنا يزيد النحوي،
عن عكرمة، عن ابن عباس، في قوله ‏{‏ ما ننسخ من آية أو ننسها نأت بخير
منها أو مثلها ‏}‏ وقال ‏{‏ وإذا بدلنا آية مكان آية والله أعلم بما
ينزل ‏}‏ الآية وقال ‏{‏ يمحو الله ما يشاء ويثبت وعنده أم الكتاب ‏}‏
فأول ما نسخ من القرآن القبلة وقال ‏{‏ والمطلقات يتربصن بأنفسهن
ثلاثة قروء ولا يحل لهن أن يكتمن ما خلق الله في أرحامهن ‏}‏ إلى قوله
‏{‏ إن أرادوا إصلاحا ‏}‏ وذلك بأن الرجل كان إذا طلق امرأته فهو أحق
برجعتها وإن طلقها ثلاثا فنسخ ذلك وقال ‏{‏ الطلاق مرتان فإمساك
بمعروف أو تسريح بإحسان ‏}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Ibn 'Abbas, regarding Allah's
saying: "Whatever a Verse do We abrogate or cause to be forgotten,
We bring a better one or similar to it." and "And when We change a
Verse in place of another -and Allah knows best what He sends down"
(Al-Nahl 16:101) and "Allah blots out what He wills and confirms
(what He wills). And with Him is the Mother of the Book." The first
thing that was abrogated in the Qur'an was the Qiblah. And He said:
"And divorced women shall wait (as regards their marriage) for
three menstrual periods, and it is not lawful for them to conceal
what Allah has created in their wombs, if they believe in Allah and
the Last Day." "And their husbands have better right to take them
back in that period, if they wish for reconciliation." -that is
because when a man divorced his wife, he had more right to take her
back, even if he had divorced her three times. Then (Allah)
abrogated that and said: "The divorce is twice, after that, either
you retain her on reasonable terms or release her with
kindness."</english-text>
</hadith>
