<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43577</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>28</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3563</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Horses, Races and Shooting - كتاب
الخيل</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 36017, 30234, 20001, 11163, 11161,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، والحارث بن مسكين، قراءة عليه وأنا
أسمع، - واللفظ له - عن ابن القاسم، قال حدثني مالك، عن زيد بن أسلم،
عن أبي صالح السمان، عن أبي هريرة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ الخيل لرجل أجر ولرجل ستر وعلى رجل وزر فأما الذي هي له أجر
فرجل ربطها في سبيل الله فأطال لها في مرج أو روضة فما أصابت في طيلها
ذلك في المرج أو الروضة كان له حسنات ولو أنها قطعت طيلها ذلك فاستنت
شرفا أو شرفين كانت آثارها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وفي حديث الحارث ‏"‏ وأرواثها
حسنات له ولو أنها مرت بنهر فشربت منه ولم يرد أن تسقى كان ذلك حسنات
فهي له أجر ورجل ربطها تغنيا وتعففا ولم ينس حق الله عز وجل في رقابها
ولا ظهورها فهي لذلك ستر ورجل ربطها فخرا ورياء ونواء لأهل الإسلام
فهي على ذلك وزر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وسئل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عن الحمير
فقال ‏"‏ لم ينزل على فيها شىء إلا هذه الآية الجامعة الفاذة ‏{‏ فمن
يعمل مثقال ذرة خيرا يره * ومن يعمل مثقال ذرة شرا يره ‏}‏ ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Hurairah that the Messenger
of Allah said: "Horses may bring reward to a man, or they may be a
means of protection, or they may be a burden (of sin). As for that
which brings reward, it is a man who keeps it for the cause of
Allah and ties it with a long rope in a pasture or a garden;
whatever it eats or drinks in that pasture or garden will count as
good deeds for him. If it breaks its rope and jumps over one or two
hills, its footsteps" -and according to the Hadith of Al-Harith,
"its dung will count as good deeds for him. If it passes by a river
and drinks from it, even though (its owner) did not intend to give
it water from that river, that will also bring him reward. If a man
keeps a horse in order to earn an independent living and avoid
asking others for help, and he does not forget his duty toward
Allah with regard to their (the horses') necks and backs, then they
will be a means of protection for him. If a man keeps horses out of
pride, to show off before others and to fight the Muslims, then
that will be a burden (of sin) for him." The Prophet was asked
about donkeys and he said: "Nothing has been revealed to me
concerning them except this Verse which is comprehensive in
meaning: 'So whosoever does good equal to the weight of an atom (or
a small ant) shall see it. And whosoever does evil equal to the
weight of an atom (or a small ant) shall see it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
