<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43622</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3608</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Endowments - كتاب الإحباس</chapter>
<chain-index>30249, 20232, 11286, 10673</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني زياد بن أيوب، قال حدثنا سعيد بن عامر، عن يحيى
بن أبي الحجاج، عن سعيد الجريري، عن ثمامة بن حزن القشيري، قال شهدت
الدار حين أشرف عليهم عثمان فقال أنشدكم بالله وبالإسلام هل تعلمون أن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قدم المدينة وليس بها ماء يستعذب غير
بئر رومة فقال ‏"‏ من يشتري بئر رومة فيجعل فيها دلوه مع دلاء
المسلمين بخير له منها في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاشتريتها من صلب مالي فجعلت
دلوي فيها مع دلاء المسلمين وأنتم اليوم تمنعوني من الشرب منها حتى
أشرب من ماء البحر قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدكم بالله والإسلام هل
تعلمون أني جهزت جيش العسرة من مالي قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدكم
بالله والإسلام هل تعلمون أن المسجد ضاق بأهله فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من يشتري بقعة آل فلان فيزيدها في المسجد بخير له
منها في الجنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاشتريتها من صلب مالي فزدتها في المسجد وأنتم
تمنعوني أن أصلي فيه ركعتين قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال أنشدكم بالله
والإسلام هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان على ثبير
ثبير مكة ومعه أبو بكر وعمر وأنا فتحرك الجبل فركضه رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم برجله وقال ‏"‏ اسكن ثبير فإنما عليك نبي وصديق
وشهيدان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا اللهم نعم ‏.‏ قال الله أكبر شهدوا لي ورب
الكعبة ‏.‏ يعني أني شهيد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Thumamah bin Hazn Al-Qushairi
said: "I was present at the house when 'Uthman looked out over them
and said: 'I adjure you by Allah and by Islam, are you aware that
when the Messenger of Allah came to Al-Madinah, and it had no water
that was considered sweet (suitable for drinking) except the well
of Rumah, he said: "Who will buy the well of Rumah and dip his
bucket in it alongside the buckets of the Muslims, in return for a
better one in Paradise?" and I bought it with my capital and dipped
my bucket into it alongside the buckets of the Muslims? Yet today
you are preventing me from drinking from it, so that I have to
drink salty water.' They said: 'By Allah, yes.' He said: 'I adjure
you by Allah and by Islam, are you aware that I equipped the army
of Al-'Usrah (Tabuk) from my own wealth?' They said: 'By Allah,
yes.' He said: 'I adjure you by Allah and by Islam, are you aware
that when the Masjid became too small for the people and the
Messenger of Allah said: Who will buy the plot of the family of so
and so and add it to the Masjid, in return for a better plot in
Paradise? I bought it with my capital and added it to the Masjid?
Yet now you are preventing me from praying two Rak'ahs therein.'
They said: 'By Allah, yes.' He said: 'I adjure you by Allah and by
Islam, are you aware that when the Messenger of Allah was atop
Thabir -the Thabir in Makkah- and with him were Abu Bakr, 'Umar and
myself, the mountain shook, and the Messenger of Allah kicked it
with his foot and said: Be still, Thabir, for upon you are a
Prophet, a Siddiq and two martyrs?' They said: 'By Allah, yes.' He
said: 'Allahu Akbar! They have testified for me, by the Lord of the
Ka'bah' -i.e., that I am a martyr."</english-text>
</hadith>
