<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43620</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3606</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Endowments - كتاب الإحباس</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20288, 11289, 15097, 11112</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال أنبأنا المعتمر بن سليمان،
قال سمعت أبي يحدث، عن حصين بن عبد الرحمن، عن عمرو بن جاوان، - رجل
من بني تميم - وذاك أني قلت له أرأيت اعتزال الأحنف بن قيس ما كان قال
سمعت الأحنف يقول أتيت المدينة وأنا حاج فبينا نحن في منازلنا نضع
رحالنا إذ أتى آت فقال قد اجتمع الناس في المسجد فاطلعت فإذا يعني
الناس مجتمعون وإذا بين أظهرهم نفر قعود فإذا هو علي بن أبي طالب
والزبير وطلحة وسعد بن أبي وقاص رحمة الله عليهم فلما قمت عليهم قيل
هذا عثمان بن عفان قد جاء - قال - فجاء وعليه ملية صفراء فقلت لصاحبي
كما أنت حتى أنظر ما جاء به ‏.‏ فقال عثمان أها هنا علي أها هنا
الزبير أها هنا طلحة أها هنا سعد قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدكم بالله
الذي لا إله إلا هو أتعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
من يبتاع مربد بني فلان غفر الله له ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فابتعته فأتيت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت إني ابتعت مربد بني فلان ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاجعله
في مسجدنا وأجره لك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدكم بالله الذي لا
إله إلا هو هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من
يبتاع بئر رومة غفر الله له ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقلت قد ابتعت بئر رومة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاجعلها سقاية للمسلمين
وأجرها لك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال فأنشدكم بالله الذي لا إله إلا
هو هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من يجهز جيش
العسرة غفر الله له ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فجهزتهم حتى ما يفقدون عقالا ولا خطاما
‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال اللهم اشهد اللهم اشهد اللهم اشهد
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Al-Ahnaf said: "I came to Al-Madinah, and I was
performing Hajj, and while we were in our camping place unloading
our mounts, someone came to us and said: 'The people have gathered
in the Masjid.' I looked and found the people gathered, and in the
midst of them was a group; there I saw 'Ali bin Abi Talib,
Az-Zubair, Talhah and Sa'd bin Abi Waqqas, may Allah have mercy on
them. When I got there, it was said that 'Uthman bin 'Affan had
come. He came, wearing a yellowish cloak. I said to my companion:
Stay where you are until I find out what is happening. 'Uthman
said: Is 'Ali here? Is Az-Zubair here? Is Talhah here? Is Sa'd
here? They said: Yes. He said: I adjure you by Allah, beside Whom
there is none worthy of worship, are you aware that the Messenger
of Allah said: Whoever buys the Mirbad of Banu so and so, Allah
will forgive him, and I bought it, then I came to the Messenger of
Allah and told him, and he said: Add it to our Masjid and the
reward for it will be yours? They said: Yes. He said: I adjure you
by Allah, beside Whom there is none worthy of worship, are you
aware that the Messenger of Allah said: Whoever buys the well of
Rumah, Allah will forgive him, so I came to the Messenger of Allah
and said: I have bought the well of Rumah. He said: Give it to
provide water for the Muslims, and the reward for it will be yours?
They said: Yes. He said: 'I adjure you by Allah, beside Whom there
is none worthy of worship, are you aware that the Messenger of
Allah said: Whoever equips the army of Al-'Usrah (i.e. Tabuk),
Allah will forgive him, so I equipped them until they were not
lacking even a rope or a bridle?' They said: Yes. He said: O Allah,
bear witness, O Allah, bear witness, O Allah, bear
witness."</english-text>
</hadith>
