<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43778</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>35</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3763</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Oaths and Vows - كتاب الأيمان
والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20452, 11220, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسحاق بن إبراهيم، قال أنبأنا الفضل بن موسى، قال
حدثني محمد بن عمرو، قال حدثنا أبو سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ لما خلق الله الجنة والنار أرسل جبريل
عليه السلام إلى الجنة فقال انظر إليها وإلى ما أعددت لأهلها فيها ‏.‏
فنظر إليها فرجع فقال وعزتك لا يسمع بها أحد إلا دخلها ‏.‏ فأمر بها
فحفت بالمكاره فقال اذهب إليها فانظر إليها وإلى ما أعددت لأهلها فيها
فنظر إليها فإذا هي قد حفت بالمكاره فقال وعزتك لقد خشيت أن لا يدخلها
أحد ‏.‏ قال اذهب فانظر إلى النار وإلى ما أعددت لأهلها فيها ‏.‏ فنظر
إليها فإذا هي يركب بعضها بعضا فرجع فقال وعزتك لا يدخلها أحد ‏.‏
فأمر بها فحفت بالشهوات فقال ارجع فانظر إليها ‏.‏ فإذا هي قد حفت
بالشهوات فرجع وقال وعزتك لقد خشيت أن لا ينجو منها أحد إلا دخلها ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Hurairah that the Messenger
of Allah said: "When Allah created Paradise and Hell, He sent
Jibril, peace be upon him, to Paradise and said: 'Look at it and at
what I have prepared for its people in it.' He looked at it, then
he came back and said: 'By Your Glory, no one will hear of it but
he will enter it.' So He commanded that it be surrounded by
hardships and said: 'Go and look at it and at what I have prepared
for its people in it.' He looked at it and saw that it had been
surrounded with hardships. He (Jibril) said: 'By Your Glory, I fear
that no one will enter it.' He (Allah) said: 'Go and look at the
Fire and at what I have prepared for its people in it.' So he
looked at it and parts of it were piled upon other parts. He came
back and said: 'By Your Glory, no one will enter it.' So He
commanded that it be surrounded with pleasures and said: 'Go and
look at it.' So he looked at it and saw that it was surrounded with
pleasures. He came back and said: 'By Your Glory, I fear that no
one will be saved from it and all will enter it.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
