<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43770</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3755</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of 'Umra - كتاب العمرى</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20287, 20295, 11019, 11035</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن المثنى، قال حدثنا معاذ بن هشام، قال
حدثني أبي، عن قتادة، قال سألني سليمان بن هشام عن العمرى، فقلت حدث
محمد بن سيرين، عن شريح، قال قضى نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن
العمرى جائزة ‏.‏ قال قتادة وقلت حدثني النضر بن أنس عن بشير بن نهيك
عن أبي هريرة أن نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ العمرى جائزة
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قتادة وقلت كان الحسن يقول العمرى جائزة ‏.‏ قال قتادة
فقال الزهري إنما العمرى إذا أعمر وعقبه من بعده فإذا لم يجعل عقبه من
بعده كان للذي يجعل شرطه ‏.‏ قال قتادة فسئل عطاء بن أبي رباح فقال
حدثني جابر بن عبد الله أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
العمرى جائزة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال قتادة فقال الزهري كان الخلفاء لا يقضون
بهذا ‏.‏ قال عطاء قضى بها عبد الملك بن مروان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Qatadah said: "Sulaiman bin
Hisham asked me about a lifelong gift. I said: 'Muhammad bin Sirin
narrated that Shuraih said: "The Prophet of Allah ruled that a
lifelong gift is permissible."'" Qatadah said: "I said: 'And
An-Nadr bin Anas narrated to me, from Bashir bin Nahik, from Abu
Hurairah, that the Prophet of Allah said: "A lifelong gift is
permissible."'" Qatadah said: "I said: 'Al-Hasan used to say: "A
lifelong gift is permissible."'" Qatadah said: "Az-Zuhri said: 'A
lifelong gift is when it is stipulated that it is for the one to
whom it is given and his descendants, but if his descendants were
not mentioned then the condition is valid (and it reverts to the
one who gave it).'" Qatadah said: "So 'Ata' bin Abi Rabah was
asked, and he said: 'Jabir bin Abdullah narrated to me that Allah's
Messenger said: "Umra is permissible."'" Qatadah said: "Az-Zuhri
said: 'The Caliphs (Khulafa') did not rule according to this.'"
'Ata' said: "Abdul-Malik bin Marwan ruled according to
this."</english-text>
</hadith>
