<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43960</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3944</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Kind Treatment of Women - كتاب عشرة
النساء</chapter>
<chain-index>11176, 11013, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني عبيد الله بن سعد بن إبراهيم بن سعد، قال حدثنا
عمي، قال حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني محمد بن عبد
الرحمن بن الحارث بن هشام، أن عائشة، قالت أرسل أزواج النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فاطمة بنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فاستأذنت عليه وهو مضطجع معي في مرطي فأذن لها فقالت
يا رسول الله إن أزواجك أرسلنني إليك يسألنك العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة
‏.‏ وأنا ساكتة فقال لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أى بنية
ألست تحبين من أحب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت بلى ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأحبي هذه ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فقامت فاطمة حين سمعت ذلك من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرجعت إلى
أزواج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرتهن بالذي قالت والذي قال لها
فقلن لها ما نراك أغنيت عنا من شىء فارجعي إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقولي له إن أزواجك ينشدنك العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة ‏.‏
قالت فاطمة لا والله لا أكلمه فيها أبدا ‏.‏ قالت عائشة فأرسل أزواج
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زينب بنت جحش إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وهي التي كانت تساميني من أزواج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في
المنزلة عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ولم أر امرأة قط خيرا في
الدين من زينب وأتقى لله عز وجل وأصدق حديثا وأوصل للرحم وأعظم صدقة
وأشد ابتذالا لنفسها في العمل الذي تصدق به وتقرب به ما عدا سورة من
حدة كانت فيها تسرع منها الفيأة فاستأذنت على رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مع عائشة في مرطها على الحال التي
كانت دخلت فاطمة عليها فأذن لها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت
يا رسول الله إن أزواجك أرسلنني يسألنك العدل في ابنة أبي قحافة ووقعت
بي فاستطالت وأنا أرقب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأرقب طرفه هل
أذن لي فيها فلم تبرح زينب حتى عرفت أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
لا يكره أن أنتصر فلما وقعت بها لم أنشبها بشىء حتى أنحيت عليها فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنها ابنة أبي بكر ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Aishah said: "The wives of the Prophet sent Fatimah,
the daughter of the Messenger of Allah, to the Messenger of Allah.
She asked permission to enter when he was lying with me under my
cover. He gave her permission to enter, and she said: 'O Messenger
of Allah, your wives have sent me to you to ask you to be equitable
with regard to the matter of the daughter of Abu Quhafah.' I
('Aishah) kept quiet and the Messenger of Allah said to her: 'O my
daughter! Do you not love the one whom I love?' She said: 'Yes.' He
said: 'Then love this one.' Fatimah stood up when she heard this
and left the Messenger of Allah, and went back to the wives of the
Prophet. She told them what she had said, and what he had said to
her. They said to her: 'We do not think that you have been of any
avail to us. Go back to the Messenger of Allah and say to him: Your
wives are urging you to be equitable with regard to the matter of
the daughter of Abu Quhafah.' Fatimah said: 'No, by Allah; I will
never speak to him about her again.'" 'Aishah said: "So the wives
of the Prophet sent Zainab bint Jahsh to the Messenger of Allah;
she was one who was somewhat equal to me in rank in the eyes of the
Messenger of Allah. And I have never seen a woman who was better in
religious commitment than Zainab, more fearing of Allah, more
honest in speech, more dutiful in upholding the ties of kinship,
more generous in giving charity, and devoted in giving of herself
in acts of charity, by means of which she sought to draw closer to
Allah. But she was quick-tempered; however, she was also quick to
calm down. She asked permission to enter upon the Messenger of
Allah when he was with 'Aishah under her cover, in the same
situation as when Fatimah had entered. The Messenger of Allah gave
her permission to enter and she said: 'O Messenger of Allah, your
wives have sent me to ask you to be equitable with regard to the
matter of the daughter of Abu Quhafah.' Then she verbally abused me
at length, and I was watching the Messenger of Allah to see if he
would allow me to respond. Zainab went on until I realized that the
Messenger of Allah would not disapprove if I responded. Then I
spoke back to her in such a way, until I silenced her. Then the
Messenger of Allah said: 'She is the daughter of Abu
Bakr.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
