<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>43979</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3963</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Kind Treatment of Women - كتاب عشرة
النساء</chapter>
<chain-index>30584, 20029, 11070, 11252</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا سليمان بن داود، قال أنبأنا ابن وهب، قال أخبرني
ابن جريج، عن عبد الله بن كثير، أنه سمع محمد بن قيس، يقول سمعت
عائشة، تقول ألا أحدثكم عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وعني قلنا بلى
‏.‏ قالت لما كانت ليلتي انقلب فوضع نعليه عند رجليه ووضع رداءه وبسط
إزاره على فراشه ولم يلبث إلا ريثما ظن أني قد رقدت ثم انتعل رويدا
وأخذ رداءه رويدا ثم فتح الباب رويدا وخرج وأجافه رويدا وجعلت درعي في
رأسي فاختمرت وتقنعت إزاري وانطلقت في إثره حتى جاء البقيع فرفع يديه
ثلاث مرات وأطال القيام ثم انحرف وانحرفت فأسرع فأسرعت فهرول فهرولت
فأحضر فأحضرت وسبقته فدخلت وليس إلا أن اضطجعت فدخل فقال ‏"‏ ما لك يا
عائش رابية ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال سليمان حسبته قال حشيا قال ‏"‏ لتخبرني أو
ليخبرني اللطيف الخبير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله بأبي أنت وأمي
فأخبرته الخبر قال ‏"‏ أنت السواد الذي رأيت أمامي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلت نعم -
قالت - فلهدني لهدة في صدري أوجعتني ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أظننت أن يحيف الله
عليك ورسوله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت مهما يكتم الناس فقد علمه الله عز وجل ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ نعم - قال - فإن جبريل عليه السلام أتاني حين رأيت ولم يكن
يدخل عليك وقد وضعت ثيابك فناداني فأخفى منك فأجبته وأخفيته منك وظننت
أنك قد رقدت فكرهت أن أوقظك وخشيت أن تستوحشي فأمرني أن آتي أهل
البقيع فأستغفر لهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ خالفه حجاج بن محمد فقال عن ابن جريج عن
ابن أبي مليكة عن محمد بن قيس ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Aishah said: "Shall I not tell you about the Prophet
and I?" We said: "Yes." She said: "When it was my night, he came
in, placed his shoes by his feet, lay down his Rida' (upper
garment), and spread his Izar (lower garment) on his bed. As soon
as he thought that I had gone to sleep, he put his shoes on slowly
and picked up his Rida' slowly. Then he opened the door slowly,
went out and shut it slowly. I put my garment over my head, covered
myself and put on my Izar (lower garment), and I set out after him
until he came to Al-Baqi', raised his hands three times and stood
there for a long time. Then he left and I left, he hurried and I
hurried, he ran and I ran, and I got there before him and entered
(the house). I had only just laid down when he came in and said: 'O
'Aishah, why are you out of breath?' (one of the reporters)
Sulaiman said: I thought he (Ibn Wahb) said: 'short of breath.' He
said: 'Either you tell me or the All-Aware, All-Knowing will tell
me.' I said: 'O Messenger of Allah, may my father and mother be
sacrificed for you;' and I told him the story. He said: 'You were
the black shape I saw in front of me?' I said: 'Yes.'" She said:
"He gave me a shove in the chest that hurt me and said: 'You
thought that Allah and His Messenger would be unfair to you.' She
said: 'Whatever people conceal, Allah, the Mighty and Sublime,
knows it.' He said: 'Yes.' He said: 'Jibril came to me when you saw
(me leave) but he did not enter upon you because you have taken off
your garments. So he called me but he concealed himself from you,
and I answered him but I concealed it from you. I thought that you
had gone to sleep and I did not want to wake you and I was afraid
that you would feel lonely. He told me to go to Al-Baqi' and pray
for forgiveness for them.'" Hajjaj bin Muhammad contradicted him
(Ibn Wahb), he said: "From Ibn Juraij, from Ibn Abi Mulaikah, from
Muhammad bin Qais."</english-text>
</hadith>
