<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44083</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4067</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fighting [The Prohibition of Bloodshed] - كتاب
تحريم الدم</chapter>
<chain-index>30475, 10556, 9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا القاسم بن زكريا بن دينار، قال حدثني أحمد بن
مفضل، قال حدثنا أسباط، قال زعم السدي عن مصعب بن سعد، عن أبيه، قال
لما كان يوم فتح مكة أمن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الناس إلا
أربعة نفر وامرأتين وقال ‏"‏ اقتلوهم وإن وجدتموهم متعلقين بأستار
الكعبة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ عكرمة بن أبي جهل وعبد الله بن خطل ومقيس بن صبابة
وعبد الله بن سعد بن أبي السرح فأما عبد الله بن خطل فأدرك وهو متعلق
بأستار الكعبة فاستبق إليه سعيد بن حريث وعمار بن ياسر فسبق سعيد
عمارا - وكان أشب الرجلين - فقتله وأما مقيس بن صبابة فأدركه الناس في
السوق فقتلوه وأما عكرمة فركب البحر فأصابتهم عاصف فقال أصحاب السفينة
أخلصوا فإن آلهتكم لا تغني عنكم شيئا ها هنا ‏.‏ فقال عكرمة والله لئن
لم ينجني من البحر إلا الإخلاص لا ينجيني في البر غيره اللهم إن لك
على عهدا إن أنت عافيتني مما أنا فيه أن آتي محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم
حتى أضع يدي في يده فلأجدنه عفوا كريما ‏.‏ فجاء فأسلم وأما عبد الله
بن سعد بن أبي السرح فإنه اختبأ عند عثمان بن عفان فلما دعا رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم الناس إلى البيعة جاء به حتى أوقفه على النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال يا رسول الله بايع عبد الله ‏.‏ قال فرفع رأسه
فنظر إليه ثلاثا كل ذلك يأبى فبايعه بعد ثلاث ثم أقبل على أصحابه فقال
‏"‏ أما كان فيكم رجل رشيد يقوم إلى هذا حيث رآني كففت يدي عن بيعته
فيقتله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقالوا وما يدرينا يا رسول الله ما في نفسك هلا أومأت
إلينا بعينك ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إنه لا ينبغي لنبي أن يكون له خائنة أعين ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Mus'ab bin Sa'd that his father
said: "On the day of the Conquest of Makkah, the Messenger of Allah
[SAW] granted amnesty to the people, except four men and two women.
He said: 'Kill them, even if you find them clinging to the covers
of Ka'bah.' (They were) 'Ikrimah bin Abi Jahl, 'Abdullah bin
Khatal, Miqyas bin Subabah and 'Abdullah bin Sa'd bin Abi As-Sarh.
'Abdullah bin Khatl was caught while he was clinging to the covers
of Ka'bah. Sa'eed bin Huraith and 'Ammar bin Yasir both rushed
toward him, but Sa'eed, who was the younger of the two, got there
before 'Ammar, and he killed him. Miqyas bin Subabah was caught by
the people in the marketplace, and they killed him. 'Ikrimah
traveled by sea, and he was caught in a storm. The crew of the ship
said: 'Turn sincerely toward Allah, for your (false) gods cannot
help you at all in this situation.' 'Ikrimah said: 'By Allah, if
nothing came to save me at sea except sincerity toward Allah then
nothing else will save me on land. O Allah, I promise You that if
You save me from this predicament I will go to Muhammad [SAW] and
put my hand in his, and I am sure that I will find him generous and
forgiving.' So he came, and accepted Islam. 'Abdullah (bin Sa'd)
bin Abi Sarh hid in the house of 'Uthman bin 'Affan, and when the
Messenger of Allah [SAW] called the people to give their Oath of
Allegiance, he brought him, and made him stand before the Prophet
[SAW]. He ('Uthman) said: 'O Messenger of Allah! Accept the
allegiance of 'Abdullah.' He raised his head and looked at him
three times, refusing his allegiance each time, then he accepted
his allegiance after three times. Then he turned to his Companions
and said: 'Was there not any sensible man among you who would get
up when he saw me refusing to give him my hand and kill him?' They
said: 'We did not know, O Messenger of Allah, what was in your
heart. Why did you not gesture to us with your eyes?' He said: 'It
is not befitting for a Prophet that his eyes be
deceitful.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
