<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44093</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4077</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Fighting [The Prohibition of Bloodshed] - كتاب
تحريم الدم</chapter>
<chain-index>30002, 30106, 20304, 11075, 11281, 227</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرني أبو داود، قال حدثنا عفان، قال حدثنا يزيد بن
زريع، قال حدثنا يونس بن عبيد، عن حميد بن هلال، عن عبد الله بن مطرف
بن الشخير، عن أبي برزة الأسلمي، أنه قال كنا عند أبي بكر الصديق فغضب
على رجل من المسلمين فاشتد غضبه عليه جدا فلما رأيت ذلك قلت يا خليفة
رسول الله أضرب عنقه فلما ذكرت القتل أضرب عن ذلك الحديث أجمع إلى غير
ذلك من النحو فلما تفرقنا أرسل إلى فقال يا أبا برزة ما قلت ونسيت
الذي قلت قلت ذكرنيه ‏.‏ قال أما تذكر ما قلت قلت لا والله ‏.‏ قال
أرأيت حين رأيتني غضبت على رجل فقلت أضرب عنقه يا خليفة رسول الله أما
تذكر ذلك أوكنت فاعلا ذلك قلت نعم والله والآن إن أمرتني فعلت ‏.‏ قال
والله ما هي لأحد بعد محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الرحمن
هذا الحديث أحسن الأحاديث وأجودها والله تعالى أعلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Yunus bin 'Ubaid, from Humaid
bin Hilal, from 'Abdullah bin Mutarrif bin Ash-Shikhkhir, from Abu
Barzah Al-Aslami, that he said: "We were with Abu Bakr As-Siddiq,
and he got angry with a man from among the Muslims, and became very
angry indeed. When I saw that, I said: 'O Khalifah of the Messenger
of Allah, shall I strike his neck?' When I mentioned killing him,
he stopped being angry with him and changed the subject. When we
parted, he sent for me and said: 'O Abu Barzah, what did you say?'
I said: 'I have forgotten what I said; remind me.' He said: 'Do you
not remember what you said?' I said: 'No, by Allah.' He said:
'Don't you remember, when you saw me angry with a man, and said, 'I
will strike his neck O Khalifah of the Messenger of Allah?' Don't
you remember that? Would you really have done that?' I said: 'Yes,
by Allah, and if you tell me to do it now, I will do it.' He said:
'By Allah, that is not for anyone after Muhammad
[SAW].'"</english-text>
</hadith>
