<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44578</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>44</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4562</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Financial Transactions - كتاب البيوع</chapter>
<chain-index>34033, 20212, 11593, 11035, 13118</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسماعيل بن مسعود، قال حدثنا بشر بن المفضل، قال
حدثنا سلمة بن علقمة، عن محمد، قال حدثني مسلم بن يسار، وعبد الله بن
عبيد، قالا جمع المنزل بين عبادة بن الصامت وبين معاوية فقال عبادة
نهى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن نبيع الذهب بالذهب والورق بالورق
والبر بالبر والشعير بالشعير والتمر بالتمر - قال أحدهما والملح
بالملح ولم يقل الآخر - إلا سواء بسواء مثلا بمثل - قال أحدهما من زاد
أو ازداد فقد أربى ولم يقل الآخر - وأمرنا أن نبيع الذهب بالورق
والورق بالذهب والبر بالشعير والشعير بالبر يدا بيد كيف شئنا فبلغ هذا
الحديث معاوية فقام فقال ما بال رجال يحدثون أحاديث عن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قد صحبناه ولم نسمعه منه ‏.‏ فبلغ ذلك عبادة بن الصامت
فقام فأعاد الحديث فقال لنحدثن بما سمعناه من رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وإن رغم معاوية ‏.‏ خالفه قتادة رواه عن مسلم بن يسار عن أبي
الأشعث عن عبادة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Muslim bin Yasar and 'Abdullah bin 'Ubaid said:
"Ubadah bin As-Samit and Muawiyah met at a stopping place on the
road. 'Ubadah said: 'The Messenger of Allah forbade us to sell gold
for gold, silver for silver, wheat for wheat, barley for barley,
dates for dates"' - one of them said: "salt for salt, " but the
other did not say "unless it was equal amount for equal amount,
like for like." One of them said: "Whoever gives more or takes more
has engaged in Riba," but the other one did not say it. "And the
commanded us to sell gold for silver and silver for gold, and wheat
for barley and barley for wheat, hand to hand, however we wanted.'
News of this hadith reached Muawiyah and he stood up and said:
'What is the matter with men who narrate Hadiths from the Messenger
of Allah when we accompanied him and we never heard him say it?
News of that reached 'Ubadah bin As-Samit and he stood up and
repeated the Hadith, then he said: 'We will narrate what we heard
from the Messenger of Allah, whether Muawiyah likes it or not."'
Qatadah contradicted him, he reported it from Muslim bin Yasar,
from Abu Al-=Ashath, from 'Ubadah.</english-text>
</hadith>
