<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44727</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4711</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Oaths (qasamah), Retaliation and Blood Money -
كتاب القسامة</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 30234, 20001, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن سلمة، قال أنبأنا ابن القاسم، قال حدثني
مالك، عن أبي ليلى بن عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن سهل، عن سهل بن أبي
حثمة، أنه أخبره ورجال، من كبراء قومه أن عبد، الله بن سهل ومحيصة
خرجا إلى خيبر من جهد أصابهم فأتي محيصة فأخبر أن عبد الله بن سهل قد
قتل وطرح في فقير أو عين فأتى يهود وقال أنتم والله قتلتموه قالوا
والله ما قتلناه ‏.‏ فأقبل حتى قدم على قومه فذكر لهم ثم أقبل هو
وأخوه حويصة وهو أكبر منه وعبد الرحمن بن سهل فذهب محيصة ليتكلم وهو
الذي كان بخيبر فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمحيصة ‏"‏ كبر كبر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ يريد السن فتكلم حويصة ثم تكلم محيصة فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إما أن يدوا صاحبكم وإما أن يؤذنوا بحرب ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فكتب
إليهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في ذلك فكتبوا إنا والله ما
قتلناه ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لحويصة ومحيصة وعبد
الرحمن ‏"‏ أتحلفون وتستحقون دم صاحبكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فتحلف لكم يهود ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا ليسوا بمسلمين ‏.‏ فوداه رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم من عنده فبعث إليهم بمائة ناقة حتى أدخلت عليهم الدار
‏.‏ قال سهل لقد ركضتني منها ناقة حمراء ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Laila bin 'Abdullah bin
'Abdur-Rahman bin Sahl, from Sahl bin Abi Hathmah, that: he
informed him, ans some men among the elders of his people, that
"Abdullah bin Sahl and Muhayysah set out for Khaibar because of
some problem that had arisen. Someone came to Muhayysah, and he
told him that 'Abdullah bin Sahl had been killed and thrown into a
pit or well. He came to the Jews and said: "By Allah, you killed
him." They said: "By Allah, we did not kill him." Then he went
baack to his people and told them about that. Then he and his
brother Huwayysah, who was older than him, and 'Abdur-Rahman bin
Sahl, came (to the prophet). Muhayysah, who was the one who had
been at Khaibar, bnegan to speak, but the Messenger of Allah said:
"Let the elder speak first." So Huwayysah spoke, then Muhayysah
spoke. The Messenger of Allah said: "Either (the Jews) will pay the
Diyah for your companion, or war will be declared on them." The
Messenger of Allah sent a letter to that effect (to the Jews) and
they wrote back saying: "By Allah, we did not kill him." The
Messenger of Allah and 'Abdur-Rahman: "Will you swear an oath
establishing your claim to the blood money of your companion?" They
said: "No." He said: "Should the Jews swear an oath for you?" They
said: "They are not Muslims." So the Messenger of Allah paid it
himself, and he sent one hundred she-camels to their abodes. Sahl
said: "A red she-camel from among them kicked me."</english-text>
</hadith>
