<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44732</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4716</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Oaths (qasamah), Retaliation and Blood Money -
كتاب القسامة</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20259, 11062, 11810, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا محمد بن بشار، قال حدثنا عبد الوهاب، قال سمعت
يحيى بن سعيد، يقول أخبرني بشير بن يسار، عن سهل بن أبي حثمة، أن عبد
الله بن سهل الأنصاري، ومحيصة بن مسعود، خرجا إلى خيبر فتفرقا في
حاجتهما فقتل عبد الله بن سهل الأنصاري فجاء محيصة وعبد الرحمن أخو
المقتول وحويصة بن مسعود حتى أتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذهب
عبد الرحمن يتكلم فقال له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ الكبر الكبر
‏"‏ ‏.‏ فتكلم محيصة وحويصة فذكروا شأن عبد الله بن سهل فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تحلفون خمسين يمينا فتستحقون قاتلكم ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا كيف نحلف ولم نشهد ولم نحضر فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ فتبرئكم يهود بخمسين يمينا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله كيف
نقبل أيمان قوم كفار قال فوداه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال
بشير قال لي سهل بن أبي حثمة لقد ركضتني فريضة من تلك الفرائض في مربد
لنا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Sahl bin Abi Hathmah that:
'Abdullah bin Sahi Al-Anasri and Muhayysah bin Mas'ud went out to
Khaibar and went their separate ways to go about their business.
'Abdullah bin Sahl Al-Anasari was killed and Muhayysah.
'Abdur-Rahman, who was the brother of the victim, and Huwayysah,
came to the Messenger of Allah. 'Abdur-Rahman started to speak, but
the prophert said to him: "Let the elders speak first." So
Muhayysah and Huwayysah spoke and told him about the case of
'Abdullah bin Sahl. The Messenger of Allah said: "Will you swear
fifty oaths, then you will receive compensation or be entitled to
retaliate?" They said: "How can we swear an oath when we did not
witness (what happened) and we were not there?" The Messenger of
Allah said: "Then can the Jews swear fifty oaths declaring their
innocence?" They said: "O Messenger of Allah, how can we accept the
oath of a disbelieving people?" So the Messenger of Allah paid the
blood money himself. (One of the narrators) Bushair said: 'One of
those camels kicked me in a Mirbad of ours."'</english-text>
</hadith>
