<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44743</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>45</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4727</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Oaths (qasamah), Retaliation and Blood Money -
كتاب القسامة</chapter>
<chain-index>34033, 20423, 20159, 10770, 10801</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا إسماعيل بن مسعود، قال حدثنا خالد، قال حدثنا
حاتم، عن سماك، ذكر أن علقمة بن وائل، أخبره عن أبيه، أنه كان قاعدا
عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ جاء رجل يقود آخر بنسعة فقال يا
رسول الله قتل هذا أخي ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
أقتلته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله لو لم يعترف أقمت عليه البينة ‏.‏
قال نعم قتلته ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ كيف قتلته ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال كنت أنا وهو نحتطب
من شجرة فسبني فأغضبني فضربت بالفأس على قرنه ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل لك من مال تؤديه عن نفسك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يا
رسول الله مالي إلا فأسي وكسائي ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أترى قومك يشترونك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أنا أهون على قومي من ذاك ‏.‏
فرمى بالنسعة إلى الرجل فقال ‏"‏ دونك صاحبك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما ولى قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن قتله فهو مثله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأدركوا
الرجل فقالوا ويلك إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن قتله
فهو مثله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرجع إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول
الله حدثت أنك قلت ‏"‏ إن قتله فهو مثله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ وهل أخذته إلا بأمرك
فقال ‏"‏ ما تريد أن يبوء بإثمك وإثم صاحبك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال بلى ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ فإن ذاك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال ذلك كذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>'Alqamah bin Wa'il narrated from his father that he
was sitting with the Messenger of Allah when a man came leading
another man by a string. He said: "O Messenger of Allah, this man
killed my brother." The Messenger of Allah said to him: "Did you
kill him?" He said: "O Messenger of Allah even if he did not
confess I would have brought proof against him." He said: "Yes, I
killed him." He said: "How did you kill him?" He said: "He and I
were chopping firewood from a tree and he insulted me, so I got
angry and struck him with the ax on the forehead." The Messenger of
Allah said: "Do you have any wealth with which you can pay the
Diyah to save yourself?" He said: "O Messenger of Allah, I do not
have anything but my ax and my clothes." The Messenger of Allah
said to him: "Do you think your people will pay to save you?" He
said: "I am too insignificant to them for that." He threw the
string to the man and said: "Here, thank him." When he turned to
go, the Messenger of Allah said: "If he kills him, he will be like
him. "They caught up with the man, and said: "Woe to you! The
Messenger of Allah said: 'If he kills him, he will be like him. "So
he went back to the Messenger of Allah and said: "O Messenger of
Allah, I have been told that you said: 'if he kills him, he will be
like him. 'But I only took him because you told me to. He said:
'Don't you want him to carry your sin and the sin of your companion
(the victim)?' He said: 'Yes, if that is the case.' He said: 'And
that is how it is."'</english-text>
</hadith>
