<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>44914</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>46</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4898</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Cutting off the Hand of the Thief - كتاب قطع
السارق</chapter>
<chain-index>38437, 30317, 20428, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عمران بن بكار، قال حدثنا بشر بن شعيب، قال
أخبرني أبي، عن الزهري، عن عروة، عن عائشة، قالت استعارت امرأة على
ألسنة أناس يعرفون - وهي لا تعرف - حليا فباعته وأخذت ثمنه فأتي بها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسعى أهلها إلى أسامة بن زيد فكلم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيها فتلون وجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وهو يكلمه ثم قال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أتشفع إلى في
حد من حدود الله ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال أسامة استغفر لي يا رسول الله ‏.‏ ثم
قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عشيتئذ فأثنى على الله عز وجل بما
هو أهله ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد فإنما هلك الناس قبلكم أنهم كانوا إذا سرق
الشريف فيهم تركوه وإذا سرق الضعيف فيهم أقاموا عليه الحد والذي نفس
محمد بيده لو أن فاطمة بنت محمد سرقت لقطعت يدها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قطع تلك
المرأة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that 'Aishah said: "A woman borrowed
some jewelry, saying that other people whose names were known but
hers was not then she sold it and kept the money. She was brought
to the Messenger of Allah, and her people went to Usamah bin Zaid,
who spoke to the Messenger of Allah concerning her. The face of ht
Messenger of Allah changed color while he was speaking to him. Then
the Messenger of Allah said to him: 'Are you interceding with me
concerning one of ht Hadd punishments decreed by Allah?' Usamah
said: 'Pray for forgiveness for me, O Messenger of Allah! Then the
Messenger of Allah stood up that evening, he praised and glorified
Allah, the mighty and sublime, as he deserves, then he said: 'The
people who came before you were destroyed because, whenever a noble
person among them stole, they let him go. But if a low-class person
stole, they would carry out the punishment on him. By the One in
whose hand is the soul of Muhammad, if Fatimah bint Muhammad were
to steal, I would cut off her hand.' Then he cut off that
woman."</english-text>
</hadith>
