<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>45106</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5091</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Adornment - كتاب الزينة من السنن</chapter>
<chain-index>36039, 20378, 10871</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبد الرحمن بن عبد الله بن عبد الحكم، قال حدثنا
أبي وأبو الأسود النضر بن عبد الجبار، قالا حدثنا المفضل بن فضالة، عن
عياش بن عباس القتباني، عن أبي الحصين الهيثم بن شفى، - وقال أبو
الأسود شفي - إنه سمعه يقول خرجت أنا وصاحب، لي يسمى أبا عامر - رجل
من المعافر - لنصلي بإيلياء وكان قاصهم رجلا من الأزد يقال له أبو
ريحانة من الصحابة قال أبو الحصين فسبقني صاحبي إلى المسجد ثم أدركته
فجلست إلى جنبه فقال هل أدركت قصص أبي ريحانة فقلت لا ‏.‏ فقال سمعته
يقول نهى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن عشر عن الوشر والوشم والنتف
وعن مكامعة الرجل الرجل بغير شعار وعن مكامعة المرأة المرأة بغير شعار
وأن يجعل الرجل أسفل ثيابه حريرا مثل الأعاجم أو يجعل على منكبيه
حريرا أمثال الأعاجم وعن النهبى وعن ركوب النمور ولبوس الخواتيم إلا
لذي سلطان ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Al-Husain Al-Haitham bin
Shufayy that he said: "A friend of mine who was called Abu 'Amir,
from Al-Ma'afir, and I went out to pray in Jerusalem. Their
preacher was a man from (the tribe of) Azd who was called Abu
Raihanah, one of the Companions." Abu Al-Husain said: "My companion
reached the Masjid before I did, then I caught up with him, and sat
beside him. He said: 'Have you heard the preaching of Abu
Raihanah?' I said: 'No.' He said: 'I heard him say: 'The Messenger
of Allah [SAW] forbade ten things: Filing (the teeth), tattoos,
plucking (hair), for two men to lie under one cover with no barrier
between them, for two women to lie under one cover with no barrier
between them, for a man to add more than four fingers' width of
silk to the bottom of his garment like the foreigners (Persians),
(and he forbade) plundering, riding (while sitting on) leopard
skins and wearing rings- except for rulers."</english-text>
</hadith>
