<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>45155</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5140</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Adornment - كتاب الزينة من السنن</chapter>
<chain-index>30359, 20287, 20295, 11449, 15, 10883</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا عبيد الله بن سعيد، قال حدثنا معاذ بن هشام، قال
حدثني أبي، عن يحيى بن أبي كثير، قال حدثني زيد، عن أبي سلام، عن أبي
أسماء الرحبي، أن ثوبان، مولى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حدثه قال
جاءت بنت هبيرة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وفي يدها فتخ - فقال
كذا في كتاب أبي أى خواتيم ضخام - فجعل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يضرب يدها فدخلت على فاطمة بنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم تشكو
إليها الذي صنع بها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فانتزعت فاطمة سلسلة
في عنقها من ذهب وقالت هذه أهداها إلى أبو حسن فدخل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم والسلسلة في يدها فقال ‏"‏ يا فاطمة أيغرك أن يقول
الناس ابنة رسول الله وفي يدها سلسلة من نار ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم خرج ولم يقعد
فأرسلت فاطمة بالسلسلة إلى السوق فباعتها واشترت بثمنها غلاما - وقال
مرة عبدا - وذكر كلمة معناها فأعتقته فحدث بذلك فقال ‏"‏ الحمد لله
الذي أنجى فاطمة من النار ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Asma' Ar-Rahabi that
Thawban, the freed slave of the Messenger of Allah [SAW], told him:
"Fatimah bint Hubairah came to the Messenger of Allah [SAW] with a
big ring on her hand." He (the narrator) said: "This is what I
found in the book of my father, a huge ring."- "The Messenger of
Allah [SAW] started hitting her hand, so she entered upon Fatimah,
the daughter of the Messenger of Allah [SAW], and complained to her
about what the Messenger of Allah [SAW] had done. Fatimah took off
a gold chain from her neck and said: 'This was given to me by Abu
Hasan.' The Messenger of Allah [SAW] came in and (ﷺ) the chain in
her hand. He said: 'O Fatimah, would you like the people to say
that the daughter of the Messenger of Allah [SAW] has a chain of
fire in her hand?' Then he went out, without sitting down. Fatimah
sent the chain to the market and sold it, and she bought a slave
with the money, and set him free. He was told of that and he said:
'Praise be to Allah, Who has saved Fatimah from the
Fire.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
