<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>45426</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5411</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Etiquette of Judges - كتاب آداب
القضاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20005, 11013, 11004, 13, 3625,
11559</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا قتيبة، قال حدثنا سفيان، عن الزهري، عن عبيد الله
بن عبد الله، عن أبي هريرة، وزيد بن خالد، وشبل، قالوا كنا عند النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقام إليه رجل فقال أنشدك بالله إلا ما قضيت بيننا
بكتاب الله ‏.‏ فقام خصمه - وكان أفقه منه - فقال صدق اقض بيننا بكتاب
الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ قل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا فزنى
بامرأته فافتديت منه بمائة شاة وخادم - وكأنه أخبر أن على ابنه الرجم
فافتدى منه - ثم سألت رجالا من أهل العلم فأخبروني أن على ابني جلد
مائة وتغريب عام ‏.‏ فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي
نفسي بيده لأقضين بينكما بكتاب الله عز وجل أما المائة شاة والخادم
فرد عليك وعلى ابنك جلد مائة وتغريب عام اغد يا أنيس على امرأة هذا
فإن اعترفت فارجمها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغدا عليها فاعترفت فرجمها
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Abu Hurairah, Zaid bin Khalid
and Shibl said: "We were with the Prophet [SAW] when a man stood up
and said: 'I adjure you, by Allah, pass judgment between us
according to the Book of Allah.' His opponent, who was wiser than
him, stood up and said: 'He is right, pass judgment between us
according to the Book of Allah.' He said: 'Speak.' He said: 'My son
was a laborer serving this man, and he committed Zina with his
wife. I ransomed him with one hundred sheep and a servant.' It is
as if he was told that his son was to be stoned to death but he
ransomed him from that. 'Then I asked some knowledgeable men and
they told me that my son was to be given one hundred lashes and
exiled for a year.' The Messenger of Allah [SAW] said to him: 'By
the One in Whose hand is my soul, I will pass judgment between you
according to the Book of Allah, the Mighty and Sublime. As for the
one hundred sheep and the servant, take them back, and your son is
to be given one hundred lashes and exiled for a year. O Unais, go
tomorrow to the wife of this man and if she confesses, then stone
her to death.' She did confess, so he stoned her to
death."</english-text>
</hadith>
