<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>45422</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5407</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Etiquette of Judges - كتاب آداب
القضاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30493, 36017, 20029, 20475, 20023, 11013, 10511, 106,
7</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا يونس بن عبد الأعلى، والحارث بن مسكين، عن ابن
وهب، قال أخبرني يونس بن يزيد، والليث بن سعد، عن ابن شهاب، أن عروة
بن الزبير، حدثه أن عبد الله بن الزبير حدثه عن الزبير بن العوام، أنه
خاصم رجلا من الأنصار قد شهد بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
شراج الحرة كانا يسقيان به كلاهما النخل فقال الأنصاري سرح الماء يمر
عليه ‏.‏ فأبى عليه فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اسق يا
زبير ثم أرسل الماء إلى جارك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغضب الأنصاري وقال يا رسول الله
أن كان ابن عمتك فتلون وجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم قال ‏"‏
يا زبير اسق ثم احبس الماء حتى يرجع إلى الجدر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فاستوفى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم للزبير حقه وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قبل ذلك أشار على الزبير برأى فيه السعة له وللأنصاري فلما أحفظ
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الأنصاري استوفى للزبير حقه في صريح
الحكم ‏.‏ قال الزبير لا أحسب هذه الآية أنزلت إلا في ذلك ‏{‏ فلا
وربك لا يؤمنون حتى يحكموك فيما شجر بينهم ‏}‏ وأحدهما يزيد على صاحبه
في القصة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Az-Zubair bin Al-'Awwam that: He
disputed with a man among Ansar who had been present at Badr with
the Messenger of Allah [SAW], concerning a stream in Al-Harrah from
which they both used to water their date palm trees. The Ansari
said: "Let the water flow." But he (Az-Zubair) refused. The
Messenger of Allah [SAW] said: "Irrigate (your land), O Zubair!
Then let the water flow to your neighbor." The Ansari became angry
and said, "O Messenger of Allah, is it because he is your cousin?"
The face of the Messenger of Allah [SAW] changed color (because of
anger) and he said: "O Zubair! Irrigate (your land) then block the
water, until it flows back to the walls." So the Messenger of Allah
[SAW] allowed Az-Zubair to take his rights in full, although before
that he had suggested to Az-Zubair a middle way that benefited both
him and the Ansari. But when the Ansari made the Messenger of Allah
[SAW] angry, he gave Az-Zubair his rights in full, as stated
clearly in his ruling. Az-Zubair said: "I think that this Verse was
revealed concerning this matter: 'But no, by your Lord, they can
have no faith, until they make you (O Muhammad) judge in all
disputes between them.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
