<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>45555</id>
<source>Sunan an-Nasa'i</source>
<chapter-number>51</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5540</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>20547, 20340, 20311, 11049, 11644, 3</chain-index>
<arabic-text>أخبرنا أبو بكر، أحمد بن محمد بن إسحاق السني قراءة عليه
في بيته قال أنبأنا الإمام أبو عبد الرحمن أحمد بن شعيب النسائي رحمه
الله تعالى قال أنبأنا أبو داود قال حدثنا عبيد الله بن موسى قال
أنبأنا إسرائيل عن أبي إسحاق عن أبي ميسرة عن عمر رضى الله عنه قال
لما نزل تحريم الخمر قال عمر اللهم بين لنا في الخمر بيانا شافيا‏.‏
فنزلت الآية التي في البقرة فدعي عمر فقرئت عليه فقال عمر اللهم بين
لنا في الخمر بيانا شافيا‏.‏ فنزلت الآية التي في النساء ‏{‏ يا أيها
الذين آمنوا لا تقربوا الصلاة وأنتم سكارى ‏}‏ فكان منادي رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا أقام الصلاة نادى لا تقربوا الصلاة وأنتم
سكارى فدعي عمر فقرئت عليه فقال اللهم بين لنا في الخمر بيانا
شافيا‏.‏ فنزلت الآية التي في المائدة فدعي عمر فقرئت عليه فلما بلغ
‏{‏ فهل أنتم منتهون ‏}‏ قال عمر رضى الله عنه انتهينا
انتهينا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Umar that: When the prohibition
of Khamr was revealed, 'Umar said: "O Allah, give us a clear ruling
on Khamr," and the Verse in Al-Baqarah was revealed. 'Umar was
called and it was recited to him. Then 'Umar said: "O Allah, give
us a clear ruling on Khamr," and the Verse in An-Nisa' was
revealed: "O you who believe! Approach not As-Salah (the prayer)
when you are in a drunken state". And when the Iqamah for prayer
was said, the caller of the Messenger of Allah [SAW] would cry out:
"O you who believe! Approach not As-Salah (the prayer) when you are
in a drunken state." 'Umar was called and this was recited to him.
Then he said: "O Allah, give us a clear ruling on Khamr." Then the
Verse in Surat Al-Ma'idah was revealed, and 'Umar was called, and
it was recited to him. When he reached the words, "So, will you not
then abstain?," 'Umar said: "We have abstained, we have
abstained."</english-text>
</hadith>
