<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>50018</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>0</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>18</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Sunnah - كتاب المقدمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20402, 19839</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، حدثنا يحيى بن حمزة، حدثني برد بن
سنان، عن إسحاق بن قبيصة، عن أبيه، أن عبادة بن الصامت الأنصاري
النقيب، صاحب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غزا مع معاوية أرض الروم
فنظر إلى الناس وهم يتبايعون كسر الذهب بالدنانير وكسر الفضة بالدراهم
فقال يا أيها الناس إنكم تأكلون الربا سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يقول ‏"‏ لا تبتاعوا الذهب بالذهب إلا مثلا بمثل لا زيادة بينهما
ولا نظرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال له معاوية يا أبا الوليد لا أرى الربا في هذا
إلا ما كان من نظرة ‏.‏ فقال عبادة أحدثك عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وتحدثني عن رأيك لئن أخرجني الله لا أساكنك بأرض لك على فيها
إمرة ‏.‏ فلما قفل لحق بالمدينة فقال له عمر بن الخطاب ما أقدمك يا
أبا الوليد فقص عليه القصة وما قال من مساكنته فقال ارجع يا أبا
الوليد إلى أرضك فقبح الله أرضا لست فيها وأمثالك ‏.‏ وكتب إلى معاوية
لا إمرة لك عليه واحمل الناس على ما قال فإنه هو الأمر
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Ishaq bin Qabisah from his
father that : Ubadah bin Samit Al-Ansari, head of the army unit,
the Companion of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), went on a military
campaign with Mu'awiyah in the land of the Byzantines. He saw
people trading pieces of gold for Dinar and pieces of silver for
Dirham. He said: "O people, you are consuming Riba (usury)! For I
heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: 'Do not sell gold for gold
unless it is like for like; there should be no increase and no
delay (between the two transactions).'" Mu'awiyah said to him: "O
Abu Walid, I do not think there is any Riba involved in this ,
except in cases where there is a delay." 'Ubadah said to him: "I
tell you a Hadith from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and you tell me
your opinion! If Allah brings me back safely I will never live in a
land in which you have authority over me." When he returned, he
stayed in Al-Madinah, and 'Umar bin Khattab said to him: "What
brought you here, O Abu Walid?" So he told him the story, and what
he had said about not living in the same land as Mu'awiyah. 'Umar
said: "Go back to your land, O Abu Walid, for what a bad land is
the land from where you and people like you are absent." Then he
wrote to Mu'awiyah and said: "You have no authority over him; make
the people follow what he says , for he is right."</english-text>
</hadith>
