<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>50188</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>0</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>188</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Sunnah - كتاب المقدمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30430, 20226, 11168, 11019, 11693</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حميد بن مسعدة، حدثنا خالد بن الحارث، حدثنا سعيد،
عن قتادة، عن صفوان بن محرز المازني، قال بينما نحن مع عبد الله بن
عمر وهو يطوف بالبيت إذ عرض له رجل فقال يا ابن عمر كيف سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يذكر في النجوى قال سمعت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ يدنى المؤمن من ربه يوم القيامة حتى يضع عليه كنفه
ثم يقرره بذنوبه فيقول هل تعرف فيقول يا رب أعرف ‏.‏ حتى إذا بلغ منه
ما شاء الله أن يبلغ قال إني سترتها عليك في الدنيا وأنا أغفرها لك
اليوم ‏.‏ قال ثم يعطى صحيفة حسناته أو كتابه بيمينه ‏.‏ قال وأما
الكافر أو المنافق فينادى على رءوس الأشهاد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال خالد في ‏"‏
الأشهاد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ شىء من انقطاع ‏.‏ ‏{هؤلاء الذين كذبوا على ربهم ألا
لعنة الله على الظالمين}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Safwan bin Muhriz Al-Mazini
said: "We were with 'Abdullah bin 'Umar when he was
circumambulating the House; a man came up to him and said: 'O Ibn
'Umar, what did you hear the Messenger of Allah say about the
Najwa?' He said: 'I heard the Messenger of Allah say: 'On the Day
of Resurrection, the believer will be brought close to his Lord
until He will cover him with His screen, then He will make him
confess his sins. He will ask him: "Do you confess?" He will say:
"O Lord, I confess." This will continue as long as Allah wills,
then He will say: "I concealed them for you in the world, and I
forgive you for them today." Then he will be given the scroll of
his good deeds, or his record, in his right hand. But as for the
disbeliever or the hypocrite, (his sins) will be announced before
the witnesses.' " (One of the narrators) Khalid said: "At: 'before
the witnesses' there is something missing." "These are the ones who
lied against their Lord!' No doubt! The curse of Allah is on the
wrongdoers."</english-text>
</hadith>
