<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>50712</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>2</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>667</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Prayer - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30269, 30297, 20411, 20012, 38412, 20462, 20005,
11374, 10916, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن الصباح، وأحمد بن سنان، قالا حدثنا إسحاق
بن يوسف الأزرق، أنبأنا سفيان، ح وحدثنا علي بن ميمون الرقي، حدثنا
مخلد بن يزيد، عن سفيان، عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن سليمان بن بريدة، عن
أبيه، قال جاء رجل إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسأله عن وقت الصلاة
فقال ‏"‏ صل معنا هذين اليومين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما زالت الشمس أمر بلالا
فأذن ثم أمره فأقام الظهر ثم أمره فأقام العصر والشمس مرتفعة بيضاء
نقية ثم أمره فأقام المغرب حين غابت الشمس ثم أمره فأقام العشاء حين
غاب الشفق ثم أمره فأقام الفجر حين طلع الفجر فلما كان من اليوم
الثاني أمره فأذن الظهر فأبرد بها وأنعم أن يبرد بها ثم صلى العصر
والشمس مرتفعة أخرها فوق الذي كان وصلى المغرب قبل أن يغيب الشفق وصلى
العشاء بعدما ذهب ثلث الليل وصلى الفجر فأسفر بها ثم قال ‏"‏ أين
السائل عن وقت الصلاة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال الرجل أنا يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ وقت صلاتكم بين ما رأيتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Sulaiman bin Buraidah that his
father said: "A man came to the Prophet and asked him about the
times of the prayer. He said: 'Pray with us for two days.' When the
sun passed its zenith he commanded Bilal to call the Adhan, then he
commanded him to give the Iqamah for Zuhr; then he commanded him to
give the Iqamah for 'Asr when the sun was high and clearly white.
Then he commanded him to give the Iqamah for Maghrib when the sun
had set; then he commanded him to give the Iqamah for 'Isha' when
the red afterglow had disappeared; then he commanded him to give
the Iqamah for Fajr when dawn came. On the following day he
commanded him to give the Adhan for Zuhr when the extreme heat had
passed and it had cooled down; then he prayed 'Asr when the sun was
still high, but he delayed it more than he had done the day before;
then he prayed Maghrib before the red afterglow disappeared; he
prayed 'Isha' when one-third of the night had passed; and he prayed
Fajr at the time when it was already light. Then he said: 'Where is
the one who was asking about the times of Prayer?' The man said:
'Here I am, O Messenger of Allah.' He said: 'The times of your
prayer are between the times you have seen.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
