<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>50751</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>706</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book of the Adhan and the Sunnah Regarding It - كتاب
الأذان والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>20672, 11107, 11213, 10615, 47</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عبيد، محمد بن عبيد بن ميمون المدني حدثنا
محمد بن سلمة الحراني، حدثنا محمد بن إسحاق، حدثنا محمد بن إبراهيم
التيمي، عن محمد بن عبد الله بن زيد، عن أبيه، قال كان رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قد هم بالبوق وأمر بالناقوس فنحت فأري عبد الله بن زيد
في المنام قال رأيت رجلا عليه ثوبان أخضران يحمل ناقوسا فقلت له يا
عبد الله تبيع الناقوس قال وما تصنع به قلت أنادي به إلى الصلاة ‏.‏
قال أفلا أدلك على خير من ذلك قلت وما هو قال تقول الله أكبر الله
أكبر الله أكبر الله أكبر أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله أشهد أن لا إله إلا
الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله أشهد أن محمدا رسول الله حى على الصلاة
حى على الصلاة حى على الفلاح حى على الفلاح ‏.‏ الله أكبر الله أكبر
لا إله إلا الله ‏.‏ قال فخرج عبد الله بن زيد حتى أتى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأخبره بما رأى ‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله رأيت رجلا عليه
ثوبان أخضران يحمل ناقوسا ‏.‏ فقص عليه الخبر فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن صاحبكم قد رأى رؤيا فاخرج مع بلال إلى المسجد فألقها
عليه وليناد بلال فإنه أندى صوتا منك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فخرجت مع بلال إلى
المسجد فجعلت ألقيها عليه وهو ينادي بها ‏.‏ قال فسمع عمر بن الخطاب
بالصوت فخرج فقال يا رسول الله والله لقد رأيت مثل الذي رأى ‏.‏ قال
أبو عبيد فأخبرني أبو بكر الحكمي أن عبد الله بن زيد الأنصاري قال في
ذلك أحمد الله ذا الجلال وذا الإكرام حمدا على الأذان كثيرا إذ أتاني
به البشير من الله فأكرم به لدى بشيرا في ليال والى بهن ثلاث كلما جاء
زادني توقيرا</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Muhammed bin 'Abdullah bin Zaid
that his father said that: The Messenger of Allah was thinking of a
horn, and he commanded that a bell be made and it was done. Then
'Abdullah bin Zaid had a dream. He said: "I saw a man wearing two
green garments, carrying a bell. I said to him, 'O slave of Allah,
will you sell the bell?' He said; 'What will you do with it?' I
said, 'I will call (the people) to prayer.' He said, 'Shall I not
tell you of something better than that?' I said, 'What is it?' he
said, 'Say: Allahu Akbar Allahu Akbar, Allahu Akbar Allahu Akbar;
Ash-hadu an la ilaha illallah, Ash-hadu an la ilaha illallah;
Ash-hadu anna Muhammadan Rasulullah, Ash-hadu anna Muhammadan
Rasulullah; Hayya 'alas-salah, Hayya 'alas-salah; Hayya
'alal-falah, Hayya 'alal-falah; Allahu Akbar Allahu Akbar; La ilaha
illallah (Allah is The Most Great, Allah is The Most Great; Allah
is The Most Great, Allah is The Most Great; I bear witness that
none has the right to be worshipped but Allah, I bear witness that
none has the right to be worshipped but Allah; I bear witness that
Muhammed is the Messenger of Allah, I bear witness that Muhammed is
the Messenger of Allah; Come to the Prayer, Come to the Prayer;
Come to the prosperity, Come to the prosperity; Allah is the Most
great, Allah is the Most Great; None has the right to be worshipped
but Allah)." 'Abdullah bin Zaid went out and came to the Messenger
of Allah, and told him what he had seen. He said, "O Messenger of
Allah, I saw a man wearing two green garments carrying a bell," and
he told him the story. The Messenger of Allah said, "Your companion
has had a dream. Go out with Bilal to the mosque and teach it to
him, for he has a louder voice than you." I ('Abdullah) went out
with Bilal to the mosque, and I started teaching him the words and
he was calling them out. 'Umar Al-Khattab heard the voice and came
out saying, "O Messenger of Allah! By Allah, I saw the same (dream)
as him." (Hasan)Abu 'Ubaid said: "Abu Bakr Al-Hakami told me that
'Abdullah bin Zaid Al-Ansari said concerning that:'I praise Allah,
the Possessor of majesty and honor,A great deal of praise for the
Adhan.Since the news of it came to me from Allah,So due to it, I
was honored by the information.During the three nights.Each of
which increased me in honor.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
