<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>50799</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>754</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Book On The Mosques And The Congregations - كتاب
المساجد والجماعات</chapter>
<chain-index>20150, 11013, 5278</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو مروان، محمد بن عثمان حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد،
عن ابن شهاب، عن محمود بن الربيع الأنصاري، - وكان قد عقل مجة مجها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من دلو في بئر لهم - عن عتبان بن مالك
السالمي - وكان إمام قومه بني سالم وكان شهد بدرا مع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم - قال جئت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا رسول
الله إني قد أنكرت من بصري وإن السيل يأتيني فيحول بيني وبين مسجد
قومي ويشق على اجتيازه فإن رأيت أن تأتيني فتصلي في بيتي مكانا أتخذه
مصلى فافعل ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أفعل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغدا على رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأبو بكر بعد ما اشتد النهار واستأذن فأذنت له ولم يجلس حتى
قال ‏"‏ أين تحب أن أصلي لك من بيتك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأشرت له إلى المكان الذي
أحب أن أصلي فيه فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وصففنا خلفه فصلى
بنا ركعتين ثم احتبسته على خزيرة تصنع لهم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Mahmud bin Rabi' Al-Ansari, who remembered that the
Messenger of Allah spat a mouthful of water from a bucket into a
well that belonged to them, narrated that : 'Itban bin Malik
As-Salimi who was the chief of his people Banu Salim and had
participated in (the battle of) Badr with the Messenger of Allah
said: "I came to the Messenger of Allah and said: 'O Messenger of
Allah, my sight is failing and the flood comes and prevents me from
reaching the mosque of my people, and it is too hard for me to
cross the water. Do you think you could come and perform prayer in
my house in a place which I can then take as a place of prayer?' He
said: 'I will do that.' The following day, the Messenger of Allah
and Abu Bakr came, when the heat of the day had grown intense. He
asked permission to enter, and I gave him permission. He did not
sit down until he said: 'Where would you like me to perform prayer
for you in your house?' I showed him the place where I wanted him
to pray, so the Messenger of Allah stood and we lined up behind
him, and he led us in praying two Rak'ah (units). Then I asked him
to stay and eat some Khazirah that had been prepared for
them.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
