<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51059</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1063</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>20373, 11049, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علقمة بن عمرو الدارمي، حدثنا أبو بكر بن عياش، عن
أبي إسحاق، عن البراء، قال صلينا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نحو
بيت المقدس ثمانية عشر شهرا وصرفت القبلة إلى الكعبة بعد دخوله إلى
المدينة بشهرين وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا صلى إلى بيت
المقدس أكثر تقلب وجهه في السماء وعلم الله من قلب نبيه صلى الله عليه
وسلم أنه يهوى الكعبة فصعد جبريل فجعل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يتبعه بصره وهو يصعد بين السماء والأرض ينظر ما يأتيه به فأنزل الله
‏{قد نرى تقلب وجهك في السماء}‏ الآية فأتانا آت فقال إن القبلة قد
صرفت إلى الكعبة وقد صلينا ركعتين إلى بيت المقدس ونحن ركوع فتحولنا
فبنينا على ما مضى من صلاتنا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
يا جبريل كيف حالنا في صلاتنا إلى بيت المقدس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأنزل الله عز
وجل ‏{وما كان الله ليضيع إيمانكم}‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Bara’ said: “We prayed with the
Messenger ofAllah(ﷺ) facing towards Baitul-Maqdis (Jerusalem) for
eighteenmonths,then the Qiblah was changed to the Ka’bah two months
after theProphet (ﷺ) entered Al-Madinah. When the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ)prayed towards Baitul-Maqdis, he would often lift his face
towardstheheavens, and Allah knew what was in the heart of His
Prophet andhowhe longed to face the Ka’bah (during prayer). Jibril
appeared(in thesky), and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) started
watching himas he wasdescending between the heavens and the earth,
waiting tosee what hewould bring. Then Allah revealed the words:
‘Verily, Wehave seen theturning of your face towards the heaven.
Surely, Weshall turn you toa Qiblah that shall please you, so turn
your facein the direction ofAl-Masjid Al-Haram (at Makkah). And
wherever youpeople are, turn yourfaces (during prayer) in that
direction.’[2:144] Then someone came tous and said: ‘The Qiblah has
beenchanged to the Ka’bah.’ We hadperformed two Rak’ah
facingtowards Jerusalem. And we were bowing. Sowe turned around,
and wecontinued our prayer. The Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) said: ‘O
Jibril!What about our prayer facing towards Baitul-Maqdis?’ Then
Allahrevealed the words: “And Allah would never makeyour faith to
belost.” [2:143]</english-text>
</hadith>
