<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51110</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1114</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20241, 11875, 11220</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا أبو عاصم، حدثنا عبد الحميد
بن جعفر، حدثنا محمد بن عمرو بن عطاء، قال سمعت أبا حميد الساعدي، في
عشرة من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيهم أبو قتادة فقال أبو
حميد أنا أعلمكم بصلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قالوا لم
فوالله ما كنت بأكثرنا له تبعة ولا أقدمنا له صحبة ‏.‏ قال بلى ‏.‏
قالوا فاعرض ‏.‏ قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا قام إلى
الصلاة كبر ثم رفع يديه حتى يحاذي بهما منكبيه ويقر كل عضو منه في
موضعه ثم يقرأ ثم يكبر ويرفع يديه حتى يحاذي بهما منكبيه ثم يركع ويضع
راحتيه على ركبتيه معتمدا لا يصب رأسه ولا يقنع معتدلا ثم يقول ‏"‏
سمع الله لمن حمده ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ويرفع يديه حتى يحاذي بهما منكبيه حتى يقر
كل عظم إلى موضعه ثم يهوي إلى الأرض ويجافي يديه عن جنبيه ثم يرفع
رأسه ويثني رجله اليسرى فيقعد عليها ويفتخ أصابع رجليه إذا سجد ثم
يسجد ثم يكبر ويجلس على رجله اليسرى حتى يرجع كل عظم منه إلى موضعه ثم
يقوم فيصنع في الركعة الأخرى مثل ذلك ثم إذا قام من الركعتين رفع يديه
حتى يحاذي بهما منكبيه كما صنع عند افتتاح الصلاة ثم يصلي بقية صلاته
هكذا حتى إذا كانت السجدة التي ينقضي فيها التسليم أخر إحدى رجليه
وجلس على شقه الأيسر متوركا ‏.‏ قالوا صدقت هكذا كان يصلي رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Muhammadbin ‘Amr bin ‘Ata’ said: ‘While he was among
ten of theCompanions of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) including Abu
Qatadah: “Iheard Abu Humaid As-Sa’idi say: ‘I am the most
knowledgeable ofyouconcerning the prayer of the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ).’ Theysaid:‘Why? By Allah, you did not follow him more than we
did, andyou didnot accompany him for longer.’ He said: ‘Yes I
am.’They said: ‘Showus.’ He said: ‘When the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)
stood up for prayer,he would say the Takbir, then he wouldraise his
hands parallel to hisshoulders, and every part of his bodywould
settle in place. Then hewould recite, then he would raise hishands
parallel to his shouldersand bow, placing his palms on hisknees and
supporting his weight onthem. He neither lowered his head,nor
raised it up, it was evenlybalanced (between either extreme).Then
he would say: “Sami’ Allahuliman hamidah (Allah hears thosewho
praise Him); and he would raisehis hands parallel with
hisshoulders, until every bone returned toits place. Then he
wouldprostrate himself on the ground, keeping hisarms away from
hissides. Then he would raise his head and tuck hisleft foot under
himand sit on it, and he would spread his toes whenhe prostrated.*
Thenhe would prostrate, then say the Takbir and siton his left
foot,until every bone returned to its place. Then hewould stand up
and dothe same in the next Rak’ah. Then when he stoodup after
twoRak’ah, he would raise his hands level with his shouldersas he
didat the beginning of the prayer. Then he would offer the restof
hisprayer in like manner until, when he did the prostration
aftertheTaslim comes, he would push one of his feet back and sit
and hisweight on his left side, Mutawarrikan.’** They said: ‘You
havespokenthe truth; this is how the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) used
toperformthe prayer.’”***</english-text>
</hadith>
