<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51131</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1135</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30460, 20246, 11107, 1134</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن خلف أبو سلمة، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، عن محمد
بن إسحاق، عن محمد بن أبي أمامة بن سهل بن حنيف، عن أبيه أبي أمامة،
عن عبد الرحمن بن كعب بن مالك، قال كنت قائد أبي حين ذهب بصره وكنت
إذا خرجت به إلى الجمعة فسمع الأذان استغفر لأبي أمامة أسعد بن زرارة
ودعا له فمكثت حينا أسمع ذلك منه ثم قلت في نفسي والله إن ذا لعجز إني
أسمعه كلما سمع أذان الجمعة يستغفر لأبي أمامة ويصلي عليه ولا أسأله
عن ذلك لم هو فخرجت به كما كنت أخرج به إلى الجمعة فلما سمع الأذان
استغفر كما كان يفعل فقلت له يا أبتاه أرأيتك صلاتك على أسعد بن زرارة
كلما سمعت النداء بالجمعة لم هو قال أى بنى كان أول من صلى بنا صلاة
الجمعة قبل مقدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من مكة في نقيع الخضمات
في هزم من حرة بني بياضة ‏.‏ قلت كم كنتم يومئذ قال أربعين رجلا
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Abdur-Rahman bin Ka’b bin Malik
said: “I usedtoguide my father after he lost his sight, and when I
took him outforthe Friday (prayer), when he heard the Adhan he
would pray forforgiveness for Abu Umamah As’ad bin Zurarah, and
supplicate forhim.I heard that from him for a while, then I said to
myself: ‘ByAllah!What is this weakness? Every time he heard the
Adhan forFriday(prayer) I hear him praying for forgiveness for Abu
Umamah andsupplicate for him, and I do not ask him about why he
does that.’ThenI took him out for Friday (prayer), as I used to
take him out,andwhen he heard the Adhan he prayed for forgiveness
as he used todo. Isaid to him: ‘O my father! I see you supplicating
for As’adbinZurarah every time you hear the call for Friday; why is
that?’Hesaud: ‘O my son, he was the first one who led us for the
Fridayprayerbefore the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came from Makkah, in
Naqi’Al-Khadamat (a place near Al-Madinah), in the plain of Harrah
BanuBayadah.’ I asked: ‘How many of you were there at that time?’He
said:‘Forty men.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
