<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51243</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1247</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20352, 11073, 11019, 11284, 11166,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا محمد بن بشر، حدثنا
سعيد بن أبي عروبة، عن قتادة، عن زرارة بن أوفى، عن سعد بن هشام، قال
سألت عائشة قلت يا أم المؤمنين أفتني عن وتر رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ قالت كنا نعد له سواكه وطهوره فيبعثه الله فيما شاء أن يبعثه
من الليل فيتسوك ويتوضأ ثم يصلي تسع ركعات لا يجلس فيها إلا عند
الثامنة فيدعو ربه فيذكر الله ويحمده ويدعوه ثم ينهض ولا يسلم ثم يقوم
فيصلي التاسعة ثم يقعد فيذكر الله ويحمده ويدعو ربه ويصلي على نبيه ثم
يسلم تسليما يسمعنا ثم يصلي ركعتين بعد ما يسلم وهو قاعد فتلك إحدى
عشرة ركعة فلما أسن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأخذ اللحم أوتر
بسبع وصلى ركعتين بعد ما سلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Sa’d bin Hisham said: “I asked
‘Aishah: ‘OMother of the Believers! Tell me about the Witr of the
Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ).’ She said: ‘We used to keep his tooth stick
andwater forablution ready for him. Allah would wake him as He
willedto duringthe night, and he would use the tooth stick and
performablution, thenhe would pray nine Rak’ah, during which he
would notsit until theeighth Rak’ah. Then he would call upon his
Lord andremember Allah andpraise Him and supplicate to Him. Then he
wouldget up without sayingthe Salam. Then he would stand up and
pray theninth Rak’ah. Then hewould sit and remember Allah and
praise Him,and supplicate to hisLord and send blessing upon His
Prophet. Thenhe would say Salam thatwe could hear. Then he would
pray two Rak’ahafter the Salam, while hewas sitting down. That was
eleven Rak’ah.When the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) grew older and had
gained weight,he would pray Witr with sevenRak’ah and then pray two
more Rak’ahafter he had said the Salam.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
