<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51286</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1290</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20354, 20032, 11060, 38409, 20032, 11060,
11051, 11054, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو معاوية، ووكيع، عن
الأعمش، ح وحدثنا علي بن محمد، حدثنا وكيع، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، عن
الأسود، عن عائشة، قالت لما مرض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مرضه
الذي مات فيه - وقال أبو معاوية لما ثقل - جاء بلال يؤذنه بالصلاة
فقال ‏"‏ مروا أبا بكر فليصل بالناس ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قلنا يا رسول الله إن أبا
بكر رجل أسيف - تعني رقيق - ومتى ما يقوم مقامك يبكي فلا يستطيع فلو
أمرت عمر فصلى بالناس ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ مروا أبا بكر فليصل بالناس فإنكن
صواحبات يوسف ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فأرسلنا إلى أبي بكر فصلى بالناس فوجد رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من نفسه خفة فخرج إلى الصلاة يهادى بين رجلين
ورجلاه تخطان في الأرض فلما أحس به أبو بكر ذهب ليتأخر فأومى إليه
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن مكانك ‏.‏ قال فجاء حتى أجلساه إلى جنب
أبي بكر فكان أبو بكر يأتم بالنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس يأتمون
بأبي بكر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “When the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ)fell ill with the sickness that would be his last” –
(One of thenarrators) Abu Mu’awiyah said: “When he was overcome by
sickness”–“Bilal came to tell him that it was time for prayer. He
said,‘TellAbu Bakr to lead the people in prayer.” We said:
‘OMessenger ofAllah! Abu Bakr is a tender-hearted man, and when
hetakes your placehe will weep and not be able to do it. Why do
younot tell ‘Umar tolead the people in prayer?’ He said: ‘TellAbu
Bakr to lead the peoplein prayer; you are (like) the
femalecompanions of Yusuf.’” She said:“So we sent word to Abu
Bakr,and he led the people in prayer. Thenthe Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ)began to feel alittle better, so he cameout to the prayer,
supportedby two men with his feet making linesalong the ground.
When Abu Bakrrealized that he was there, he wantedto step back, but
the Prophet(ﷺ) gestured to him to stay where hewas. Then (the two
men)brought him to sit beside Abu Bakr, and AbuBakr was following
thelead of the Prophet (ﷺ) and the people werefollowing Abu
Bakr.”</english-text>
</hadith>
