<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51317</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1321</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عمرو بن السرح المصري، حدثنا عبد الله بن
وهب، أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة،
قالت كسفت الشمس في حياة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرج رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى المسجد فقام فكبر فصف الناس وراءه فقرأ رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قراءة طويلة ثم كبر فركع ركوعا طويلا ثم رفع
رأسه فقال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ربنا ولك الحمد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قام فقرأ
قراءة طويلة هي أدنى من القراءة الأولى ثم كبر فركع ركوعا طويلا هو
أدنى من الركوع الأول ثم قال ‏"‏ سمع الله لمن حمده ربنا ولك الحمد
‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم فعل في الركعة الأخرى مثل ذلك فاستكمل أربع ركعات وأربع
سجدات وانجلت الشمس قبل أن ينصرف ثم قام فخطب الناس فأثنى على الله
بما هو أهله ثم قال ‏"‏ إن الشمس والقمر آيتان من آيات الله لا
ينكسفان لموت أحد ولا لحياته فإذا رأيتموهما فافزعوا إلى الصلاة ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “The sun was
eclipsed during thelifeof the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ)wentout to the mosque and stood and said the Takbir,
and the peopleformed rows behind him. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
recited for along time, then he said the Takbir and bowed for a
long time. Then heraised his head and said: ‘Sami’ Allahu liman
hamidah, Rabban waslakal-hamd.’ Then he stood and recited for a
long time, but shorterthan the first recitation. Then he said the
Takbir and bowed for along time, but less than the first bowing.
Then he said: ‘Sami’Allahuliman hamidah, Rabbana wa lakal-hamd.’
Then he did the samein thenext Rak’ah, and he completed four Rak’ah
and four sets ofprostration, and the eclipse ended before he
finished. Then he stoodand addressed the people. He praised Allah
as He deserves to bepraised, then he said: ‘The sun and the moon
are two of the signsofAllah. They do not become eclipsed for the
death or birth ofanyone.If you see that then seek help in
prayer.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
