<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51384</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1388</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30450, 20568, 11585, 10975, 4097, 23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الملك بن أبي الشوارب، حدثنا مسلمة بن
علقمة، عن داود بن أبي هند، عن الوليد بن عبد الرحمن الجرشي، عن جبير
بن نفير الحضرمي، عن أبي ذر، قال صمنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم رمضان فلم يقم بنا شيئا منه حتى بقي سبع ليال فقام بنا ليلة
السابعة حتى مضى نحو من ثلث الليل ثم كانت الليلة السادسة التي تليها
فلم يقمها حتى كانت الخامسة التي تليها ثم قام بنا حتى مضى نحو من شطر
الليل فقلت يا رسول الله لو نفلتنا بقية ليلتنا هذه ‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إنه
من قام مع الإمام حتى ينصرف فإنه يعدل قيام ليلة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم كانت
الرابعة التي تليها فلم يقمها حتى كانت الثالثة التي تليها ‏.‏ قال
فجمع نساءه وأهله واجتمع الناس ‏.‏ قال فقام بنا حتى خشينا أن يفوتنا
الفلاح ‏.‏ قيل وما الفلاح قال السحور ‏.‏ قال ثم لم يقم بنا شيئا من
بقية الشهر ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Abu Dharr said: “We fasted
Ramadan with theMessengerof Allah (ﷺ) and he did not lead us in
praying Qiyam(prayers atnight) during any part of it, until there
were sevennights left. Heled us in praying Qiyam on the seventh
night untilapproximately onethird of the night had passed. Then on
the sixthnight which followedit he did not lead us in prayer. Then
he led usin praying Qiyam onthe fifth night which followed it until
almosthalf the night hadpassed. I said: ‘O Messenger of Allah,
would thatwe had offeredvoluntary prayers throughout the whole
night.’ He said:‘Whoeverstands with the Imam until he finishes, it
is equivalent tospendingthe whole night in prayer.’ Then on the
fourth night whichfollowedit, he did not lead us in prayer, until
the third night thatfollowedit, when he gathered his wives and
family, and he peoplegathered,and he led us in prayer until we
feared that we would misstheFalah.” It was asked: “What is the
Falah?” He said: “Suhur.”Hesaid: “Then he did not lead us in prayer
at night for the restof themonth.”</english-text>
</hadith>
