<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51402</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1406</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20326, 18713</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو خالد الأحمر، عن
عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن يعلى الطائفي، عن عثمان بن عبد الله بن
أوس، عن جده، أوس بن حذيفة قال قدمنا على رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في وفد ثقيف فنزلوا الأحلاف على المغيرة بن شعبة وأنزل رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بني مالك في قبة له فكان يأتينا كل ليلة بعد
العشاء فيحدثنا قائما على رجليه حتى يراوح بين رجليه وأكثر ما يحدثنا
ما لقي من قومه من قريش ويقول ‏"‏ ولا سواء كنا مستضعفين مستذلين فلما
خرجنا إلى المدينة كانت سجال الحرب بيننا وبينهم ندال عليهم ويدالون
علينا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما كان ذات ليلة أبطأ عن الوقت الذي كان يأتينا فيه
فقلت يا رسول الله لقد أبطأت علينا الليلة ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إنه طرأ على
حزبي من القرآن فكرهت أن أخرج حتى أتمه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أوس فسألت أصحاب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كيف تحزبون القرآن قالوا ثلاث وخمس وسبع
وتسع وإحدى عشرة وثلاث عشرة وحزب المفصل ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from ‘Uthman bin ‘Abdullah bin Aws
that hisgrandfatherAws bin Hudhaifah said: “We came to the
Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) inthe delegation of Thaqif. The allies of
Quraish stayed at thehouseof Mughirah bin Shu’bah, and the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) campedBani Malik in a tent belonging to him.
He used to come to us everynight after the ‘Isha’ and speak to us
standing on his two feet,untilhe started to shift his weight from
one foot to the other. Mostofwhat he told us was what he had
suffered from his people, theQuraish.He said: ‘(The two sides) were
not equal. We were weak andoppressedand humiliated, and when we
went out to Al-Madinah, theoutcome of thebattles between us varied;
sometimes we would defeatthem andsometimes they would defeat us.’
One night he was laterthan heusually was, and I said: ‘O Messenger
of Allah, you havecome to uslate tonight.’ He said: ‘It occurred to
me that I hadnot read mydaily portion of Qur’an and I did not want
to come outuntil I hadcompleted it.’” Aws said: “I asked the
Companionsof the Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ): ‘How did you used to divide
up theQur’an?’ They said: ‘Athird, a fifth, a seventh, a ninth,
aneleventh, a thirteenth, andHizbul-Mufassal.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
