<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51412</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1416</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20005, 11247, 11053, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، حدثنا سفيان بن عيينة، عن سليمان
الأحول، عن طاوس، عن ابن عباس، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
إذا تهجد من الليل قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك الحمد أنت نور السموات والأرض ومن
فيهن ولك الحمد أنت قيام السموات والأرض ومن فيهن ولك الحمد أنت مالك
السموات والأرض ومن فيهن ولك الحمد أنت الحق ووعدك حق ولقاؤك حق وقولك
حق والجنة حق والنار حق والساعة حق والنبيون حق ومحمد حق اللهم لك
أسلمت وبك آمنت وعليك توكلت وإليك أنبت وبك خاصمت وإليك حاكمت فاغفر
لي ما قدمت وما أخرت وما أسررت وما أعلنت أنت المقدم وأنت المؤخر لا
إله إلا أنت ولا إله غيرك ولا حول ولا قوة إلا بك ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Ibn ‘Abbas said: “When the
Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)prayed Tahajjud at night, he would say:
“Allahumma lakal-hamd,Antanurus-samawati wal-ard wa man fihinna. Wa
lakal-hamd, Antaqayyamus-samawati wal-ard wa man fihinna. Wa
lakal-hamd, Antamalikus-samawati wal-ard wa man fihinna. Wa
lakal-hamd, Antal-haqq,wa wa’dukahaqq, wa liqa’uka haqq, wa qawluka
haqq, wal-jannatuhaqq, wan-nabiyyuna haqq, wa Muhammadun haqq.
Allahumma laka aslamtu,wa bikaamantu, wa ‘alaika tawakkaltu wa
ilaika anabtu, wa bikakhasamtu, wailaika hakamtu, faghfirli ma
qaddamtu wa ma akhkhartu,wa ma asrartuwa ma a’lantu.
Antal-muqaddimu wa Antal-muakhkhiru.La ilaha illa antawa la ilaha
ghairuka, wa la hawla wa la quwwatailla bika (O allah, toyou is
praise, You are the Light of theheavens and the earth, andeveryone
therein. To You is praise, Youare the Sustainer of theheavens and
the earth, and everyone therein.To You is praise, You arethe
Sovereign of the heavens and the earth,and everyone therein. ToYou
is praise, You are the Truth; Yourpromise is true, the meetingwith
You is true, Your saying is true,Paradise is true, the Fire istrue,
the Hour is true, the Prophetsare true, and Muhammad is true.
OAllah, to You have I submitted, inYou I believe, in You have I put
mytrust, to You I turn inrepentance, by Your help I argue, to You
Irefer my case, so forgiveme for my past and future sins, what I
havedone in secret and what Ihave done openly. You are the One Who
bringsforward and puts back.None has the right to be worshipped but
You,and there is none whohas the right to be worshipped other than
You.And there is no powerand no strength except with
You.”</english-text>
</hadith>
