<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51421</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1425</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30357, 30112, 20001, 11223, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن خلاد الباهلي، حدثنا معن بن عيسى،
حدثنا مالك بن أنس، عن مخرمة بن سليمان، عن كريب، مولى ابن عباس عن
ابن عباس، أخبره أنه، نام عند ميمونة زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم -
وهي خالته - قال فاضطجعت في عرض الوسادة واضطجع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأهله في طولها فنام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى إذا
انتصف الليل أو قبله بقليل أو بعده بقليل استيقظ النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فجعل يمسح النوم عن وجهه بيده ثم قرأ العشر آيات من آخر سورة آل
عمران ثم قام إلى شن معلقة فتوضأ منها فأحسن وضوءه ثم قام يصلي ‏.‏
قال عبد الله بن عباس فقمت فصنعت مثل ما صنع ثم ذهبت فقمت إلى جنبه
فوضع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده اليمنى على رأسي وأخذ أذني
اليمنى يفتلها فصلى ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين ثم ركعتين
ثم ركعتين ثم أوتر ‏.‏ ثم اضطجع حتى جاءه المؤذن فصلى ركعتين خفيفتين
ثم خرج إلى الصلاة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Kurraib, the freed slave of Ibn
‘Abbas, that Ibn‘Abbas told him that he slept at the house of
Maimunah, the wife ofthe Prophet (ﷺ), who was his maternal aunt. He
said: “I lay downacross the pillow and the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
and his wife werelaying along it. The prophet (ﷺ) slept until
midnight, or a littlebefore, or a little after. The Prophet (ﷺ)
woke up and began to rubthe sleep from his face with his hand. Then
he recited the last tenVerses of Surah Al ‘Imran. Then he got up
and went to a water skinthat was hanging up and performed ablution
from it, and he performedablution well, then he stood up and
prayed.” ‘Abdullah bin ‘Abbassaid: “I stood up and did what he had
done, then I went and stoodbeside him. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
put his right hand on myhead, took hold of my right ear and tweaked
it. Then he prayed twoRak’ah, then two Rak’ah, then two Rak’ah,
then two Rak’ah,then twoRak’ah, then two Rak’ah, then he prayed
Witr. Then helay down untilthe Mu’adh-dhin came to him and he
prayed two briefRak’ah, then hewent out to pray.”</english-text>
</hadith>
