<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51443</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1447</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30547, 24515</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سويد بن سعيد، حدثنا أبو عاصم العباداني، عن فائد
بن عبد الرحمن، عن عبد الله بن أبي أوفى الأسلمي، قال خرج علينا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ من كانت له حاجة إلى الله أو إلى
أحد من خلقه فليتوضأ وليصل ركعتين ثم ليقل لا إله إلا الله الحليم
الكريم سبحان الله رب العرش العظيم الحمد لله رب العالمين اللهم إني
أسألك موجبات رحمتك وعزائم مغفرتك والغنيمة من كل بر والسلامة من كل
إثم أسألك ألا تدع لي ذنبا إلا غفرته ولا هما إلا فرجته ولا حاجة هي
لك رضا إلا قضيتها لي ثم يسأل الله من أمر الدنيا والآخرة ما شاء فإنه
يقدر ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Abdullah bin Abi Awfa Al-Aslami
said: “TheMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) came out to us and said: ‘Whoever
has someneed from Allah or from any of His creation, let him
perform ablutionand pray two Rak’ah, then let him say: La
ilahaillallahul-Halimul-Karim. Subhan-Allahi
Rabbil-‘arshil-‘azim.Al-hamdu LillahiRabbil-‘Alamin. Allahumma inni
as’aluka mujibatrahmatika, wa ‘aza’imamaghfiratika, wal-ghanimata
min kullibarrin, was-salamata min kulliithmnin. As’aluka alla
tada’a lidhanban illa ghafartahu, wa la hammanilla farrajtahu, wa
la hajahhiya laka irdan illa qadaitaha li (Nonehas the right to
beworshipped but Allah, the Forbearing, the MostGenerous. Glory is
toAllah, the Lord of the Mighty Throne. Praise isto Allah, the Lord
ofthe worlds. O Allah, I ask You for the means ofYour mercy
andforgiveness, the benefit of every good deed and safetyfrom all
sins.I ask You not to leave any sin of mine but You forgiveit, or
anydistress but You relieve it, or any need that is pleasingto You
butYou meet it). Then he should ask Allah for whatever hewants in
thisworld and in the Hereafter, for it is decreed.”</english-text>
</hadith>
