<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51442</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1446</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>30535, 30463, 20441, 11048, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن يوسف السلمي، حدثنا خالد بن مخلد، حدثنا
عبد الرحمن بن أبي الموال، قال سمعت محمد بن المنكدر، يحدث عن جابر بن
عبد الله، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعلمنا الاستخارة كما
يعلمنا السورة من القرآن يقول ‏"‏ إذا هم أحدكم بالأمر فليركع ركعتين
من غير الفريضة ثم ليقل اللهم إني أستخيرك بعلمك وأستقدرك بقدرتك
وأسألك من فضلك العظيم فإنك تقدر ولا أقدر وتعلم ولا أعلم وأنت علام
الغيوب اللهم إن كنت تعلم هذا الأمر - فيسميه ما كان من شىء - خيرا لي
في ديني ومعاشي وعاقبة أمري - أو خيرا لي في عاجل أمري وآجله - فاقدره
لي ويسره لي وبارك لي فيه وإن كنت تعلم - يقول مثل ما قال في المرة
الأولى - وإن كان شرا لي فاصرفه عني واصرفني عنه واقدر لي الخير حيثما
كان ثم رضني به ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Jabir bin ‘Abdullah said: “The
Messenger ofAllah(ﷺ) used to teach us Istikharah, just as he used
to teach us aSurah of the Qur’an. He said: ‘If anyone of you is
deliberatingabouta decision he has to make, then let him pray two
Rak’ah ofnon-obligatory prayer, then say: Allahumma inni
astakhiruka bin‘ilmika waastaqdiruka bi qudratika wa as’aluka
minfadlikal-‘azim, fa innakataqdiru wa la aqdir, wa ta’lamu wa
laa’lam, wa Anta ‘allamul-ghuyub.Allahumma in kunta
ta’lamuhadhal-amra (then the matter should bementioned by name) ma
kan minshay’in khairan li fi dini wa ma’ashi wa‘aqibati amri,
awkhairanli fi ‘ajili amri wa ajilihi, faqdurhu li wayassirhu li
wabarik li fihi. Wa in kunta ta’lamu [O Allah, I seekYour
guidance(in making a choice) by virtue of Your knowledge, and Iseek
abilityby virtue of Your power, and I ask You of Your greatbounty.
You havepower, I have none. And You know, I know not. You arethe
Knower ofhidden things. O Allah, if in Your knowledge, thismatter
(then itshould be mentioned by name) is good for me in myreligion,
mylivelihood and my affairs, or both in this world and inthe
Hereafterthen ordain it for me, make it easy for me, and bless
itfor me. Andif in Your knowledge]. Then saying similar to what he
saidthe firsttime, except: Wa in kana sharrun li fasrifhu ‘anni
wasrifni‘anhuwaqdur li al-khair haithuma kana thumma raddini bihi
(If it isbadfor me then turn it away from me and turn me away from
it, andordainfor me the good wherever it may be and make me pleased
withit).’”</english-text>
</hadith>
