<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51446</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1450</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>19904, 11023, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن بشر بن الحكم النيسابوري، حدثنا
موسى بن عبد العزيز، حدثنا الحكم بن أبان، عن عكرمة، عن ابن عباس، قال
قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم للعباس بن عبد المطلب ‏"‏ يا عباس
يا عماه ألا أعطيك ألا أمنحك ألا أحبوك ألا أفعل لك عشر خصال إذا أنت
فعلت ذلك غفر الله لك ذنبك أوله وآخره وقديمه وحديثه وخطأه وعمده
وصغيره وكبيره وسره وعلانيته عشر خصال أن تصلي أربع ركعات تقرأ في كل
ركعة بفاتحة الكتاب وسورة فإذا فرغت من القراءة في أول ركعة قلت وأنت
قائم سبحان الله والحمد لله ولا إله إلا الله والله أكبر خمس عشرة مرة
ثم تركع فتقول وأنت راكع عشرا ثم ترفع رأسك من الركوع فتقولها عشرا ثم
تهوي ساجدا فتقولها وأنت ساجد عشرا ثم ترفع رأسك من السجود فتقولها
عشرا ثم تسجد فتقولها عشرا ثم ترفع رأسك من السجود فتقولها عشرا فذلك
خمسة وسبعون في كل ركعة تفعل في أربع ركعات إن استطعت أن تصليها في كل
يوم مرة فافعل فإن لم تستطع ففي كل جمعة مرة فإن لم تفعل ففي كل شهر
مرة فإن لم تفعل ففي عمرك مرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Ibn ‘Abbas said: “The Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ)saidto ‘Abbas bin ‘Abdul-Muttalib: ‘O ‘Abbas, O my
uncle, shall Inotgive you a gift, shall I not give you something,
shall I not tellyouof something which, if you do it, will expiate
for ten types ofsins?If you do them, Allah will forgive you your
sins, the first andthelast of them, the old and the new, the
unintentional and thedeliberate, the minor and the major, the
secret and the open, tentypes of sin. Pray four Rak’ah, and recite
in each Rak’ah theOpeningof the Book (Al-Fatihah) and a Surah. When
you have finishedrecitingin the first Rak’ah, while you are
standing, say:Subhan-Allah wal-hamdu Lillah wa la ilaha illallah wa
Allahu Akbar(Glory if to Allah,praise is to Allah, none has the
right to beworshipped but Allah andAllah is the Most Great) fifteen
times. Thenbow and say it ten timeswhile you are bowing. Then raise
your headfrom Ruku’ and say it tentimes. Then go into prostration
and sayit ten times while you areprostrating. Then raise your head
fromprostration and say it tentimes. Then prostrate and say it
tentimes. Then raise your head fromprostration and say it ten
times.That will be seventy-five times ineach Rak’ah. Do that in all
fourRak’ah. If you can pray it once eachday then do so. If you
cannot,then once each week; if you cannot,then once each month. If
youcannot, then once in your lifetime.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
