<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51475</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>5</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1479</hadith-number>
<chapter>Establishing the Prayer and the Sunnah Regarding Them -
كتاب إقامة الصلاة والسنة فيها</chapter>
<chain-index>38111, 20445, 12246, 18938</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل بن عبد الله الرقي، حدثنا عبيد الله بن
عمرو الرقي، عن عبد الله بن محمد بن عقيل، عن الطفيل بن أبى بن كعب،
عن أبيه، قال كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي إلى جذع إذ كان
المسجد عريشا وكان يخطب إلى ذلك الجذع فقال رجل من أصحابه هل لك أن
نجعل لك شيئا تقوم عليه يوم الجمعة حتى يراك الناس وتسمعهم خطبتك قال
‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فصنع له ثلاث درجات فهي التي على المنبر فلما وضع
المنبر وضعوه في موضعه الذي هو فيه فلما أراد رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم أن يقوم إلى المنبر مر إلى الجذع الذي كان يخطب إليه فلما جاوز
الجذع خار حتى تصدع وانشق فنزل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لما سمع
صوت الجذع فمسحه بيده حتى سكن ثم رجع إلى المنبر فكان إذا صلى صلى
إليه فلما هدم المسجد وغير أخذ ذلك الجذع أبى بن كعب وكان عنده في
بيته حتى بلي فأكلته الأرضة وعاد رفاتا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Tufail bin Ubayy bin Ka’b that
his father said: “TheMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) used to pray facing the
trunk of a date-palmtree when the mosque was still a hut, and he
used to deliver thesermon leaning on that trunk. A man from among
his Companions said:‘Would you like us to make you something upon
which you can standonFridays so that the people will be able to see
you and hear yoursermon?’ He said: ‘Yes.’ So he made three steps
for him, as apulpit.When they put the pulpit in place, they put it
in the placewhere itstands now. When the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
wanted tostand on thepulpit, he passed by the tree trunk from which
he usedto deliver thesermon, and when he went beyond the trunk, it
moanedand split andcracked. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) came down
when heheard thevoice of the trunk, and rubbed it with his hand
until itfell silent.Then he went back to the pulpit and when he
prayed, heprayed facingit. When the mosque was knocked down (for
renovation)and (thepillars, etc.) were changed, Ubayy bin Ka’b took
thattrunk and keptit in his house until it became very old and
thetermites consumed itand it became grains of
dust.”</english-text>
</hadith>
