<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51662</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1666</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters Regarding Funerals - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20472, 22137, 18860, 246, 56</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، أنبأنا
عبد الملك بن قدامة الجمحي، عن أبيه، عن عمر بن أبي سلمة، عن أم سلمة،
أن أبا سلمة، حدثها أنه، سمع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏
ما من مسلم يصاب بمصيبة فيفزع إلى ما أمر الله به من قوله إنا لله
وإنا إليه راجعون اللهم عندك احتسبت مصيبتي فأجرني فيها وعضني منها -
إلا آجره الله عليها وعاضه خيرا منها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فلما توفي أبو سلمة
ذكرت الذي حدثني عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت إنا لله وإنا
إليه راجعون اللهم عندك احتسبت مصيبتي هذه فأجرني عليها ‏.‏ فإذا أردت
أن أقول وعضني خيرا منها قلت في نفسي أعاض خيرا من أبي سلمة ثم قلتها
فعاضني الله محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وآجرني في مصيبتي
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Umm Salamah that Abu Salamah told
her that heheard theMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: “There is no Muslim
who isstrickenwith a calamity and reacts by saying as Allah has
commanded:‘Innalillahi, wa inna ilayhi raji’un. Allahumma
indakah-tasabtumusibati, fajurni iha, wa ‘awwidni minha (Truly, to
Allah we belongand truly, to Him we shall return. O Allah, with You
I seek rewardformy calamity, so reward me for it and compensate
me),’ but Allahwillreward him for that and compensate him with
something betterthan it.”She said: “When Abu Salamah died, I
remembered what hehad told mefrom the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and I
said: ‘Innalillahi, wa innailayhi raji’un. Allahumma
indakah-tasabtumusibati, fajurni ihaiha(Truly, to Allah we belong
and truly, to Himwe shall return. O Allah,with You I seek reward
for my calamity, soreward me for it).’ Butwhen I wanted to say wa
‘awwidni minha(and compensate me withbetter), I said to myself:
‘How can I becompensated with somethingbetter than Abu Salamah?’
Then I saidit, and Allah compensated mewith Muhammad (ﷺ) and
rewarded me formy calamity.”</english-text>
</hadith>
