<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51685</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1689</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters Regarding Funerals - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20331, 11338, 11385, 11052, 11018,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، عن
زكريا، عن فراس، عن عامر، عن مسروق، عن عائشة، قالت اجتمعن نساء النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فلم تغادر منهن امرأة فجاءت فاطمة كأن مشيتها مشية
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ مرحبا بابنتي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم
أجلسها عن شماله ثم إنه أسر إليها حديثا فبكت فاطمة ثم إنه سارها
فضحكت أيضا فقلت لها ما يبكيك قالت ما كنت لأفشي سر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ فقلت ما رأيت كاليوم فرحا أقرب من حزن ‏.‏ فقلت
لها حين بكت أخصك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بحديث دوننا ثم تبكين
وسألتها عما قال ‏.‏ فقالت ما كنت لأفشي سر رسول الله - -- ص - ‏.‏
حتى إذا قبض سألتها عما قال فقالت إنه كان يحدثني أن جبرائيل كان
يعارضه بالقرآن في كل عام مرة وأنه عارضه به العام مرتين ‏"‏ ولا
أراني إلا قد حضر أجلي وأنك أول أهلي لحوقا بي ونعم السلف أنا لك ‏"‏
‏.‏ فبكيت ثم إنه سارني فقال ‏"‏ ألا ترضين أن تكوني سيدة نساء
المؤمنين - أو نساء هذه الأمة - ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فضحكت لذلك ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “The wives of the
Prophet (ﷺ)gathered together and not one of them lagged behind.
Fatimah came,andher gait was like that of the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ). He said,‘Welcome to my daughter.’ Then he made her sit to his
left, andhewhispered something to her, and she smiled. I said to
her: ‘Whatmadeyou weep?’ She said: ‘I will not disclose the secret
of theMessengerof Allah (ﷺ).’ I said: ‘I never saw joy so close
togrief as I sawtoday.’ When she wept I said: ‘Did the Messengerof
Allah (ﷺ) tellyou some special words that were not for us, thenyou
wept?’ And Iasked her about what he had said. She said: ‘Iwill not
disclose thesecret of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).’After he died I
asked herwhat he had said, and she said: ‘He toldme that Jibra’il
used toreview the Qur’an with him once eachyear, but he had
reviewed it withhim twice that year, (and he said:)“I do not think
but that my timeis near. You will be the first ofmy family to join
me, and what agood predecessor I am for you.” SoI wept. Then he
whispered to me andsaid: “Will you not be pleasedto be the leader
of the women of thisUmmah?” So I smiled.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
