<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51692</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1696</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters Regarding Funerals - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30395, 20298, 11272, 11107, 11023, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا نصر بن علي الجهضمي، أنبأنا وهب بن جرير، حدثنا
أبي، عن محمد بن إسحاق، حدثني حسين بن عبد الله، عن عكرمة، عن ابن
عباس، قال لما أرادوا أن يحفروا، لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعثوا
إلى أبي عبيدة بن الجراح وكان يضرح كضريح أهل مكة وبعثوا إلى أبي طلحة
وكان هو الذي يحفر لأهل المدينة وكان يلحد فبعثوا إليهما رسولين
وقالوا اللهم خر لرسولك ‏.‏ فوجدوا أبا طلحة فجيء به ولم يوجد أبو
عبيدة فلحد لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال فلما فرغوا من
جهازه يوم الثلاثاء وضع على سريره في بيته ‏.‏ ثم دخل الناس على رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أرسالا ‏.‏ يصلون عليه حتى إذا فرغوا أدخلوا
النساء حتى إذا فرغوا أدخلوا الصبيان ولم يؤم الناس على رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أحد ‏.‏ لقد اختلف المسلمون في المكان الذي يحفر له
فقال قائلون يدفن في مسجده ‏.‏ وقال قائلون يدفن مع أصحابه ‏.‏ فقال
أبو بكر إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ ما قبض نبي
إلا دفن حيث يقبض ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فرفعوا فراش رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم الذي توفي عليه فحفروا له ثم دفن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وسط الليل من ليلة الأربعاء ‏.‏ ونزل في حفرته علي بن أبي طالب والفضل
وقثم ابنا العباس وشقران مولى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وقال
أوس بن خولي وهو أبو ليلى لعلي بن أبي طالب أنشدك الله وحظنا من رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال له علي انزل ‏.‏ وكان شقران مولاه
أخذ قطيفة كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يلبسها فدفنها في القبر
وقال والله لا يلبسها أحد بعدك أبدا ‏.‏ فدفنت مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Ibn ‘Abbas said: “When they
wanted to dig agravefor the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), they sent for
Abu ‘Ubaidah binJarrah, who used to dig graves in the manner of the
people of Makkah,and they sent for Abu Talhah, who used to dig
graves for the peopleofAl-Madinah, and he used to make a niche in
the grave. They senttwomessengers to both of them, and they said:
‘O Allah, choosewhat isbest for Your Messenger.’ They found Abu
Talhah and broughthim, butthey did not find Abu ‘Ubaidah. So he dug
a grave with aniche for theMessenger of Allah (ﷺ). When they had
finishedpreparing him, onTuesday, he was placed on his bed in his
house.Then the peopleentered upon the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) in
groupsand offered thefuneral prayer for him, and when they finished
thewomen entered, andwhen they finished the children entered, and
noone led the people inoffering the funeral prayer for the
Messengerof Allah (ﷺ). TheMuslims differed concerning the place
where heshould be buried. Somesaid that he should be buried in his
mosque.Others said that heshould be buried with his Companions.
Then AbuBakr said: ‘I heard theMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) say: “No
Prophetever passed away but he wasburied where he died.” So they
liftedup the bed of the Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ) on which he had died,
anddug the grave for him, then he(ﷺ) was buried in the middle
ofTuesday night. ‘Ali bin Abu Talib,Fadl bin ‘Abbas and hisbrother
Qutham, and Shuqran the freed slave ofthe Messenger of Allah(ﷺ)
went down in his grave. Aws bin Khawli,who was Abu Laila, saidto
‘Ali bin Abi Talib: ‘I adjure you by Allah!Give us our shareof the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).’ So ‘Ali said tohim: ‘Comedown.’ Shuqran,
his freed slave, had taken a Qatifah whichtheMessenger of Allah (ﷺ)
used to wear. He buried it in his graveandsaid, ‘By Allah, no one
will ever wear it after you.’ So it wasburied with the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ).”</english-text>
</hadith>
