<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51691</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1695</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters Regarding Funerals - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>38409, 20354, 107, 11090, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن محمد، حدثنا أبو معاوية، عن عبد الرحمن بن
أبي بكر، عن ابن أبي مليكة، عن عائشة، قالت لما قبض رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وأبو بكر عند امرأته ابنة خارجة بالعوالي فجعلوا
يقولون لم يمت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إنما هو بعض ما كان يأخذه عند
الوحى ‏.‏ فجاء أبو بكر فكشف عن وجهه وقبل بين عينيه وقال أنت أكرم
على الله من أن يميتك مرتين قد والله مات رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏.‏ وعمر في ناحية المسجد يقول والله ما مات رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ولا يموت حتى يقطع أيدي أناس من المنافقين كثير وأرجلهم ‏.‏
فقام أبو بكر فصعد المنبر فقال من كان يعبد الله فإن الله حى لم يمت
ومن كان يعبد محمدا فإن محمدا قد مات ‏{وما محمد إلا رسول قد خلت من
قبله الرسل أفإن مات أو قتل انقلبتم على أعقابكم ومن ينقلب على عقبيه
فلن يضر الله شيئا وسيجزي الله الشاكرين}‏ ‏.‏ قال عمر فلكأني لم
أقرأها إلا يومئذ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “When the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ)passed away, Abu Bakr was with his wife, the daughter
of Kharijah, invillages surrounding Al-Madinah. They started to
say: ‘The Prophet(ﷺ) has not died, rather he has been overcome with
what used toovercome him at the time of Revelation.’ Then Abu Bakr
came anduncovered his (the Prophet’s (ﷺ)) face, kissed him between
theeyesand said: ‘You are too noble before Allah for Him to cause
youto dietwice. By Allah, the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) has
indeeddied.’ ‘Umarwas in a corner of the mosque saying: ‘By
Allah,the Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ) has not died and he will never die
untilthe hands andfeet of most of the hypocrites are cut off.’ Then
AbuBakr stood up,ascended the pulpit and said: ‘Whoever used
toworship Allah, Allah isalive and will never die. Whoever used
toworship Muhammad, Muhammadis dead. “Muhammad is no more than
aMessenger, and indeed (many)Messengers have passed away before
him.If he dies or is killed, willyou then turn back on your heels
(asdisbelievers)? And he who turnsback on his heels, not the least
harmwill he do to Allah; and Allahwill give reward to those who
aregrateful.’” [3:144] ‘Umar said: ‘Itwas as if I had neverread
(that Verse) before that day.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
