<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51864</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1871</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters Regarding Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>38552, 20420, 20187, 11210, 11232, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عقيل بن خويلد النيسابوري، حدثنا حفص بن
عبد الله السلمي، حدثنا إبراهيم بن طهمان، عن عمرو بن يحيى بن عمارة،
عن أبيه، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ ليس فيما دون خمس من الإبل صدقة وليس في الأربع شىء فإذا بلغت
خمسا ففيها شاة إلى أن تبلغ تسعا فإذا بلغت عشرا ففيها شاتان إلى أن
تبلغ أربع عشرة فإذا بلغت خمس عشرة ففيها ثلاث شياه إلى أن تبلغ تسع
عشرة فإذا بلغت عشرين ففيها أربع شياه إلى أن تبلغ أربعا وعشرين فإذا
بلغت خمسا وعشرين ففيها بنت مخاض إلى خمس وثلاثين فإذا لم تكن بنت
مخاض فابن لبون ذكر فإن زادت بعيرا ففيها بنت لبون إلى أن تبلغ خمسا
وأربعين فإن زادت بعيرا ففيها حقة إلى أن تبلغ ستين فإن زادت بعيرا
ففيها جذعة إلى أن تبلغ خمسا وسبعين فإن زادت بعيرا ففيها بنتا لبون
إلى أن تبلغ تسعين فإن زادت بعيرا ففيها حقتان إلى أن تبلغ عشرين
ومائة ثم في كل خمسين حقة وفي كل أربعين بنت لبون ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that: that Abu Sa'eed Al-Khudri said:
“The Messenger of Allah said: 'There is no Sadaqah on any less then
five camels, or for four. If the number of camels reaches five then
one sheep must be given, up to nine. If the number reaches ten,
then two sheep must be given, up to fourteen. If the number reaches
fifteen, then three sheep must be given, up to nineteen. If the
number reaches twenty, then four sheep must be given, up to
twenty-four. If the number reaches twenty-five, then a Bint Makhad
(a one year old she-camel), must be given up to thirty-five; if
there is not Bint Makhad, then a Bin Labun (a two-year-old male
camel). If there are more camels then a Bint Labun (a two-year-old
she-camel) up to forty-five. If there are more camels then a Hiqqah
(a three-year-old she-camel) must be given up to sixty. If there
are more camels then a Jadha'ah (a five-year-old she-camel) must be
given up to seventy-five. If there are more camels, then two Bint
Labun must be given, up to ninety. If there are more camels, then
two Hiqqah must be given, up to one hundred and twenty. The for
each fifty, one Hiqqah, and for each forty, a Bint Labun.'
”</english-text>
</hadith>
