<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51863</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1870</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters Regarding Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>34043, 20033, 20235, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بشر، بكر بن خلف حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن مهدي،
حدثنا سليمان بن كثير، حدثنا ابن شهاب، عن سالم بن عبد الله، عن أبيه،
عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال أقرأني سالم كتابا كتبه رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في الصدقات قبل أن يتوفاه الله فوجدت فيه ‏"‏ في
خمس من الإبل شاة وفي عشر شاتان وفي خمس عشرة ثلاث شياه وفي عشرين
أربع شياه وفي خمس وعشرين بنت مخاض إلى خمس وثلاثين فإن لم توجد بنت
مخاض فابن لبون ذكر فإن زادت على خمس وثلاثين واحدة ففيها بنت لبون
إلى خمسة وأربعين فإن زادت على خمس وأربعين واحدة ففيها حقة إلى ستين
فإن زادت على ستين واحدة ففيها جذعة إلى خمس وسبعين فإن زادت على خمس
وسبعين واحدة ففيها ابنتا لبون إلى تسعين فإن زادت على تسعين واحدة
ففيها حقتان إلى عشرين ومائة فإذا كثرت ففي كل خمسين حقة وفي كل
أربعين بنت لبون ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Ibn Shihab narrated from Salim bin Abdullah, from his
father, from the Prophet(ﷺ): Ibn Shihab said: “Salim read to me a
letter that the Messenger of Allah had written concerning Sadaqat,
before Allah caused him to pass away, in which it was said: 'For
five camels one sheep; for ten, two sheep; for twenty, four sheep.
For twenty five, a Bint Makhad(a one year old she-camel), up to
thirty-five; if there is no Bint Makhad, then a Bin Labun ( a
two-year-old male camel). If there are more than thirty-five even
one, then a Bint Labun ( a two-year-old she-camel) must be given up
to forty-five. If there are more than forty-five, even one, then a
Hiqqah (a three-year-old she-camel), up to sixty camels. If there
are more than sixty, even one more, then a Jadha'ah ( a
four-year-old she-camel) must be given, up to seventy-five. If
there are more than seventy-five, even one more, then two Bint
Labun must be given, upto ninety. If there are more than ninety,
even one more, then two Hiqqah must be given, up to one hundred and
twenty. If there are many camels, then for each fifty, one Hiqqah
must be given and for each forty a Bint Labun' ”</english-text>
</hadith>
