<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>51887</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1894</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters Regarding Zakat - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>34011, 20597, 20643, 10743, 11372, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن محمد بن يحيى بن سعيد القطان، حدثنا عمرو
بن محمد العنقزي، حدثنا أسباط بن نصر، عن السدي، عن عدي بن ثابت، عن
البراء بن عازب، في قوله سبحانه ‏{‏ومما أخرجنا لكم من الأرض ولا
تيمموا الخبيث منه تنفقون}‏ ‏.‏ قال نزلت في الأنصار كانت الأنصار
تخرج إذا كان جداد النخل من حيطانها أقناء البسر فيعلقونه على حبل بين
أسطوانتين في مسجد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيأكل منه فقراء
المهاجرين فيعمد أحدهم فيدخل قنو الحشف يظن أنه جائز في كثرة ما يوضع
من الأقناء فنزل فيمن فعل ذلك ‏{ولا تيمموا الخبيث منه تنفقون}‏ ‏.‏
يقول لا تعمدوا للحشف منه تنفقون ‏.‏ ‏{ولستم بآخذيه إلا أن تغمضوا
فيه }‏ يقول لو أهدي لكم ما قبلتموه إلا على استحياء من صاحبه غيظا
أنه بعث إليكم ما لم يكن لكم فيه حاجة واعلموا أن الله غني عن صدقاتكم
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that: Bara bin Azib said concerning
the Verse: “And of that which We have priduced from the earth for
you, and don not aim at that which is bad to spend from it. ”
[Al-Baqarah 2:267] “This was revealed concerning the Ansar. At the
time of the new date-palm harvest, they would take a bunch of dates
that were beginning to ripen and hang it on a rope between two of
the pillars in the mosque of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), and the
poor emigrants would eat from it.” One of them deliberately mixed a
bunch containing rotten and shriveled dates, and thought this was
permissible because of the large number of dates that had been put
there. So the following was revealed about the one who did that: '…
and do not aim at that which is bad to spend from it'. Meaning do
not seek out the rotten and shriveled dates to give in charity:
'…(thought) you would not accept it save if you close your eyes and
tolerate therein.' Meaning, if you were given this as a gift you
would only accept it because you felt embarrassed, and you would
get angry that he had sent something of which you have no need. And
know that Allah has no need of your charity.”</english-text>
</hadith>
