<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52178</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2185</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Expiation - كتاب الكفارات</chapter>
<chain-index>30423, 20022, 11300, 11901</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عبدة، أنبأنا حماد بن زيد، حدثنا غيلان بن
جرير، عن أبي بردة، عن أبيه أبي موسى، قال أتيت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في رهط من الأشعريين نستحمله فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ والله ما أحملكم وما عندي ما أحملكم عليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فلبثنا
ما شاء الله ثم أتي بإبل فأمر لنا بثلاثة إبل ذود غر الذرى فلما
انطلقنا قال بعضنا لبعض أتينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نستحمله
فحلف ألا يحملنا ثم حملنا ارجعوا بنا ‏.‏ فأتيناه فقلنا يا رسول الله
إنا أتيناك نستحملك فحلفت أن لا تحملنا ‏.‏ ثم حملتنا فقال ‏"‏ والله
ما أنا حملتكم فإن الله حملكم والله ما أنا حملتكم بل الله حملكم إني
والله إن شاء الله لا أحلف على يمين فأرى غيرها خيرا منها إلا كفرت عن
يميني وأتيت الذي هو خير ‏"‏ ‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ أتيت الذي هو خير وكفرت
عن يميني ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Burdah that his father Abu
Musa said: "I came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) with a group of
Asharites and asked him to give us animals to ride. He said: 'By
Allah, I cannot give you anything to ride, and I have nothing to
give you to ride.' We stayed as long as Allah willed, then some
camels were brought to him. He ordered that we be given three
she-camels with fine humps. When we left, we said to one another:
'We came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) to ask him for animals to
ride, and he swore by Allah that he would not give us anything to
ride, then he gave us something. Let us go back.' So we went to him
and we said: 'O Messenger of Allah! We came to you seeking mounts,
and you took an oath that you would not give us mounts, then you
gave us some mounts.' He said: 'By Allah, I did not give you
animals to ride, rather Allah gave you them to ride. I, by Allah,
if Allah wills, do not swear and then see something better than it,
but I offer expiation for what I swore about, and do that which is
better.' Or he said: 'I do that which is better and offer expiation
for what I swore about.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
