<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52275</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>12</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2282</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Business Transactions - كتاب
التجارات</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20347, 19836, 20254, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، حدثنا عيسى بن يونس، حدثنا الأخضر
بن عجلان، حدثنا أبو بكر الحنفي، عن أنس بن مالك، أن رجلا، من الأنصار
جاء إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يسأله فقال ‏"‏ لك في بيتك شىء ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال بلى حلس نلبس بعضه ونبسط بعضه وقدح نشرب فيه الماء ‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ ائتني بهما ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فأتاه بهما فأخذهما رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بيده ثم قال ‏"‏ من يشتري هذين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فقال رجل أنا آخذهما
بدرهم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ من يزيد على درهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ مرتين أو ثلاثا قال رجل
أنا آخذهما بدرهمين ‏.‏ فأعطاهما إياه وأخذ الدرهمين فأعطاهما
الأنصاري وقال ‏"‏ اشتر بأحدهما طعاما فانبذه إلى أهلك واشتر بالآخر
قدوما فأتني به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ففعل فأخذه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فشد
فيه عودا بيده وقال ‏"‏ اذهب فاحتطب ولا أراك خمسة عشر يوما ‏"‏ ‏.‏
فجعل يحتطب ويبيع فجاء وقد أصاب عشرة دراهم فقال ‏"‏ اشتر ببعضها
طعاما وببعضها ثوبا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ هذا خير لك من أن تجيء
والمسألة نكتة في وجهك يوم القيامة إن المسألة لا تصلح إلا لذي فقر
مدقع أو لذي غرم مفظع أو دم موجع ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Anas bin Malik that : a man from
among the Ansar came to the Prophet (ﷺ) and begged from him. He
said, "Do you have anything in your house?" He said: "Yes, a
blanket, part of which we cover ourselves with and part we spread
beneath us, and a bowl from which we drink water." He said:
"Givethem to me." So he brought them to him, and the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) took them in his hand and said, "Who will by these two
things?" A man said: "I will by them for one Dirham." He said: "Who
will offer more than a Dirham?" two or three times. A man said: "I
will buy them for two Dirham." So he gave them to him and took the
two Dirham, which he gave to the Ansari and said: "Buy food with
one of them and give it to your family, and buy an axe with the
other and bring it to me." So he did that, and the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) took it and fixed a handle to it, and said: "Go and
gather firewood, and I do not want to see you for fifteen days." So
he went and gathered firewood and sold it, then he came back, and
he had earned ten Dirham. (The Prophet (ﷺ)) said: "Buy food with
some of it and clothes with some." Then he said: "This is better
for you than coming with begging (appearing) as a spot on your face
on the Day of Resurrection. Begging is only appropriate for one who
is extremely poor or who is in severe debt, or one who must pay
painful blood money.”[1]</english-text>
</hadith>
