<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52565</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2574</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Pawning - كتاب الرهون</chapter>
<chain-index>30490, 20023, 11013, 10511, 106</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن رمح، أنبأنا الليث بن سعد، عن ابن شهاب،
عن عروة بن الزبير، عن عبد الله بن الزبير، أن رجلا، من الأنصار خاصم
الزبير عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في شراج الحرة التي يسقون
بها النخل فقال الأنصاري سرح الماء يمر ‏.‏ فأبى عليه فاختصما عند
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
اسق يا زبير ثم أرسل الماء إلى جارك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فغضب الأنصاري فقال يا
رسول الله أن كان ابن عمتك فتلون وجه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم
قال ‏"‏ يا زبير اسق ثم احبس الماء حتى يرجع إلى الجدر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال
فقال الزبير والله إني لأحسب هذه الآية أنزلت في ذلك ‏{‏فلا وربك لا
يؤمنون حتى يحكموك فيما شجر بينهم ثم لا يجدوا في أنفسهم حرجا مما
قضيت ويسلموا تسليما‏}‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Abdullah bin Zubair that : a
man from among the Ansar had a dispute with Zubair in the presence
of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) concerning the streams of the Harrah
with which he irrigated his palm trees. The Ansari said: “Let the
water flow,” but he refused. So they referred their dispute to the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said: “Irrigate
(your trees) O Zubair, then let the water flow to your neighbor.”
The Ansari became angry and said: “O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ), is it
because he is your cousin (son of your paternal aunt)?” The
expression of the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) changed, then he said: “O
Zubair, irrigate (your trees) then retain the water until it
reaches the walls.” Zubair said: “I think this Verse was revealed
concerning that: “But no, by your Lord, they make you (O Muhammad)
judge in all disputes between them, and find in themselves no
resistance against your decisions, and accept (them) with full
submission [1].'” (Sahih) [1] An-Nisa 4.65</english-text>
</hadith>
