<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52723</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2732</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Blood Money - كتاب الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30313, 20472, 20719, 10880, 19934, 19911</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق بن منصور المروزي، أنبأنا يزيد بن هارون،
أنبأنا محمد بن راشد، عن سليمان بن موسى، عن عمرو بن شعيب، عن أبيه،
عن جده، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ من قتل خطأ فديته من
الإبل ثلاثون بنت مخاض وثلاثون ابنة لبون وثلاثون حقة وعشرة بني لبون
‏"‏ ‏.‏ وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقومها على أهل القرى
أربعمائة دينار أو عدلها من الورق ويقومها على أزمان الإبل إذا غلت
رفع في ثمنها وإذا هانت نقص من ثمنها على نحو الزمان ما كان فبلغ
قيمتها على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما بين الأربعمائة دينار
إلى ثمانمائة دينار أو عدلها من الورق ثمانية آلاف درهم قضى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن من كان عقله في البقر على أهل البقر مائتى بقرة
ومن كان عقله في الشاء على أهل الشاء ألفى شاة ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Amr bin Shu'aib, from his
father, from his grandfather, that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
“Whoever is killed by mistake, his blood money in camels is thirty
Bint Makhad (a one-year-old she-camel), thirty Bint Labun (a
two-year-old she-camel), thirty Hiqqah (a three-year-old she-camel)
and ten Bani Labun (two-years-old male-camel).” The Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) used to fix the value (of the blood money for accidental
killing) among town-dwellers at four hundred Dinar or the
equivalent value in silver. When he calculated the price in terms
of camels (for Bedouins), it would vary from one time to another.
When prices roses, the value (in dinars) would rise: and when
prices fell, the value (in Dinar) would fall. At the time of the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) the value was between four hundred and eight
hundred dinar, or the equivalent value in silver, eight thousand
Dirham. And the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) ruled that if a person's
blood money was paid in cattle, among those who kept cattle, the
amount was two hundred cows; and if person's blood money was paid
in sheep, among those who kept sheep, the value was two thousand
sheep. (Hasan).</english-text>
</hadith>
