<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52731</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2740</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Blood Money - كتاب الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 20121, 20115, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أنبأنا معمر، عن
الزهري، عن عروة، عن عائشة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث أبا
جهم بن حذيفة مصدقا فلاجه رجل في صدقته فضربه أبو جهم فشجه فأتوا
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا القود يا رسول الله ‏.‏ فقال النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لكم كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلم يرضوا فقال ‏"‏ لكم
كذا وكذا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فرضوا فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني خاطب
على الناس ومخبرهم برضاكم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ فخطب النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ إن هؤلاء الليثيين أتوني يريدون القود فعرضت عليهم
كذا وكذا أرضيتم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا لا ‏.‏ فهم بهم المهاجرون فأمر النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يكفوا فكفوا ثم دعاهم فزادهم فقال ‏"‏ أرضيتم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ إني خاطب على الناس ومخبرهم برضاكم ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ فخطب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم قال ‏"‏ أرضيتم
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال ابن ماجه سمعت محمد بن يحيى يقول تفرد بهذا
معمر لا أعلم رواه غيره ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from 'Aishah that : the Messenger of
Allah (ﷺ) sent Abu Jahm bin Hudhaifah to collect Sadaqah. A man
disputed with him concerning his Sadaqah, and Abu Jahm struck him
and wounded his head. They came to Prophet (ﷺ) and said:
“Compensatory money, O Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)!” The Prophet (ﷺ)
said: “You will have such and such,” but they did not accept that.
He said: “You will have such and such,” and they agreed. Then the
Prophet (ﷺ) said: “I am going to address the people and tell them
that you agreed.” They said: “Yes.” So the Prophet (ﷺ) addressed
(the people) and said: “These people of Laith came to me seeking
compensatory money, and I have offered them such and such. Do you
agree?” They said: “No.” The Emigrants wanted to attack them, but
the Prophet (ﷺ) told them not to, so they refrained. Then he called
them and offered them more and said: “Do you agree?” They said:
“Yes.” He said: “I am going to address the people and tell them
that you agreed.” They said: “Yes.” So the Prophet (ﷺ) addressed
(the people) then said: “Do you Agree?” They said:
“Yes.”</english-text>
</hadith>
