<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52828</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2837</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Shares of Inheritance - كتاب الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20318, 11278, 19934, 19911</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا حسين
المعلم، عن عمرو بن شعيب، عن أبيه، عن جده، قال تزوج رئاب بن حذيفة بن
سعيد بن سهم أم وائل بنت معمر الجمحية فولدت له ثلاثة فتوفيت أمهم
فورثها بنوها رباعا وولاء مواليها فخرج بهم عمرو بن العاص معه إلى
الشام فماتوا في طاعون عمواس فورثهم عمرو وكان عصبتهم فلما رجع عمرو
بن العاص جاء بنو معمر يخاصمونه في ولاء أختهم إلى عمر فقال عمر أقضي
بينكم بما سمعت من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سمعته يقول ‏"‏ ما
أحرز الولد أو الوالد فهو لعصبته من كان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فقضى لنا به وكتب
لنا به كتابا فيه شهادة عبد الرحمن بن عوف وزيد بن ثابت وآخر حتى إذا
استخلف عبد الملك بن مروان توفي مولى لها وترك ألفى دينار فبلغني أن
ذلك القضاء قد غير فخاصموه إلى هشام بن إسماعيل فرفعنا إلى عبد الملك
فأتيناه بكتاب عمر فقال إن كنت لأرى أن هذا من القضاء الذي لا يشك فيه
وما كنت أرى أن أمر أهل المدينة بلغ هذا أن يشكوا في هذا القضاء ‏.‏
فقضى لنا به فلم نزل فيه بعد ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from ‘Amr bin Shu’aib, from his
father, that hisgrandfather said: “Rabab bin Hudhaifah (bin Sa’eed)
bin SahmmarriedUmm Wa’il bint Ma’mar Al-Jumahiyyah, and she bore
himthree sons.Their mother died and her sons inherited her houses
andthe Wala’ ofher freed slaves. ‘Amr bin ‘As took them out toSham,
and they died ofthe plague of ‘Amwas. ‘Amr inherited fromthem, and
he was their‘Asabah.* When ‘Amr came back, Banu Ma’marcame to him
and theyreferred their dispute with him concerning theWala’ of
their sisterto ‘Umar. ‘Umar said: ‘I will judgebetween you
according to what Iheard from the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ). I heard
him say: “What theson or father acquires goes tohis. ‘Asabah, no
matter who they are.’”So he ruled in ourfavour and wrote a document
to that effect, inwhich was thetestimony of ‘Abdur-Rahman bin ‘Awf,
Zaid bin Thabit andsomeoneelse. Then when ‘Abdul-Malik bin Marwan
was appointed caliph,afreed slave of hers (Umm Wa’il’s) died,
leaving behind twothousandDinar. I heard that that ruling had been
changed, so theyreferred thedispute to Hisham bin Isma’il. We
referred the matterto ‘Abdul-Malik,and brought him the document of
‘Umar. He said:‘I thought that thiswas a ruling concerning which
there was nodoubt. I never thought thatthe people of Al-Madinah
would reach sucha state that they woulddoubt this ruling. So he
ruled in our favour,and it remained likethat
afterwards.”</english-text>
</hadith>
