<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52842</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2851</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Shares of Inheritance - كتاب الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 30512, 20719, 10880, 19934, 19911</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى، حدثنا محمد بن بكار بن بلال
الدمشقي، أنبأنا محمد بن راشد، عن سليمان بن موسى، عن عمرو بن شعيب،
عن أبيه، عن جده، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ كل مستلحق
استلحق بعد أبيه الذي يدعى له ادعاه ورثته من بعده فقضى أن من كان من
أمة يملكها يوم أصابها فقد لحق بمن استلحقه وليس له فيما قسم قبله من
الميراث شىء وما أدرك من ميراث لم يقسم فله نصيبه ولا يلحق إذا كان
أبوه الذي يدعى له أنكره وإن كان من أمة لا يملكها أو من حرة عاهر بها
فإنه لا يلحق ولا يورث وإن كان الذي يدعى له هو ادعاه فهو ولد زنا
لأهل أمه من كانوا حرة أو أمة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال محمد بن راشد يعني بذلك ما
قسم في الجاهلية قبل الإسلام ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from ‘Amr bin Shu’aib, from his
father, from hisgrandfather, that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) said:
“Every childwhois attributed to his father after his father to whom
he isattributedhas died, and his heirs attributed him to him after
hedied, he ruledthat* whoever was born to a slave woman whom he
ownedat the time whenhe had intercourse with her, he should be
namedafter the one to whomhe was attributed, but he has no share of
anyinheritance that wasdistributed previously. Whatever inheritance
hefinds has not yet beendistributed, he will have a share of it.
Buthe cannot be named afterhis father if the man whom he claimed as
hisfather did notacknowledge him. If he as born to a slave woman
whomhis father didnot own, or to a free woman with whom he
committedadultery, then hecannot be named after him and he does not
inheritfrom him, even ifthe one whom he claims as his father
acknowledgeshim. So he is anillegitimate child who belongs to his
mother’speople, whoever theyare, whether she is a free woman or a
slave.”</english-text>
</hadith>
