<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52958</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2967</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Jihad - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>11222, 20034, 20012, 11374, 11432, 3131</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يحيى، حدثنا محمد بن يوسف الفريابي، حدثنا
سفيان، عن علقمة بن مرثد، عن ابن بريدة، عن أبيه، قال كان رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا أمر رجلا على سرية أوصاه في خاصة نفسه بتقوى
الله ومن معه من المسلمين خيرا فقال ‏"‏ اغزوا باسم الله وفي سبيل
الله قاتلوا من كفر بالله اغزوا ولا تغدروا ولا تغلوا ولا تمثلوا ولا
تقتلوا وليدا وإذا أنت لقيت عدوك من المشركين فادعهم إلى إحدى ثلاث
خلال أو خصال فأيتهن أجابوك إليها فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم ادعهم إلى
الإسلام فإن أجابوك فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم ثم ادعهم إلى التحول من دارهم
إلى دار المهاجرين وأخبرهم إن هم فعلوا ذلك أن لهم ما للمهاجرين وأن
عليهم ما على المهاجرين وإن أبوا فأخبرهم أنهم يكونون كأعراب المسلمين
يجري عليهم حكم الله الذي يجري على المؤمنين ولا يكون لهم في الفىء
والغنيمة شىء إلا أن يجاهدوا مع المسلمين فإن هم أبوا أن يدخلوا في
الإسلام فسلهم إعطاء الجزية فإن فعلوا فاقبل منهم وكف عنهم فإن هم
أبوا فاستعن بالله عليهم وقاتلهم وإن حاصرت حصنا فأرادوك أن تجعل لهم
ذمة الله وذمة نبيك فلا تجعل لهم ذمة الله ولا ذمة نبيك ولكن اجعل لهم
ذمتك وذمة أبيك وذمة أصحابك فإنكم إن تخفروا ذمتكم وذمة آبائكم أهون
عليكم من أن تخفروا ذمة الله وذمة رسوله وإن حاصرت حصنا فأرادوك أن
ينزلوا على حكم الله فلا تنزلهم على حكم الله ولكن أنزلهم على حكمك
فإنك لا تدري أتصيب فيهم حكم الله أم لا ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Ibn Buraidah that his father
said: “Whenever heappointed a man to lead a military detachment,
the Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) would advise him especially to fear Allah
and treat the Muslimswith him well. He (ﷺ) said: ‘Fight in the Name
of Allah and inthecause of Allah. Fight those how disbelieve in
Allah. Fight but donotbe treacherous, do not steal from the spoils
of war, do notmutilateand do not kill children. When you meet your
enemy fromamong thepolytheists, call them to one of three things.
Whichever ofthem theyrespond to, accept it from them and refrain
from fightingthem. Invitethem to accept Islam, and if they respond
then accept itfrom them andrefrain from fighting them. Then invite
them to leavetheir land andmove to the land of the polytheists.
Tell them that ifthey do that,then they will have the same rights
and duties as thepolytheists. Ifthey refuse, then tell them that
they will be likethe Muslim Bedouins(who live in the desert),
subject to the samerulings of Allah as thebelievers. But they will
have no share ofFay’* or war spoils, unlessthey fight alongside the
Muslims. Ifthey refuse to enter Islam, thenask them to pay the
Poll-tax. Ifthey do that, then accept it fromthem and refrain from
fightingthem. But if they refuse, then seek thehelp of Allah
against themand fight them. If you lay siege to themand they want
you to givethem the protection of Allah and yourProphet, do not
give them theprotection of Allah and your Prophet,rather give them
yourprotection and the protection of your father andyour
Companions, forif you violate your protection and the protectionof
your fathers,that is easier than violating the protection of
Allahand theprotection of His Messenger. If you lay siege to them
and theywantyou to let them come out with a promise of the
judgement of AllahandHis Messenger (ﷺ), do not offer them a promise
of the judgementofAllah and His Messenger (ﷺ), rather offer them
your judgement,because you do not know if you will actually pass
(the same as)Allah’s judgement regarding them or
not.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
