<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>52964</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2973</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Chapters on Jihad - كتاب الجهاد</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20472, 11220, 11897, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا يزيد بن هارون، حدثنا
محمد بن عمرو، عن عمر بن الحكم بن ثوبان، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث علقمة بن مجزز على بعث وأنا فيهم فلما
انتهى إلى رأس غزاته أو كان ببعض الطريق استأذنته طائفة من الجيش فأذن
لهم وأمر عليهم عبد الله بن حذافة بن قيس السهمي فكنت فيمن غزا معه
فلما كان ببعض الطريق أوقد القوم نارا ليصطلوا أو ليصنعوا عليها صنيعا
فقال عبد الله - وكانت فيه دعابة - أليس لي عليكم السمع والطاعة قالوا
بلى ‏.‏ قال فما أنا بآمركم بشىء إلا صنعتموه قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال فإني
أعزم عليكم إلا تواثبتم في هذه النار ‏.‏ فقام ناس فتحجزوا فلما ظن
أنهم واثبون قال أمسكوا على أنفسكم فإنما كنت أمزح معكم ‏.‏ فلما
قدمنا ذكروا ذلك للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أمركم منهم بمعصية الله فلا تطيعوه ‏"‏
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Abu Sa’eed Al-Khudri that the
Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) sent ‘Alqamah bin Mujazziz at the head of a
detachment, and Iwas among them. When he reached the battle site,
or when he waspartway there, a group of the army asked permission
to take adifferent route, and he gave them permission, and
appointed ‘Abdullahbin Hudhafah bin Qais As-Sahmi as their leader,
and I was one ofthosewho fought alongside with him. When we were
partway there, thepeoplelit a fire to warm themselves and cook some
food. ‘Abdullah,who was aman who liked to joke, said: “Do I not
have the rightthat you shouldlisten to me and obey?” They said:
“Yes.” Hesaid: “And if I commandyou to do something, will you not
do it?”They said: “Of course.” Hesaid: “Then I command you to
jumpinto this fire.” Some people got upand got ready to jump, and
whenhe saw that they were about to jump,he said: “Restrain
yourselves,for I was joking with you.” When wecame to Al-Madinah,
theymentioned that to the Prophet (ﷺ), and theMessenger of Allah
(ﷺ)said: “Whoever among you commands you to dosomething that
involvesdisobedience to Allah, do not obey him.”</english-text>
</hadith>
