<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53061</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3070</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Hajj Rituals - كتاب المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20736, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، حدثنا إسماعيل بن عياش، حدثنا حميد
بن أبي سوية، قال سمعت ابن هشام، يسأل عطاء بن أبي رباح عن الركن
اليماني، وهو يطوف بالبيت فقال عطاء حدثني أبو هريرة أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ وكل به سبعون ملكا فمن قال اللهم إني أسألك
العفو والعافية في الدنيا والآخرة ربنا آتنا في الدنيا حسنة وفي
الآخرة حسنة وقنا عذاب النار - قالوا آمين ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فلما بلغ الركن
الأسود قال يا أبا محمد ما بلغك في هذا الركن الأسود فقال عطاء حدثني
أبو هريرة أنه سمع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ من فاوضه
فإنما يفاوض يد الرحمن ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال له ابن هشام يا أبا محمد فالطواف
قال عطاء حدثني أبو هريرة أنه سمع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏
من طاف بالبيت سبعا ولا يتكلم إلا بسبحان الله والحمد لله ولا إله إلا
الله والله أكبر ولا حول ولاقوة إلا بالله محيت عنه عشر سيئات وكتبت
له عشر حسنات ورفع له بها عشر درجات ومن طاف فتكلم وهو في تلك الحال
خاض في الرحمة برجليه كخائض الماء برجليه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Humaidbin Abu Sawiyyah said: I heard Ibn Hisham
asking ‘Ata’ bin AbuRabah about the Yemenite Corner, when he was
performing Tawaf aroundthe House. ‘Ata’ said: Abu Hurairah told me
that the Prophet(ﷺ) said: “Seventy angels have been appointed over
it. Whoeversays: Allahumma inni as’alukal-‘afwa wal-‘afiyah
fid-dunyawal-akhirah; Rabbana atina fid-dunya hasanah, wa
fil-akhiratihasanah, wa qina ‘adhaban-Nar (O Allah, I ask You for
pardon andwell-being in this world and in the Hereafter. Our Lord,
give us goodin this world and good in the Hereafter and protect us
from thetorment of the Fire), they say: Amin.” When he reached the
BlackCorner (where the Black Stone is), he said: O Abu Muhammad!
What haveyou heard about this Black Corner? ‘Ata’ said: Abu
Hurairah toldme that he heard the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) say:
“Whoever facesit is facing the Hand of the Most Merciful.’”Ibn
Hisham said to him: O Abu Muhammad, what about Tawaf? ‘Ata’ said:
Abu Hurairah told me that he heard the Prophet (ﷺ) say: “Whoever
performs Tawaf around the House seven times and does not say
anything except: Subhan Allah wal-hamdu lillah, wa la ilaha
illallah wa Allahu Akbar, wa la hawla wa la quwwata illa billah
(Glory is to Allah, praise is to Allah, none has the right to be
worshipping but Allah, and there is no power nor strength except
with Allah), ten bad deeds will be erased from him, ten merits will
be recorded for him, and he will be raised ten degrees in status.
Whoever performs Tawaf and talks when he is in that situation, is
wading in mercy like one who wades in water.”</english-text>
</hadith>
