<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53105</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3114</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Hajj Rituals - كتاب المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20337, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبدة بن سليمان، عن
هشام بن عروة، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في حجة الوداع نوافي هلال ذي الحجة فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أراد منكم أن يهل بعمرة فليهلل فلولا أني أهديت
لأهللت بعمرة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فكان من القوم من أهل بعمرة ومنهم من أهل
بحج فكنت أنا ممن أهل بعمرة ‏.‏ قالت فخرجنا حتى قدمنا مكة فأدركني
يوم عرفة وأنا حائض لم أحل من عمرتي فشكوت ذلك إلى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ دعي عمرتك وانقضي رأسك وامتشطي وأهلي بالحج ‏"‏
‏.‏ قالت ففعلت فلما كانت ليلة الحصبة وقد قضى الله حجنا أرسل معي عبد
الرحمن بن أبي بكر فأردفني وخرج إلى التنعيم فأهللت بعمرة فقضى الله
حجنا وعمرتنا ولم يكن في ذلك هدى ولا صدقة ولا صوم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “We went out with
the Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ) on the Farewell Pilgrimage, close to the
time of thecrescent of Dhul-Hijjah. The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
said: ‘Whoeveramong you wants to begin the Talbiyah for ‘Umrah, let
him do so. Ifitwere not for the fact that I have brought a
sacrificial animalwithme, I would have began the Talbiyah for
‘Umrah.’” Shesaid: “Some ofthe people began the Talbiyah for
‘Umrah, and somebegan the Talbiyahfor Hajj. I was one of those who
began theTalbiyah for ‘Umrah.” Shesaid: “We set out until we
reachedMakkah, then the Day of ‘Arafahcame while I was in menses,
but Idid not exit Ihram for ‘Umrah Icomplained about that to
theProphet (ﷺ) and he said: ‘Leave your‘Umrah, undo your hair
andcomb it, and begin the Talbiyah for Hajj.’”She said: “So I
didthat, then on the night of Hasbah (i.e., thetwelfth night
ofDhul-Hijjah), when Allah had enables us to completeour Hajj, he
sent‘Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr with me. He seated mebehind him
andwent out to Tan’im, then I began the Talbiyah for‘Umrah andAllah
enabled us to complete our Hajj and ‘Umrah, and therewas
nosacrificial animal, charity nor fasting.”</english-text>
</hadith>
