<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53118</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3127</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Hajj Rituals - كتاب المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>34035, 24271</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أيوب بن محمد الهاشمي، حدثنا عبد القاهر بن السري
السلمي، حدثنا عبد الله بن كنانة بن عباس بن مرداس السلمي، أن أباه،
أخبره عن أبيه، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم دعا لأمته عشية عرفة
بالمغفرة فأجيب إني قد غفرت لهم ما خلا الظالم فإني آخذ للمظلوم منه
‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أى رب إن شئت أعطيت المظلوم من الجنة وغفرت للظالم ‏"‏
‏.‏ فلم يجب عشيته فلما أصبح بالمزدلفة أعاد الدعاء فأجيب إلى ما سأل
‏.‏ قال فضحك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ أو قال تبسم ‏.‏ فقال
له أبو بكر وعمر بأبي أنت وأمي إن هذه لساعة ما كنت تضحك فيها فما
الذي أضحكك أضحك الله سنك قال ‏"‏ إن عدو الله إبليس لما علم أن الله
عز وجل قد استجاب دعائي وغفر لأمتي أخذ التراب فجعل يحثوه على رأسه
ويدعو بالويل والثبور فأضحكني ما رأيت من جزعه ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>‘Abdullah bin Kinanah bin ‘Abbas bin Mirdas As-Sulami
narratedthathis father told him, from his father, that the
Messenger ofAllah(ﷺ) prayed for forgiveness for his nation one
evening at‘Arafat,and the response came: “I have forgiven them,
except forthewrongdoer, with whom I will settle the score in favor
of the onewhomhe wronged.” He said: “O Lord, if You will, then
grantParadise to theone who is wronged, and forgive the wrongdoer.”
Noresponse came (thatevening).The next day at Muzdalifah he
repeatedthe supplication, andreceived a response to what he asked
for. He(the narrator) said: “TheMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) laughed,”
orhe said, “He smiled. Abu Bakrand ‘Umar said to him: ‘May myfather
and mother be ransomed for you,this is not a time when youusually
laugh. What made you laugh, mayAllah make your years filledwith
laughter?’ He said: ‘The enemy ofAllah, Iblis, when he cameto know
that Allah answered my prayer andforgiven my nation, tooksome dust
and started to sprinkle it on hishead, uttering cries ofwoe and
doom, and what I saw of his anguishmade me laugh.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
