<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53162</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3171</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Hajj Rituals - كتاب المناسك</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 30480, 20327, 11430, 19868</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، وهناد بن السري، قالا حدثنا
أبو الأحوص، عن شبيب بن غرقدة، عن سليمان بن عمرو بن الأحوص، عن أبيه،
قال سمعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول في حجة الوداع ‏"‏ يا أيها
الناس ألا أى يوم أحرم ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث مرات قالوا يوم الحج الأكبر ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم وأعراضكم بينكم حرام كحرمة يومكم هذا في
شهركم هذا في بلدكم هذا ألا لا يجني جان إلا على نفسه ولا يجني والد
على ولده ولا مولود على والده ‏.‏ ألا إن الشيطان قد أيس أن يعبد في
بلدكم هذا أبدا ولكن سيكون له طاعة في بعض ما تحتقرون من أعمالكم
فيرضى بها ألا وكل دم من دماء الجاهلية موضوع وأول ما أضع منها دم
الحارث بن عبد المطلب - كان مسترضعا في بني ليث فقتلته هذيل - ألا وإن
كل ربا من ربا الجاهلية موضوع لكم رءوس أموالكم لا تظلمون ولا تظلمون
ألا يا أمتاه هل بلغت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث مرات قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اللهم
اشهد ‏"‏ ‏.‏ ثلاث مرات ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Sulaiman bin ‘Amr bin Ahwas that
his fathersaid: “Iheard the Prophet (ﷺ) say, during the Farewell
Pilgrimage:‘Opeople! Which day is the most sacred?’ three times.
They said: ‘Theday of the greatest Hajj.’ He said: ‘Your blood and
your wealthandyour honor are sacred to one another, as sacred as
this day ofyours,in this land of your. No sinner commits a sin but
it isagainsthimself. No father is to be punished for the sins of
hischild, and nochild is to be punished for the sins of his
father.Satan hasdespaired of ever being worshipping in this land of
yours,but he willbe obeyed in some matters which you regard
asinsignificant, and hewill be content with that. All the blood
feudsof the Ignorance daysare abolished, and the first of them that
Iabolish is the blood feudof Harith bin ‘Abdul-Muttalib, who
wasnursed among Banu Laith andkilled by Hudhail. All the usuries of
theIgnorance days areabolished, but you will have your capital. Do
notwrong others and youwill not be wronged. O my nation, have
Iconveyed (the message)?’ (Heasked this) three times. They
said:‘Yes.’ He said: ‘O Allah, bearwitness!’ three
times.”</english-text>
</hadith>
