<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53665</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>31</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3674</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20331, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، عن
هشام، عن أبيه، عن عائشة، قالت سحر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يهودي من
يهود بني زريق يقال له لبيد بن الأعصم حتى كان النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم يخيل إليه أنه يفعل الشىء ولا يفعله ‏.‏ قالت حتى إذا كان ذات
يوم أو كان ذات ليلة دعا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم دعا ثم دعا
ثم قال ‏"‏ يا عائشة أشعرت أن الله قد أفتاني فيما استفتيته فيه جاءني
رجلان فجلس أحدهما عند رأسي والآخر عند رجلي فقال الذي عند رأسي للذي
عند رجلي أو الذي عند رجلي للذي عند رأسي ما وجع الرجل قال مطبوب ‏.‏
قال من طبه قال لبيد بن الأعصم ‏.‏ قال في أى شىء قال في مشط ومشاطة
وجف طلعة ذكر ‏.‏ قال وأين هو قال في بئر ذي أروان ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالت فأتاه
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في أناس من أصحابه ثم جاء فقال ‏"‏ والله يا
عائشة لكأن ماءها نقاعة الحناء ولكأن نخلها رءوس الشياطين ‏"‏ ‏.‏
قالت قلت يا رسول الله أفلا أحرقته قال ‏"‏ لا أما أنا فقد عافاني
الله وكرهت أن أثير على الناس منه شرا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأمر بها فدفنت
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that ‘Aishah said: “A Jew from among
the Jews of BaniZuraiq, whose name was Labid bin A’sam, cast a
spell on the Prophet(ﷺ), and the Prophet (ﷺ) began to imagine that
he had donesomething when he had not. One day, or one night, the
Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ) supplicated, and then supplicated again. Then
he said: ‘O‘Aishah, do you know that Allah has instructed me
concerning thematter I asked Him about? Two men came to me, and one
of them sat atmy head and the other at my feet. The one at my head
said to the one at my feet, or the one at my feet said to the one
at my head "what is ailing this man ?" Hesaid: “He has been
affected by a spell.” He said: “Who cast thespell on him?” He said:
“Labid bin A’sam.” He said: “Withwhat?” He said: “With a comb and
the hairs stuck to it, and thespathe of a male date palm.” He said:
“Where is that?” He said:“In the well of Dhu Arwan.”She said: “So
the Prophet (ﷺ) went to it, with a group of his Companions, then he
came and said: ‘By Allah. O ‘Aishah. It was as if its water was
infused with henna and its date palms were like the heads of
devils.’”She said: “I said: ‘O Messenger of Allah, why don’t you
burn them?’ He said: ‘As for me, Allah has healed me, and I do not
like to let evil spread among the people.’ Then he issued orders
that the well be filled up with earth.”</english-text>
</hadith>
