<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53669</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>31</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3678</hadith-number>
<chapter>Chapters on Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20337, 11196</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هارون بن حيان، حدثنا إبراهيم بن موسى، أنبأنا
عبدة بن سليمان، حدثنا أبو جناب، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي ليلى، عن أبيه
أبي ليلى، قال كنت جالسا عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ جاءه أعرابي
فقال إن لي أخا وجعا ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما وجع أخيك ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال به لمم ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ اذهب فأتني به ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال فذهب فجاء به فأجلسه بين يديه
فسمعته عوذه بفاتحة الكتاب وأربع آيات من أول البقرة وآيتين من وسطها
وإلهكم إله واحد وآية الكرسي وثلاث آيات من خاتمتها وآية من آل عمران
- أحسبه قال ‏{شهد الله أنه لا إله إلا هو}‏ - وآية من الأعراف ‏{إن
ربكم الله الذي خلق}‏ الآية وآية من المؤمنين ‏{ومن يدع مع الله إلها
آخر لا برهان له به }‏ وآية من الجن ‏{وأنه تعالى جد ربنا ما اتخذ
صاحبة ولا ولدا}‏ وعشر آيات من أول الصافات وثلاث آيات من آخر الحشر و
‏{قل هو الله أحد }‏ والمعوذتين ‏.‏ فقام الأعرابي قد برأ ليس به بأس
‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from ‘Abdur-Rahman bin Abi Laila that
his father AbuLailasaid: “I was sitting with the Prophet (ﷺ) when a
Bedouin cametohim and said: ‘I have a brother who is sick.’ He
said: ‘What isthematter with your brother?’ He said: ‘He suffers
from a slightmentalderangement.’ He said: ‘Go and bring him.’” He
said:“(So he went) andhe brought him. He made him sit down in front
ofhim and I heard himseeking refuge for him with Fatihatil-Kitab;
fourVerses from thebeginning of Al-Baqarah, two Verses from its
middle:‘And your Ilah(God) is One Ilah (God – Allah),’ [2:163]
andAyat Al-Kursi; and threeVerses from its end; a Verse from Al
‘Imran,I think it was: ‘Allahbears witness that La ilaha illa Huwa
(nonehas the right to beworshipped but He),’ [3:18] a Verse
fromAl-A’raf: ‘Indeed, your Lordis Allah,’ [7:54] a Verse
fromAl-Mu’minn: ‘And whoever invokes (orworships), besides
Allah,any other ilah (god), of whom he has noproof,’[23:117] a
Versefrom Al-Jinn: ‘And He, exalted is the Majestyof our
Lord,’[72:3] ten Verses from the beginning of As-Saffat;
threeVerses fromthe end of Al-Hashr; (then) ‘Say: He is Allah,
(the) One,’[112:1] and Al-Mu’awwidhatain. Then the Bedouin stood
up, healed,andthere was nothing wrong with him.”</english-text>
</hadith>
