<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53842</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>33</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3719</hadith-number>
<chapter>Etiquette - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>20436, 20032, 10636, 11013, 56, 38409, 20032, 10636,
11013, 2308, 56</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر، حدثنا وكيع، عن زمعة بن صالح، عن الزهري،
عن وهب بن عبد بن زمعة، عن أم سلمة، ح وحدثنا علي بن محمد، حدثنا
وكيع، حدثنا زمعة بن صالح، عن الزهري، عن عبد الله بن وهب بن زمعة، عن
أم سلمة، قالت خرج أبو بكر في تجارة إلى بصرى قبل موت النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم بعام ومعه نعيمان وسويبط بن حرملة وكانا شهدا بدرا وكان
نعيمان على الزاد وكان سويبط رجلا مزاحا فقال لنعيمان أطعمني ‏.‏ قال
حتى يجيء أبو بكر ‏.‏ قال فلأغيظنك ‏.‏ قال فمروا بقوم فقال لهم سويبط
تشترون مني عبدا لي قالوا نعم ‏.‏ قال إنه عبد له كلام وهو قائل لكم
إني حر ‏.‏ فإن كنتم إذا قال لكم هذه المقالة تركتموه فلا تفسدوا على
عبدي ‏.‏ قالوا لا بل نشتريه منك ‏.‏ فاشتروه منه بعشر قلائص ثم أتوه
فوضعوا في عنقه عمامة أو حبلا ‏.‏ فقال نعيمان إن هذا يستهزئ بكم وإني
حر لست بعبد ‏.‏ فقالوا قد أخبرنا خبرك ‏.‏ فانطلقوا به فجاء أبو بكر
فأخبروه بذلك ‏.‏ قال فاتبع القوم ورد عليهم القلائص وأخذ نعيمان ‏.‏
قال فلما قدموا على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأخبروه ‏.‏ قال فضحك
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأصحابه منه حولا ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Umm Salamah said: "Abu Bakr went
our to trade in Busra, one year before the Prophet(ﷺ) died, and
with him were Nu'aiman and Suwaibit the sons of Harmalah, who had
been present at Badr. Nu'iaman was in charge of the provisions, and
Suwaibit was a man who joked a lot. He said to Nu'iman: 'Feed me'.
He said: 'Not until Abu Bakr comes'. He said: 'Then I will have to
annoy you'. Then they passed by some people, and Suwaibit said to
them: 'Will you buy a slave from me?' They said: 'Yes'. He said '
He is a slave who talks a lot and he will tell you, "I am a free
man". If you are going to let him go when says that to you, do not
bother buying him.' They said: 'We will buy him from you.' So they
bought him from him in return for ten young she-camels, then they
brought him and tied a turban or a rope around his neck. Nu'aiman
said: 'This man is making fun of you. I am a free man, not a
slave.' They said: 'He has already told us about you; and they took
him off.' THen Abu Bakr came and he (Suwaibit) told him about that.
So he followed those people and returned their camels to them, and
took Nu'iaman back. Whent hey came to the Prophet(ﷺ) they told him
what had happened, and the Prophet(ﷺ) and his companions laughed
about it for a year."</english-text>
</hadith>
