<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>53953</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3830</hadith-number>
<chapter>Supplication - كتاب الدعاء</chapter>
<chain-index>38409, 11381, 10780, 19870, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن محمد، سنة إحدى وثلاثين ومائتين حدثنا
وكيع، في سنة خمس وتسعين ومائة قال حدثنا سفيان في مجلس الأعمش منذ
خمسين سنة حدثنا عمرو بن مرة الجملي في زمن خالد عن عبد الله بن
الحارث المكتب عن طليق بن قيس الحنفي عن ابن عباس أن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم كان يقول في دعائه ‏"‏ رب أعني ولا تعن على وانصرني ولا
تنصر على وامكر لي ولا تمكر على واهدني ويسر الهدى لي وانصرني على من
بغى على رب اجعلني لك شكارا لك ذكارا لك رهابا لك مطيعا إليك مخبتا
إليك أواها منيبا رب تقبل توبتي واغسل حوبتي وأجب دعوتي واهد قلبي
وسدد لساني وثبت حجتي واسلل سخيمة قلبي ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو الحسن
الطنافسي قلت لوكيع أقوله في قنوت الوتر قال نعم ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Ibn 'Abbas that : the Prophet
(saas) used to say in his supplication: "Rabbi! A'inni wa la tu'in
'alayya, wansurni wa la tansur 'alayya, wamkurli wa la tamkur
'alayya, wahdini wa yassiril-huda li, wansurni 'ala man bagha
'alayya. Rabbij'alni laka shakkaran laka dhakkaran, laka rahhaban,
laka muti'an, 'ilayka mukhbitan, 'ilayka awwahan muniba. Rabbi!
Taqabbal tawbati, waghsil hawbati wa ajib da'wati, wahdi qalbi, wa
saddid lisani, wa thabbit hujjati, waslul sakhimata qalbi (O Lord!
Help me and do not help others against me, support me and do not
support others against me, plan for me and do not plan against me,
guide me and make guidance easy for me, and help me against those
who wrong me. O Lord! Make me grateful to You, make me remember You
much, make me fearful of You, obedient to You, humble before You
and turning to You. O Lord! Accept my repentance and wash away my
sins, answer my supplication, guide my heart, make my tongue speak
the truth, make my proof firm and remove resentment from my
heard)." (Sahih)(One of the narrators) Abul-Hasan At-Tanafisi said:
"I said to Waki': 'Shall I say it in the Qunut of Witr?' He said:
'Yes.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
