<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54043</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>35</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3920</hadith-number>
<chapter>Interpretation of Dreams - كتاب تعبير الرؤيا</chapter>
<chain-index>30201, 20383, 20021, 11358, 11394, 4026</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو بكر بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا الحسن بن موسى الأشيب،
حدثنا حماد بن سلمة، عن عاصم بن بهدلة، عن المسيب بن رافع، عن خرشة بن
الحر، قال قدمت المدينة فجلست إلى أشيخة في مسجد النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فجاء شيخ يتوكأ على عصا له فقال القوم من سره أن ينظر إلى رجل من
أهل الجنة فلينظر إلى هذا ‏.‏ فقام خلف سارية فصلى ركعتين فقمت إليه
فقلت له قال بعض القوم كذا وكذا ‏.‏ قال الحمد لله الجنة لله يدخلها
من يشاء وإني رأيت على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رؤيا رأيت
كأن رجلا أتاني فقال لي انطلق ‏.‏ فذهبت معه فسلك بي في منهج عظيم
فعرضت على طريق على يساري فأردت أن أسلكها فقال إنك لست من أهلها ‏.‏
ثم عرضت على طريق عن يميني فسلكتها حتى إذا انتهيت إلى جبل زلق فأخذ
بيدي فزجل بي فإذا أنا على ذروته فلم أتقار ولم أتماسك وإذا عمود من
حديد في ذروته حلقة من ذهب فأخذ بيدي فزجل بي حتى أخذت بالعروة فقال
استمسكت قلت نعم فضرب العمود برجله ‏.‏ فاستمسكت بالعروة ‏.‏ فقال
قصصتها على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ رأيت خيرا أما
المنهج العظيم فالمحشر وأما الطريق التي عرضت عن يسارك فطريق أهل
النار ولست من أهلها وأما الطريق التي عرضت عن يمينك فطريق أهل الجنة
وأما الجبل الزلق فمنزل الشهداء وأما العروة التي استمسكت بها فعروة
الإسلام فاستمسك بها حتى تموت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ فأنا أرجو أن أكون من أهل الجنة
فإذا هو عبد الله بن سلام ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Kharashah bin Hurr said: “I came
to Al-Madinah andsat with some old men in the mosque of the Prophet
(ﷺ). Then an oldman came, leaning on his stick, and the people
said: ‘Whoever wouldlike to look at a man from among the people of
Paradise, let him lookat this man.’ He stood behind a pillar and
prayed two Rak’ah. Igot up and went to him, and said to him: ‘Some
of the people saidsuch and such.’ He said: ‘Praise is to Allah.
Paradise belongs toAllah and He admits whomsoever He wills to it.
At the time of theMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) I saw a dream in which a
man came to me andsaid: “Let’s go.” So I went with him and he took
me along agreat road. A road was shown to me on the left and I
wanted to followit, but he said: “You are not one of its people.”
Then a road wasshown to me on the right, and I followed him until I
reached aslippery mountain. He took me by the hand and helped me
up. When Ireached the top I could not stand firm. There was an iron
pillarthere with a golden ring at the top. He took my hand and
helped me upuntil I reached the handhold, then he said: “Have you
gotten a firmhold?” I said: “Yes.” Then he struck the pillar with
his footand I held tight to the pillar. I told this to the Prophet
(ﷺ) and he said: "You have seen something good. The great road is
the plain of gathering (on the Day of Resurrection). The road that
you were shown on your left is the way of the people of Hell, and
you are not one of its people. The road which you were shown on
your right is the way of the people of Paradise. The slippery
mountain is the place of the martyrs, and the handhold that you
held on tight to is the handhold of Islam. Hold on tight to it
until you die." I hope to be one of the people of Paradise,' and he
was 'Abdullah bin Salam."</english-text>
</hadith>
