<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54041</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>35</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3918</hadith-number>
<chapter>Interpretation of Dreams - كتاب تعبير الرؤيا</chapter>
<chain-index>32048, 20005, 11013, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يعقوب بن حميد بن كاسب المدني، حدثنا سفيان بن
عيينة، عن الزهري، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، عن ابن عباس، قال أتى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم رجل منصرفه من أحد فقال يا رسول الله إني
رأيت في المنام ظلة تنطف سمنا وعسلا ورأيت الناس يتكففون منها
فالمستكثر والمستقل ورأيت سببا واصلا إلى السماء رأيتك أخذت به فعلوت
به ثم أخذ به رجل بعدك فعلا به ثم أخذ به رجل بعده فعلا به ثم أخذ به
رجل بعده فانقطع به ثم وصل له فعلا به ‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر دعني أعبرها
يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اعبرها ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أما الظلة فالإسلام وأما
ما ينطف منها من العسل والسمن فهو القرآن حلاوته ولينه وأما ما يتكفف
منه الناس فالآخذ من القرآن كثيرا وقليلا وأما السبب الواصل إلى
السماء فما أنت عليه من الحق أخذت به فعلا بك ثم يأخذه رجل من بعدك
فيعلو به ثم آخر فيعلو به ثم آخر فينقطع به ثم يوصل له فيعلو به ‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ أصبت بعضا وأخطأت بعضا ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال أبو بكر أقسمت عليك يا
رسول الله لتخبرني بالذي أصبت من الذي أخطأت ‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقسم يا أبا بكر ‏"‏ ‏.‏ حدثنا محمد بن يحيى، حدثنا
عبد الرزاق، أنبأنا معمر، عن الزهري، عن عبيد الله، عن ابن عباس، قال
كان أبو هريرة يحدث أن رجلا، أتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
يا رسول الله رأيت ظلة بين السماء والأرض تنطف سمنا وعسلا فذكر الحديث
نحوه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated that Ibn ‘Abbas said: “A man came to
the Prophet(ﷺ),upon his return from Uhud, and said: ‘O Messenger of
Allah, inmydream I saw a cloud giving shade, from which drops of
ghee andhoneywere falling, and I saw people collecting them in the
palms oftheirhands, some gathering a lot and some a little. And I
saw a ropereaching up into heaven, and I saw you take hold of it
and rise withit. Then another man took hold of it after you rose
with it, thenanother man took hold of it after him and rose with
it. Then a mantook hold of it after him and it broke, then it was
reconnected andherose with it.’ Abu Bakr said: ‘Let me interpret
it, OMessenger ofAllah.’ He said: ‘Interpret it.’ He said: ‘Asfor
the cloud givingshade, it is Islam, and the drops of honey andghee
that fall from it(represent) the Qur’an with its sweetnessand
softness. As for thepeople collecting that in their palms,
somelearn a lot of the Qur’anand some learn a little. As for the
ropereaching up into heaven, itis the truth that you are following;
youtook hold of it and rose withit, then another man till take hold
ofit after you and rise with you,then another, who will rise with
it,then another, but it will breakand then he reconnected, then he
willrise with it.’ He said: ‘Youhave got some of it right and
someof it wrong.’ Abu Bakr said: ‘Iadjure you O Messenger of
Allah,tell me what I got right and what Igot wrong.’ The Prophet
(ﷺ)said: ‘Do not swear, O Abu Bakr.”*</english-text>
</hadith>
