<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54048</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>35</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3925</hadith-number>
<chapter>Interpretation of Dreams - كتاب تعبير الرؤيا</chapter>
<chain-index>30490, 20023, 11234, 11213, 10567, 6</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن رمح، أنبأنا الليث بن سعد، عن ابن الهاد،
عن محمد بن إبراهيم التيمي، عن أبي سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، عن طلحة بن
عبيد الله، أن رجلين، من بلي قدما على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وكان إسلامهما جميعا فكان أحدهما أشد اجتهادا من الآخر فغزا المجتهد
منهما فاستشهد ثم مكث الآخر بعده سنة ثم توفي ‏.‏ قال طلحة فرأيت في
المنام بينا أنا عند باب الجنة إذا أنا بهما فخرج خارج من الجنة فأذن
للذي توفي الآخر منهما ثم خرج فأذن للذي استشهد ثم رجع إلى فقال ارجع
فإنك لم يأن لك بعد ‏.‏ فأصبح طلحة يحدث به الناس فعجبوا لذلك فبلغ
ذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ وحدثوه الحديث فقال ‏"‏ من أى
ذلك تعجبون ‏"‏ فقالوا يا رسول الله هذا كان أشد الرجلين اجتهادا ثم
استشهد ودخل هذا الآخر الجنة قبله ‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أليس قد مكث هذا بعده سنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا بلى ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
وأدرك رمضان فصامه وصلى كذا وكذا من سجدة في السنة ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا بلى
قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فما بينهما أبعد مما بين السماء
والأرض ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It wasnarrated from Talhah bin ‘Ubaidullah that two
men from Balicame tothe Messenger of Allah (ﷺ). They had become
Muslim together,butone of them used to strive harder than the
other. The one who usedtostrive harder went out to fight and was
martyred. The other onestayed for a year longer, then he passed
away. Talhah said: “I sawina dream that I was at the gate of
Paradise and I saw them (thosetwomen). Someone came out of Paradise
and admitted the one who haddiedlast, then he came out and admitted
the one who had beenmartyred.Then he came back to me and said: ‘Go
back, for your timehas not yetcome.’” The next morning, Talhah told
the people ofthat and they wereamazed. News of that reached the
Messenger ofAllah (ﷺ) and theytold him the story. He said: “Why are
you soamazed at that?” Theysaid: “O Messenger of Allah, the first
onewas the one who stroveharder, then he was martyred, but the
otherone was admitted toParadise before him. The Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ)said: “Did he notstay behind for a year?” They said: “Yes.”He
said: “And did notRamadan come and he fasted, and he offeredsuch
and such prayersduring that year?” They said: “Yes.” TheMessenger
of Allah (ﷺ)said: “The difference between them isgreater than the
differencebetween heaven and earth.”</english-text>
</hadith>
