<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54053</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4064</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30547, 20345, 11080</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سويد بن سعيد، حدثنا علي بن مسهر، عن عاصم، عن
السميط بن السمير، عن عمران بن الحصين، قال أتى نافع بن الأزرق
وأصحابه فقالوا هلكت يا عمران ‏.‏ قال ما هلكت ‏.‏ قالوا بلى ‏.‏ قال
ما الذي أهلكني قالوا قال الله ‏{وقاتلوهم حتى لا تكون فتنة ويكون
الدين كله لله}‏ ‏.‏ قال قد قاتلناهم حتى نفيناهم فكان الدين كله لله
إن شئتم حدثتكم حديثا سمعته من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏
قالوا وأنت سمعته من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏.‏ قال نعم شهدت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقد بعث جيشا من المسلمين إلى المشركين
فلما لقوهم قاتلوهم قتالا شديدا فمنحوهم أكتافهم فحمل رجل من لحمتي
على رجل من المشركين بالرمح فلما غشيه قال أشهد أن لا إله إلا الله
إني مسلم فطعنه فقتله فأتى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول
الله هلكت قال ‏"‏ وما الذي صنعت ‏"‏ ‏.‏ مرة أو مرتين فأخبره بالذي
صنع فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فهلا شققت عن بطنه
فعلمت ما في قلبه ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله لو شققت بطنه أكنت أعلم ما
في قلبه قال ‏"‏ فلا أنت قبلت ما تكلم به ولا أنت تعلم ما في قلبه ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال فسكت عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلم يلبث إلا يسيرا
حتى مات فدفناه فأصبح على ظهر الأرض فقالوا لعل عدوا نبشه فدفناه ثم
أمرنا غلماننا يحرسونه فأصبح على ظهر الأرض فقلنا لعل الغلمان نعسوا
فدفناه ثم حرسناه بأنفسنا فأصبح على ظهر الأرض فألقيناه في بعض تلك
الشعاب ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Sumait bin Sumair, that ‘Imran
bin Husainsaid: “Nafi’ bin Azraq and his companions came and said:
‘Youare doomed, O ‘Imran!’ He (‘Imran) said: ‘I am not doomed.’They
said: ‘Yes you are.’ I said: ‘Why am I doomed?’ Theysaid: ‘Allah
says: “And fight them until there is no more Fitnah(disbelief and
polytheism, i.e., worshipping others besides Allah),and the
religion (worship) will be all for Allah Alone.”[8:39] Hesaid: ‘We
fought them until they were defeated and the religion wasall for
Allah Alone. If you wish, I will tell you a Hadith that Iheard from
the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ).’ They said: ‘Did you(really) hear it
from the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)?’ He said: ‘Yes.I was with the
Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) and he had sent an army ofthe Muslims to the
idolaters. When they met them they fought themfiercely, and they
(the idolaters) gave them their shoulders (i.e.,turned and fled). A
man among my kin attacked an idolator man with aspear, and when he
was defeated he said: “I bear witness that nonehas the right to be
worshipped but Allah, I am a Muslim.” But hestabbed him and killed
him. He came to the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)and said: “O Messenger of
Allah, I am doomed.” He said “What isit that you have done?” one or
two times. He told him what he haddone and the Messenger of Allah
(ﷺ) said to him: “Why didn’tyou cut open his belly and find out
what was in his heart?” Hesaid: “O Messenger of Allah, I wish I had
cut open his belly andcould have known what was in his heart.” He
said: “You did notaccept what he said, and you could not have known
what was in hisheart!” The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ) remained silent
concerning him(that man), and a short while later he died. We
buried him, but thefollowing morning he was on the surface of the
earth. They said:“Perhaps an enemy of his disinterred him.” So we
buried him(again) and told our slaves to stand guard. But the
following morninghe was on the surface of the earth again then we
said: ‘Perhaps theslaves dozed off.’ So we buried him (again) and
stood guardourselves, but the following morning he was on the
surface of theearth (again). So we threw him into one of these
mountain passes.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
