<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54121</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4132</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>20029, 20475, 11013, 10511, 2201, 30154</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يونس بن عبد الأعلى المصري، أخبرني ابن وهب،
أخبرني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، عن عروة بن الزبير، ‏.‏ أن المسور بن
مخرمة، أخبره عن عمرو بن عوف، - وهو حليف بني عامر بن لؤى وكان شهد
بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم - أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم بعث أبا عبيدة بن الجراح إلى البحرين يأتي بجزيتها وكان النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم هو صالح أهل البحرين وأمر عليهم العلاء بن الحضرمي
فقدم أبو عبيدة بمال من البحرين فسمعت الأنصار بقدوم أبي عبيدة فوافوا
صلاة الفجر مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما صلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم انصرف فتعرضوا له فتبسم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
حين رآهم ثم قال ‏"‏ أظنكم سمعتم أن أبا عبيدة قدم بشىء من البحرين
‏"‏ ‏.‏ قالوا أجل يا رسول الله ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أبشروا وأملوا ما يسركم
فوالله ما الفقر أخشى عليكم ولكني أخشى عليكم أن تبسط الدنيا عليكم
كما بسطت على من كان قبلكم فتنافسوها كما تنافسوها فتهلككم كما
أهلكتهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from ‘Amr bin ‘Awf, who was an ally
of Banu ‘AmirbinLu’ai and was present at (the battle of) Badr with
theMessenger ofAllah (ﷺ), that the Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)
sent‘Ubaidah binJarrah to Bahrain to collect the Jizyah, and
theProphet (ﷺ) hadmade a treaty with the people of Bahrain, and
heappointed as theirgovernor ‘Ala’ bin Hadrami. Abu ‘Ubaidancame
with the wealth fromBahrain and the Ansar heard that Abu‘Ubaidah
had come, so theyattended the Fajr prayer with theMessenger of
Allah (ﷺ). When theMessenger of Allah (ﷺ) hadprayed, he went away,
so they interceptedhim. The Messenger of Allah(ﷺ) smiled when he
saw them, then hesaid: ‘I think you haveheard that Abu ‘Ubaidah has
brought somethingfrom Bahrain?’ Theysaid: ‘Yes, O Messenger of
Allah.’ He said: ‘Be ofgood cheerand hope for that which will make
you happy. By Allah, I donot fearpoverty for you, rather I fear
that you will enjoy ease andplentylike those who came before you,
and that you will compete withoneanother as they did, and you will
be destroyed as they were.’”</english-text>
</hadith>
