<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54155</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4166</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20733, 20710, 11019, 11028, 17,
39</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هشام بن عمار، حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا سعيد
بن بشير، عن قتادة، عن مجاهد، عن ابن عباس، عن أبى بن كعب، عن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه ليلة أسري به وجد ريحا طيبة فقال ‏"‏ يا
جبريل ما هذه الريح الطيبة قال هذه ريح قبر الماشطة وابنيها وزوجها
‏.‏ قال وكان بدء ذلك أن الخضر كان من أشراف بني إسرائيل وكان ممره
براهب في صومعته فيطلع عليه الراهب فيعلمه الإسلام فلما بلغ الخضر
زوجه أبوه امرأة فعلمها الخضر وأخذ عليها أن لا تعلمه أحدا وكان لا
يقرب النساء فطلقها ثم زوجه أبوه أخرى فعلمها وأخذ عليها أن لا تعلمه
أحدا فكتمت إحداهما وأفشت عليه الأخرى فانطلق هاربا حتى أتى جزيرة في
البحر فأقبل رجلان يحتطبان فرأياه فكتم أحدهما وأفشى الآخر وقال قد
رأيت الخضر ‏.‏ فقيل ومن رآه معك قال فلان فسئل فكتم وكان في دينهم أن
من كذب قتل قال فتزوج المرأة الكاتمة فبينما هي تمشط ابنة فرعون إذ
سقط المشط فقالت تعس فرعون ‏.‏ فأخبرت أباها وكان للمرأة ابنان وزوج
فأرسل إليهم فراود المرأة وزوجها أن يرجعا عن دينهما فأبيا فقال إني
قاتلكما ‏.‏ فقالا إحسانا منك إلينا إن قتلتنا أن تجعلنا في بيت ففعل
فلما أسري بالنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وجد ريحا طيبة فسأل جبريل فأخبره
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Ubayy bin Ka’b that on the night
when he (ﷺ)was taken on the Night Journey (Isra’), the Messenger of
Allah(ﷺ)noticed a good fragrance and said: “O Jibril, what is
thisgoodfragrance?” He said: “This is the fragrance of the grave
ofthehairdresser and her two sons and her husband.” He said:
“Thatbeganwhen Khadir, who was one of the nobles of the Children
ofIsrael, usedto pass by a monk in his cell. The monk used to meet
himand he taughthim Islam. When Khadir reached adolescence, his
fathermarried him toa woman. He taught her and made her promise not
toteach it to anyone.He used not to touch women, so he divorced
her,then his fathermarried him to another woman, and he taught her
andmade her promisenot to teach it to anyone. One of them kept
thesecret but the otherdisclosed it, so he fled until he came to
anisland in the sea. Twomen came, gathering firewood, and saw him.
Oneof them kept the secretbut the other disclosed it and said:
‘Ihave seen Khadir.’ It wassaid: ‘Who else saw him besides you?’He
said: ‘So-and-so.’ (The otherman) was questioned but he keptsilent.
According to their religion,the liar was to be killed. Thewoman who
had kept the secret gotmarried, and while she was combingthe hair
of Pharoah’s daughter, shedropped the comb and said: ‘MayPharoah
perish!’ (The daughter) toldher father about that. Thewoman had two
sons and a husband. (Pharoah)sent for them, and triedto make the
woman and her husband give uptheir religion, but theyrefused. He
said: ‘I am going to kill you.’They said: ‘Itwould be an act of
kindness on your part, if you killus, to put usin one grave.’ So he
did that.” When the Prophet (ﷺ)was takenon the Night Journey
(Isra’), he noticed a good fragranceand askedJibril about it and he
told him.”</english-text>
</hadith>
