<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54201</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4212</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30212, 20331, 11418, 10820, 11052, 224</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا
إسماعيل بن أبي خالد، عن مجالد، عن الشعبي، عن فاطمة بنت قيس، قالت
صلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات يوم وصعد المنبر وكان لا يصعد
عليه قبل ذلك إلا يوم الجمعة فاشتد ذلك على الناس فمن بين قائم وجالس
فأشار إليهم بيده أن اقعدوا ‏"‏ فإني والله ما قمت مقامي هذا لأمر
ينفعكم لرغبة ولا لرهبة ولكن تميما الداري أتاني فأخبرني خبرا منعني
القيلولة من الفرح وقرة العين فأحببت أن أنشر عليكم فرح نبيكم ألا إن
ابن عم لتميم الداري أخبرني أن الريح ألجأتهم إلى جزيرة لا يعرفونها
فقعدوا في قوارب السفينة فخرجوا فيها فإذا هم بشىء أهدب أسود قالوا له
ما أنت قال أنا الجساسة ‏.‏ قالوا أخبرينا ‏.‏ قالت ما أنا بمخبرتكم
شيئا ولا سائلتكم ولكن هذا الدير قد رمقتموه فأتوه فإن فيه رجلا
بالأشواق إلى أن تخبروه ويخبركم فأتوه فدخلوا عليه فإذا هم بشيخ موثق
شديد الوثاق يظهر الحزن شديد التشكي فقال لهم من أين قالوا من الشام
‏.‏ قال ما فعلت العرب قالوا نحن قوم من العرب عم تسأل قال ما فعل هذا
الرجل الذي خرج فيكم قالوا خيرا ناوى قوما فأظهره الله عليهم فأمرهم
اليوم جميع إلههم واحد ودينهم واحد قال ما فعلت عين زغر قالوا خيرا
يسقون منها زروعهم ويستقون منها لسقيهم قال فما فعل نخل بين عمان
وبيسان قالوا يطعم ثمره كل عام ‏.‏ قال فما فعلت بحيرة الطبرية قالوا
تدفق جنباتها من كثرة الماء ‏.‏ قال فزفر ثلاث زفرات ثم قال لو انفلت
من وثاقي هذا لم أدع أرضا إلا وطئتها برجلى هاتين إلا طيبة ليس لي
عليها سبيل ‏"‏ ‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إلى هذا ينتهي
فرحي هذه طيبة والذي نفسي بيده ما فيها طريق ضيق ولا واسع ولا سهل ولا
جبل إلا وعليه ملك شاهر سيفه إلى يوم القيامة ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated that Fatimah bint Qais said: "The
Messenger ofAllah(ﷺ) prayed one day, and ascended the pulpit, and
he neverused toascend it, before that, except on Fridays. The
people werealarmed bythat, and some were standing and some were
sitting. Hegestured tothem with his hand, telling them to sit.
(Then he said:)'By Allah, Iam not standing here for something that
will benefityou, anexhortation or warning. Rather Tamim Dari has
come to me andtold mesomething that prevented me from taking a rest
because of thejoy anddelight (I felt), and I wanted to spread that
joy among you.A cousinof Tamim Dari told me that the wind drove
them to an islandthat theydid not know, so they sat in the rowing
boats of the shipand set out.There they saw something black, with
long eyelashes.They said to it:"What are you?" It said: "I
amJassasah," They said: "Tell us." Itsaid: "I willnot tell you
anything or ask you anything. Rather thereis thismonastery that you
have looked at. Go to it, for there is aman therewho is longing to
hear your news and tell you news." So theywent there and entered
upon him, and they saw an old man firmlyshackled, with a sorrowful
appearance and complaining a great deal.Hesaid to them: "Where have
you come from?" They said:"From Sham." Hesaid: "How are the Arabs
faring?"They said: "We are from among theArabs. What do you want to
askabout?" He said: "What has this mandone who has appearedamong
you?" They said: "(He has done) well. Hemade enemiesof some people,
but Allah supported him against them andnow theyhave become one,
with one God and one religion." He said:"Whathappened to the spring
of Zughar?" They said: "It is good;weirrigate out crops from it and
drink from it." He said: "Whathappenedto the date-palms between
'Amman and Baisan?" Theysaid: "They bearfruit every year." He said:
"Whathappened to the Lake of Tiberias?"They said: "It
overflowsbecause of the abundance of water." He gavethree deep
sighs,then he said: "If I were to free myself from thesechains,
Iwould not leave any land without entering it on these twofeet
ofmine, except for Taibah, for I have no way to enter it."
TheProphet (ﷺ) said: 'My joy is so great. This (Al-Madinah) is
Taibah,and by the One in Whose Hand is my soul, there is no narrow
or broadroad in it, or any plain or mountain, but there is an
angel(standing)over it with his sword unsheathed, until the Day
ofResurrection.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
