<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54207</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4218</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>38091, 20246, 11168, 11019, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أزهر بن مروان، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، حدثنا سعيد، عن
قتادة، قال حدثنا أبو رافع، عن أبي هريرة، قال قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن يأجوج ومأجوج يحفرون كل يوم حتى إذا كادوا يرون شعاع
الشمس قال الذي عليهم ارجعوا فسنحفره غدا ‏.‏ فيعيده الله أشد ما كان
حتى إذا بلغت مدتهم وأراد الله أن يبعثهم على الناس حفروا حتى إذا
كادوا يرون شعاع الشمس قال الذي عليهم ارجعوا فستحفرونه غدا إن شاء
الله تعالى واستثنوا فيعودون إليه وهو كهيئته حين تركوه فيحفرونه
ويخرجون على الناس فينشفون الماء ويتحصن الناس منهم في حصونهم فيرمون
بسهامهم إلى السماء فترجع عليها الدم الذي اجفظ فيقولون قهرنا أهل
الأرض وعلونا أهل السماء فيبعث الله نغفا في أقفائهم فيقتلهم بها ‏"‏
‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده إن دواب
الأرض لتسمن وتشكر شكرا من لحومهم ‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Hurairah that the Messenger
of Allah (ﷺ)said: "Gog and Magog people dig every day until, when
they canalmostsee the rays of the sun, the one in charge of them
says: "Goback andwe will dig it tomorrow." Then Allah puts it
back,stronger than itwas before. (This will continue) until, when
theirtime has come, andAllah wants to send them against the people,
theywill dig until theycan almost see the rays of the sun, then the
onewho is in charge ofthem will say: "Go back, and we will dig
ittomorrow if Allah wills.'So they will say: "If Allah wills."Then
they will come back to it andit will be as they left it. Sothey
will dig and will come out to thepeople, and they will drinkall the
water. The people will fortifythemselves against them intheir
fortresses. They will shoot theirarrows towards the sky andthey
will come back with blood on them, andthey will say: "Wehave
defeated the people of earth and dominated thepeople ofheaven."
Then Allah will send a worm in the napes of theirnecksand will kill
them thereby.'" The Messenger of Allah (ﷺ)said:"By the One in Whose
Hand is my soul, the beasts of the earthwill grow fat on their
flesh."</english-text>
</hadith>
