<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>54206</id>
<source>Sunan Ibn Majah</source>
<chapter-number>36</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4217</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tribulations - كتاب الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20118, 11107, 11103, 1830, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو كريب، حدثنا يونس بن بكير، عن محمد بن إسحاق،
حدثني عاصم بن عمر بن قتادة، عن محمود بن لبيد، عن أبي سعيد الخدري،
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ تفتح يأجوج ومأجوج فيخرجون
كما قال الله تعالى ‏{وهم من كل حدب ينسلون}‏ فيعمون الأرض وينحاز
منهم المسلمون حتى تصير بقية المسلمين في مدائنهم وحصونهم ويضمون
إليهم مواشيهم حتى أنهم ليمرون بالنهر فيشربونه حتى ما يذرون فيه شيئا
فيمر آخرهم على أثرهم فيقول قائلهم لقد كان بهذا المكان مرة ماء
ويظهرون على الأرض فيقول قائلهم هؤلاء أهل الأرض قد فرغنا منهم
ولننازلن أهل السماء حتى إن أحدهم ليهز حربته إلى السماء فترجع مخضبة
بالدم فيقولون قد قتلنا أهل السماء ‏.‏ فبينما هم كذلك إذ بعث الله
دواب كنغف الجراد فتأخذ بأعناقهم فيموتون موت الجراد يركب بعضهم بعضا
فيصبح المسلمون لا يسمعون لهم حسا فيقولون من رجل يشري نفسه وينظر ما
فعلوا فينزل منهم رجل قد وطن نفسه على أن يقتلوه فيجدهم موتى فيناديهم
ألا أبشروا فقد هلك عدوكم ‏.‏ فيخرج الناس ويخلون سبيل مواشيهم فما
يكون لهم رعى إلا لحومهم فتشكر عليها كأحسن ما شكرت من نبات أصابته قط
‏"‏ ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>It was narrated from Abu Sa'eed Al-Khudri that the
Messenger ofAllah(ﷺ) said: "Gog and Magog people will be set free
and they willemerge as Allah says: "swoop(ing) down from every
mound."[21:96]Theywill spread throughout the earth, and the Muslims
will flee fromthemuntil the remainder of the Muslims are in their
cities andfortresses,taking their flocks with them. They will pass
by a riverand drinkfrom it, until they leave nothing behind, and
the last ofthem willfollow in their footsteps and one of them will
say: 'Therewas oncewater in this place.' They will prevail over the
earth, thentheirleader will say: 'These are the people of the
earth, and wehavefinished them off. Now let us fight the people of
heaven!' Thenoneof them will throw his spear towards the sky, and
it will comebackdown smeared with blood. And they will say: 'We
have killed thepeople of heaven.' While they are like that, Allah
will send a wormlike the worm that is found in the noses of sheep,
which willpenetrate their necks and they will die like locusts, one
on top ofanother. In the morning the Muslims will not hear any
sound fromthem,and they will say: 'Who will sell his soul for the
sake ofAllah andsee what they are doing?' A man will go down,
havingprepared himselfto be killed by them, and he will find them
dead, sohe will call outto them: 'Be of good cheer, for your enemy
is dead!'Then the peoplewill come out and let their flocks loose,
but theywill not haveanything to graze on except their flesh, and
they willbecome very fatas if they were grazing on the best
vegetation theyever found.'"</english-text>
</hadith>
