<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1019</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1046</hadith-number>
<chapter>Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 30226, 11716, 20475,
11013, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، قال حدثني الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن
شهاب، ح وحدثني أحمد بن صالح، قال حدثنا عنبسة، قال حدثنا يونس، عن
ابن شهاب، حدثني عروة، عن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت
خسفت الشمس في حياة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرج إلى المسجد فصف
الناس وراءه، فكبر فاقترأ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قراءة طويلة،
ثم كبر فركع ركوعا طويلا، ثم قال سمع الله لمن حمده‏.‏ فقام ولم يسجد،
وقرأ قراءة طويلة، هي أدنى من القراءة الأولى، ثم كبر وركع ركوعا
طويلا، وهو أدنى من الركوع الأول، ثم قال سمع الله لمن حمده، ربنا ولك
الحمد‏.‏ ثم سجد، ثم قال في الركعة الآخرة مثل ذلك، فاستكمل أربع
ركعات في أربع سجدات، وانجلت الشمس قبل أن ينصرف، ثم قام فأثنى على
الله بما هو أهله ثم قال ‏"‏ هما آيتان من آيات الله، لا يخسفان لموت
أحد ولا لحياته، فإذا رأيتموهما فافزعوا إلى الصلاة ‏"‏‏.‏ وكان يحدث
كثير بن عباس أن عبد الله بن عباس رضى الله عنهما كان يحدث يوم خسفت
الشمس بمثل حديث عروة عن عائشة‏.‏ فقلت لعروة إن أخاك يوم خسفت
بالمدينة لم يزد على ركعتين مثل الصبح‏.‏ قال أجل لأنه أخطأ
السنة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: (the wife of the Prophet (p.b.u.h)
In the lifetime of the Prophet the sun eclipsed and he went to the
Mosque and the people aligned behind him. He said the Takbir
(starting the prayer) and prolonged the recitation (from the
Qur'an) and then said Takbir and performed a prolonged bowing; then
he (lifted his head and) said, "Sami allahu liman hamidah" (Allah
heard him who sent his praises to Him). He then did not prostrate
but stood up and recited a prolonged recitation which was shorter
than the first recitation. He again said Takbir and then bowed a
prolonged bowing but shorter than the first one and then said,
"Sami`a l-lahu Lyman hamidah Rabbana walak-lhamd, (Allah heard him
who sent his praises to Him. O our Sustainer! All the praises are
for You)" and then prostrated and did the same in the second rak`a;
thus he completed four bowing and four prostrations. The sun
(eclipse) had cleared before he finished the prayer. (After the
prayer) he stood up, glorified and praised Allah as He deserved and
then said, "The sun and the moon are two of the signs of Allah.
They do not eclipse because of the death or the life (i.e. birth)
of someone. When you see them make haste for the prayer." Narrated
Az-Zuhri: I said to 'Ursa, "When the sun eclipsed at Medina your
brother (`Abdullah bin Az- Zubair) offered only a two-rak`at prayer
like that of the morning (Fajr) prayer." 'Ursa replied, "Yes, for
he missed the Prophet's tradition (concerning this
matter)."</english-text>
</hadith>
