<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1022</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1050</hadith-number>
<chapter>Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11062, 11455</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن يحيى بن سعيد، عن
عمرة بنت عبد الرحمن، عن عائشة، زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن
يهودية جاءت تسألها فقالت لها أعاذك الله من عذاب القبر‏.‏ فسألت
عائشة رضى الله عنها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أيعذب الناس في
قبورهم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عائذا بالله من ذلك‏.‏ ثم
ركب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات غداة مركبا، فخسفت الشمس، فرجع
ضحى، فمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بين ظهرانى الحجر، ثم قام
يصلي، وقام الناس وراءه، فقام قياما طويلا، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا، ثم
رفع فقام قياما طويلا، وهو دون القيام الأول ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا، وهو
دون الركوع الأول، ثم رفع فسجد، ثم قام فقام قياما طويلا، وهو دون
القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع الأول، ثم قام قياما
طويلا وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع
الأول، ثم رفع فسجد وانصرف، فقال ما شاء الله أن يقول، ثم أمرهم أن
يتعوذوا من عذاب القبر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amra bint `Abdur-Rahman: A Jewess came to
ask `Aisha (the wife of the Prophet) about something. She said to
her, "May Allah give you refuge from the punishment of the grave."
So `Aisha ' asked Allah's Apostle "Would the people be punished in
their graves?" Allah's Apostle after seeking refuge with Allah from
the punishment of the grave (and thus replied in the affirmative).
Then one day, Allah's Apostle rode to go to some place but the sun
eclipsed. He returned in the forenoon and passed through the rear
of the dwellings (of his wives) and stood for the (eclipse) prayer,
and the people stood behind him. He stood up for a long period and
then performed a prolonged bowing which was shorter than the first
bowing. Then he raised his head and prostrated. Then he stood up
(for the second rak`a) for a long while but the standing was
shorter than that of the first rak`a. Then he performed a prolonged
bowing which was shorter than the first one. Then he raised his
head and prostrated. Then he stood up for a long time but shorter
than the first. Then he performed a prolonged bowing but shorter
than the first. Then he raised his head and prostrated and finished
the prayer and (then delivered the sermon and) said as much as
Allah wished. And then he ordered the people to seek refuge with
Allah from the punishment of the grave.</english-text>
</hadith>
