<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1027</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1056</hadith-number>
<chapter>Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11062, 11455, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن يحيى بن سعيد، عن
عمرة بنت عبد الرحمن، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن يهودية، جاءت تسألها
فقالت أعاذك الله من عذاب القبر‏.‏ فسألت عائشة رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم أيعذب الناس في قبورهم فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
عائذا بالله من ذلك‏.‏ ثم ركب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ذات غداة
مركبا، فكسفت الشمس فرجع ضحى، فمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بين
ظهرانى الحجر، ثم قام فصلى، وقام الناس وراءه، فقام قياما طويلا، ثم
ركع ركوعا طويلا، ثم رفع فقام قياما طويلا، وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم
ركع ركوعا طويلا، وهو دون الركوع الأول، ثم رفع فسجد سجودا طويلا ثم
قام فقام قياما طويلا، وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا، وهو
دون الركوع الأول، ثم قام قياما طويلا، وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم ركع
ركوعا طويلا، وهو دون الركوع الأول، ثم سجد وهو دون السجود الأول، ثم
انصرف فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله أن يقول، ثم
أمرهم أن يتعوذوا من عذاب القبر</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amra bint `Abdur-Rahman: A Jewess came to
`Aisha to ask her about something and then she said, "May Allah
give you refuge from the punishment of the grave." So `Aisha asked
Allah's Apostle, "Would the people be punished in their graves?"
Allah's Apostle asked Allah's refuge from the punishment of the
grave (indicating an affirmative reply). Then one day Allah's
Apostle rode (to leave for some place) but the sun eclipsed. He
returned on the forenoon and passed through the rear of the
dwellings (of his wives) and stood up and started offering the
(eclipse) prayer and the people stood behind him. He stood for a
long period and then performed a long bowing and then stood
straight for a long period which was shorter than that of the first
standing, then he performed a prolonged bowing which was shorter
than the first bowing, then he raised his head and prostrated for a
long time and then stood up (for the second rak`a) for a long
while, but the standing was shorter than the standing of the first
rak`a. Then he performed a prolonged bowing which was shorter than
that of the first one. He then stood up for a long time but shorter
than the first, then again performed a long bowing which was
shorter than the first and then prostrated for a shorter while than
that of the first prostration. Then he finished the prayer and
delivered the sermon and) said what Allah wished; and ordered the
people to seek refuge with Allah from the punishment of the
grave.</english-text>
</hadith>
