<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1036</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>16</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1066</hadith-number>
<chapter>Eclipses - كتاب الكسوف</chapter>
<chain-index>30383, 20733, 20400, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن مهران، قال حدثنا الوليد، قال أخبرنا ابن
نمر، سمع ابن شهاب، عن عروة، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها جهر النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم في صلاة الخسوف بقراءته، فإذا فرغ من قراءته كبر فركع،
وإذا رفع من الركعة قال سمع الله لمن حمده، ربنا ولك الحمد‏.‏ ثم
يعاود القراءة في صلاة الكسوف، أربع ركعات في ركعتين وأربع سجدات‏.‏
وقال الأوزاعي وغيره سمعت الزهري، عن عروة، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن
الشمس، خسفت على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فبعث مناديا
بالصلاة جامعة، فتقدم فصلى أربع ركعات في ركعتين وأربع سجدات‏.‏
وأخبرني عبد الرحمن بن نمر سمع ابن شهاب مثله‏.‏ قال الزهري فقلت ما
صنع أخوك ذلك، عبد الله بن الزبير ما صلى إلا ركعتين مثل الصبح إذ صلى
بالمدينة‏.‏ قال أجل، إنه أخطأ السنة‏.‏ تابعه سفيان بن حسين وسليمان
بن كثير عن الزهري في الجهر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: The Prophet (p.b.u.h) recited (the
Qur'an) aloud during the eclipse prayer and when he had finished
the eclipse prayer he said the Takbir and bowed. When he stood
straight from bowing he would say "Sami 'al-l-ahu Lyman hamidah
Rabbana wa laka l-hamd." And he would again start reciting. In the
eclipse prayer there are four bowing and four prostrations in two
rak`at. Al-Auza'i and others said that they had heard Az-Zuhi from
'Ursa from `Aisha saying, "In the lifetime of Allah's Apostle the
sun eclipsed, and he made a person to announce: 'Prayer in
congregation.' He led the prayer and performed four bowing and four
prostrations in two rak`at." Narrated Al-Walid that `Abdur-Rahman
bin Namir had informed him that he had heard the same. Ibn Shihab
heard the same. Az-Zuhri said, "I asked ('Ursa), 'What did your
brother `Abdullah bin Az-Zubair do? He prayed two rak`at (of the
eclipse prayer) like the morning prayer, when he offered the
(eclipse) prayer in Median.' 'Ursa replied that he had missed (i.e.
did not pray according to) the Prophet's tradition." Sulaiman bin
Kathir and Sufyan bin Husain narrated from Az-Zuhri that the prayer
for the eclipse used to be offered with loud
recitation.</english-text>
</hadith>
