<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>104</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>104</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20023, 11168, 5355</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، قال حدثني الليث، قال حدثني
سعيد، عن أبي شريح، أنه قال لعمرو بن سعيد وهو يبعث البعوث إلى مكة
ائذن لي أيها الأمير أحدثك قولا قام به النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم الغد
من يوم الفتح، سمعته أذناى ووعاه قلبي، وأبصرته عيناى، حين تكلم به،
حمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ إن مكة حرمها الله، ولم يحرمها الناس،
فلا يحل لامرئ يؤمن بالله واليوم الآخر أن يسفك بها دما، ولا يعضد بها
شجرة، فإن أحد ترخص لقتال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيها فقولوا
إن الله قد أذن لرسوله، ولم يأذن لكم‏.‏ وإنما أذن لي فيها ساعة من
نهار، ثم عادت حرمتها اليوم كحرمتها بالأمس، وليبلغ الشاهد الغائب
‏"‏‏.‏ فقيل لأبي شريح ما قال عمرو قال أنا أعلم منك يا أبا شريح، لا
يعيذ عاصيا، ولا فارا بدم، ولا فارا بخربة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id: Abu Shuraih said, "When `Amr bin
Sa`id was sending the troops to Mecca (to fight `Abdullah bin Az-
Zubair) I said to him, 'O chief! Allow me to tell you what the
Prophet said on the day following the conquests of Mecca. My ears
heard and my heart comprehended, and I saw him with my own eyes,
when he said it. He glorified and praised Allah and then said,
"Allah and not the people has made Mecca a sanctuary. So anybody
who has belief in Allah and the Last Day (i.e. a Muslim) should
neither shed blood in it nor cut down its trees. If anybody argues
that fighting is allowed in Mecca as Allah's Apostle did fight (in
Mecca), tell him that Allah gave permission to His Apostle, but He
did not give it to you. The Prophet added: Allah allowed me only
for a few hours on that day (of the conquest) and today (now) its
sanctity is the same (valid) as it was before. So it is incumbent
upon those who are present to convey it (this information) to those
who are absent." Abu- Shuraih was asked, "What did `Amr reply?" He
said `Amr said, "O Abu Shuraih! I know better than you (in this
respect). Mecca does not give protection to one who disobeys
(Allah) or runs after committing murder, or theft (and takes refuge
in Mecca).</english-text>
</hadith>
