<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1061</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>18</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1092</hadith-number>
<chapter>Shortening the Prayers (At-Taqseer) - كتاب
التقصير</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، قال أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال
أخبرني سالم، عن عبد الله بن عمر رضى الله عنهما قال رأيت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا أعجله السير في السفر يؤخر المغرب حتى يجمع
بينها وبين العشاء‏.‏ قال سالم وكان عبد الله يفعله إذا أعجله
السير‏.‏ وزاد الليث قال حدثني يونس، عن ابن شهاب، قال سالم كان ابن
عمر رضى الله عنهما يجمع بين المغرب والعشاء بالمزدلفة‏.‏ قال سالم
وأخر ابن عمر المغرب، وكان استصرخ على امرأته صفية بنت أبي عبيد فقلت
له الصلاة‏.‏ فقال سر‏.‏ فقلت الصلاة‏.‏ فقال سر‏.‏ حتى سار ميلين أو
ثلاثة ثم نزل فصلى ثم قال هكذا رأيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي
إذا أعجله السير‏.‏ وقال عبد الله رأيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا
أعجله السير يؤخر المغرب، فيصليها ثلاثا ثم يسلم، ثم قلما يلبث حتى
يقيم العشاء فيصليها ركعتين ثم يسلم، ولا يسبح بعد العشاء حتى يقوم من
جوف الليل‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Umar: "I saw Allah's Apostle
delaying the Maghrib prayer till he offered it along with the
`Isha' prayer whenever he was in a hurry during the journey." Salim
narrated, "Ibn `Umar used to do the same whenever he was in a hurry
during the journey." And Salim added, "Ibn `Umar used to pray the
Maghrib and `Isha' prayers together in Al-Muzdalifa." Salim said,
"Ibn `Umar delayed the Maghrib prayer because at that time he heard
the news of the death of his wife Safiya bint Abi `Ubaid. I said to
him, 'The prayer (is due).' He said, 'Go on.' Again I said, 'The
prayer (is due).' He said, 'Go on,' till we covered two or three
miles. Then he got down, prayed and said, 'I saw the Prophet
praying in this way, whenever he was in a hurry during the
journey.' `Abdullah (bin `Umar) added, "Whenever the Prophet was in
a hurry, he used to delay the Maghrib prayer and then offer three
rak`at (of the Maghrib) and perform Taslim, and after waiting for a
short while, Iqama used to be pronounced for the `Isha' prayer when
he would offer two rak`at and perform Taslim. He would never offer
any optional prayer till the middle of the night (when he used to
pray the Tahajjud)."</english-text>
</hadith>
