<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1089</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>19</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1120</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayer at Night (Tahajjud) - كتاب التهجد</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11247, 11053, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، قال حدثنا سفيان، قال حدثنا
سليمان بن أبي مسلم، عن طاوس، سمع ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال كان
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا قام من الليل يتهجد قال ‏"‏ اللهم لك
الحمد أنت قيم السموات والأرض ومن فيهن ولك الحمد، لك ملك السموات
والأرض ومن فيهن، ولك الحمد أنت نور السموات والأرض، ولك الحمد أنت
الحق، ووعدك الحق، ولقاؤك حق، وقولك حق، والجنة حق، والنار حق،
والنبيون حق، ومحمد صلى الله عليه وسلم حق، والساعة حق، اللهم لك
أسلمت، وبك آمنت وعليك توكلت، وإليك أنبت، وبك خاصمت، وإليك حاكمت،
فاغفر لي ما قدمت وما أخرت، وما أسررت وما أعلنت، أنت المقدم وأنت
المؤخر، لا إله إلا أنت أو لا إله غيرك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سفيان وزاد عبد
الكريم أبو أمية ‏"‏ ولا حول ولا قوة إلا بالله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سفيان قال
سليمان بن أبي مسلم سمعه من طاوس عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما عن النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: When the Prophet got up at night
to offer the Tahajjud prayer, he used to say: Allahumma lakal-hamd.
Anta qaiyimus-samawati wal-ard wa man fihinna. Walakal-hamd, Laka
mulkus-samawati wal-ard wa man fihinna. Walakal-hamd, anta
nurus-samawati wal-ard. Walakalhamd, anta-l-haq wa wa'duka-lhaq, wa
liqa'uka Haq, wa qualuka Haq, wal-jannatu Han wan-naru Haq
wannabiyuna Haq. Wa Muhammadun, sallal-lahu'alaihi wasallam, Haq,
was-sa'atu Haq. Allahumma aslamtu Laka wabika amantu, wa 'Alaika
tawakkaltu, wa ilaika anabtu wa bika khasamtu, wa ilaika hakamtu
faghfir li ma qaddamtu wama akh-khartu wama as-rartu wama'a lantu,
anta-l-muqaddim wa anta-l-mu akh-khir, la ilaha illa anta (or la
ilaha ghairuka). (O Allah! All the praises are for you, You are the
Holder of the Heavens and the Earth, And whatever is in them. All
the praises are for You; You have the possession of the Heavens and
the Earth And whatever is in them. All the praises are for You; You
are the Light of the Heavens and the Earth And all the praises are
for You; You are the King of the Heavens and the Earth; And all the
praises are for You; You are the Truth and Your Promise is the
truth, And to meet You is true, Your Word is the truth And Paradise
is true And Hell is true And all the Prophets (Peace be upon them)
are true; And Muhammad is true, And the Day of Resurrection is
true. O Allah ! I surrender (my will) to You; I believe in You and
depend on You. And repent to You, And with Your help I argue (with
my opponents, the non-believers) And I take You as a judge (to
judge between us). Please forgive me my previous And future sins;
And whatever I concealed or revealed And You are the One who make
(some people) forward And (some) backward. There is none to be
worshipped but you . Sufyan said that `Abdul Karim Abu Umaiya added
to the above, 'Wala haula Wala quwata illa billah' (There is
neither might nor power except with Allah).</english-text>
</hadith>
