<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>112</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>112</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20348, 20240, 11449, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو نعيم الفضل بن دكين، قال حدثنا شيبان، عن
يحيى، عن أبي سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، أن خزاعة، قتلوا رجلا من بني ليث
عام فتح مكة بقتيل منهم قتلوه، فأخبر بذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فركب راحلته، فخطب فقال ‏"‏ إن الله حبس عن مكة القتل أو الفيل شك أبو
عبد الله وسلط عليهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والمؤمنين، ألا
وإنها لم تحل لأحد قبلي، ولا تحل لأحد بعدي ألا وإنها حلت لي ساعة من
نهار، ألا وإنها ساعتي هذه حرام، لا يختلى شوكها، ولا يعضد شجرها، ولا
تلتقط ساقطتها إلا لمنشد، فمن قتل فهو بخير النظرين إما أن يعقل، وإما
أن يقاد أهل القتيل ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاء رجل من أهل اليمن فقال اكتب لي يا
رسول الله‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ اكتبوا لأبي فلان ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رجل من قريش إلا
الإذخر يا رسول الله، فإنا نجعله في بيوتنا وقبورنا‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إلا الإذخر، إلا الإذخر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله
يقال يقاد بالقاف‏.‏ فقيل لأبي عبد الله أى شىء كتب له قال كتب له هذه
الخطبة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: In the year of the Conquest of
Mecca, the tribe of Khuza`a killed a man from the tribe of Bani
Laith in revenge for a killed person, belonging to them. They
informed the Prophet about it. So he rode his Rahila (she-camel for
riding) and addressed the people saying, "Allah held back the
killing from Mecca. (The sub-narrator is in doubt whether the
Prophet said "elephant or killing," as the Arabic words standing
for these words have great similarity in shape), but He (Allah) let
His Apostle and the believers over power the infidels of Mecca.
Beware! (Mecca is a sanctuary) Verily! Fighting in Mecca was not
permitted for anyone before me nor will it be permitted for anyone
after me. It (war) in it was made legal for me for few hours or so
on that day. No doubt it is at this moment a sanctuary, it is not
allowed to uproot its thorny shrubs or to uproot its trees or to
pick up its Luqat (fallen things) except by a person who will look
for its owner (announce it publicly). And if somebody is killed,
then his closest relative has the right to choose one of the two--
the blood money (Diyya) or retaliation having the killer killed. In
the meantime a man from Yemen came and said, "O Allah's Apostle!
Get that written for me." The Prophet ordered his companions to
write that for him. Then a man from Quraish said, "Except
Al-Idhkhir (a type of grass that has good smell) O Allah's Apostle,
as we use it in our houses and graves." The Prophet said, "Except
Al-Idhkhir i.e. Al-Idhkhir is allowed to be
plucked."</english-text>
</hadith>
