<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1161</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1198</hadith-number>
<chapter>Actions while Praying - كتاب العمل فى الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11223, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن مخرمة بن
سليمان، عن كريب، مولى ابن عباس أنه أخبره عن عبد الله بن عباس رضى
الله عنهما أنه بات عند ميمونة أم المؤمنين رضى الله عنها وهى خالته
قال فاضطجعت على عرض الوسادة، واضطجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وأهله في طولها، فنام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى انتصف الليل
أو قبله بقليل أو بعده بقليل، ثم استيقظ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فجلس، فمسح النوم عن وجهه بيده، ثم قرأ العشر آيات خواتيم سورة آل
عمران، ثم قام إلى شن معلقة فتوضأ منها، فأحسن وضوءه، ثم قام يصلي‏.‏
قال عبد الله بن عباس رضى الله عنهما فقمت فصنعت مثل ما صنع، ثم ذهبت
فقمت إلى جنبه، فوضع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده اليمنى على
رأسي، وأخذ بأذني اليمنى يفتلها بيده، فصلى ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم
ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم أوتر، ثم اضطجع حتى جاءه
المؤذن، فقام فصلى ركعتين خفيفتين، ثم خرج فصلى
الصبح‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Kuraib Maula Ibn `Abbas: `Abdullah bin
`Abbas said that he had passed a night in the house of Maimuna the
mother of the faithful believers , who was his aunt. He said, "I
slept across the bed, and Allah's Apostle along with his wife slept
lengthwise. Allah's Apostle slept till midnight or slightly before
or after it. Then Allah's Apostle woke up, sat, and removed the
traces of sleep by rubbing his hands over his face. Then he recited
the last ten verses of Surat-Al `Imran (2). Then he went towards a
hanging leather watercontainer and performed a perfect ablution and
then stood up for prayer." `Abdullah bin `Abbas added, "I got up
and did the same as Allah's Apostle had done and then went and
stood by his side. Allah's Apostle then put his right hand over my
head and caught my right ear and twisted it. He offered two rak`at,
then two rak`at, then two rak`at, then two rak`at, then two rak`at,
then two rak`at and then offered one rak`a witr. Then he lay down
till the Mu'adh-dhin came and then he prayed two light rak`at and
went out and offered the early morning (Fajr)
prayer."</english-text>
</hadith>
