<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1182</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>21</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1218</hadith-number>
<chapter>Actions while Praying - كتاب العمل فى الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20167, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد العزيز، عن أبي حازم، عن سهل بن
سعد رضى الله عنه قال بلغ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن بني عمرو
بن عوف بقباء كان بينهم شىء، فخرج يصلح بينهم في أناس من أصحابه، فحبس
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وحانت الصلاة، فجاء بلال إلى أبي بكر
رضى الله عنهما فقال يا أبا بكر، إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد
حبس وقد حانت الصلاة، فهل لك أن تؤم الناس قال نعم إن شئت‏.‏ فأقام
بلال الصلاة، وتقدم أبو بكر رضى الله عنه فكبر للناس، وجاء رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يمشي في الصفوف يشقها شقا، حتى قام في الصف، فأخذ
الناس في التصفيح‏.‏ قال سهل التصفيح هو التصفيق‏.‏ قال وكان أبو بكر
رضى الله عنه لا يلتفت في صلاته، فلما أكثر الناس التفت فإذا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأشار إليه، يأمره أن يصلي، فرفع أبو بكر رضى
الله عنه يده، فحمد الله، ثم رجع القهقرى وراءه حتى قام في الصف،
وتقدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى للناس، فلما فرغ أقبل على
الناس فقال ‏"‏ يا أيها الناس ما لكم حين نابكم شىء في الصلاة أخذتم
بالتصفيح إنما التصفيح للنساء، من نابه شىء في صلاته فليقل سبحان الله
‏"‏‏.‏ ثم التفت إلى أبي بكر رضى الله عنه فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا بكر، ما
منعك أن تصلي للناس حين أشرت إليك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو بكر ما كان ينبغي
لابن أبي قحافة أن يصلي بين يدى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: The news about the
differences amongst the people of Bani `Amr bin `Auf at Quba
reached Allah's Apostle and so he went to them along with some of
his companions to affect a reconciliation. Allah's Apostle was
delayed there and the time for the prayer became due. Bilal came to
Abu Bakr! and said, "O Abu Bakr! Allah's Apostle is detained
(there) and the time for the prayer is due. Will you lead the
people in prayer?" Abu Bakr replied, "Yes, if you wish." So Bilal
pronounced the Iqama and Abu Bakr went forward and the people said
Takbir. In the meantime, Allah's Apostle came piercing through the
rows till he stood in the (first) row and the people started
clapping. Abu Bakr, would never look hither and thither during the
prayer but when the people clapped much he looked back and saw
Allah's Apostle. The Prophet beckoned him to carry on. Abu Bakr
raised both his hands, praised Allah and retreated till he stood in
the row and Allah's Apostle went forward and led the people in the
prayer. When he had finished the prayer, he addressed the people
and said, "O people! Why did you start clapping when something
happened to you in the prayer? Clapping is for women. Whenever one
is confronted with something unusual in the prayer one should say,
'Sub Han Allah'." Then the Prophet looked towards Abu Bakr and
asked, "What prevented you from leading the prayer when I beckoned
you to carry on?" Abu Bakr replied, "It does not befit the son of
Al Quhafa to lead the prayer in the presence of Allah's
Apostle.</english-text>
</hadith>
