<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>122</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>122</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20005, 11081, 11050, 39</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، قال حدثنا سفيان، قال حدثنا
عمرو، قال أخبرني سعيد بن جبير، قال قلت لابن عباس إن نوفا البكالي
يزعم أن موسى ليس بموسى بني إسرائيل، إنما هو موسى آخر‏.‏ فقال كذب
عدو الله، حدثنا أبى بن كعب عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ قام
موسى النبي خطيبا في بني إسرائيل، فسئل أى الناس أعلم فقال أنا
أعلم‏.‏ فعتب الله عليه، إذ لم يرد العلم إليه، فأوحى الله إليه أن
عبدا من عبادي بمجمع البحرين هو أعلم منك‏.‏ قال يا رب وكيف به فقيل
له احمل حوتا في مكتل فإذا فقدته فهو ثم، فانطلق وانطلق بفتاه يوشع بن
نون، وحملا حوتا في مكتل، حتى كانا عند الصخرة وضعا رءوسهما وناما
فانسل الحوت من المكتل فاتخذ سبيله في البحر سربا، وكان لموسى وفتاه
عجبا، فانطلقا بقية ليلتهما ويومهما فلما أصبح قال موسى لفتاه آتنا
غداءنا، لقد لقينا من سفرنا هذا نصبا، ولم يجد موسى مسا من النصب حتى
جاوز المكان الذي أمر به‏.‏ فقال له فتاه أرأيت إذ أوينا إلى الصخرة
فإني نسيت الحوت، قال موسى ذلك ما كنا نبغي، فارتدا على آثارهما قصصا،
فلما انتهيا إلى الصخرة إذا رجل مسجى بثوب أو قال تسجى بثوبه فسلم
موسى‏.‏ فقال الخضر وأنى بأرضك السلام فقال أنا موسى‏.‏ فقال موسى بني
إسرائيل قال نعم‏.‏ قال هل أتبعك على أن تعلمني مما علمت رشدا قال إنك
لن تستطيع معي صبرا، يا موسى إني على علم من علم الله علمنيه لا تعلمه
أنت، وأنت على علم علمكه لا أعلمه‏.‏ قال ستجدني إن شاء الله صابرا،
ولا أعصي لك أمرا، فانطلقا يمشيان على ساحل البحر ليس لهما سفينة،
فمرت بهما سفينة، فكلموهم أن يحملوهما، فعرف الخضر، فحملوهما بغير
نول، فجاء عصفور فوقع على حرف السفينة، فنقر نقرة أو نقرتين في
البحر‏.‏ فقال الخضر يا موسى، ما نقص علمي وعلمك من علم الله إلا
كنقرة هذا العصفور في البحر‏.‏ فعمد الخضر إلى لوح من ألواح السفينة
فنزعه‏.‏ فقال موسى قوم حملونا بغير نول، عمدت إلى سفينتهم فخرقتها
لتغرق أهلها قال ألم أقل إنك لن تستطيع معي صبرا قال لا تؤاخذني بما
نسيت‏.‏ فكانت الأولى من موسى نسيانا‏.‏ فانطلقا فإذا غلام يلعب مع
الغلمان، فأخذ الخضر برأسه من أعلاه فاقتلع رأسه بيده‏.‏ فقال موسى
أقتلت نفسا زكية بغير نفس قال ألم أقل لك إنك لن تستطيع معي صبرا قال
ابن عيينة وهذا أوكد فانطلقا حتى إذا أتيا أهل قرية استطعما أهلها،
فأبوا أن يضيفوهما، فوجدا فيها جدارا يريد أن ينقض فأقامه‏.‏ قال
الخضر بيده فأقامه‏.‏ فقال له موسى لو شئت لاتخذت عليه أجرا‏.‏ قال
هذا فراق بيني وبينك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يرحم
الله موسى، لوددنا لو صبر حتى يقص علينا من أمرهما
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id bin Jubair: I said to Ibn `Abbas,
"Nauf-Al-Bakali claims that Moses (the companion of Khadir) was not
the Moses of Bani Israel but he was another Moses." Ibn `Abbas
remarked that the enemy of Allah (Nauf) was a liar.Narrated Ubai
bin Ka`b:The Prophet said, "Once the Prophet Moses stood up and
addressed Bani Israel. He was asked, "Who is the most learned man
amongst the people. He said, "I am the most learned." Allah
admonished Moses as he did not attribute absolute knowledge to Him
(Allah). So Allah inspired to him "At the junction of the two seas
there is a slave amongst my slaves who is more learned than you."
Moses said, "O my Lord! How can I meet him?" Allah said: Take a
fish in a large basket (and proceed) and you will find him at the
place where you will lose the fish. So Moses set out along with his
(servant) boy, Yusha` bin Noon and carried a fish in a large basket
till they reached a rock, where they laid their heads (i.e. lay
down) and slept. The fish came out of the basket and it took its
way into the sea as in a tunnel. So it was an amazing thing for
both Moses and his (servant) boy. They proceeded for the rest of
that night and the following day. When the day broke, Moses said to
his (servant) boy: "Bring us our early meal. No doubt, we have
suffered much fatigue in this journey." Moses did not get tired
till he passed the place about which he was told. There the
(servant) boy told Moses, "Do you remember when we betook ourselves
to the rock, I indeed forgot the fish." Moses remarked, "That is
what we have been seeking. So they went back retracing their
footsteps, till they reached the rock. There they saw a man covered
with a garment (or covering himself with his own garment). Moses
greeted him. Al-Khadir replied saying, "How do people greet each
other in your land?" Moses said, "I am Moses." He asked, "The Moses
of Bani Israel?" Moses replied in the affirmative and added, "May I
follow you so that you teach me of that knowledge which you have
been taught." Al-Khadir replied, "Verily! You will not be able to
remain patient with me, O Moses! I have some of the knowledge of
Allah which He has taught me and which you do not know, while you
have some knowledge which Allah has taught you which I do not
know." Moses said, "Allah willing, you will find me patient and I
will disobey no order of yours. So both of them set out walking
along the seashore, as they did not have a boat. In the meantime a
boat passed by them and they requested the crew of the boat to take
them on board. The crew recognized Al-Khadir and took them on board
without fare. Then a sparrow came and stood on the edge of the boat
and dipped its beak once or twice in the sea. Al-Khadir said: "O
Moses! My knowledge and your knowledge have not decreased Allah's
knowledge except as much as this sparrow has decreased the water of
the sea with its beak." Al- Khadir went to one of the planks of the
boat and plucked it out. Moses said, "These people gave us a free
lift but you have broken their boat and scuttled it so as to drown
its people." Al-Khadir replied, "Didn't I tell you that you will
not be able to remain patient with me." Moses said, "Call me not to
account for what I forgot." The first (excuse) of Moses was that he
had forgotten. Then they proceeded further and found a boy playing
with other boys. Al-Khadir took hold of the boy's head from the top
and plucked it out with his hands (i.e. killed him). Moses said,
"Have you killed an innocent soul who has killed none." Al-Khadir
replied, "Did I not tell you that you cannot remain patient with
me?" Then they both proceeded till when they came to the people of
a town, they asked them for food, but they refused to entertain
them. Then they found there a wall on the point of collapsing.
Al-Khadir repaired it with his own hands. Moses said, "If you had
wished, surely you could have taken wages for it." Al-Khadir
replied, "This is the parting between you and me." The Prophet
added, "May Allah be Merciful to Moses! Would that he could have
been more patient to learn more about his story with Al-Khadir.
"</english-text>
</hadith>
