<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1245</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1284</hadith-number>
<chapter>Funerals (Al-Janaa'iz) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 30213, 20025, 11080, 11113, 50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، ومحمد، قالا أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا عاصم
بن سليمان، عن أبي عثمان، قال حدثني أسامة بن زيد رضى الله عنهما قال
أرسلت ابنة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إليه إن ابنا لي قبض فائتنا‏.‏
فأرسل يقرئ السلام ويقول ‏"‏ إن لله ما أخذ وله ما أعطى وكل عنده بأجل
مسمى، فلتصبر ولتحتسب ‏"‏‏.‏ فأرسلت إليه تقسم عليه ليأتينها، فقام
ومعه سعد بن عبادة ومعاذ بن جبل وأبى بن كعب وزيد بن ثابت ورجال، فرفع
إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الصبي ونفسه تتقعقع قال حسبته أنه
قال كأنها شن‏.‏ ففاضت عيناه‏.‏ فقال سعد يا رسول الله ما هذا فقال
‏"‏ هذه رحمة جعلها الله في قلوب عباده، وإنما يرحم الله من عباده
الرحماء ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Usama bin Zaid: The daughter of the Prophet
(p.b.u.h) sent (a messenger) to the Prophet requesting him to come
as her child was dying (or was gasping), but the Prophet returned
the messenger and told him to convey his greeting to her and say:
"Whatever Allah takes is for Him and whatever He gives, is for Him,
and everything with Him has a limited fixed term (in this world)
and so she should be patient and hope for Allah's reward." She
again sent for him, swearing that he should come. The Prophet got
up, and so did Sa`d bin 'Ubada, Mu`adh bin Jabal, Ubai bin Ka`b,
Zaid bin Thabit and some other men. The child was brought to
Allah's Apostle while his breath was disturbed in his chest (the
sub-narrator thinks that Usama added: ) as if it was a leather
water-skin. On that the eyes of the Prophet (p.b.u.h) started
shedding tears. Sa`d said, "O Allah's Apostle! What is this?" He
replied, "It is mercy which Allah has lodged in the hearts of His
slaves, and Allah is merciful only to those of His slaves who are
merciful (to others).</english-text>
</hadith>
