<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1247</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1286</hadith-number>
<chapter>Funerals (Al-Janaa'iz) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 20025, 11070, 11090</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، حدثنا عبد الله، أخبرنا ابن جريج، قال
أخبرني عبد الله بن عبيد الله بن أبي مليكة، قال توفيت ابنة لعثمان
رضى الله عنه بمكة وجئنا لنشهدها، وحضرها ابن عمر وابن عباس رضى الله
عنهم وإني لجالس بينهما أو قال جلست إلى أحدهما‏.‏ ثم جاء الآخر، فجلس
إلى جنبي فقال عبد الله بن عمر رضى الله عنهما لعمرو بن عثمان ألا
تنهى عن البكاء، فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن الميت
ليعذب ببكاء أهله عليه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قد كان
عمر رضى الله عنه يقول بعض ذلك، ثم حدث قال صدرت مع عمر رضى الله عنه
من مكة حتى إذا كنا بالبيداء، إذا هو بركب تحت ظل سمرة فقال اذهب،
فانظر من هؤلاء الركب قال فنظرت فإذا صهيب، فأخبرته فقال ادعه لي‏.‏
فرجعت إلى صهيب فقلت ارتحل فالحق أمير المؤمنين‏.‏ فلما أصيب عمر دخل
صهيب يبكي يقول واأخاه، واصاحباه‏.‏ فقال عمر رضى الله عنه يا صهيب
أتبكي على وقد قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الميت يعذب
ببعض بكاء أهله عليه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما فلما مات عمر
رضى الله عنه ذكرت ذلك لعائشة رضى الله عنها فقالت رحم الله عمر،
والله ما حدث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إن الله ليعذب المؤمن
ببكاء أهله عليه‏.‏ ولكن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إن
الله ليزيد الكافر عذابا ببكاء أهله عليه ‏"‏‏.‏ وقالت حسبكم القرآن
‏{‏ولا تزر وازرة وزر أخرى‏}‏‏.‏ قال ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما عند ذلك
والله هو أضحك وأبكى‏.‏ قال ابن أبي مليكة والله ما قال ابن عمر رضى
الله عنهما شيئا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin 'Ubaidullah bin Abi Mulaika:
One of the daughters of `Uthman died at Mecca. We went to attend
her funeral procession. Ibn `Umar and Ibn `Abbas were also present.
I sat in between them (or said, I sat beside one of them. Then a
man came and sat beside me.) `Abdullah bin `Umar said to `Amr bin
`Uthman, "Will you not prohibit crying as Allah's Apostle has said,
'The dead person is tortured by the crying of his relatives.?" Ibn
`Abbas said, "`Umar used to say so." Then he added narrating, "I
accompanied `Umar on a journey from Mecca till we reached Al-Baida.
There he saw some travelers in the shade of a Samura (A kind of
forest tree). He said (to me), "Go and see who those travelers
are." So I went and saw that one of them was Suhaib. I told this to
`Umar who then asked me to call him. So I went back to Suhaib and
said to him, "Depart and follow the chief of the faithful
believers." Later, when `Umar was stabbed, Suhaib came in weeping
and saying, "O my brother, O my friend!" (on this `Umar said to
him, "O Suhaib! Are you weeping for me while the Prophet said, "The
dead person is punished by some of the weeping of his relatives?"
Ibn `Abbas added, "When `Umar died I told all this to Aisha and she
said, 'May Allah be merciful to `Umar. By Allah, Allah's Apostle
did not say that a believer is punished by the weeping of his
relatives. But he said, Allah increases the punishment of a
non-believer because of the weeping of his relatives." Aisha
further added, "The Qur'an is sufficient for you (to clear up this
point) as Allah has stated: 'No burdened soul will bear another's
burden.' " (35.18). Ibn `Abbas then said, "Only Allah makes one
laugh or cry." Ibn `Umar did not say anything after
that.</english-text>
</hadith>
