<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1254</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1295</hadith-number>
<chapter>Funerals (Al-Janaa'iz) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11013, 10554, 9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عامر بن سعد بن أبي وقاص، عن أبيه رضى الله عنه قال كان رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يعودني عام حجة الوداع من وجع اشتد بي فقلت إني قد بلغ
بي من الوجع وأنا ذو مال، ولا يرثني إلا ابنة، أفأتصدق بثلثى مالي قال
‏"‏ لا ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت بالشطر فقال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ الثلث والثلث
كبير أو كثير إنك أن تذر ورثتك أغنياء خير من أن تذرهم عالة يتكففون
الناس، وإنك لن تنفق نفقة تبتغي بها وجه الله إلا أجرت بها، حتى ما
تجعل في في امرأتك ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت يا رسول الله، أخلف بعد أصحابي قال ‏"‏
إنك لن تخلف فتعمل عملا صالحا إلا ازددت به درجة ورفعة، ثم لعلك أن
تخلف حتى ينتفع بك أقوام ويضر بك آخرون، اللهم أمض لأصحابي هجرتهم،
ولا تردهم على أعقابهم، لكن البائس سعد ابن خولة، يرثي له رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن مات بمكة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Amir bin Sa`d bin Abi Waqqas: That his
father said, "In the year of the last Hajj of the Prophet I became
seriously ill and the Prophet used to visit me inquiring about my
health. I told him, 'I am reduced to this state because of illness
and I am wealthy and have no inheritors except a daughter, (In this
narration the name of 'Amir bin Sa`d is mentioned and in fact it is
a mistake; the narrator is `Aisha bint Sa`d bin Abi Waqqas). Should
I give two-thirds of my property in charity?' He said, 'No.' I
asked, 'Half?' He said, 'No.' then he added, 'Onethird, and even
one-third is much. You'd better leave your inheritors wealthy
rather than leaving them poor, begging others. You will get a
reward for whatever you spend for Allah's sake, even for what you
put in your wife's mouth.' I said, 'O Allah's Apostle! Will I be
left alone after my companions have gone?' He said, 'If you are
left behind, whatever good deeds you will do will upgrade you and
raise you high. And perhaps you will have a long life so that some
people will be benefited by you while others will be harmed by you.
O Allah! Complete the emigration of my companions and do not turn
them renegades.' But Allah's Apostle felt sorry for poor Sa`d bin
Khaula as he died in Mecca." (but Sa`d bin Abi Waqqas lived long
after the Prophet (p.b.u.h).)</english-text>
</hadith>
