<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1314</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>23</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1360</hadith-number>
<chapter>Funerals (Al-Janaa'iz) - كتاب الجنائز</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 11002,
2070</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق، أخبرنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، قال حدثني أبي،
عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني سعيد بن المسيب، عن أبيه، أنه أخبره
أنه، لما حضرت أبا طالب الوفاة جاءه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فوجد عنده أبا جهل بن هشام، وعبد الله بن أبي أمية بن المغيرة، قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأبي طالب ‏"‏ يا عم، قل لا إله إلا
الله، كلمة أشهد لك بها عند الله ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أبو جهل وعبد الله بن
أبي أمية يا أبا طالب، أترغب عن ملة عبد المطلب فلم يزل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يعرضها عليه، ويعودان بتلك المقالة، حتى قال أبو طالب
آخر ما كلمهم هو على ملة عبد المطلب، وأبى أن يقول لا إله إلا الله‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما والله لأستغفرن لك، ما لم
أنه عنك ‏"‏‏.‏ فأنزل الله تعالى فيه ‏{‏ما كان للنبي‏}‏
الآية‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id bin Al-Musaiyab from his father: When
the time of the death of Abu Talib approached, Allah's Apostle went
to him and found Abu Jahl bin Hisham and `Abdullah bin Abi Umaiya
bin Al-Mughira by his side. Allah's Apostle said to Abu Talib, "O
uncle! Say: None has the right to be worshipped but Allah, a
sentence with which I shall be a witness (i.e. argue) for you
before Allah. Abu Jahl and `Abdullah bin Abi Umaiya said, "O Abu
Talib! Are you going to denounce the religion of `Abdul Muttalib?"
Allah's Apostle kept on inviting Abu Talib to say it (i.e. 'None
has the right to be worshipped but Allah') while they (Abu Jahl and
`Abdullah) kept on repeating their statement till Abu Talib said as
his last statement that he was on the religion of `Abdul Muttalib
and refused to say, 'None has the right to be worshipped but
Allah.' (Then Allah's Apostle said, "I will keep on asking Allah's
forgiveness for you unless I am forbidden (by Allah) to do so." So
Allah revealed (the verse) concerning him (i.e. It is not fitting
for the Prophet and those who believe that they should invoke
(Allah) for forgiveness for pagans even though they be of kin,
after it has become clear to them that they are companions of the
fire (9.113).</english-text>
</hadith>
