<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1422</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11061, 11197, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحكم بن نافع، أخبرنا شعيب، حدثنا أبو الزناد، أن
عبد الرحمن بن هرمز الأعرج، حدثه أنه، سمع أبا هريرة رضى الله عنه
يقول قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تأتي الإبل على صاحبها، على
خير ما كانت، إذا هو لم يعط فيها حقها، تطؤه بأخفافها، وتأتي الغنم
على صاحبها على خير ما كانت، إذا لم يعط فيها حقها، تطؤه بأظلافها،
وتنطحه بقرونها ‏"‏‏.‏ وقال ‏"‏ ومن حقها أن تحلب على الماء ‏"‏‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ ولا يأتي أحدكم يوم القيامة بشاة يحملها على رقبته لها يعار،
فيقول يا محمد‏.‏ فأقول لا أملك لك شيئا قد بلغت‏.‏ ولا يأتي ببعير،
يحمله على رقبته له رغاء، فيقول يا محمد‏.‏ فأقول لا أملك لك شيئا قد
بلغت ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: The Prophet said, "(On the Day
of Resurrection) camels will come to their owner in the best state
of health they have ever had (in the world), and if he had not paid
their Zakat (in the world) then they would tread him with their
feet; and similarly, sheep will come to their owner in the best
state of health they have ever had in the world, and if he had not
paid their Zakat, then they would tread him with their hooves and
would butt him with their horns." The Prophet added, "One of their
rights is that they should be milked while water is kept in front
of them." The Prophet added, "I do not want anyone of you to come
to me on the Day of Resurrection, carrying over his neck a sheep
that will be bleating. Such a person will (then) say, 'O Muhammad!
(please intercede for me,) I will say to him. 'I can't help you,
for I conveyed Allah's Message to you.' Similarly, I do not want
anyone of you to come to me carrying over his neck a camel that
will be grunting. Such a person (then) will say "O Muhammad!
(please intercede for me)." I will say to him, "I can't help you
for I conveyed Allah's message to you."</english-text>
</hadith>
