<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1427</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30157, 20246, 11286, 11112, 30313, 20250, 20258,
11286, 11318, 11112</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عياش، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، حدثنا الجريري، عن أبي
العلاء، عن الأحنف بن قيس، قال جلست‏.‏ وحدثني إسحاق بن منصور، أخبرنا
عبد الصمد، قال حدثني أبي، حدثنا الجريري، حدثنا أبو العلاء بن
الشخير، أن الأحنف بن قيس، حدثهم قال جلست إلى ملإ من قريش، فجاء رجل
خشن الشعر والثياب والهيئة حتى قام عليهم فسلم ثم قال بشر الكانزين
برضف يحمى عليه في نار جهنم، ثم يوضع على حلمة ثدى أحدهم حتى يخرج من
نغض كتفه، ويوضع على نغض كتفه حتى يخرج من حلمة ثديه يتزلزل، ثم ولى
فجلس إلى سارية، وتبعته وجلست إليه، وأنا لا أدري من هو فقلت له لا
أرى القوم إلا قد كرهوا الذي قلت‏.‏ قال إنهم لا يعقلون شيئا‏.‏ قال
لي خليلي قال قلت من خليلك قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا أبا
ذر أتبصر أحدا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فنظرت إلى الشمس ما بقي من النهار وأنا أرى
أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يرسلني في حاجة له، قلت نعم‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ ما أحب أن لي مثل أحد ذهبا أنفقه كله إلا ثلاثة دنانير ‏"‏‏.‏ وإن
هؤلاء لا يعقلون، إنما يجمعون الدنيا‏.‏ لا والله لا أسألهم دنيا، ولا
أستفتيهم عن دين حتى ألقى الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Ahnaf bin Qais: While I was sitting with
some people from Quraish, a man with very rough hair, clothes, and
appearance came and stood in front of us, greeted us and said,
"Inform those who hoard wealth, that a stone will be heated in the
Hell-fire and will be put on the nipples of their breasts till it
comes out from the bones of their shoulders and then put on the
bones of their shoulders till it comes through the nipples of their
breasts the stone will be moving and hitting." After saying that,
the person retreated and sat by the side of the pillar, I followed
him and sat beside him, and I did not know who he was. I said to
him, "I think the people disliked what you had said." He said,
"These people do not understand anything, although my friend told
me." I asked, "Who is your friend?" He said, "The Prophet said (to
me), 'O Abu Dhar! Do you see the mountain of Uhud?' And on that I
(Abu Dhar) started looking towards the sun to judge how much
remained of the day as I thought that Allah's Apostle wanted to
send me to do something for him and I said, 'Yes!' He said, 'I do
not love to have gold equal to the mountain of Uhud unless I spend
it all (in Allah's cause) except three Dinars (pounds). These
people do not understand and collect worldly wealth. No, by Allah,
Neither I ask them for worldly benefits nor am I in need of their
religious advice till I meet Allah, The Honorable, The Majestic."
'</english-text>
</hadith>
