<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1434</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20241, 11651, 212</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا أبو عاصم النبيل، أخبرنا
سعدان بن بشر، حدثنا أبو مجاهد، حدثنا محل بن خليفة الطائي، قال سمعت
عدي بن حاتم رضى الله عنه يقول كنت عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فجاءه رجلان أحدهما يشكو العيلة، والآخر يشكو قطع السبيل، فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما قطع السبيل فإنه لا يأتي عليك إلا
قليل حتى تخرج العير إلى مكة بغير خفير، وأما العيلة فإن الساعة لا
تقوم حتى يطوف أحدكم بصدقته لا يجد من يقبلها منه، ثم ليقفن أحدكم بين
يدى الله ليس بينه وبينه حجاب ولا ترجمان يترجم له، ثم ليقولن له ألم
أوتك مالا فليقولن بلى‏.‏ ثم ليقولن ألم أرسل إليك رسولا فليقولن
بلى‏.‏ فينظر عن يمينه فلا يرى إلا النار، ثم ينظر عن شماله فلا يرى
إلا النار، فليتقين أحدكم النار ولو بشق تمرة، فإن لم يجد فبكلمة طيبة
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Adi bin Hatim: While I was sitting with
Allah's Apostle (p.b.u.h) two person came to him; one of them
complained about his poverty and the other complained about the
prevalence of robberies. Allah's Apostle said, "As regards stealing
and robberies, there will shortly come a time when a caravan will
go to Mecca (from Medina) without any guard. And regarding poverty,
The Hour (Day of Judgment) will not be established till one of you
wanders about with his object of charity and will not find anybody
to accept it And (no doubt) each one of you will stand in front of
Allah and there will be neither a curtain nor an interpreter
between him and Allah, and Allah will ask him, 'Did not I give you
wealth?' He will reply in the affirmative. Allah will further ask,
'Didn't send a messenger to you?' And again that person will reply
in the affirmative Then he will look to his right and he will see
nothing but Hell-fire, and then he will look to his left and will
see nothing but Hell-fire. And so, any (each one) of you should
save himself from the fire even by giving half of a date-fruit (in
charity). And if you do not find a hall datefruit, then (you can do
it through saying) a good pleasant word (to your brethren). (See
Hadith No. 793 Vol. 4).</english-text>
</hadith>
