<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>138</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>138</hadith-number>
<chapter>Ablutions (Wudu') - كتاب الوضوء</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11081, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، قال حدثنا سفيان، عن عمرو، قال
أخبرني كريب، عن ابن عباس، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم نام حتى نفخ
ثم صلى وربما قال اضطجع حتى نفخ ثم قام فصلى‏.‏ ثم حدثنا به سفيان مرة
بعد مرة عن عمرو عن كريب عن ابن عباس قال بت عند خالتي ميمونة ليلة،
فقام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم من الليل، فلما كان في بعض الليل قام
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فتوضأ من شن معلق وضوءا خفيفا يخففه عمرو
ويقلله وقام يصلي فتوضأت نحوا مما توضأ، ثم جئت فقمت عن يساره وربما
قال سفيان عن شماله فحولني فجعلني عن يمينه، ثم صلى ما شاء الله، ثم
اضطجع، فنام حتى نفخ، ثم أتاه المنادي فآذنه بالصلاة، فقام معه إلى
الصلاة، فصلى ولم يتوضأ‏.‏ قلنا لعمرو إن ناسا يقولون إن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم تنام عينه ولا ينام قلبه‏.‏ قال عمرو سمعت عبيد بن
عمير يقول رؤيا الأنبياء وحى، ثم قرأ ‏{‏إني أرى في المنام أني
أذبحك‏}‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Kuraib: Ibn `Abbas said, "The Prophet slept
till he snored and then prayed (or probably lay till his breath
sounds were heard and then got up and prayed)." Ibn `Abbas added:
"I stayed overnight in the house of my aunt, Maimuna, the Prophet
slept for a part of the night, (See Fath-al-Bari page 249, Vol. 1),
and late in the night, he got up and performed ablution from a
hanging water skin, a light (perfect) ablution and stood up for the
prayer. I, too, performed a similar ablution, then I went and stood
on his left. He drew me to his right and prayed as much as Allah
wished, and again lay and slept till his breath sounds were heard.
Later on the Mu'adh-dhin (call maker for the prayer) came to him
and informed him that it was time for Prayer. The Prophet went with
him for the prayer without performing a new ablution." (Sufyan said
to `Amr that some people said, "The eyes of Allah's Apostle sleep
but his heart does not sleep." `Amr replied, "I heard `Ubaid bin
`Umar saying that the dreams of Prophets were Divine Inspiration,
and then he recited the verse: 'I (Abraham) see in a dream, (O my
son) that I offer you in sacrifice (to Allah)." (37.102) (See
Hadith No. 183)</english-text>
</hadith>
