<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1477</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>11270, 19, 20436</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله بن المثنى الأنصاري، قال حدثني
أبي قال، حدثني ثمامة بن عبد الله بن أنس، أن أنسا، حدثه أن أبا بكر
رضى الله عنه كتب له هذا الكتاب لما وجهه إلى البحرين بسم الله الرحمن
الرحيم ‏"‏ هذه فريضة الصدقة التي فرض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
على المسلمين، والتي أمر الله بها رسوله، فمن سئلها من المسلمين على
وجهها فليعطها، ومن سئل فوقها فلا يعط في أربع وعشرين من الإبل فما
دونها من الغنم من كل خمس شاة، إذا بلغت خمسا وعشرين إلى خمس وثلاثين
ففيها بنت مخاض أنثى، فإذا بلغت ستا وثلاثين إلى خمس وأربعين ففيها
بنت لبون أنثى، فإذا بلغت ستا وأربعين إلى ستين ففيها حقة طروقة
الجمل، فإذا بلغت واحدة وستين إلى خمس وسبعين ففيها جذعة، فإذا بلغت
يعني ستا وسبعين إلى تسعين ففيها بنتا لبون، فإذا بلغت إحدى وتسعين
إلى عشرين ومائة ففيها حقتان طروقتا الجمل، فإذا زادت على عشرين ومائة
ففي كل أربعين بنت لبون، وفي كل خمسين حقة، ومن لم يكن معه إلا أربع
من الإبل فليس فيها صدقة، إلا أن يشاء ربها، فإذا بلغت خمسا من الإبل
ففيها شاة، وفي صدقة الغنم في سائمتها إذا كانت أربعين إلى عشرين
ومائة شاة، فإذا زادت على عشرين ومائة إلى مائتين شاتان، فإذا زادت
على مائتين إلى ثلاثمائة ففيها ثلاث، فإذا زادت على ثلاثمائة ففي كل
مائة شاة، فإذا كانت سائمة الرجل ناقصة من أربعين شاة واحدة فليس فيها
صدقة، إلا أن يشاء ربها، وفي الرقة ربع العشر، فإن لم تكن إلا تسعين
ومائة فليس فيها شىء، إلا أن يشاء ربها ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: When Abu Bakr; sent me to (collect the
Zakat from) Bahrain, he wrote to me the following:-- (In the name
of Allah, the Beneficent, the Merciful). These are the orders for
compulsory charity (Zakat) which Allah's Apostle had made
obligatory for every Muslim, and which Allah had ordered His
Apostle to observe: Whoever amongst the Muslims is asked to pay
Zakat accordingly, he should pay it (to the Zakat collector) and
whoever is asked more than that (what is specified in this script)
he should not pay it; for twenty-four camels or less, sheep are to
be paid as Zakat; for every five camels one sheep is to be paid,
and if there are between twenty-five to thirty-five camels, one
Bint Makhad is to be paid; and if they are between thirty-six to
forty-five (camels), one Bint Labun is to be paid; and if they are
between forty-six to sixty (camels), one Hiqqa is to be paid; and
if the number is between sixty-one to seventy-five (camels), one
Jadha is to be paid; and if the number is between seventy-six to
ninety (camels), two Bint Labuns are to be paid; and if they are
from ninety-one to one-hundredand twenty (camels), two Hiqqas are
to be paid; and if they are over one-hundred and-twenty (camels),
for every forty (over one-hundred-and-twenty) one Bint Labun is to
be paid, and for every fifty camels (over one-hundred-and-twenty)
one Hiqqa is to be paid; and who ever has got only four camels, has
to pay nothing as Zakat, but if the owner of these four camels
wants to give something, he can. If the number of camels increases
to five, the owner has to pay one sheep as Zakat. As regards the
Zakat for the (flock) of sheep; if they are between forty and
one-hundred-and-twenty sheep, one sheep is to be paid; and if they
are between one-hundred-and-twenty to two hundred (sheep), two
sheep are to be paid; and if they are between two-hundred to
three-hundred (sheep), three sheep are to be paid; and for over
three-hundred sheep, for every extra hundred sheep, one sheep is to
be paid as Zakat. And if somebody has got less than forty sheep, no
Zakat is required, but if he wants to give, he can. For silver the
Zakat is one-fortieth of the lot (i.e. 2.5%), and if its value is
less than two-hundred Dirhams, Zakat is not required, but if the
owner wants to pay he can.'</english-text>
</hadith>
