<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1484</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه يقول كان أبو
طلحة أكثر الأنصار بالمدينة مالا من نخل، وكان أحب أمواله إليه بيرحاء
وكانت مستقبلة المسجد، وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يدخلها
ويشرب من ماء فيها طيب قال أنس فلما أنزلت هذه الآية ‏{‏لن تنالوا
البر حتى تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏ قام أبو طلحة إلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله‏.‏ إن الله تبارك وتعالى يقول ‏{‏لن
تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏ وإن أحب أموالي إلى بيرحاء،
وإنها صدقة لله أرجو برها وذخرها عند الله، فضعها يا رسول الله حيث
أراك الله‏.‏ قال فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بخ، ذلك مال
رابح، ذلك مال رابح، وقد سمعت ما قلت وإني أرى أن تجعلها في الأقربين
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أبو طلحة أفعل يا رسول الله‏.‏ فقسمها أبو طلحة في أقاربه
وبني عمه‏.‏ تابعه روح‏.‏ وقال يحيى بن يحيى وإسماعيل عن مالك
رايح‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Is-haq bin `Abdullah bin Al Talha: I heard
Anas bin Malik saying, "Abu Talha had more property of date-palm
trees gardens than any other amongst the Ansar in Medina and the
most beloved of them to him was Bairuha garden, and it was in front
of the Mosque of the Prophet . Allah's Apostle used to go there and
used to drink its nice water." Anas added, "When these verses were
revealed:--'By no means shall you Attain righteousness unless You
spend (in charity) of that Which you love. ' (3.92) Abu Talha said
to Allah's Apostle 'O Allah's Apostle! Allah, the Blessed, the
Superior says: By no means shall you attain righteousness, unless
you spend (in charity) of that which you love. And no doubt,
Bairuha' garden is the most beloved of all my property to me. So I
want to give it in charity in Allah's Cause. I expect its reward
from Allah. O Allah's Apostle! Spend it where Allah makes you think
it feasible.' On that Allah's Apostle said, 'Bravo! It is useful
property. I have heard what you have said (O Abu Talha), and I
think it would be proper if you gave it to your Kith and kin.' Abu
Talha said, I will do so, O Allah's Apostle.' Then Abu Talha
distributed that garden amongst his relatives and his
cousins."</english-text>
</hadith>
