<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1488</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30177, 20295, 11449, 11229, 11020, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا معاذ بن فضالة، حدثنا هشام، عن يحيى، عن هلال بن
أبي ميمونة، حدثنا عطاء بن يسار، أنه سمع أبا سعيد الخدري رضى الله
عنه يحدث أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم جلس ذات يوم على المنبر وجلسنا
حوله فقال ‏"‏ إني مما أخاف عليكم من بعدي ما يفتح عليكم من زهرة
الدنيا وزينتها ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رجل يا رسول الله أويأتي الخير بالشر فسكت
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقيل له ما شأنك تكلم النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ولا يكلمك فرأينا أنه ينزل عليه‏.‏ قال فمسح عنه الرحضاء فقال
‏"‏ أين السائل ‏"‏ وكأنه حمده‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إنه لا يأتي الخير بالشر،
وإن مما ينبت الربيع يقتل أو يلم إلا آكلة الخضراء، أكلت حتى إذا
امتدت خاصرتاها استقبلت عين الشمس، فثلطت وبالت ورتعت، وإن هذا المال
خضرة حلوة، فنعم صاحب المسلم ما أعطى منه المسكين واليتيم وابن السبيل
أو كما قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وإنه من يأخذه بغير حقه كالذي
يأكل ولا يشبع، ويكون شهيدا عليه يوم القيامة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: Once the Prophet sat on
a pulpit and we sat around him. Then he said, "The things I am
afraid of most for your sake (concerning what will befall you after
me) is the pleasures and splendors of the world and its beauties
which will be disclosed to you." Somebody said, "O Allah's Apostle!
Can the good bring forth evil?" The Prophet remained silent for a
while. It was said to that person, "What is wrong with you? You are
talking to the Prophet (p.b.u.h) while he is not talking to you."
Then we noticed that he was being inspired divinely. Then the
Prophet wiped off his sweat and said, "Where is the questioner?" It
seemed as if the Prophet liked his question. Then he said, "Good
never brings forth evil. Indeed it is like what grows on the banks
of a water-stream which either kill or make the animals sick,
except if an animal eats its fill the Khadira (a kind of vegetable)
and then faces the sun, and then defecates and urinates and grazes
again. No doubt this wealth is sweet and green. Blessed is the
wealth of a Muslim from which he gives to the poor, the orphans and
to needy travelers. (Or the Prophet said something similar to it)
No doubt, whoever takes it illegally will be like the one who eats
but is never satisfied, and his wealth will be a witness against
him on the Day of Resurrection."</english-text>
</hadith>
