<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1489</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30204, 20317, 11060, 11353, 20377</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمر بن حفص، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا الأعمش، قال حدثني
شقيق، عن عمرو بن الحارث، عن زينب، امرأة عبد الله رضى الله عنهما قال
فذكرته لإبراهيم فحدثني إبراهيم عن أبي عبيدة عن عمرو بن الحارث عن
زينب امرأة عبد الله بمثله سواء، قالت كنت في المسجد فرأيت النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ تصدقن ولو من حليكن ‏"‏‏.‏ وكانت زينب تنفق
على عبد الله وأيتام في حجرها، قال فقالت لعبد الله سل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أيجزي عني أن أنفق عليك وعلى أيتامي في حجري من الصدقة
فقال سلي أنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فانطلقت إلى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فوجدت امرأة من الأنصار على الباب، حاجتها مثل
حاجتي، فمر علينا بلال فقلنا سل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أيجزي عني
أن أنفق على زوجي وأيتام لي في حجري وقلنا لا تخبر بنا‏.‏ فدخل فسأله
فقال ‏"‏ من هما ‏"‏‏.‏ قال زينب قال ‏"‏ أى الزيانب ‏"‏‏.‏ قال امرأة
عبد الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ نعم لها أجران أجر القرابة وأجر الصدقة
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amr bin Al-Harith: Zainab, the wife of
`Abdullah said, "I was in the Mosque and saw the Prophet (p.b.u.h)
saying, 'O women ! Give alms even from your ornaments.' " Zainab
used to provide for `Abdullah and those orphans who were under her
protection. So she said to `Abdullah, "Will you ask Allah's Apostle
whether it will be sufficient for me to spend part of the Zakat on
you and the orphans who are under my protection?" He replied "Will
you yourself ask Allah's Apostle ?" (Zainab added): So I went to
the Prophet and I saw there an Ansari woman who was standing at the
door (of the Prophet ) with a similar problem as mine. Bilal passed
by us and we asked him, 'Ask the Prophet whether it is permissible
for me to spend (the Zakat) on my husband and the orphans under my
protection.' And we requested Bilal not to inform the Prophet about
us. So Bilal went inside and asked the Prophet regarding our
problem. The Prophet (p.b.u.h) asked, "Who are those two?" Bilal
replied that she was Zainab. The Prophet said, "Which Zainab?"
Bilal said, "The wife of `Abdullah (bin Mas`ud)." The Prophet said,
"Yes, (it is sufficient for her) and she will receive a double
rewards (for that): One for helping relatives, and the other for
giving Zakat."</english-text>
</hadith>
