<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1502</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30109, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 10554,
9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن غرير الزهري، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، عن
أبيه، عن صالح بن كيسان، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عامر بن سعد، عن
أبيه، قال أعطى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رهطا وأنا جالس فيهم قال
فترك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منهم رجلا لم يعطه، وهو أعجبهم
إلى، فقمت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فساررته فقلت ما لك عن
فلان والله إني لأراه مؤمنا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أو مسلما ‏"‏ قال فسكت قليلا
ثم غلبني ما أعلم فيه فقلت يا رسول الله‏.‏ ما لك عن فلان والله إني
لأراه مؤمنا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أو مسلما ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فسكت قليلا ثم غلبني ما
أعلم فيه فقلت يا رسول الله ما لك عن فلان والله إني لأراه مؤمنا‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ أو مسلما يعني فقال إني لأعطي الرجل وغيره أحب إلى منه، خشية
أن يكب في النار على وجهه ‏"‏‏.‏ وعن أبيه عن صالح عن إسماعيل بن محمد
أنه قال سمعت أبي يحدث هذا فقال في حديثه فضرب رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بيده فجمع بين عنقي وكتفي ثم قال ‏"‏ أقبل أى سعد إني لأعطي
الرجل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله ‏{‏فكبكبوا‏}‏ قلبوا ‏{‏مكبا‏}‏ أكب
الرجل إذا كان فعله غير واقع على أحد، فإذا وقع الفعل قلت كبه الله
لوجهه، وكببته أنا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`d (bin Abi Waqqas): Allah's Apostle
distributed something (from the resources of Zakat) amongst a group
of people while I was sitting amongst them, but he left a man whom
I considered the best of the lot. So, I went up to Allah's Apostle
and asked him secretly, "Why have you left that person? By Allah! I
consider him a believer." The Prophet said, "Or merely a Muslim
(Who surrender to Allah)." I remained quiet for a while but could
not help repeating my question because of what I knew about him. I
said, "O Allah's Apostle! Why have you left that person? By Allah!
I consider him a believer. " The Prophet said, "Or merely a
Muslim." I remained quiet for a while but could not help repeating
my question because of what I knew about him. I said, "O Allah's
Apostle! Why have you left that person? By Allah! I consider him a
believer." The Prophet said, "Or merely a Muslim." Then Allah's
Apostle (p.b.u.h) said, "I give to a person while another is dearer
to me, for fear that he may be thrown in the Hell-fire on his face
(by reneging from Islam)."</english-text>
</hadith>
