<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>24</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>24</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1505</hadith-number>
<chapter>Obligatory Charity Tax (Zakat) - كتاب الزكاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30138, 20299, 11210, 1457</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سهل بن بكار، حدثنا وهيب، عن عمرو بن يحيى، عن
عباس الساعدي، عن أبي حميد الساعدي، قال غزونا مع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم غزوة تبوك فلما جاء وادي القرى إذا امرأة في حديقة لها فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لأصحابه ‏"‏ اخرصوا ‏"‏‏.‏ وخرص رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم عشرة أوسق فقال لها ‏"‏ أحصي ما يخرج منها ‏"‏‏.‏
فلما أتينا تبوك قال ‏"‏ أما إنها ستهب الليلة ريح شديدة فلا يقومن
أحد، ومن كان معه بعير فليعقله ‏"‏‏.‏ فعقلناها وهبت ريح شديدة فقام
رجل فألقته بجبل طيئ وأهدى ملك أيلة للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بغلة
بيضاء، وكساه بردا وكتب له ببحرهم فلما أتى وادي القرى قال للمرأة ‏"‏
كم جاء حديقتك ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت عشرة أوسق خرص رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني متعجل إلى المدينة، فمن
أراد منكم أن يتعجل معي فليتعجل ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما قال ابن بكار كلمة معناها
أشرف على المدينة قال ‏"‏ هذه طابة ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما رأى أحدا قال ‏"‏ هذا
جبيل يحبنا ونحبه، ألا أخبركم بخير دور الأنصار ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا بلى‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ دور بني النجار، ثم دور بني عبد الأشهل، ثم دور بني ساعدة، أو
دور بني الحارث بن الخزرج، وفي كل دور الأنصار يعني خيرا ‏"‏‏.‏ وقال
سليمان بن بلال حدثني عمرو، ‏"‏ ثم دار بني الحارث، ثم بني ساعدة
‏"‏‏.‏ وقال سليمان عن سعد بن سعيد، عن عمارة بن غزية، عن عباس، عن
أبيه، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ أحد جبل يحبنا ونحبه
‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله كل بستان عليه حائط فهو حديقة، وما لم يكن
عليه حائط لم يقل حديقة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Humaid As-Sa`idi: We took part in the
holy battle of Tabuk in the company of the Prophet and when we
arrived at the Wadi-al-Qura, there was a woman in her garden. The
Prophet asked his companions to estimate the amount of the fruits
in the garden, and Allah's Apostle estimated it at ten Awsuq (One
Wasaq = 60 Sa's) and 1 Sa'= 3 kg. approximately). The Prophet said
to that lady, "Check what your garden will yield." When we reached
Tabuk, the Prophet said, "There will be a strong wind tonight and
so no one should stand and whoever has a camel, should fasten it."
So we fastened our camels. A strong wind blew at night and a man
stood up and he was blown away to a mountain called Taiy, The King
of Aila sent a white mule and a sheet for wearing to the Prophet as
a present, and wrote to the Prophet that his people would stay in
their place (and will pay Jizya taxation.) (1) When the Prophet
reached Wadi-al- Qura he asked that woman how much her garden had
yielded. She said, "Ten Awsuq," and that was what Allah's Apostle
had estimated. Then the Prophet said, "I want to reach Medina
quickly, and whoever among you wants to accompany me, should hurry
up." The sub-narrator Ibn Bakkar said something which meant: When
the Prophet (p.b.u.h) saw Medina he said, "This is Taba." And when
he saw the mountain of Uhud, he said, "This mountain loves us and
we love it. Shall I tell you of the best amongst the Ansar?" They
replied in the affirmative. He said, "The family of Bani-n-Najjar,
and then the family of Bani Sa`ida or Bani Al-Harith bin
Al-Khazraj. (The above-mentioned are the best) but there is
goodness in all the families of Ansar."</english-text>
</hadith>
