<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1581</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، حدثنا مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
قالت خرجنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في حجة الوداع، فأهللنا بعمرة
ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من كان معه هدى فليهل بالحج مع
العمرة، ثم لا يحل حتى يحل منهما جميعا ‏"‏ فقدمت مكة وأنا حائض، ولم
أطف بالبيت ولا بين الصفا والمروة، فشكوت ذلك إلى النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال ‏"‏ انقضي رأسك وامتشطي، وأهلي بالحج، ودعي العمرة ‏"‏‏.‏
ففعلت فلما قضينا الحج أرسلني النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مع عبد الرحمن
بن أبي بكر إلى التنعيم فاعتمرت فقال ‏"‏ هذه مكان عمرتك ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت
فطاف الذين كانوا أهلوا بالعمرة بالبيت وبين الصفا والمروة، ثم حلوا،
ثم طافوا طوافا واحدا بعد أن رجعوا من منى، وأما الذين جمعوا الحج
والعمرة فإنما طافوا طوافا واحدا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha: (the wife of the Prophet (p.b.u.h) We
set out with the Prophet in his last Hajj and we assumed Ihram for
Umra. The Prophet then said, "Whoever has the Hadi with him should
assume Ihram for Hajj along with `Umra and should not finish the
Ihram till he finishes both." I was menstruating when I reached
Mecca, and so I neither did Tawaf round the Ka`ba nor Tawaf between
Safa and Marwa. I complained about that to the Prophet on which he
replied, "Undo and comb your head hair, and assume Ihram for Hajj
(only) and leave the Umra." So, I did so. When we had performed the
Hajj, the Prophet sent me with my brother `Abdur-Rahman bin Abu
Bakr to Tan`im. So I performed the `Umra. The Prophet said to me,
"This `Umra is instead of your missed one." Those who had assumed
Ihram for `Umra (Hajj-atTamattu) performed Tawaf round the Ka`ba
and between Safa and Marwa and then finished their Ihram. After
returning from Mina, they performed another Tawaf (between Safa and
Marwa). Those who had assumed Ihram for Hajj and `Umra together
(Hajj-al-Qiran) performed only one Tawaf (between Safa and
Marwa).</english-text>
</hadith>
