<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1585</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20254, 20156, 10535, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، قال حدثني أبو بكر الحنفي، حدثنا
أفلح بن حميد، سمعت القاسم بن محمد، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت
خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في أشهر الحج، وليالي الحج
وحرم الحج، فنزلنا بسرف قالت فخرج إلى أصحابه فقال ‏"‏ من لم يكن منكم
معه هدى فأحب أن يجعلها عمرة فليفعل، ومن كان معه الهدى فلا ‏"‏‏.‏
قالت فالآخذ بها والتارك لها من أصحابه قالت فأما رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ورجال من أصحابه فكانوا أهل قوة، وكان معهم الهدى، فلم
يقدروا على العمرة قالت فدخل على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنا
أبكي فقال ‏"‏ ما يبكيك يا هنتاه ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت سمعت قولك لأصحابك فمنعت
العمرة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وما شأنك ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت لا أصلي‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فلا يضيرك،
إنما أنت امرأة من بنات آدم كتب الله عليك ما كتب عليهن، فكوني في
حجتك، فعسى الله أن يرزقكيها ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فخرجنا في حجته حتى قدمنا
منى فطهرت، ثم خرجت من منى فأفضت بالبيت قالت ثم خرجت معه في النفر
الآخر حتى نزل المحصب، ونزلنا معه فدعا عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر فقال
‏"‏ اخرج بأختك من الحرم، فلتهل بعمرة ثم افرغا، ثم ائتيا ها هنا،
فإني أنظركما حتى تأتياني ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فخرجنا حتى إذا فرغت، وفرغت من
الطواف ثم جئته بسحر فقال ‏"‏ هل فرغتم ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم‏.‏ فآذن
بالرحيل في أصحابه، فارتحل الناس فمر متوجها إلى المدينة‏.‏ ضير من
ضار يضير ضيرا، ويقال ضار يضور ضورا وضر يضر ضرا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Qasim bin Muhammad: ' Aisha said, "We set
out with Allah's Apostles in the months of Hajj, and (in) the
nights of Hajj, and at the time and places of Hajj and in a state
of Hajj. We dismounted at Sarif (a village six miles from Mecca).
The Prophet then addressed his companions and said, "Anyone who has
not got the Hadi and likes to do Umra instead of Hajj may do so
(i.e. Hajj-al-Tamattu`) and anyone who has got the Hadi should not
finish the Ihram after performing ' `Umra). (i.e. Hajj-al-Qiran).
Aisha added, "The companions of the Prophet obeyed the above
(order) and some of them (i.e. who did not have Hadi) finished
their Ihram after Umra." Allah's Apostle and some of his companions
were resourceful and had the Hadi with them, they could not perform
Umra (alone) (but had to perform both Hajj and Umra with one
Ihram). Aisha added, "Allah's Apostle came to me and saw me weeping
and said, "What makes you weep, O Hantah?" I replied, "I have heard
your conversation with your companions and I cannot perform the
Umra." He asked, "What is wrong with you?' I replied, ' I do not
offer the prayers (i.e. I have my menses).' He said, ' It will not
harm you for you are one of the daughters of Adam, and Allah has
written for you (this state) as He has written it for them. Keep on
with your intentions for Hajj and Allah may reward you that." Aisha
further added, "Then we proceeded for Hajj till we reached Mina and
I became clean from my menses. Then I went out from Mina and
performed Tawaf round the Ka`ba." Aisha added, "I went along with
the Prophet in his final departure (from Hajj) till he dismounted
at Al-Muhassab (a valley outside Mecca), and we too, dismounted
with him." He called ' `Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr and said to him,
' Take your sister outside the sanctuary of Mecca and let her
assume Ihram for ' `Umra, and when you had finished ' `Umra, return
to this place and I will wait for you both till you both return to
me.' " ' Aisha added, " So we went out of the sanctuary of Mecca
and after finishing from the ' `Umra and the Tawaf we returned to
the Prophet at dawn. He said, 'Have you performed the ' `Umra?' We
replied in the affirmative. So he announced the departure amongst
his companions and the people set out for the journey, and the
Prophet: too left for Medina.''</english-text>
</hadith>
