<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1593</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20348, 11613, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا أبو شهاب، قال قدمت متمتعا مكة
بعمرة فدخلنا قبل التروية بثلاثة أيام، فقال لي أناس من أهل مكة تصير
الآن حجتك مكية‏.‏ فدخلت على عطاء أستفتيه فقال حدثني جابر بن عبد
الله رضى الله عنهما أنه حج مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم ساق
البدن معه، وقد أهلوا بالحج مفردا، فقال لهم ‏"‏ أحلوا من إحرامكم
بطواف البيت وبين الصفا والمروة، وقصروا ثم أقيموا حلالا، حتى إذا كان
يوم التروية فأهلوا بالحج، واجعلوا التي قدمتم بها متعة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا
كيف نجعلها متعة وقد سمينا الحج فقال ‏"‏ افعلوا ما أمرتكم، فلولا أني
سقت الهدى لفعلت مثل الذي أمرتكم، ولكن لا يحل مني حرام حتى يبلغ
الهدى محله ‏"‏‏.‏ ففعلوا‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله أبو شهاب ليس له مسند
إلا هذا</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Shihab: I left for Mecca for
Hajj-at-Tamattu` assuming Ihram for `Umra. I reached Mecca three
days before the day of Tarwiya (8th Dhul-Hijja). Some people of
Mecca said to me, "Your Hajj will be like the Hajj performed by the
people of Mecca (i.e. you will lose the superiority of assuming
Ihram from the Miqat). So I went to `Ata' asking him his view about
it. He said, "Jabir bin `Abdullah narrated to me, 'I performed Hajj
with Allah's Apostle on the day when he drove camels with him. The
people had assumed Ihram for Hajj-al-Ifrad. The Prophet ordered
them to finish their Ihram after Tawaf round the Ka`ba, and between
Safa and Marwa and to cut short their hair and then to stay there
(in Mecca) as non-Muhrims till the day of Tarwiya (i.e. 8th of
Dhul-Hijja) when they would assume Ihram for Hajj and they were
ordered to make the Ihram with which they had come as for `Umra
only. They asked, 'How can we make it `Umra (Tamattu`) as we have
intended to perform Hajj?' The Prophet said, 'Do what I have
ordered you. Had I not brought the Hadi with me, I would have done
the same, but I cannot finish my Ihram till the Hadi reaches its
destination (i.e. is slaughtered).' So, they did (what he ordered
them to do)."</english-text>
</hadith>
