<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1611</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30320, 20472, 11272, 11233, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا بيان بن عمرو، حدثنا يزيد، حدثنا جرير بن حازم،
حدثنا يزيد بن رومان، عن عروة، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال لها ‏"‏ يا عائشة لولا أن قومك حديث عهد بجاهلية
لأمرت بالبيت فهدم، فأدخلت فيه ما أخرج منه وألزقته بالأرض، وجعلت له
بابين بابا شرقيا وبابا غربيا، فبلغت به أساس إبراهيم ‏"‏‏.‏ فذلك
الذي حمل ابن الزبير رضى الله عنهما على هدمه‏.‏ قال يزيد وشهدت ابن
الزبير حين هدمه وبناه وأدخل فيه من الحجر، وقد رأيت أساس إبراهيم
حجارة كأسنمة الإبل‏.‏ قال جرير فقلت له أين موضعه قال أريكه الآن‏.‏
فدخلت معه الحجر فأشار إلى مكان فقال ها هنا‏.‏ قال جرير فحزرت من
الحجر ستة أذرع أو نحوها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Yazid bin Ruman from `Urwa: `Aisha said that
the Prophet said to her, "O Aisha! Were your nation not close to
the Pre-Islamic Period of Ignorance, I would have had the Ka`ba
demolished and would have included in it the portion which had been
left, and would have made it at a level with the ground and would
have made two doors for it, one towards the east and the other
towards the west, and then by doing this it would have been built
on the foundations laid by Abraham." That was what urged
Ibn-Az-Zubair to demolish the Ka`ba. Jazz said, "I saw
Ibn-Az-Zubair when he demolished and rebuilt the Ka`ba and included
in it a portion of Al-Hijr (the unroofed portion of Ka`ba which is
at present in the form of a compound towards the northwest of the
Ka`ba). I saw the original foundations of Abraham which were of
stones resembling the humps of camels." So Jarir asked Yazid,
"Where was the place of those stones?" Jazz said, "I will just now
show it to you." So Jarir accompanied Yazid and entered Al-Hijr,
and Jazz pointed to a place and said, "Here it is." Jarir said, "It
appeared to me about six cubits from Al-Hijr or so."</english-text>
</hadith>
