<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1668</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال عروة
سألت عائشة رضى الله عنها فقلت لها أرأيت قول الله تعالى ‏{‏إن الصفا
والمروة من شعائر الله فمن حج البيت أو اعتمر فلا جناح عليه أن يطوف
بهما‏}‏ فوالله ما على أحد جناح أن لا يطوف بالصفا والمروة‏.‏ قالت
بئس ما قلت يا ابن أختي إن هذه لو كانت كما أولتها عليه كانت لا جناح
عليه أن لا يتطوف بهما، ولكنها أنزلت في الأنصار، كانوا قبل أن يسلموا
يهلون لمناة الطاغية التي كانوا يعبدونها عند المشلل، فكان من أهل
يتحرج أن يطوف بالصفا والمروة، فلما أسلموا سألوا رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم عن ذلك قالوا يا رسول الله، إنا كنا نتحرج أن نطوف بين
الصفا والمروة، فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏إن الصفا والمروة من شعائر
الله‏}‏ الآية‏.‏ قالت عائشة رضى الله عنها وقد سن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم الطواف بينهما، فليس لأحد أن يترك الطواف بينهما‏.‏ ثم
أخبرت أبا بكر بن عبد الرحمن، فقال إن هذا لعلم ما كنت سمعته، ولقد
سمعت رجالا من أهل العلم، يذكرون أن الناس إلا من ذكرت عائشة ممن كان
يهل بمناة، كانوا يطوفون كلهم بالصفا والمروة، فلما ذكر الله تعالى
الطواف بالبيت، ولم يذكر الصفا والمروة في القرآن قالوا يا رسول الله
كنا نطوف بالصفا والمروة، وإن الله أنزل الطواف بالبيت، فلم يذكر
الصفا فهل علينا من حرج أن نطوف بالصفا والمروة فأنزل الله تعالى
‏{‏إن الصفا والمروة من شعائر الله‏}‏ الآية‏.‏ قال أبو بكر فأسمع هذه
الآية نزلت في الفريقين كليهما في الذين كانوا يتحرجون أن يطوفوا
بالجاهلية بالصفا والمروة، والذين يطوفون ثم تحرجوا أن يطوفوا بهما في
الإسلام من أجل أن الله تعالى أمر بالطواف بالبيت، ولم يذكر الصفا حتى
ذكر ذلك بعد ما ذكر الطواف بالبيت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa: I asked `Aisha : "How do you
interpret the statement of Allah,. : Verily! (the mountains)
As-Safa and Al-Marwa are among the symbols of Allah, and whoever
performs the Hajj to the Ka`ba or performs `Umra, it is not harmful
for him to perform Tawaf between them (Safa and Marwa.) (2.158). By
Allah! (it is evident from this revelation) there is no harm if one
does not perform Tawaf between Safa and Marwa." `Aisha said, "O, my
nephew! Your interpretation is not true. Had this interpretation of
yours been correct, the statement of Allah should have been, 'It is
not harmful for him if he does not perform Tawaf between them.' But
in fact, this divine inspiration was revealed concerning the Ansar
who used to assume lhram for worship ping an idol called "Manat"
which they used to worship at a place called Al-Mushallal before
they embraced Islam, and whoever assumed Ihram (for the idol),
would consider it not right to perform Tawaf between Safa and
Marwa. When they embraced Islam, they asked Allah's Apostle
(p.b.u.h) regarding it, saying, "O Allah's Apostle! We used to
refrain from Tawaf between Safa and Marwa." So Allah revealed:
'Verily; (the mountains) As-Safa and Al-Marwa are among the symbols
of Allah.' " Aisha added, "Surely, Allah's Apostle set the
tradition of Tawaf between Safa and Marwa, so nobody is allowed to
omit the Tawaf between them." Later on I (`Urwa) told Abu Bakr bin
`Abdur-Rahman (of `Aisha's narration) and he said, 'I have not
heard of such information, but I heard learned men saying that all
the people, except those whom `Aisha mentioned and who used to
assume lhram for the sake of Manat, used to perform Tawaf between
Safa and Marwa. When Allah referred to the Tawaf of the Ka`ba and
did not mention Safa and Marwa in the Qur'an, the people asked, 'O
Allah's Apostle! We used to perform Tawaf between Safa and Marwa
and Allah has revealed (the verses concerning) Tawaf of the Ka`ba
and has not mentioned Safa and Marwa. Is there any harm if we
perform Tawaf between Safa and Marwa?' So Allah revealed: "Verily
As-Safa and Al- Marwa are among the symbols of Allah." Abu Bakr
said, "It seems that this verse was revealed concerning the two
groups, those who used to refrain from Tawaf between Safa and Marwa
in the Pre- Islamic Period of ignorance and those who used to
perform the Tawaf then, and after embracing Islam they refrained
from the Tawaf between them as Allah had enjoined Tawaf of the
Ka`ba and did not mention Tawaf (of Safa and Marwa) till later
after mentioning the Tawaf of the Ka`ba.'</english-text>
</hadith>
