<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1677</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 30132, 20259, 11276, 11029, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد الوهاب،‏.‏ قال وقال لي
خليفة حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا حبيب المعلم، عن عطاء، عن جابر بن عبد
الله رضى الله عنهما قال أهل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم هو وأصحابه
بالحج، وليس مع أحد منهم هدى، غير النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وطلحة،
وقدم علي من اليمن، ومعه هدى فقال أهللت بما أهل به النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم‏.‏ فأمر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أصحابه أن يجعلوها عمرة،
ويطوفوا، ثم يقصروا ويحلوا، إلا من كان معه الهدى، فقالوا ننطلق إلى
منى، وذكر أحدنا يقطر، فبلغ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ لو
استقبلت من أمري ما استدبرت ما أهديت، ولولا أن معي الهدى لأحللت
‏"‏‏.‏ وحاضت عائشة رضى الله عنها فنسكت المناسك كلها، غير أنها لم
تطف بالبيت، فلما طهرت طافت بالبيت‏.‏ قالت يا رسول الله تنطلقون بحجة
وعمرة، وأنطلق بحج فأمر عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر أن يخرج معها إلى
التنعيم، فاعتمرت بعد الحج‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: The Prophet and his
companions assumed Ihram for Hajj and none except the Prophet
(p.b.u.h) and Talha had the Hadi (sacrifice) with them. `Ali
arrived from Yemen and had a Hadi with him. `Ali said, "I have
assumed Ihram for what the Prophet has done." The Prophet ordered
his companions to perform the `Umra with the lhram which they had
assumed, and after finishing Tawaf (of Ka`ba, Safa and Marwa) to
cut short their hair, and to finish their lhram except those who
had Hadi with them. They (the people) said, "How can we proceed to
Mina (for Hajj) after having sexual relations with our wives?" When
that news reached the Prophet he said, "If I had formerly known
what I came to know lately, I would not have brought the Hadi with
me. Had there been no Hadi with me, I would have finished the state
of lhram." `Aisha got her menses, so she performed all the
ceremonies of Hajj except Tawaf of the Ka`ba, and when she got
clean (from her menses), she performed Tawaf of the Ka`ba. She
said, "O Allah's Apostle! (All of you) are returning with the Hajj
and `Umra, but I am returning after performing Hajj only." So the
Prophet ordered `Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr to accompany her to
Tan`im and thus she performed the `Umra after the
Hajj.</english-text>
</hadith>
