<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1678</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30180, 20208, 11015, 11039</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مؤمل بن هشام، حدثنا إسماعيل، عن أيوب، عن حفصة،
قالت كنا نمنع عواتقنا أن يخرجن، فقدمت امرأة فنزلت قصر بني خلف،
فحدثت أن أختها كانت تحت رجل من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قد غزا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثنتى عشرة غزوة، وكانت أختي
معه في ست غزوات، قالت كنا نداوي الكلمى ونقوم على المرضى‏.‏ فسألت
أختي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت هل على إحدانا بأس إن لم يكن
لها جلباب أن لا تخرج قال ‏"‏ لتلبسها صاحبتها من جلبابها، ولتشهد
الخير، ودعوة المؤمنين ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما قدمت أم عطية رضى الله عنها سألنها
أو قالت سألناها فقالت وكانت لا تذكر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
إلا قالت بأبي‏.‏ فقلنا أسمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول كذا
وكذا قالت نعم بأبي‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ لتخرج العواتق ذوات الخدور أو العواتق
وذوات الخدور والحيض، فيشهدن الخير، ودعوة المسلمين، ويعتزل الحيض
المصلى ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت الحائض‏.‏ فقالت أو ليس تشهد عرفة، وتشهد كذا
وتشهد كذا</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hafsa: (On `Id) We used to forbid our
virgins to go out (for `Id prayer). A lady came and stayed at the
Palace of Bani Khalaf. She mentioned that her sister was married to
one of the companions of Allah's Apostle who participated in twelve
Ghazawats along with Allah's Apostle and her sister was with him in
six of them. She said, "We used to dress the wounded and look after
the patients." She (her sister) asked Allah's Apostle , "Is there
any harm for a woman to stay at home if she doesn't have a veil?"
He said, "She should cover herself with the veil of her companion
and she should take part in the good deeds and in the religious
gatherings of the believers." When Um 'Atiyya came, I asked her.
"Did you hear anything about that?" Um 'Atiyya said, "Bi Abi" and
she never mentioned the name of Allah's Apostle without saying "Bi
Abi" (i.e. 'Let my father be sacrificed for you'). We asked her,
"Have you heard Allah's Apostle saying so and so (about women)?"
She replied in the affirmative and said, "Let my father be
sacrificed for him. He told us that unmarried mature virgins who
stay often screened or unmarried young virgins and mature girls who
stay often screened should come out and take part in the good deeds
and in the religious gatherings of the believers. But the
menstruating women should keep away from the Musalla (praying
place)." I asked her, "The menstruating women?" She replied, "Don't
they present themselves at `Arafat and at such and such
places?"</english-text>
</hadith>
