<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1709</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20245, 20311, 11049, 20395</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن رجاء، حدثنا إسرائيل، عن أبي إسحاق،
عن عبد الرحمن بن يزيد، قال خرجنا مع عبد الله رضى الله عنه إلى مكة،
ثم قدمنا جمعا، فصلى الصلاتين، كل صلاة وحدها بأذان وإقامة، والعشاء
بينهما، ثم صلى الفجر حين طلع الفجر، قائل يقول طلع الفجر‏.‏ وقائل
يقول لم يطلع الفجر‏.‏ ثم قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ إن هاتين الصلاتين حولتا عن وقتهما في هذا المكان المغرب والعشاء،
فلا يقدم الناس جمعا حتى يعتموا، وصلاة الفجر هذه الساعة ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم
وقف حتى أسفر، ثم قال لو أن أمير المؤمنين أفاض الآن أصاب السنة‏.‏
فما أدري أقوله كان أسرع أم دفع عثمان رضى الله عنه فلم يزل يلبي حتى
رمى جمرة العقبة يوم النحر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdur-Rahman bin Yazid: I went out with
`Abdullah , to Mecca and when we proceeded to am' he offered the
two prayers (the Maghrib and the `Isha') together, making the Adhan
and Iqama separately for each prayer. He took his supper in between
the two prayers. He offered the Fajr prayer as soon as the day
dawned. Some people said, "The day had dawned (at the time of the
prayer)," and others said, "The day had not dawned." `Abdullah then
said, "Allah's Apostle said, 'These two prayers have been shifted
from their stated times at this place only (at Al-Muzdalifa);
first: The Maghrib and the `Isha'. So the people should not arrive
at Al-Muzdalifa till the time of the `Isha' prayer has become due.
The second prayer is the morning prayer which is offered at this
hour.' " Then `Abdullah stayed there till it became a bit brighter.
He then said, "If the chief of the believers hastened onwards to
Mina just now, then he had indeed followed the Sunna." I do not
know which proceeded the other, his (`Abdullah's) statement or the
departure of `Uthman . `Abdullah was reciting Talbiya till he threw
pebbles at the Jamrat-Al- `Aqaba on the Day of Nahr (slaughtering)
(that is the 10th of Dhul-Hijja).</english-text>
</hadith>
