<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1716</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب،
عن سالم بن عبد الله، أن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما قال تمتع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في حجة الوداع بالعمرة إلى الحج، وأهدى فساق معه
الهدى من ذي الحليفة، وبدأ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأهل
بالعمرة، ثم أهل بالحج، فتمتع الناس مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بالعمرة إلى الحج، فكان من الناس من أهدى فساق الهدى، ومنهم من لم
يهد، فلما قدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مكة، قال للناس ‏"‏ من كان
منكم أهدى فإنه لا يحل لشىء حرم منه حتى يقضي حجه، ومن لم يكن منكم
أهدى فليطف بالبيت، وبالصفا والمروة، وليقصر، وليحلل، ثم ليهل بالحج،
فمن لم يجد هديا فليصم ثلاثة أيام في الحج وسبعة إذا رجع إلى أهله
‏"‏‏.‏ فطاف حين قدم مكة، واستلم الركن أول شىء، ثم خب ثلاثة أطواف،
ومشى أربعا، فركع حين قضى طوافه بالبيت عند المقام ركعتين، ثم سلم،
فانصرف فأتى الصفا فطاف بالصفا والمروة سبعة أطواف، ثم لم يحلل من شىء
حرم منه حتى قضى حجه ونحر هديه يوم النحر، وأفاض فطاف بالبيت، ثم حل
من كل شىء حرم منه، وفعل مثل ما فعل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من
أهدى وساق الهدى من الناس‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: During the last Hajj
(Hajj-al-Wada`) of Allah's Apostle he performed `Umra and Hajj. He
drove a Hadi along with him from Dhul-Hulaifa. Allah's Apostle
started by assuming Ihram for `Umra and Hajj. And the people, too,
performed the `Umra and Hajj along with the Prophet. Some of them
brought the Hadi and drove it along with them, while the others did
not. So, when the Prophet arrived at Mecca. he said to the people,
"Whoever among you has driven the Hadi, should not finish his Ihram
till he completes his Hajj. And whoever among you has not (driven)
the Hadi with him, should perform Tawaf of the Ka`ba and the Tawaf
between Safa and Marwa, then cut short his hair and finish his
Ihram, and should later assume Ihram for Hajj; but he must offer a
Hadi (sacrifice); and if anyone cannot afford a Hadi, he should
fast for three days during the Hajj and seven days when he returns
home. The Prophet performed Tawaf of the Ka`ba on his arrival (at
Mecca); he touched the (Black Stone) corner first of all and then
did Ramal (fast walking with moving of the shoulders) during the
first three rounds round the Ka`ba, and during the last four rounds
he walked. After finishing Tawaf of the Ka`ba, he offered a two
rak`at prayer at Maqam Ibrahim, and after finishing the prayer he
went to Safa and Marwa and performed seven rounds of Tawaf between
them and did not do any deed forbidden because of Ihram, till he
finished all the ceremonies of his Hajj and sacrificed his Hadi on
the day of Nahr (10th day of Dhul-Hijja). He then hastened onwards
(to Mecca) and performed Tawaf of the Ka`ba and then everything
that was forbidden because of Ihram became permissible. Those who
took and drove the Hadi with them did the same as Allah's Apostle
did.</english-text>
</hadith>
