<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1733</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30308, 20157, 11106, 11014</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن المنذر، حدثنا أبو ضمرة، حدثنا موسى بن
عقبة، عن نافع، قال أراد ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما الحج عام حجة
الحرورية في عهد ابن الزبير رضى الله عنهما فقيل له إن الناس كائن
بينهم قتال، ونخاف أن يصدوك‏.‏ فقال ‏{‏لقد كان لكم في رسول الله أسوة
حسنة‏}‏ إذا أصنع كما صنع، أشهدكم أني أوجبت عمرة‏.‏ حتى كان بظاهر
البيداء قال ما شأن الحج والعمرة إلا واحد، أشهدكم أني جمعت حجة مع
عمرة‏.‏ وأهدى هديا مقلدا اشتراه حتى قدم، فطاف بالبيت وبالصفا، ولم
يزد على ذلك، ولم يحلل من شىء حرم منه حتى يوم النحر، فحلق ونحر ورأى
أن قد قضى طوافه الحج والعمرة بطوافه الأول، ثم قال كذلك صنع النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Nafi`: Ibn `Umar intended to perform Hajj in
the year of the Hajj of Al-Harawriya during the rule of Ibn Az-
Zubair. Some people said to him, "It is very likely that there will
be a fight among the people, and we are afraid that they might
prevent you (from performing Hajj)." He replied, "Verily, in
Allah's Apostle there is a good example for you (to follow). In
this case I would do the same as he had done. I make you witness
that I have intended to perform `Umra." When he reached Al-Baida',
he said, "The conditions for both Hajj and `Umra are the same. I
make you witness that I have intended to perform Hajj along with
`Umra." After that he took a garlanded Hadi (to Mecca) which he
bought (on the way). When he reached (Mecca), he performed Tawaf of
the Ka`ba and of Safa (and Marwa) and did not do more than that. He
did not make legal for himself the things which were illegal for a
Muhrim till it was the Day of Nahr (sacrifice), when he had his
head shaved and slaughtered (the sacrifice) and considered
sufficient his first Tawaf (between Safa and Marwa), as a (Sa`i)
for his Hajj and `Umra both. He then said, "The Prophet used to do
like that."</english-text>
</hadith>
