<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>166</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>166</hadith-number>
<chapter>Ablutions (Wudu') - كتاب الوضوء</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11168, 11887</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، قال أخبرنا مالك، عن سعيد
المقبري، عن عبيد بن جريج، أنه قال لعبد الله بن عمر يا أبا عبد
الرحمن، رأيتك تصنع أربعا لم أر أحدا من أصحابك يصنعها‏.‏ قال وما هي
يا ابن جريج قال رأيتك لا تمس من الأركان إلا اليمانيين، ورأيتك تلبس
النعال السبتية، ورأيتك تصبغ بالصفرة، ورأيتك إذا كنت بمكة أهل الناس
إذا رأوا الهلال ولم تهل أنت حتى كان يوم التروية‏.‏ قال عبد الله أما
الأركان فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يمس إلا اليمانيين،
وأما النعال السبتية فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يلبس
النعل التي ليس فيها شعر ويتوضأ فيها، فأنا أحب أن ألبسها، وأما
الصفرة فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصبغ بها، فأنا أحب أن
أصبغ بها، وأما الإهلال فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يهل
حتى تنبعث به راحلته‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Ubaid Ibn Juraij: I asked `Abdullah bin
`Umar, "O Abu `Abdur-Rahman! I saw you doing four things which I
never saw being done by anyone of you companions?" `Abdullah bin
`Umar said, "What are those, O Ibn Juraij?" I said, "I never saw
you touching any corner of the Ka`ba except these (two) facing
south (Yemen) and I saw you wearing shoes made of tanned leather
and dyeing your hair with Hinna (a kind of red dye). I also noticed
that whenever you were in Mecca, the people assume Ihram on seeing
the new moon crescent (1st of Dhul-Hijja) while you did not assume
the Ihlal (Ihram) -(Ihram is also called Ihlal which means 'Loud
calling' because a Muhrim has to recite Talbiya aloud when assuming
the state of Ihram) - till the 8th of Dhul-Hijja (Day of Tarwiya).
`Abdullah replied, "Regarding the corners of Ka`ba, I never saw
Allah's Apostle touching except those facing south (Yemen) and
regarding the tanned leather shoes, no doubt I saw Allah's Apostle
wearing non-hairy shoes and he used to perform ablution while
wearing the shoes (i.e. wash his feet and then put on the shoes).
So I love to wear similar shoes. And about the dyeing of hair with
Hinna; no doubt I saw Allah's Apostle dyeing his hair with it and
that is why I like to dye (my hair with it). Regarding Ihlal, I did
not see Allah's Apostle assuming Ihlal till he set out for Hajj (on
the 8th of Dhul-Hijja).</english-text>
</hadith>
