<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1768</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20443, 11301, 11035, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا أبو عامر، حدثنا قرة، عن
محمد بن سيرين، قال أخبرني عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكرة، عن أبي بكرة،،
ورجل، أفضل في نفسي من عبد الرحمن حميد بن عبد الرحمن عن أبي بكرة رضى
الله عنه قال خطبنا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم النحر، قال ‏"‏
أتدرون أى يوم هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه
سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس يوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ أى شهر هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه
سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أليس ذو الحجة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ أى بلد هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه
سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليست بالبلدة الحرام ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم عليكم حرام، كحرمة يومكم هذا، في شهركم
هذا، في بلدكم هذا، إلى يوم تلقون ربكم‏.‏ ألا هل بلغت ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا
نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اللهم اشهد، فليبلغ الشاهد الغائب، فرب مبلغ أوعى من
سامع، فلا ترجعوا بعدي كفارا يضرب بعضكم رقاب بعض
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Bakra: The Prophet delivered to us a
sermon on the Day of Nahr. He said, "Do you know what is the day
today?" We said, "Allah and His Apostle know better." He remained
silent till we thought that he might give that day another name. He
said, "Isn't it the Day of Nahr?" We said, "It is." He further
asked, "Which month is this?" We said, "Allah and His Apostle know
better." He remained silent till we thought that he might give it
another name. He then said, "Isn't it the month of Dhul-Hijja?" We
replied: "Yes! It is." He further asked, "What town is this?" We
replied, "Allah and His Apostle know it better." He remained silent
till we thought that he might give it another name. He then said,
"Isn't it the forbidden (Sacred) town (of Mecca)?" We said, "Yes.
It is." He said, "No doubt, your blood and your properties are
sacred to one another like the sanctity of this day of yours, in
this month of yours, in this town of yours, till the day you meet
your Lord. No doubt! Haven't I conveyed Allah's message to you?
They said, "Yes." He said, "O Allah! Be witness. So it is incumbent
upon those who are present to convey it (this information) to those
who are absent because the informed one might comprehend it (what I
have said) better than the present audience, who will convey it to
him. Beware! Do not renegade (as) disbelievers after me by striking
the necks (cutting the throats) of one another."</english-text>
</hadith>
