<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>25</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>25</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1789</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hajj (Pilgrimage) - كتاب الحج</chapter>
<chain-index>20283, 20469, 11067, 11051, 11054, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو النعمان، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن منصور، عن
إبراهيم، عن الأسود، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت خرجنا مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ولا نرى إلا الحج، فقدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فطاف
بالبيت وبين الصفا والمروة، ولم يحل وكان معه الهدى، فطاف من كان معه
من نسائه وأصحابه، وحل منهم من لم يكن معه الهدى، فحاضت هي، فنسكنا
مناسكنا من حجنا، فلما كان ليلة الحصبة ليلة النفر، قالت يا رسول الله
كل أصحابك يرجع بحج وعمرة غيري‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما كنت تطوفي بالبيت ليالي
قدمنا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فاخرجي مع أخيك إلى التنعيم فأهلي
بعمرة، وموعدك مكان كذا وكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرجت مع عبد الرحمن إلى التنعيم،
فأهللت بعمرة، وحاضت صفية بنت حيى، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
عقرى حلقى، إنك لحابستنا، أما كنت طفت يوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت بلى‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فلا بأس‏.‏ انفري ‏"‏‏.‏ فلقيته مصعدا على أهل مكة، وأنا
منهبطة، أو أنا مصعدة، وهو منهبط‏.‏ وقال مسدد قلت لا‏.‏ تابعه جرير
عن منصور في قوله لا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: We set out with the Prophet with the
intention of performing Hajj only. The Prophet reached Mecca and
performed Tawaf of the Ka`ba and between Safa and Marwa and did not
finish the Ihram, because he had the Hadi with him. His companions
and his wives performed Tawaf (of the Ka`ba and between Safa and
Marwa), and those who had no Hadi with them finished their Ihram. I
got the menses and performed all the ceremonies of Hajj. So, when
the Night of Hasba (night of departure) came, I said, "O Allah's
Apostle! All your companions are returning with Hajj and `Umra
except me." He asked me, "Didn't you perform Tawaf of the Ka`ba
(Umra) when you reached Mecca?" I said, "No." He said, "Go to
Tan`im with your brother `Abdur-Rahman, and assume Ihram for `Umra
and I will wait for you at such and such a place." So I went with
`Abdur-Rahman to Tan`im and assumed Ihram for `Umra. Then Safiya
bint Huyay got menses. The Prophet said, " 'Aqra Halqa! You will
detain us! Didn't you perform Tawaf-al-Ifada on the Day of Nahr
(slaughtering)?" She said, "Yes, I did." He said, "Then there is no
harm, depart." So I met the Prophet when he was ascending the
heights towards Mecca and I was descending, or
vice-versa.</english-text>
</hadith>
