<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>26</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1813</hadith-number>
<chapter>`Umrah (Minor pilgrimage) - كتاب العمرة</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20259, 11276, 11029, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد الوهاب بن عبد المجيد،
عن حبيب المعلم، عن عطاء، حدثني جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله عنهما أن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أهل وأصحابه بالحج وليس مع أحد منهم هدى،
غير النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وطلحة، وكان علي قدم من اليمن، ومعه
الهدى فقال أهللت بما أهل به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ وإن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أذن لأصحابه أن يجعلوها عمرة، يطوفوا
بالبيت، ثم يقصروا ويحلوا، إلا من معه الهدى، فقالوا ننطلق إلى منى
وذكر أحدنا يقطر فبلغ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ لو استقبلت
من أمري ما استدبرت ما أهديت، ولولا أن معي الهدى لأحللت ‏"‏‏.‏ وأن
عائشة حاضت فنسكت المناسك كلها، غير أنها لم تطف بالبيت قال فلما طهرت
وطافت، قالت يا رسول الله أتنطلقون بعمرة وحجة، وأنطلق بالحج فأمر عبد
الرحمن بن أبي بكر أن يخرج معها إلى التنعيم، فاعتمرت بعد الحج في ذي
الحجة، وأن سراقة بن مالك بن جعشم لقي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو
بالعقبة، وهو يرميها، فقال ألكم هذه خاصة، يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ لا،
بل للأبد ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: The Prophet and his
companions assumed Ihram for Hajj and none except the Prophet and
Talha had the Hadi with them. `Ali had come from Yemen and he had
the Hadi with him. He (`Ali) said, "I have assumed Ihram with an
intention like that of Allah's Apostle has assumed it." The Prophet
ordered his companions to intend the Ihram with which they had come
for `Umra, to perform the Tawaf of the Ka`ba (and between Safa and
Marwa), to get their hair cut short and then to finish their Ihram
with the exception of those who had the Hadi with them. They asked,
"Shall we go to Mina and the private organs of some of us are
dribbling (if we finish Ihram and have sexual relations with our
wives)?" The Prophet heard that and said, "Had I known what I know
now, I would not have brought the Hadi. If I did not have the Hadi
with me I would have finished my Ihram." `Aisha got her menses and
performed all the ceremonies (of Hajj) except the Tawaf . So when
she became clean from her menses, and she had performed the Tawaf
of the Ka`ba, she said, "O Allah's Apostle! You (people) are
returning with both Hajj and `Umra and I am returning only with
Hajj!" So, he ordered `Abdur Rahman bin Abu Bakr to go with her to
at-Tan`im. Thus she performed `Umra after the Hajj in the month of
Dhi-l-Hijja. Suraqa bin Malik bin Ju'sham met the Prophet at
Al-`Aqaba (Jamrat-ul 'Aqaba) while the latter was stoning it and
said, "O Allah's Apostle! Is this permissible only for you?" The
Prophet replied, "No, it is for ever (i.e. it is permissible for
all Muslims to perform `Umra before Hajj."</english-text>
</hadith>
