<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>26</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1814</hadith-number>
<chapter>`Umrah (Minor pilgrimage) - كتاب العمرة</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20031, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا يحيى، حدثنا هشام، قال
أخبرني أبي قال، أخبرتني عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم موافين لهلال ذي الحجة، فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من أحب أن يهل بعمرة فليهل، ومن أحب أن يهل بحجة فليهل،
ولولا أني أهديت لأهللت بعمرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فمنهم من أهل بعمرة، ومنهم من
أهل بحجة، وكنت ممن أهل بعمرة، فحضت قبل أن أدخل مكة، فأدركني يوم
عرفة، وأنا حائض، فشكوت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏
دعي عمرتك، وانقضي رأسك وامتشطي، وأهلي بالحج ‏"‏‏.‏ ففعلت، فلما كانت
ليلة الحصبة أرسل معي عبد الرحمن إلى التنعيم، فأردفها، فأهلت بعمرة
مكان عمرتها، فقضى الله حجها وعمرتها، ولم يكن في شىء من ذلك هدى، ولا
صدقة، ولا صوم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: We set out with Allah's Apostle
shortly before the appearance of the new moon of Dhi-l-Hijja and he
said, "Whoever wants to assume Ihram for `Umra may do so, and
whoever wants to assume Ihram for Hajj may do so. Had not I brought
the Hadi with me, I would have assumed Ihram for `Umra." Some of
the people assumed Ihram for `Umra while others for Hajj. I was
amongst those who had assumed Ihram for `Umra. I got my menses
before entering Mecca, and was menstruating till the day of
`Arafat. I complained to Allah's Apostle about it, he said,
"Abandon your `Umra, undo and comb your hair, and assume Ihram for
Hajj." So, I did that accordingly. When it was the night of Hasba
(day of departure from Mina), the Prophet sent `Abdur Rahman with
me to at-Tan`im. The sub-narrator adds: He (`Abdur-Rahman) let her
ride behind him. And she assumed Ihram for `Umra in lieu of the
abandoned one. Aisha completed her Hajj and `Umra, and no Hadi,
Sadaqa (charity), or fasting was obligatory for her.</english-text>
</hadith>
