<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>26</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1816</hadith-number>
<chapter>`Umrah (Minor pilgrimage) - كتاب العمرة</chapter>
<chain-index>20348, 20156, 10535, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا أفلح بن حميد، عن القاسم، عن
عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت خرجنا مهلين بالحج في أشهر الحج، وحرم الحج،
فنزلنا سرف، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لأصحابه ‏"‏ من لم يكن معه
هدى، فأحب أن يجعلها عمرة، فليفعل ومن كان معه هدى فلا ‏"‏‏.‏ وكان مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ورجال من أصحابه ذوي قوة الهدى، فلم تكن لهم
عمرة، فدخل على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنا أبكي فقال ‏"‏ ما يبكيك
‏"‏‏.‏ قلت سمعتك تقول لأصحابك ما قلت فمنعت العمرة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وما
شأنك ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت لا أصلي‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فلا يضرك أنت من بنات آدم، كتب
عليك ما كتب عليهن، فكوني في حجتك عسى الله أن يرزقكها ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت
فكنت حتى نفرنا من منى، فنزلنا المحصب فدعا عبد الرحمن، فقال ‏"‏ اخرج
بأختك الحرم، فلتهل بعمرة، ثم افرغا من طوافكما، أنتظركما ها هنا
‏"‏‏.‏ فأتينا في جوف الليل‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ فرغتما ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏
فنادى بالرحيل في أصحابه، فارتحل الناس، ومن طاف بالبيت، قبل صلاة
الصبح، ثم خرج موجها إلى المدينة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: We set out assuming the Ihram for
Hajj in the months of Hajj towards the sacred precincts of Hajj. We
dismounted at Sarif and the Prophet said to his companions,
"Whoever has not got the Hadi with him and likes to make it as
`Umra, he should do it, but he who has got the Hadi with him should
not do it." The Prophet and some of his wealthy companions had the
Hadi with them, so they did not finish Ihram after performing the
`Umra. The Prophet came to me while I was weeping. He asked me the
reason for it. I replied, "I have heard of what you have said to
your companions and I cannot do the `Umra." He asked me, "What is
the matter with you?" I replied, "I am not praying." He said,
"There is no harm in it as you are one of the daughters of Adam and
the same is written for you as for others. So, you should perform
Hajj and I hope that Allah will enable you to perform the `Umra as
well." So, I carried on till we departed from Mina and halted at
Al-Mahassab. The Prophet called `Abdur- Rahman and said, "Go out of
the sanctuary with your sister and let her assume Ihram for `Umra,
and after both of you have finished the Tawaf I will be waiting for
you at this place." We came back at midnight and the Prophet asked
us, "Have you finished?" I replied in the affirmative. He announced
the departure and the people set out for the journey and some of
them had performed the Tawaf of the Ka`ba before the morning
prayer, and after that the Prophet set out for
Medina.</english-text>
</hadith>
