<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>26</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>26</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1818</hadith-number>
<chapter>`Umrah (Minor pilgrimage) - كتاب العمرة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11065, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن هشام بن عروة،
عن أبيه، أنه قال قلت لعائشة رضى الله عنها زوج النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأنا يومئذ حديث السن أرأيت قول الله تبارك وتعالى ‏{‏إن الصفا
والمروة من شعائر الله فمن حج البيت أو اعتمر فلا جناح عليه أن يطوف
بهما‏}‏ فلا أرى على أحد شيئا أن لا يطوف بهما‏.‏ فقالت عائشة كلا، لو
كانت كما تقول كانت فلا جناح عليه أن لا يطوف بهما‏.‏ إنما أنزلت هذه
الآية في الأنصار كانوا يهلون لمناة، وكانت مناة حذو قديد، وكانوا
يتحرجون أن يطوفوا بين الصفا والمروة، فلما جاء الإسلام سألوا رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن ذلك، فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏إن الصفا
والمروة من شعائر الله فمن حج البيت أو اعتمر فلا جناح عليه أن يطوف
بهما‏}‏‏.‏ زاد سفيان وأبو معاوية عن هشام ما أتم الله حج امرئ ولا
عمرته لم يطف بين الصفا والمروة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hisham Ibn `Urwa from his father who said:
While I was a youngster, I asked `Aisha the wife of the Prophet.
"What about the meaning of the Statement of Allah; "Verily! (the
mountains) As-Safa and Al Marwa, are among the symbols of Allah.
So, it is not harmful if those who perform Hajj or `Umra of the
House (Ka`ba at Mecca) to perform the going (Tawaf) between them?
(2.158) I understand (from that) that there is no harm if somebody
does not perform the Tawaf between them." `Aisha replied, "No, for
if it were as you are saying, then the recitation would have been
like this: 'It is not harmful not to perform Tawaf between them.'
This verse was revealed in connection with the Ansar who used to
assume the Ihram for the idol Manat which was put beside a place
called Qudaid and those people thought it not right to perform the
Tawaf of As- Safa and Al-Marwa. When Islam came, they asked Allah's
Apostle about that, and Allah revealed:-- "Verily! (the mountains)
As-Safa and Al-Marwa Are among the symbols of Allah. So, it is not
harmful of those who perform Hajj or `Umra of the House (Ka`ba at
Mecca) to perform the going (Tawaf) between them." (2.158) Sufyan
and Abu Muawiya added from Hisham (from `Aisha): "The Hajj or `Umra
of the person who does not perform the going (Tawaf) between
As-Safa and Al-Marwa is incomplete in Allah's sight.</english-text>
</hadith>
