<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>27</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>27</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1836</hadith-number>
<chapter>Pilgrims Prevented from Completing the Pilgrimage - كتاب
المحصر</chapter>
<chain-index>30144, 20216, 11014, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد بن أسماء، حدثنا جويرية، عن
نافع، أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، وسالم بن عبد الله، أخبراه أنهما،
كلما عبد الله بن عمر رضى الله عنهما ليالي نزل الجيش بابن الزبير
فقالا لا يضرك أن لا تحج العام، وإنا نخاف أن يحال بينك وبين البيت‏.‏
فقال خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فحال كفار قريش دون
البيت، فنحر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم هديه، وحلق رأسه، وأشهدكم أني
قد أوجبت العمرة، إن شاء الله أنطلق، فإن خلي بيني وبين البيت طفت،
وإن حيل بيني وبينه فعلت كما فعل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنا
معه‏.‏ فأهل بالعمرة من ذي الحليفة، ثم سار ساعة، ثم قال ‏"‏ إنما
شأنهما واحد، أشهدكم أني قد أوجبت حجة مع عمرتي ‏"‏‏.‏ فلم يحل منهما
حتى حل يوم النحر، وأهدى، وكان يقول لا يحل حتى يطوف طوافا واحدا يوم
يدخل مكة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Nafi`: That Ubaidullah bin `Abdullah and
Salim bin `Abdullah informed him that they told Ibn `Umar when Ibn
Az-Zubair was attacked by the army, saying "There is no harm for
you if you did not perform Hajj this year. We are afraid that you
may be prevented from reaching the Ka`ba." Ibn `Umar said "We set
out with Allah's Apostle and the non-believers of Quraish prevented
us from reaching the Ka`ba, and so the Prophet slaughtered his Hadi
and got his head shaved." Ibn `Umar added, "I make you witnesses
that I have made `Umra obligatory for me. And, Allah willing, I
will go and then if the way to Ka`ba is clear, I will perform the
Tawaf, but if I am prevented from going to the Ka`ba then I will do
the same as the Prophet did while I was in his company." Ibn `Umar
then assumed Ihram for Umra from Dhul-Hulaifa and proceeded for a
while and said, "The conditions of `Umra and Hajj are similar and I
make you witnesses that I have made `Umra and Hajj obligatory for
myself." So, he did not finish the Ihram till the day of Nahr
(slaughtering) came, and he slaughtered his Hadi. He used to say,
"I will not finish the Ihram till I perform the Tawaf, one Tawaf on
the day of entering Mecca (i.e. of Safa and Marwa for both `Umra
and Hajj).</english-text>
</hadith>
