<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>28</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>28</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1854</hadith-number>
<chapter>Penalty of Hunting while on Pilgrimage - كتاب جزاء
الصيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20005, 11176, 11224, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا صالح بن
كيسان، عن أبي محمد، نافع مولى أبي قتادة سمع أبا قتادة رضى الله عنه
قال كنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالقاحة من المدينة على ثلاث
ح‏.‏ وحدثنا علي بن عبد الله حدثنا سفيان حدثنا صالح بن كيسان عن أبي
محمد عن أبي قتادة رضى الله عنه قال كنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بالقاحة، ومنا المحرم، ومنا غير المحرم، فرأيت أصحابي يتراءون شيئا
فنظرت، فإذا حمار وحش يعني وقع سوطه فقالوا لا نعينك عليه بشىء، إنا
محرمون‏.‏ فتناولته فأخذته، ثم أتيت الحمار من وراء أكمة، فعقرته،
فأتيت به أصحابي، فقال بعضهم كلوا‏.‏ وقال بعضهم لا تأكلوا‏.‏ فأتيت
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو أمامنا، فسألته فقال ‏"‏ كلوه حلال
‏"‏‏.‏ قال لنا عمرو اذهبوا إلى صالح فسلوه عن هذا وغيره، وقدم علينا
ها هنا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Qatada: We were in the company of the
Prophet at a place called Al-Qaha (which is at a distance of three
stages of journey from Medina). Abu Qatada narrated through another
group of narrators: We were in the company of the Prophet at a
place called Al-Qaha and some of us had assumed Ihram while the
others had not. I noticed that some of my companions were watching
something, so I looked up and saw an onager. (I rode my horse and
took the spear and whip) but my whip fell down (and I asked them to
pick it up for me) but they said, "We will not help you by any
means as we are in a state of Ihram." So, I picked up the whip
myself and attacked the onager from behind a hillock and
slaughtered it and brought it to my companions. Some of them said,
"Eat it." While some others said, "Do not eat it." So, I went to
the Prophet who was ahead of us and asked him about it, He replied,
"Eat it as it is Halal (i.e. it is legal to eat it).</english-text>
</hadith>
