<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>28</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>28</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1855</hadith-number>
<chapter>Penalty of Hunting while on Pilgrimage - كتاب جزاء
الصيد</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 18716, 11804, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو عوانة، حدثنا عثمان هو
ابن موهب قال أخبرني عبد الله بن أبي قتادة، أن أباه، أخبره أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم خرج حاجا، فخرجوا معه فصرف طائفة منهم، فيهم
أبو قتادة فقال خذوا ساحل البحر حتى نلتقي‏.‏ فأخذوا ساحل البحر، فلما
انصرفوا أحرموا كلهم إلا أبو قتادة لم يحرم، فبينما هم يسيرون إذ رأوا
حمر وحش، فحمل أبو قتادة على الحمر، فعقر منها أتانا، فنزلوا فأكلوا
من لحمها، وقالوا أنأكل لحم صيد ونحن محرمون فحملنا ما بقي من لحم
الأتان، فلما أتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالوا يا رسول الله،
إنا كنا أحرمنا وقد كان أبو قتادة لم يحرم، فرأينا حمر وحش فحمل عليها
أبو قتادة، فعقر منها أتانا، فنزلنا فأكلنا من لحمها ثم قلنا أنأكل
لحم صيد ونحن محرمون فحملنا ما بقي من لحمها‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ منكم أحد أمره
أن يحمل عليها، أو أشار إليها ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فكلوا ما
بقي من لحمها ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin Abu Qatada: That his father
had told him that Allah's Apostle set out for Hajj and so did his
companions. He sent a batch of his companions by another route and
Abu Qatada was one of them. The Prophet said to them, "Proceed
along the seashore till we meet all together." So, they took the
route of the seashore, and when they started all of them assumed
Ihram except Abu Qatada. While they were proceeding on, his
companions saw a group of onagers. Abu Qatada chased the onagers
and attacked and wounded a sheonager. They got down and ate some of
its meat and said to each other: "How do we eat the meat of the
game while we are in a state of Ihram?" So, we (they) carried the
rest of the she-onager's meat, and when they met Allah's Apostle
they asked, saying, "O Allah's Apostle! We assumed Ihram with the
exception of Abu Qatada and we saw (a group) of onagers. Abu Qatada
attacked them and wounded a she-onager from them. Then we got down
and ate from its meat. Later, we said, (to each other), 'How do we
eat the meat of the game and we are in a state of Ihram?' So, we
carried the rest of its meat. The Prophet asked, "Did anyone of you
order Abu Qatada to attack it or point at it?" They replied in the
negative. He said, "Then eat what is left of its
meat."</english-text>
</hadith>
