<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>29</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>29</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1922</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues of Madinah - كتاب فضائل المدينة</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت لما قدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم المدينة وعك أبو بكر وبلال، فكان أبو بكر إذا أخذته الحمى يقول
كل امرئ مصبح في أهله والموت أدنى من شراك نعله وكان بلال إذا أقلع
عنه الحمى يرفع عقيرته يقول ألا ليت شعري هل أبيتن ليلة بواد وحولي
إذخر وجليل وهل أردن يوما مياه مجنة وهل يبدون لي شامة وطفيل قال
اللهم العن شيبة بن ربيعة، وعتبة بن ربيعة، وأمية بن خلف، كما أخرجونا
من أرضنا إلى أرض الوباء ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
اللهم حبب إلينا المدينة كحبنا مكة أو أشد، اللهم بارك لنا في صاعنا،
وفي مدنا، وصححها لنا وانقل حماها إلى الجحفة ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت وقدمنا
المدينة، وهى أوبأ أرض الله‏.‏ قالت فكان بطحان يجري نجلا‏.‏ تعني ماء
آجنا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: When Allah's Apostle reached Medina,
Abu Bakr and Bilal became ill. When Abu Bakr's fever got worse, he
would recite (this poetic verse): "Everybody is staying alive with
his People, yet Death is nearer to him than His shoe laces." And
Bilal, when his fever deserted him, would recite: "Would that I
could stay overnight in A valley wherein I would be Surrounded by
Idhkhir and Jalil (kinds of goodsmelling grass). Would that one day
I could Drink the water of the Majanna, and Would that (The two
mountains) Shama and Tafil would appear to me!" The Prophet said,
"O Allah! Curse Shaiba bin Rabi`a and `Utba bin Rabi`a and Umaiya
bin Khalaf as they turned us out of our land to the land of
epidemics." Allah's Apostle then said, "O Allah! Make us love
Medina as we love Mecca or even more than that. O Allah! Give
blessings in our Sa and our Mudd (measures symbolizing food) and
make the climate of Medina suitable for us, and divert its fever
towards Aljuhfa." Aisha added: When we reached Medina, it was the
most unhealthy of Allah's lands, and the valley of Bathan (the
valley of Medina) used to flow with impure colored
water.</english-text>
</hadith>
