<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1977</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2048</hadith-number>
<chapter>Sales and Trade - كتاب البيوع</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20150, 11063, 8</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله، حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد، عن
أبيه، عن جده، قال قال عبد الرحمن بن عوف رضى الله عنه لما قدمنا
المدينة آخى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بيني وبين سعد بن الربيع
فقال سعد بن الربيع إني أكثر الأنصار مالا، فأقسم لك نصف مالي، وانظر
أى زوجتى هويت نزلت لك عنها، فإذا حلت تزوجتها‏.‏ قال فقال عبد الرحمن
لا حاجة لي في ذلك، هل من سوق فيه تجارة قال سوق قينقاع‏.‏ قال فغدا
إليه عبد الرحمن، فأتى بأقط وسمن قال ثم تابع الغدو، فما لبث أن جاء
عبد الرحمن عليه أثر صفرة، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
تزوجت ‏"‏‏.‏ قال نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ومن ‏"‏‏.‏ قال امرأة من الأنصار‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ كم سقت ‏"‏‏.‏ قال زنة نواة من ذهب أو نواة من ذهب‏.‏ فقال له
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أولم ولو بشاة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibrahim bin Sa`d from his father from his
grandfather: `Abdur Rahman bin `Auf said, "When we came to Medina
as emigrants, Allah's Apostle established a bond of brotherhood
between me and Sa`d bin Ar-Rabi`. Sa`d bin Ar-Rabi` said (to me),
'I am the richest among the Ansar, so I will give you half of my
wealth and you may look at my two wives and whichever of the two
you may choose I will divorce her, and when she has completed the
prescribed period (before marriage) you may marry her.'
`Abdur-Rahman replied, "I am not in need of all that. Is there any
marketplace where trade is practiced?' He replied, "The market of
Qainuqa." `Abdur- Rahman went to that market the following day and
brought some dried buttermilk (yogurt) and butter, and then he
continued going there regularly. Few days later, `Abdur-Rahman came
having traces of yellow (scent) on his body. Allah's Apostle asked
him whether he had got married. He replied in the affirmative. The
Prophet said, 'Whom have you married?' He replied, 'A woman from
the Ansar.' Then the Prophet asked, 'How much did you pay her?' He
replied, '(I gave her) a gold piece equal in weigh to a date stone
(or a date stone of gold)! The Prophet said, 'Give a Walima
(wedding banquet) even if with one sheep .' "</english-text>
</hadith>
