<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>1982</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2053</hadith-number>
<chapter>Sales and Trade - كتاب البيوع</chapter>
<chain-index>30119, 20001, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن قزعة، حدثنا مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن عروة
بن الزبير، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت كان عتبة بن أبي وقاص عهد إلى
أخيه سعد بن أبي وقاص أن ابن وليدة زمعة مني فاقبضه‏.‏ قالت فلما كان
عام الفتح أخذه سعد بن أبي وقاص وقال ابن أخي، قد عهد إلى فيه‏.‏ فقام
عبد بن زمعة، فقال أخي، وابن وليدة أبي، ولد على فراشه‏.‏ فتساوقا إلى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فقال سعد يا رسول الله، ابن أخي، كان قد
عهد إلى فيه‏.‏ فقال عبد بن زمعة أخي وابن وليدة أبي، ولد على
فراشه‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هو لك يا عبد بن زمعة
‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ الولد للفراش، وللعاهر
الحجر ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال لسودة بنت زمعة زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
احتجبي منه ‏"‏‏.‏ لما رأى من شبهه بعتبة، فما رآها حتى لقي
الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha: `Utba bin Abu Waqqas took a firm
promise from his brother Sa`d bin Abu Waqqas to take the son of the
slave-girl of Zam`a into his custody as he was his (i.e. `Utba's)
son. In the year of the Conquest (of Mecca) Sa`d bin Abu Waqqas
took him, and said that he was his brother's son, and his brother
took a promise from him to that effect. 'Abu bin Zam`a got up and
said, "He is my brother and the son of the slave-girl of my father
and was born on my father's bed." Then they both went to the
Prophet Sa`d said, "O Allah's Apostle! He is the son of my brother
and he has taken a promise from me that I will take him." 'Abu bin
Zam`a said, "(He is) my brother and the son of my father's
slave-girl and was born on my father's bed." Allah's Apostle said,
"The boy is for you. O 'Abu bin Zam`a." Then the Prophet said, "The
son is for the bed (i.e. the man on whose bed he was born) and
stones (disappointment and deprivation) for the one who has done
illegal sexual intercourse." The Prophet told his wife Sauda bint
Zam`a to screen herself from that boy as he noticed a similarity
between the boy and `Utba. So, the boy did not see her till he
died.</english-text>
</hadith>
