<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2025</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2097</hadith-number>
<chapter>Sales and Trade - كتاب البيوع</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20259, 11201, 11231, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا عبيد الله،
عن وهب بن كيسان، عن جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله عنهما قال كنت مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في غزاة، فأبطأ بي جملي وأعيا، فأتى على
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ جابر ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
ما شأنك ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت أبطأ على جملي وأعيا، فتخلفت‏.‏ فنزل يحجنه
بمحجنه، ثم قال ‏"‏ اركب ‏"‏‏.‏ فركبت، فلقد رأيته أكفه عن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ تزوجت ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ بكرا أم
ثيبا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت بل ثيبا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أفلا جارية تلاعبها وتلاعبك
‏"‏‏.‏ قلت إن لي أخوات، فأحببت أن أتزوج امرأة تجمعهن، وتمشطهن،
وتقوم عليهن‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أما إنك قادم، فإذا قدمت فالكيس الكيس ‏"‏‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ أتبيع جملك ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ فاشتراه مني بأوقية، ثم قدم
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قبلي، وقدمت بالغداة، فجئنا إلى المسجد،
فوجدته على باب المسجد، قال ‏"‏ الآن قدمت ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فدع جملك، فادخل فصل ركعتين ‏"‏‏.‏ فدخلت فصليت، فأمر بلالا أن يزن له
أوقية‏.‏ فوزن لي بلال، فأرجح في الميزان، فانطلقت حتى وليت فقال ‏"‏
ادع لي جابرا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت الآن يرد على الجمل، ولم يكن شىء أبغض إلى
منه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ خذ جملك ولك ثمنه ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: I was with the Prophet
in a Ghazwa (Military Expedition) and my camel was slow and
exhausted. The Prophet came up to me and said, "O Jabir." I
replied, "Yes?" He said, "What is the matter with you?" I replied,
"My camel is slow and tired, so I am left behind." So, he got down
and poked the camel with his stick and then ordered me to ride. I
rode the camel and it became so fast that I had to hold it from
going ahead of Allah's Apostle . He then asked me, have you got
married?" I replied in the affirmative. He asked, "A virgin or a
matron?" I replied, "I married a matron." The Prophet said, "Why
have you not married a virgin, so that you may play with her and
she may play with you?" Jabir replied, "I have sisters (young in
age) so I liked to marry a matron who could collect them all and
comb their hair and look after them." The Prophet said, "You will
reach, so when you have arrived (at home), I advise you to
associate with your wife (that you may have an intelligent son)."
Then he asked me, "Would you like to sell your camel?" I replied in
the affirmative and the Prophet purchased it for one Uqiya of gold.
Allah's Apostle reached before me and I reached in the morning, and
when I went to the mosque, I found him at the door of the mosque.
He asked me, "Have you arrived just now?" I replied in the
affirmative. He said, "Leave your camel and come into (the mosque)
and pray two rak`at." I entered and offered the prayer. He told
Bilal to weigh and give me one Uqiya of gold. So Bilal weighed for
me fairly and I went away. The Prophet sent for me and I thought
that he would return to me my camel which I hated more than
anything else. But the Prophet said to me, "Take your camel as well
as its price."</english-text>
</hadith>
