<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2052</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>34</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2125</hadith-number>
<chapter>Sales and Trade - كتاب البيوع</chapter>
<chain-index>34207, 20169, 11229, 11020</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سنان، حدثنا فليح، حدثنا هلال، عن عطاء بن
يسار، قال لقيت عبد الله بن عمرو بن العاص رضى الله عنهما قلت أخبرني
عن صفة، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في التوراة‏.‏ قال أجل، والله
إنه لموصوف في التوراة ببعض صفته في القرآن يا أيها النبي إنا أرسلناك
شاهدا ومبشرا ونذيرا، وحرزا للأميين، أنت عبدي ورسولي سميتك المتوكل،
ليس بفظ ولا غليظ ولا سخاب في الأسواق، ولا يدفع بالسيئة السيئة ولكن
يعفو ويغفر، ولن يقبضه الله حتى يقيم به الملة العوجاء بأن يقولوا لا
إله إلا الله‏.‏ ويفتح بها أعينا عميا، وآذانا صما، وقلوبا غلفا‏.‏
تابعه عبد العزيز بن أبي سلمة عن هلال‏.‏ وقال سعيد عن هلال عن عطاء
عن ابن سلام‏.‏ غلف كل شىء في غلاف، سيف أغلف، وقوس غلفاء، ورجل أغلف
إذا لم يكن مختونا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ata bin Yasar: I met `Abdullah bin `Amr bin
Al-`As and asked him, "Tell me about the description of Allah's
Apostle which is mentioned in Torah (i.e. Old Testament.") He
replied, 'Yes. By Allah, he is described in Torah with some of the
qualities attributed to him in the Qur'an as follows: "O Prophet !
We have sent you as a witness (for Allah's True religion) And a
giver of glad tidings (to the faithful believers), And a warner (to
the unbelievers) And guardian of the illiterates. You are My slave
and My messenger (i.e. Apostle). I have named you "Al-Mutawakkil"
(who depends upon Allah). You are neither discourteous, harsh Nor a
noisemaker in the markets And you do not do evil to those Who do
evil to you, but you deal With them with forgiveness and kindness.
Allah will not let him (the Prophet) Die till he makes straight the
crooked people by making them say: "None has the right to be
worshipped but Allah," With which will be opened blind eyes And
deaf ears and enveloped hearts."</english-text>
</hadith>
