<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2194</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>37</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2276</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hiring - كتاب الإجارة</chapter>
<chain-index>20283, 20469, 11419, 11297, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو النعمان، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن أبي بشر، عن أبي
المتوكل، عن أبي سعيد رضى الله عنه قال انطلق نفر من أصحاب النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم في سفرة سافروها حتى نزلوا على حى من أحياء العرب
فاستضافوهم، فأبوا أن يضيفوهم، فلدغ سيد ذلك الحى، فسعوا له بكل شىء
لا ينفعه شىء، فقال بعضهم لو أتيتم هؤلاء الرهط الذين نزلوا لعله أن
يكون عند بعضهم شىء، فأتوهم، فقالوا يا أيها الرهط، إن سيدنا لدغ،
وسعينا له بكل شىء لا ينفعه، فهل عند أحد منكم من شىء فقال بعضهم نعم
والله إني لأرقي، ولكن والله لقد استضفناكم فلم تضيفونا، فما أنا براق
لكم حتى تجعلوا لنا جعلا‏.‏ فصالحوهم على قطيع من الغنم، فانطلق يتفل
عليه ويقرأ ‏{‏الحمد لله رب العالمين‏}‏ فكأنما نشط من عقال، فانطلق
يمشي وما به قلبة، قال فأوفوهم جعلهم الذي صالحوهم عليه، فقال بعضهم
اقسموا‏.‏ فقال الذي رقى لا تفعلوا، حتى نأتي النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فنذكر له الذي كان، فننظر ما يأمرنا‏.‏ فقدموا على رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فذكروا له، فقال ‏"‏ وما يدريك أنها رقية ثم قال قد
أصبتم اقسموا واضربوا لي معكم سهما ‏"‏‏.‏ فضحك رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم‏.‏ وقال شعبة حدثنا أبو بشر سمعت أبا المتوكل
بهذا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id: Some of the companions of the
Prophet went on a journey till they reached some of the 'Arab
tribes (at night). They asked the latter to treat them as their
guests but they refused. The chief of that tribe was then bitten by
a snake (or stung by a scorpion) and they tried their best to cure
him but in vain. Some of them said (to the others), "Nothing has
benefited him, will you go to the people who resided here at night,
it may be that some of them might possess something (as
treatment)," They went to the group of the companions (of the
Prophet ) and said, "Our chief has been bitten by a snake (or stung
by a scorpion) and we have tried everything but he has not
benefited. Have you got anything (useful)?" One of them replied,
"Yes, by Allah! I can recite a Ruqya, but as you have refused to
accept us as your guests, I will not recite the Ruqya for you
unless you fix for us some wages for it." They agrees to pay them a
flock of sheep. One of them then went and recited
(Surat-ul-Fatiha): 'All the praises are for the Lord of the Worlds'
and puffed over the chief who became all right as if he was
released from a chain, and got up and started walking, showing no
signs of sickness. They paid them what they agreed to pay. Some of
them (i.e. the companions) then suggested to divide their earnings
among themselves, but the one who performed the recitation said,
"Do not divide them till we go to the Prophet and narrate the whole
story to him, and wait for his order." So, they went to Allah's
Apostle and narrated the story. Allah's Apostle asked, "How did you
come to know that Suratul- Fatiha was recited as Ruqya?" Then he
added, "You have done the right thing. Divide (what you have
earned) and assign a share for me as well." The Prophet smiled
thereupon.</english-text>
</hadith>
