<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2218</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>40</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2301</hadith-number>
<chapter>Representation; Authorization; Business by Proxy - كتاب
الوكالة</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20027, 11064, 584, 8</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله، قال حدثني يوسف بن
الماجشون، عن صالح بن إبراهيم بن عبد الرحمن بن عوف، عن أبيه، عن جده
عبد الرحمن بن عوف رضى الله عنه قال كاتبت أمية بن خلف كتابا بأن
يحفظني في صاغيتي بمكة، وأحفظه في صاغيته بالمدينة، فلما ذكرت الرحمن
قال لا أعرف الرحمن، كاتبني باسمك الذي كان في الجاهلية‏.‏ فكاتبته
عبد عمرو فلما كان في يوم بدر خرجت إلى جبل لأحرزه حين نام الناس
فأبصره بلال فخرج حتى وقف على مجلس من الأنصار فقال أمية بن خلف، لا
نجوت إن نجا أمية‏.‏ فخرج معه فريق من الأنصار في آثارنا، فلما خشيت
أن يلحقونا خلفت لهم ابنه، لأشغلهم فقتلوه ثم أبوا حتى يتبعونا، وكان
رجلا ثقيلا، فلما أدركونا قلت له ابرك‏.‏ فبرك، فألقيت عليه نفسي
لأمنعه، فتخللوه بالسيوف من تحتي، حتى قتلوه، وأصاب أحدهم رجلي بسيفه،
وكان عبد الرحمن بن عوف يرينا ذلك الأثر في ظهر قدمه‏.‏ قال أبو عبد
الله سمع يوسف صالحا وإبراهيم أباه</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdur-Rahman bin `Auf: I got an agreement
written between me and Umaiya bin Khalaf that Umaiya would look
after my property (or family) in Mecca and I would look after his
in Medina. When I mentioned the word 'Ar64 Rahman' in the
documents, Umaiya said, "I do not know 'Ar-Rahman.' Write down to
me your name, (with which you called yourself) in the Pre-Islamic
Period of Ignorance." So, I wrote my name ' `Abdu `Amr'. On the day
(of the battle) of Badr, when all the people went to sleep, I went
up the hill to protect him. Bilal(1) saw him (i.e. Umaiya) and went
to a gathering of Ansar and said, "(Here is) Umaiya bin Khalaf! Woe
to me if he escapes!" So, a group of Ansar went out with Bilal to
follow us (`Abdur-Rahman and Umaiya). Being afraid that they would
catch us, I left Umaiya's son for them to keep them busy but the
Ansar killed the son and insisted on following us. Umaiya was a fat
man, and when they approached us, I told him to kneel down, and he
knelt, and I laid myself on him to protect him, but the Ansar
killed him by passing their swords underneath me, and one of them
injured my foot with his sword. (The sub narrator said, "
`Abdur-Rahman used to show us the trace of the wound on the back of
his foot.")</english-text>
</hadith>
