<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2280</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2371</hadith-number>
<chapter>Distribution of Water - كتاب المساقاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11163, 11161, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك بن أنس، عن زيد بن
أسلم، عن أبي صالح السمان، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ الخيل لرجل أجر، ولرجل ستر، وعلى رجل وزر،
فأما الذي له أجر فرجل ربطها في سبيل الله، فأطال بها في مرج أو روضة،
فما أصابت في طيلها ذلك من المرج أو الروضة كانت له حسنات، ولو أنه
انقطع طيلها فاستنت شرفا أو شرفين كانت آثارها وأرواثها حسنات له، ولو
أنها مرت بنهر فشربت منه ولم يرد أن يسقي كان ذلك حسنات له، فهي لذلك
أجر، ورجل ربطها تغنيا وتعففا ثم لم ينس حق الله في رقابها ولا
ظهورها، فهي لذلك ستر، ورجل ربطها فخرا ورياء ونواء لأهل الإسلام، فهي
على ذلك وزر ‏"‏‏.‏ وسئل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن الحمر فقال
‏"‏ ما أنزل على فيها شىء إلا هذه الآية الجامعة الفاذة ‏{‏من يعمل
مثقال ذرة خيرا يره * ومن يعمل مثقال ذرة شرا يره
‏}‏‏"‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Allah's Apostle said, "Keeping
horses may be a source of reward to some (man), a shelter to
another (i.e. means of earning one's living), or a burden to a
third. He to whom the horse will be a source of reward is the one
who keeps it in Allah's Cause (prepare it for holy battles) and
ties it by a long rope in a pasture (or a garden). He will get a
reward equal to what its long rope allows it to eat in the pasture
or the garden, and if that horse breaks its rope and crosses one or
two hills, then all its footsteps and its dung will be counted as
good deeds for its owner; and if it passes by a river and drinks
from it, then that will also be regarded as a good deed for its
owner even if he has had no intention of watering it then. Horses
are a shelter from poverty to the second person who keeps horses
for earning his living so as not to ask others, and at the same
time he gives Allah's right (i.e. rak`at) (from the wealth he earns
through using them in trading etc.,) and does not overburden them.
He who keeps horses just out of pride and for showing off and as a
means of harming the Muslims, his horses will be a source of sins
to him." When Allah's Apostle was asked about donkeys, he replied,
"Nothing particular was revealed to me regarding them except the
general unique verse which is applicable to everything: "Whoever
does goodness equal to the weight of an atom (or small ant) shall
see it (its reward) on the Day of Resurrection."</english-text>
</hadith>
