<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2284</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>42</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2375</hadith-number>
<chapter>Distribution of Water - كتاب المساقاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20295, 11070, 11013, 11045, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن موسى، أخبرنا هشام، أن ابن جريج،
أخبرهم قال أخبرني ابن شهاب، عن علي بن حسين بن علي، عن أبيه، حسين بن
علي عن علي بن أبي طالب رضى الله عنهم أنه قال أصبت شارفا مع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في مغنم يوم بدر قال وأعطاني رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم شارفا أخرى، فأنختهما يوما عند باب رجل من الأنصار،
وأنا أريد أن أحمل عليهما إذخرا لأبيعه، ومعي صائغ من بني قينقاع
فأستعين به على وليمة فاطمة، وحمزة بن عبد المطلب يشرب في ذلك البيت
معه قينة، فقالت ألا يا حمز للشرف النواء‏.‏ فثار إليهما حمزة بالسيف،
فجب أسنمتهما، وبقر خواصرهما، ثم أخذ من أكبادهما‏.‏ قلت لابن شهاب
ومن السنام قال قد جب أسنمتهما فذهب بها‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب قال علي رضى
الله عنه فنظرت إلى منظر أفظعني فأتيت نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وعنده زيد بن حارثة فأخبرته الخبر فخرج ومعه زيد، فانطلقت معه، فدخل
على حمزة فتغيظ عليه فرفع حمزة بصره وقال هل أنتم إلا عبيد لآبائي
فرجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقهقر حتى خرج عنهم، وذلك قبل
تحريم الخمر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Husain bin `Ali: `Ali bin Abi Talib said: "I
got a she-camel as my share of the war booty on the day (of the
battle) of Badr, and Allah's Apostle gave me another she-camel. I
let both of them kneel at the door of one of the Ansar, intending
to carry Idhkhir on them to sell it and use its price for my
wedding banquet on marrying Fatima. A goldsmith from Bani Qainqa'
was with me. Hamza bin `Abdul-Muttalib was in that house drinking
wine and a lady singer was reciting: "O Hamza! (Kill) the (two) fat
old she camels (and serve them to your guests). So Hamza took his
sword and went towards the two she-camels and cut off their humps
and opened their flanks and took a part of their livers." (I said
to Ibn Shihab, "Did he take part of the humps?" He replied, "He cut
off their humps and carried them away.") `Ali further said, "When I
saw that dreadful sight, I went to the Prophet and told him the
news. The Prophet came out in the company of Zaid bin Haritha who
was with him then, and I too went with them. He went to Hamza and
spoke harshly to him. Hamza looked up and said, 'Aren't you only
the slaves of my forefathers?' The Prophet retreated and went out.
This incident happened before the prohibition of
drinking."</english-text>
</hadith>
