<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2296</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2388</hadith-number>
<chapter>Loans; Payment of Loans; Freezing of Property; Bankruptcy
- كتاب فى الاستقراض</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 11613, 11060, 11341, 23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن يونس، حدثنا أبو شهاب، عن الأعمش، عن زيد
بن وهب، عن أبي ذر رضى الله عنه قال كنت مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فلما أبصر يعني أحدا قال ‏"‏ ما أحب أنه يحول لي ذهبا يمكث عندي منه
دينار فوق ثلاث، إلا دينارا أرصده لدين ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ إن الأكثرين
هم الأقلون، إلا من قال بالمال هكذا وهكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ وأشار أبو شهاب بين
يديه وعن يمينه وعن شماله وقليل ما هم وقال مكانك‏.‏ وتقدم غير بعيد،
فسمعت صوتا، فأردت أن آتيه، ثم ذكرت قوله مكانك حتى آتيك، فلما جاء
قلت يا رسول الله، الذي سمعت أو قال الصوت الذي سمعت قال ‏"‏ وهل سمعت
‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أتاني جبريل عليه السلام فقال من مات من
أمتك لا يشرك بالله شيئا دخل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت وإن فعل كذا وكذا قال
‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Dhar: Once, while I was in the company
of the Prophet, he saw the mountain of Uhud and said, "I would not
like to have this mountain turned into gold for me unless nothing
of it, not even a single Dinar remains of it with me for more than
three days (i.e. I will spend all of it in Allah's Cause), except
that Dinar which I will keep for repaying debts." Then he said,
"Those who are rich in this world would have little reward in the
Hereafter except those who spend their money here and there (in
Allah's Cause), and they are few in number." Then he ordered me to
stay at my place and went not far away. I heard a voice and
intended to go to him but I remembered his order, "Stay at your
place till I return." On his return I said, "O Allah's Apostle!
(What was) that noise which I heard?" He said, "Did you hear
anything?" I said, "Yes." He said, "Gabriel came and said to me,
'Whoever amongst your followers dies, worshipping none along with
Allah, will enter Paradise.' " I said, "Even if he did
such-and-such things (i.e. even if he stole or committed illegal
sexual intercourse)" He said, "Yes."</english-text>
</hadith>
