<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2304</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2396</hadith-number>
<chapter>Loans; Payment of Loans; Freezing of Property; Bankruptcy
- كتاب فى الاستقراض</chapter>
<chain-index>30308, 19, 11065, 11231, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن المنذر، حدثنا أنس، عن هشام، عن وهب بن
كيسان، عن جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله عنهما أنه أخبره أن أباه توفي،
وترك عليه ثلاثين وسقا لرجل من اليهود، فاستنظره جابر، فأبى أن ينظره،
فكلم جابر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليشفع له إليه، فجاء رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وكلم اليهودي ليأخذ ثمر نخله بالذي له فأبى،
فدخل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم النخل، فمشى فيها ثم قال لجابر ‏"‏
جد له فأوف له الذي له ‏"‏‏.‏ فجده بعد ما رجع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأوفاه ثلاثين وسقا، وفضلت له سبعة عشر وسقا، فجاء جابر
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ليخبره بالذي كان، فوجده يصلي العصر،
فلما انصرف أخبره بالفضل، فقال ‏"‏ أخبر ذلك ابن الخطاب ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب
جابر إلى عمر، فأخبره‏.‏ فقال له عمر لقد علمت حين مشى فيها رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ليباركن فيها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: When my father died he
owed a Jew thirty Awsuq (of dates). I requested him to give me
respite for repaying but he refused. I requested Allah's Apostle to
intercede with the Jew. Allah's Apostle went to the Jew and asked
him to accept the fruits of my trees in place of the debt but the
Jew refused. Allah's Apostle entered the garden of the date-palms,
wandering among the trees and ordered me (saying), "Pluck (the
fruits) and give him his due." So, I plucked the fruits for him
after the departure of Allah's Apostle and gave his thirty Awsuq,
and still had seventeen Awsuq extra for myself. Jabir said: I went
to Allah's Apostle to inform of what had happened, but found him
praying the `Asr prayer. After the prayer I told him about the
extra fruits which remained. Allah's Apostle told me to inform
(`Umar) Ibn Al-Khattab about it. When I went to `Umar and told him
about it, `Umar said, "When Allah's Apostle walked in your garden,
I was sure that Allah would definitely bless it."</english-text>
</hadith>
