<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2313</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>43</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2405</hadith-number>
<chapter>Loans; Payment of Loans; Freezing of Property; Bankruptcy
- كتاب فى الاستقراض</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 11072, 11052, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن مغيرة، عن عامر، عن
جابر رضى الله عنه قال أصيب عبد الله وترك عيالا ودينا، فطلبت إلى
أصحاب الدين أن يضعوا بعضا من دينه فأبوا، فأتيت النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فاستشفعت به عليهم فأبوا، فقال ‏"‏ صنف تمرك كل شىء منه على
حدته، عذق ابن زيد على حدة، واللين على حدة، والعجوة على حدة، ثم
أحضرهم حتى آتيك ‏"‏‏.‏ ففعلت، ثم جاء صلى الله عليه وسلم فقعد عليه،
وكال لكل رجل حتى استوفى، وبقي التمر كما هو كأنه لم يمس‏.‏ وغزوت مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم على ناضح لنا، فأزحف الجمل فتخلف على فوكزه
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم من خلفه، قال ‏"‏ بعنيه ولك ظهره إلى
المدينة ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما دنونا استأذنت قلت يا رسول الله إني حديث عهد
بعرس‏.‏ قال صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فما تزوجت بكرا أم ثيبا ‏"‏‏.‏
قلت ثيبا، أصيب عبد الله وترك جواري صغارا، فتزوجت ثيبا تعلمهن
وتؤدبهن، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائت أهلك ‏"‏‏.‏ فقدمت فأخبرت خالي ببيع الجمل
فلامني، فأخبرته بإعياء الجمل، وبالذي كان من النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ووكزه إياه، فلما قدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم غدوت إليه
بالجمل، فأعطاني ثمن الجمل والجمل وسهمي مع القوم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir: When `Abdullah (my father) died, he
left behind children and debts. I asked the lenders to put down
some of his debt, but they refused, so I went to the Prophet to
intercede with them, yet they refused. The Prophet said (to me),
"Classify your dates into their different kinds: 'Adha bin Zaid,
Lean and 'Ajwa, each kind alone and call all the creditors and wait
till I come to you." I did so and the Prophet came and sat beside
the dates and started measuring to each his due till he paid them
fully, and the amount of dates remained as it was before, as if he
had not touched them. (On another occasion) I took part in one of
Ghazawat among with the Prophet and I was riding one of our camels.
The camel got tired and was lagging behind the others. The Prophet
hit it on its back. He said, "Sell it to me, and you have the right
to ride it till Medina.'' When we approached Medina, I took the
permission from the Prophet to go to my house, saying, "O Allah's
Apostle! I have newly married." The Prophet asked, "Have you
married a virgin or a matron (a widow or divorcee)?" I said, "I
have married a matron, as `Abdullah (my father) died and left
behind daughters small in their ages, so I married a matron who may
teach them and bring them up with good manners." The Prophet then
said (to me), "Go to your family." When I went there and told my
maternal uncle about the selling of the camel, he admonished me for
it. On that I told him about its slowness and exhaustion and about
what the Prophet had done to the camel and his hitting it. When the
Prophet arrived, I went to him with the camel in the morning and he
gave me its price, the camel itself, and my share from the war
booty as he gave the other people.</english-text>
</hadith>
