<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2401</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2494</hadith-number>
<chapter>Partnership - كتاب الشركة</chapter>
<chain-index>20150, 11176, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله العامري الأويسي، حدثنا
إبراهيم بن سعد، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، أخبرني عروة، أنه سأل عائشة
رضى الله عنها وقال الليث حدثني يونس عن ابن شهاب قال أخبرني عروة بن
الزبير أنه سأل عائشة رضى الله عنها عن قول الله تعالى ‏{‏وإن خفتم‏}‏
إلى ‏{‏ورباع‏}‏‏.‏ فقالت يا ابن أختي هي اليتيمة تكون في حجر وليها
تشاركه في ماله، فيعجبه مالها وجمالها، فيريد وليها أن يتزوجها بغير
أن يقسط في صداقها، فيعطيها مثل ما يعطيها غيره، فنهوا أن ينكحوهن إلا
أن يقسطوا لهن ويبلغوا بهن أعلى سنتهن من الصداق، وأمروا أن ينكحوا ما
طاب لهم من النساء سواهن‏.‏ قال عروة قالت عائشة ثم إن الناس استفتوا
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعد هذه الآية فأنزل الله ‏{‏ويستفتونك
في النساء‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏وترغبون أن تنكحوهن‏}‏ والذي ذكر الله أنه
يتلى عليكم في الكتاب الآية الأولى التي قال فيها ‏{‏وإن خفتم أن لا
تقسطوا في اليتامى فانكحوا ما طاب لكم من النساء‏}‏ قالت عائشة وقول
الله في الآية الأخرى ‏{‏وترغبون أن تنكحوهن‏}‏ يعني هي رغبة أحدكم
ليتيمته التي تكون في حجره، حين تكون قليلة المال والجمال، فنهوا أن
ينكحوا ما رغبوا في مالها وجمالها من يتامى النساء إلا بالقسط من، أجل
رغبتهم عنهن‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa bin Az-Zubair: That he had asked
`Aisha about the meaning of the Statement of Allah: "If you fear
that you shall not Be able to deal justly With the orphan girls,
then Marry (Other) women of your choice Two or three or four."
(4.3) She said, "O my nephew! This is about the orphan girl who
lives with her guardian and shares his property. Her wealth and
beauty may tempt him to marry her without giving her an adequate
Mahr (bridal-money) which might have been given by another suitor.
So, such guardians were forbidden to marry such orphan girls unless
they treated them justly and gave them the most suitable Mahr;
otherwise they were ordered to marry any other woman." `Aisha
further said, "After that verse the people again asked the Prophet
(about the marriage with orphan 'girls), so Allah revealed the
following verses:-- 'They ask your instruction Concerning the
women. Say: Allah Instructs you about them And about what is
Recited unto you In the Book, concerning The orphan girls to whom
You give not the prescribed portions and yet whom you Desire to
marry..." (4.127) What is meant by Allah's Saying:-- 'And about
what is Recited unto you is the former verse which goes:-- 'If you
fear that you shall not Be able to deal justly With the orphan
girls, then Marry (other) women of your choice.' (4.3) `Aisha said,
"Allah's saying in the other verse:--'Yet whom you desire to marry'
(4.127) means the desire of the guardian to marry an orphan girl
under his supervision when she has not much property or beauty (in
which case he should treat her justly). The guardians were
forbidden to marry their orphan girls possessing property and
beauty without being just to them, as they generally refrain from
marrying them (when they are neither beautiful nor
wealthy).</english-text>
</hadith>
