<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2410</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2505</hadith-number>
<chapter>Partnership - كتاب الشركة</chapter>
<chain-index>20283, 20022, 11070, 11029, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو النعمان، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، أخبرنا عبد الملك
بن جريج، عن عطاء، عن جابر‏.‏وعن طاوس، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهم قال
قدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم صبح رابعة من ذي الحجة مهلين بالحج، لا
يخلطهم شىء، فلما قدمنا أمرنا فجعلناها عمرة، وأن نحل إلى نسائنا،
ففشت في ذلك القالة‏.‏ قال عطاء فقال جابر فيروح أحدنا إلى منى وذكره
يقطر منيا‏.‏ فقال جابر بكفه، فبلغ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقام
خطيبا فقال ‏"‏ بلغني أن أقواما يقولون كذا وكذا، والله لأنا أبر
وأتقى لله منهم، ولو أني استقبلت من أمري ما استدبرت ما أهديت، ولولا
أن معي الهدى لأحللت ‏"‏‏.‏ فقام سراقة بن مالك بن جعشم فقال يا رسول
الله هي لنا أو للأبد فقال ‏"‏ لا بل للأبد ‏"‏‏.‏ قال وجاء علي بن
أبي طالب فقال أحدهما يقول لبيك بما أهل به رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم‏.‏ وقال وقال الآخر لبيك بحجة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأمر
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يقيم على إحرامه، وأشركه في
الهدى‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: The Prophet (along with his
companions) reached Mecca in the morning of the fourth of
Dhul-Hijja assuming Ihram for Hajj only. So when we arrived at
Mecca, the Prophet ordered us to change our intentions of the Ihram
for `Umra and that we could finish our Ihram after performing the
`Umra and could go to our wives (for sexual intercourse). The
people began talking about that. Jabir said surprisingly, "Shall we
go to Mina while semen is dribbling from our male organs?" Jabir
moved his hand while saying so. When this news reached the Prophet
he delivered a sermon and said, "I have been informed that some
peoples were saying so and so; By Allah I fear Allah more than you
do, and am more obedient to Him than you. If I had known what I
know now, I would not have brought the Hadi (sacrifice) with me and
had the Hadi not been with me, I would have finished the Ihram." At
that Suraqa bin Malik stood up and asked "O Allah's Apostle! Is
this permission for us only or is it forever?" The Prophet replied,
"It is forever." In the meantime `Ali bin Abu Talib came from Yemen
and was saying Labbaik for what the Prophet has intended.
(According to another man, `Ali was saying Labbaik for Hajj similar
to Allah's Apostle's). The Prophet told him to keep on the Ihram
and let him share the Hadi with him.</english-text>
</hadith>
