<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>241</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>4</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>240</hadith-number>
<chapter>Ablutions (Wudu') - كتاب الوضوء</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 30361, 20020, 11049, 11382, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، قال أخبرني أبي، عن شعبة، عن أبي إسحاق، عن
عمرو بن ميمون، عن عبد الله، قال بينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
ساجد ح قال وحدثني أحمد بن عثمان قال حدثنا شريح بن مسلمة قال حدثنا
إبراهيم بن يوسف عن أبيه عن أبي إسحاق قال حدثني عمرو بن ميمون أن عبد
الله بن مسعود حدثه أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يصلي عند البيت،
وأبو جهل وأصحاب له جلوس، إذ قال بعضهم لبعض أيكم يجيء بسلى جزور بني
فلان فيضعه على ظهر محمد إذا سجد فانبعث أشقى القوم فجاء به، فنظر حتى
إذا سجد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وضعه على ظهره بين كتفيه وأنا أنظر،
لا أغير شيئا، لو كان لي منعة‏.‏ قال فجعلوا يضحكون ويحيل بعضهم على
بعض، ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ساجد لا يرفع رأسه، حتى جاءته
فاطمة، فطرحت عن ظهره، فرفع رأسه ثم قال ‏"‏ اللهم عليك بقريش ‏"‏‏.‏
ثلاث مرات، فشق عليهم إذ دعا عليهم قال وكانوا يرون أن الدعوة في ذلك
البلد مستجابة ثم سمى ‏"‏ اللهم عليك بأبي جهل، وعليك بعتبة بن ربيعة،
وشيبة بن ربيعة، والوليد بن عتبة، وأمية بن خلف، وعقبة بن أبي معيط
‏"‏‏.‏ وعد السابع فلم يحفظه قال فوالذي نفسي بيده، لقد رأيت الذين عد
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم صرعى في القليب قليب
بدر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin Mas`ud: Once the Prophet was
offering prayers at the Ka`ba. Abu Jahl was sitting with some of
his companions. One of them said to the others, "Who amongst you
will bring the Abdominal contents (intestines, etc.) of a camel of
Bani so and so and put it on the back of Muhammad, when he
prostrates?" The most unfortunate of them got up and brought it. He
waited till the Prophet prostrated and then placed it on his back
between his shoulders. I was watching but could not do any thing. I
wish I had some people with me to hold out against them. They
started laughing and falling on one another. Allah's Apostle was in
prostration and he did not lift his head up till Fatima (Prophet's
daughter) came and threw that (camel's Abdominal contents) away
from his back. He raised his head and said thrice, "O Allah! Punish
Quraish." So it was hard for Abu Jahl and his companions when the
Prophet invoked Allah against them as they had a conviction that
the prayers and invocations were accepted in this city (Mecca). The
Prophet said, "O Allah! Punish Abu Jahl, `Utba bin Rabi`a, Shaiba
bin Rabi`a, Al-Walid bin `Utba, Umaiya bin Khalaf, and `Uqba bin Al
Mu'it [??] (and he mentioned the seventh whose name I cannot
recall). By Allah in Whose Hands my life is, I saw the dead bodies
of those persons who were counted by Allah's Apostle in the Qalib
(one of the wells) of Badr.</english-text>
</hadith>
