<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2411</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>47</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2507</hadith-number>
<chapter>Partnership - كتاب الشركة</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20032, 20012, 20016, 11179, 1986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد، أخبرنا وكيع، عن سفيان، عن أبيه، عن عباية
بن رفاعة، عن جده، رافع بن خديج رضى الله عنه قال كنا مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم بذي الحليفة من تهامة، فأصبنا غنما وإبلا، فعجل القوم،
فأغلوا بها القدور، فجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأمر بها
فأكفئت، ثم عدل عشرا من الغنم بجزور، ثم إن بعيرا ند وليس في القوم
إلا خيل يسيرة فرماه رجل فحبسه بسهم، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إن لهذه البهائم أوابد كأوابد الوحش، فما غلبكم منها فاصنعوا
به هكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال قال جدي يا رسول الله إنا نرجو أو نخاف أن نلقى
العدو غدا وليس معنا مدى، فنذبح بالقصب فقال ‏"‏ اعجل أو أرني، ما
أنهر الدم وذكر اسم الله عليه فكلوا، ليس السن والظفر، وسأحدثكم عن
ذلك، أما السن فعظم، وأما الظفر فمدى الحبشة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abaya bin Rifaa: My grandfather, Rafi` bin
Khadij said, "We were in the valley of Dhul-Hulaifa of Tuhama in
the company of the Prophet and had some camels and sheep (of the
booty). The people hurried (in slaughtering the animals) and put
their meat in the pots and started cooking. Allah's Apostle came
and ordered them to upset the pots, and distributed the booty
considering one camel as equal to ten sheep. One of the camels fled
and the people had only a few horses, so they got worried. (The
camel was chased and) a man slopped the camel by throwing an arrow
at it. Allah's Apostle said, 'Some of these animals are untamed
like wild animals, so if anyone of them went out of your control,
then you should treat it as you have done now.' " My grandfather
said, "O Allah's Apostle! We fear that we may meet our enemy
tomorrow and we have no knives, could we slaughter the animals with
reeds?" The Prophet said, "Yes, or you can use what would make
blood flow (slaughter) and you can eat what is slaughtered and the
Name of Allah is mentioned at the time of slaughtering. But don't
use teeth or fingernails (in slaughtering). I will tell you why, as
for teeth, they are bones, and fingernails are used by Ethiopians
for slaughtering. (See Hadith 668)</english-text>
</hadith>
