<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2419</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>48</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2515</hadith-number>
<chapter>Mortgaging - كتاب الرهن</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20028, 11067, 11353, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا جرير، عن منصور، عن أبي
وائل، قال قال عبد الله رضى الله عنه من حلف على يمين، يستحق بها مالا
وهو فيها فاجر، لقي الله وهو عليه غضبان، فأنزل الله تصديق ذلك ‏{‏إن
الذين يشترون بعهد الله وأيمانهم ثمنا قليلا‏}‏ فقرأ إلى ‏{‏عذاب
أليم‏}‏‏.‏ثم إن الأشعث بن قيس خرج إلينا فقال ما يحدثكم أبو عبد
الرحمن قال فحدثناه قال فقال صدق لفي والله أنزلت، كانت بيني وبين رجل
خصومة في بئر فاختصمنا إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ شاهدك أو يمينه ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت إنه إذا يحلف
ولا يبالي‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من حلف على يمين
يستحق بها مالا هو فيها فاجر، لقي الله وهو عليه غضبان ‏"‏‏.‏ فأنزل
الله تصديق ذلك، ثم اقترأ هذه الآية ‏{‏إن الذين يشترون بعهد الله
وأيمانهم ثمنا قليلا‏}‏ إلى ‏{‏ولهم عذاب أليم‏}‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Wail: Abdullah (bin Mas'ud) said,
"Whoever took a false oath in order to grab somebody's property
will meet Allah while Allah will be angry with him." Allah revealed
the following verse to confirm that:--"Verily! Those who purchase a
small gain at the cost of Allah's covenant And their oaths...a
painful torment." (3.77) Al-Ash'ath bin Qais came to us and asked
as to what Abu Abdur-Rehman (i.e. Ibn Mas'ud) was telling you." We
related the story to him. On that he said, "He has told the truth.
This verse was revealed about me. I had some dispute with another
man regarding a well and we took the case before Allah's Apostle.
Allah's Apostle said (to me), "Produce two witnesses (to support
your claim); otherwise the defendant has the right to take an oath
(to refute your claim).' I said, 'The defendant would not mind to
take a false oath." Allah's Apostle then said, 'Whoever took a
false oath in order to grab someone else's property will meet
Allah, Allah will be angry with him.' Allah then revealed what
Confirmed it." Al-Ash'ath then recited the following
Verse:--"Verily! Those who purchase a small gain at the cost of
Allah's covenant, And their oaths . . . (to) . . . they shall have
a painful torment!' (3.77) (See Hadith No. 546)</english-text>
</hadith>
