<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2437</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2533</hadith-number>
<chapter>Manumission of Slaves - كتاب العتق</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال حدثني
عروة بن الزبير، أن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت إن عتبة بن أبي وقاص عهد
إلى أخيه سعد بن أبي وقاص أن يقبض إليه ابن وليدة زمعة، قال عتبة إنه
ابني‏.‏ فلما قدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم زمن الفتح أخذ سعد ابن
وليدة زمعة‏.‏ فأقبل به إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأقبل معه
بعبد بن زمعة‏.‏ فقال سعد يا رسول الله هذا ابن أخي عهد إلى أنه
ابنه‏.‏ فقال عبد بن زمعة يا رسول الله هذا أخي ابن وليدة زمعة، ولد
على فراشه‏.‏ فنظر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى ابن وليدة زمعة،
فإذا هو أشبه الناس به، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هو لك
يا عبد بن زمعة ‏"‏‏.‏ من أجل أنه ولد على فراش أبيه، قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ احتجبي منه يا سودة بنت زمعة ‏"‏‏.‏ مما رأى
من شبهه بعتبة‏.‏ وكانت سودة زوج النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: `Utba bin Abi Waqqas authorized his
brother Sa`d bin Abi Waqqas to take the son of the slave-girl of
Zam`a into his custody, telling him that the boy was his own
(illegal) son. When Allah's Apostle went (to Mecca) at the time of
the Conquest, Sa`d took the son of the slave-girl of Zam`a to
Allah's Apostle and also brought 'Abu bin Zam`a with him and said,
"O Allah's Apostle! This is the son of my brother `Utba who
authorized me to take him into my custody." 'Abu bin Zam`a said, "O
Allah's Apostle! He is my brother, the son of Zam`a's slave-girl
and he was born on his bed." Allah's Apostle looked at the son of
the slave-girl of Zam`a and noticed much resemblance (to `Utba).
Allah's Apostle said, "It is for you, O 'Abu bin Zam`a as he was
born on the bed of your father." Allah's Apostle then told Sauda
bint Zam`a to observe veil in the presence of the boy as he noticed
the boy's resemblance to `Utba and Sauda was the wife of the
Prophet .</english-text>
</hadith>
