<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2443</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>49</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2539</hadith-number>
<chapter>Manumission of Slaves - كتاب العتق</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20023, 11207, 11013, 10511, 20201,
2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي مريم، قال أخبرني الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن
شهاب، ذكر عروة أن مروان، والمسور بن مخرمة، أخبراه أن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قام حين جاءه وفد هوازن، فسألوه أن يرد إليهم أموالهم
وسبيهم فقال ‏"‏ إن معي من ترون، وأحب الحديث إلى أصدقه، فاختاروا
إحدى الطائفتين إما المال، وإما السبى، وقد كنت استأنيت بهم ‏"‏‏.‏
وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم انتظرهم بضع عشرة ليلة حين قفل من
الطائف، فلما تبين لهم أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم غير راد إليهم إلا
إحدى الطائفتين قالوا فإنا نختار سبينا‏.‏ فقام النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم في الناس، فأثنى على الله بما هو أهله، ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد فإن
إخوانكم جاءونا تائبين، وإني رأيت أن أرد إليهم سبيهم، فمن أحب منكم
أن يطيب ذلك فليفعل، ومن أحب أن يكون على حظه حتى نعطيه إياه من أول
ما يفيء الله علينا فليفعل ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال الناس طيبنا ذلك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
إنا لا ندري من أذن منكم ممن لم يأذن فارجعوا حتى يرفع إلينا عرفاؤكم
أمركم ‏"‏‏.‏ فرجع الناس، فكلمهم عرفاؤهم، ثم رجعوا إلى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأخبروه أنهم طيبوا وأذنوا، فهذا الذي بلغنا عن سبى
هوازن‏.‏ وقال أنس قال عباس للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فاديت نفسي،
وفاديت عقيلا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Marwan and Al-Miswar bin Makhrama: When the
delegates of the tribe of Hawazin came to the Prophet and they
requested him to return their properties and captives. The Prophet
stood up and said to them, "I have other people with me in this
matter (as you see) and the most beloved statement to me is the
true one; you may choose either the properties or the prisoners as
I have delayed their distribution." The Prophet had waited for them
for more than ten days since his arrival from Ta'if. So, when it
became evident to them that the Prophet was not going to return
them except one of the two, they said, "We choose our prisoners."
The Prophet got up amongst the people and glorified and praised
Allah as He deserved and said, "Then after, these brethren of yours
have come to us with repentance, and I see it logical to return
them the captives. So, whoever amongst you likes to do that as a
favor, then he can do it, and whoever of you likes to stick to his
share till we recompense him from the very first war booty which
Allah will give us, then he can do so (i.e. give up the present
captives)." The people unanimously said, "We do that (return the
captives) willingly." The Prophet said, "We do not know which of
you has agreed to it and which have not, so go back and let your
leaders forward us your decision." So, all the people then went
back and discussed the matter with their leaders who returned and
informed the Prophet that all the people had willingly given their
consent to return the captives. This is what has reached us about
the captives of Hawazin. Narrated Anas that `Abbas said to the
Prophet, "I paid for my ransom and `Aqil's ransom."</english-text>
</hadith>
