<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2465</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>50</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2563</hadith-number>
<chapter>Makaatib - كتاب المكاتب</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت جاءت بريرة فقالت إني كاتبت أهلي
على تسع أواق، في كل عام وقية، فأعينيني‏.‏ فقالت عائشة إن أحب أهلك
أن أعدها لهم عدة واحدة، وأعتقك فعلت، ويكون ولاؤك لي‏.‏ فذهبت إلى
أهلها، فأبوا ذلك عليها، فقالت إني قد عرضت ذلك عليهم، فأبوا إلا أن
يكون الولاء لهم‏.‏ فسمع بذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فسألني
فأخبرته، فقال ‏"‏ خذيها، فأعتقيها، واشترطي لهم الولاء، فإنما الولاء
لمن أعتق ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت عائشة فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في
الناس، فحمد الله، وأثنى عليه، ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد، فما بال رجال منكم
يشترطون شروطا ليست في كتاب الله فأيما شرط ليس في كتاب الله فهو
باطل، وإن كان مائة شرط، فقضاء الله أحق، وشرط الله أوثق، ما بال رجال
منكم يقول أحدهم أعتق يا فلان ولي الولاء إنما الولاء لمن أعتق
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha: Buraira came (to `Aisha) and said, "I
have made a contract of emancipation with my masters for nine
Uqiyas (of gold) to be paid in yearly installments. Therefore, I
seek your help." `Aisha said, "If your masters agree, I will pay
them the sum at once and free you on condition that your Wala' will
be for me." Buraira went to her masters but they refused that
offer. She (came back) and said, "I presented to them the offer but
they refused, unless the Wala' was for them." Allah's Apostle heard
of that and asked me about it, and I told him about it. On that he
said, "Buy and manumit her and stipulate that the Wala' should be
for you, as Wala' is for the liberator." `Aisha added, "Allah's
Apostle then got up amongst the people, Glorified and Praised
Allah, and said, 'Then after: What about some people who impose
conditions which are not present in Allah's Laws? So, any condition
which is not present in Allah's Laws is invalid even if they were
one-hundred conditions. Allah's ordinance is the truth, and Allah's
condition is stronger and more solid. Why do some men from you say,
O so-and-so! manumit the slave but the Wala will be for me? Verily,
the Wala is for the liberator."</english-text>
</hadith>
