<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2483</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>51</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2581</hadith-number>
<chapter>Gifts - كتاب الهبة وفضلها والتحريض عليها</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20436, 20160, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني أخي، عن سليمان، عن هشام بن
عروة، عن أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن نساء، رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم كن حزبين فحزب فيه عائشة وحفصة وصفية وسودة، والحزب الآخر
أم سلمة وسائر نساء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، وكان المسلمون قد
علموا حب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عائشة، فإذا كانت عند أحدهم
هدية يريد أن يهديها إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أخرها، حتى إذا
كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في بيت عائشة بعث صاحب الهدية إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في بيت عائشة، فكلم حزب أم سلمة، فقلن
لها كلمي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يكلم الناس، فيقول من أراد أن
يهدي إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هدية فليهده إليه حيث كان من
بيوت نسائه، فكلمته أم سلمة بما قلن، فلم يقل لها شيئا، فسألنها‏.‏
فقالت ما قال لي شيئا‏.‏ فقلن لها فكلميه‏.‏ قالت فكلمته حين دار
إليها أيضا، فلم يقل لها شيئا، فسألنها‏.‏ فقالت ما قال لي شيئا‏.‏
فقلن لها كلميه حتى يكلمك‏.‏ فدار إليها فكلمته‏.‏ فقال لها ‏"‏ لا
تؤذيني في عائشة، فإن الوحى لم يأتني، وأنا في ثوب امرأة إلا عائشة
‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فقالت أتوب إلى الله من أذاك يا رسول الله‏.‏ ثم إنهن
دعون فاطمة بنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأرسلن إلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم تقول إن نساءك ينشدنك الله العدل في بنت أبي
بكر‏.‏ فكلمته‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ يا بنية، ألا تحبين ما أحب ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت
بلى‏.‏ فرجعت إليهن، فأخبرتهن‏.‏ فقلن ارجعي إليه‏.‏ فأبت أن ترجع،
فأرسلن زينب بنت جحش، فأتته فأغلظت، وقالت إن نساءك ينشدنك الله العدل
في بنت ابن أبي قحافة‏.‏ فرفعت صوتها، حتى تناولت عائشة‏.‏ وهى قاعدة،
فسبتها حتى إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لينظر إلى عائشة هل تكلم
قال فتكلمت عائشة ترد على زينب، حتى أسكتتها‏.‏ قالت فنظر النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم إلى عائشة، وقال ‏"‏ إنها بنت أبي بكر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
البخاري الكلام الأخير قصة فاطمة يذكر عن هشام بن عروة عن رجل عن
الزهري عن محمد بن عبد الرحمن‏.‏ وقال أبو مروان عن هشام عن عروة كان
الناس يتحرون بهداياهم يوم عائشة‏.‏ وعن هشام عن رجل من قريش، ورجل من
الموالي، عن الزهري عن محمد بن عبد الرحمن بن الحارث بن هشام قالت
عائشة كنت عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فاستأذنت
فاطمة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa from `Aisha: The wives of Allah's
Apostle were in two groups. One group consisted of `Aisha, Hafsa,
Safiyya and Sauda; and the other group consisted of Um Salama and
the other wives of Allah's Apostle. The Muslims knew that Allah's
Apostle loved `Aisha, so if any of them had a gift and wished to
give to Allah's Apostle, he would delay it, till Allah's Apostle
had come to `Aisha's home and then he would send his gift to
Allah's Apostle in her home. The group of Um Salama discussed the
matter together and decided that Um Salama should request Allah's
Apostle to tell the people to send their gifts to him in whatever
wife's house he was. Um Salama told Allah's Apostle of what they
had said, but he did not reply. Then they (those wives) asked Um
Salama about it. She said, "He did not say anything to me." They
asked her to talk to him again. She talked to him again when she
met him on her day, but he gave no reply. When they asked her, she
replied that he had given no reply. They said to her, "Talk to him
till he gives you a reply." When it was her turn, she talked to him
again. He then said to her, "Do not hurt me regarding Aisha, as the
Divine Inspirations do not come to me on any of the beds except
that of Aisha." On that Um Salama said, "I repent to Allah for
hurting you." Then the group of Um Salama called Fatima, the
daughter of Allah's Apostle and sent her to Allah's Apostle to say
to him, "Your wives request to treat them and the daughter of Abu
Bakr on equal terms." Then Fatima conveyed the message to him. The
Prophet said, "O my daughter! Don't you love whom I love?" She
replied in the affirmative and returned and told them of the
situation. They requested her to go to him again but she refused.
They then sent Zainab bint Jahsh who went to him and used harsh
words saying, "Your wives request you to treat them and the
daughter of Ibn Abu Quhafa on equal terms." On that she raised her
voice and abused `Aisha to her face so much so that Allah's Apostle
looked at `Aisha to see whether she would retort. `Aisha started
replying to Zainab till she silenced her. The Prophet then looked
at `Aisha and said, "She is really the daughter of Abu
Bakr."</english-text>
</hadith>
