<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2586</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>53</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2690</hadith-number>
<chapter>Peacemaking - كتاب الصلح</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20179, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، حدثنا أبو غسان، قال حدثني أبو
حازم، عن سهل بن سعد رضى الله عنه أن أناسا، من بني عمرو بن عوف كان
بينهم شىء، فخرج إليهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في أناس من أصحابه
يصلح بينهم، فحضرت الصلاة، ولم يأت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، فجاء
بلال، فأذن بلال بالصلاة، ولم يأت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فجاء إلى
أبي بكر فقال إن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حبس، وقد حضرت الصلاة فهل
لك أن تؤم الناس فقال نعم إن شئت‏.‏ فأقام الصلاة فتقدم أبو بكر، ثم
جاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يمشي في الصفوف، حتى قام في الصف الأول،
فأخذ الناس بالتصفيح حتى أكثروا، وكان أبو بكر لا يكاد يلتفت في
الصلاة، فالتفت فإذا هو بالنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وراءه فأشار إليه
بيده، فأمره يصلي كما هو، فرفع أبو بكر يده، فحمد الله، ثم رجع
القهقرى وراءه حتى دخل في الصف، وتقدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى
بالناس، فلما فرغ أقبل على الناس فقال ‏"‏ يا أيها الناس ما لكم إذا
نابكم شىء في صلاتكم أخذتم بالتصفيح، إنما التصفيح للنساء، من نابه
شىء في صلاته فليقل سبحان الله، فإنه لا يسمعه أحد إلا التفت، يا أبا
بكر ما منعك حين أشرت إليك لم تصل بالناس ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال ما كان ينبغي
لابن أبي قحافة أن يصلي بين يدى النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: There was a dispute amongst
the people of the tribe of Bani `Amr bin `Auf. The Prophet went to
them along with some of his companions in order to make peace
between them. The time for the prayer became due but the Prophet
did not turn up; Bilal pronounced the Adhan (i.e. call) for the
prayer but the Prophet did not turn up, so Bilal went to Abu Bakr
and said, "The time for the prayer is due and the Prophet i
detained, would you lead the people in the prayer?" Abu Bakr
replied, "Yes, you wish." So, Bilal pronounced the Iqama of the
prayer and Abu Bakr went ahead (to lead the prayer), but the
Prophet came walking among the rows till he joined the first row.
The people started clapping and they clapped too much, and Abu Bakr
used not to look hither and thither in the prayer, but he turned
round and saw the Prophet standing behind him. The Prophet beckoned
him with his hand to keep on praying where he was. Abu Bakr raised
his hand and praised Allah and then retreated till he came in the
(first) row, and the Prophet went ahead and lead the people in the
prayer. When the Prophet finished the prayer, he turned towards the
people and said, "O people! When something happens to you during
the prayer, you start clapping. Really clapping is (permissible)
for women only. If something happens to one of you in his prayer,
he should say: 'Subhan Allah', (Glorified be Allah), for whoever
hears him (saying so) will direct his attention towards him. O Abu
Bakr! What prevented you from leading the people in the prayer when
I beckoned to you (to continue)?" Abu Bakr replied, "It did not
befit the son of Abu Quhafa to lead the prayer in front of the
Prophet.</english-text>
</hadith>
