<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2599</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>53</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2704</hadith-number>
<chapter>Peacemaking - كتاب الصلح</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20005, 30170, 11016</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا سفيان، عن أبي موسى، قال
سمعت الحسن، يقول استقبل والله الحسن بن علي معاوية بكتائب أمثال
الجبال فقال عمرو بن العاص إني لأرى كتائب لا تولي حتى تقتل
أقرانها‏.‏ فقال له معاوية وكان والله خير الرجلين أى عمرو إن قتل
هؤلاء هؤلاء وهؤلاء هؤلاء من لي بأمور الناس من لي بنسائهم، من لي
بضيعتهم فبعث إليه رجلين من قريش من بني عبد شمس عبد الرحمن بن سمرة
وعبد الله بن عامر بن كريز، فقال اذهبا إلى هذا الرجل فاعرضا عليه،
وقولا له، واطلبا إليه‏.‏ فأتياه، فدخلا عليه فتكلما، وقالا له، فطلبا
إليه، فقال لهما الحسن بن علي إنا بنو عبد المطلب، قد أصبنا من هذا
المال، وإن هذه الأمة قد عاثت في دمائها‏.‏ قالا فإنه يعرض عليك كذا
وكذا ويطلب إليك ويسألك‏.‏ قال فمن لي بهذا قالا نحن لك به‏.‏ فما
سألهما شيئا إلا قالا نحن لك به‏.‏ فصالحه، فقال الحسن ولقد سمعت أبا
بكرة يقول رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على المنبر والحسن بن
علي إلى جنبه، وهو يقبل على الناس مرة وعليه أخرى ويقول ‏"‏ إن ابني
هذا سيد، ولعل الله أن يصلح به بين فئتين عظيمتين من المسلمين ‏"‏‏.‏
قال لي علي بن عبد الله إنما ثبت لنا سماع الحسن من أبي بكرة بهذا
الحديث‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Hasan Al-Basri: By Allah, Al-Hasan bin
`Ali led large battalions like mountains against Muawiya. `Amr bin
Al-As said (to Muawiya), "I surely see battalions which will not
turn back before killing their opponents." Muawiya who was really
the best of the two men said to him, "O `Amr! If these killed those
and those killed these, who would be left with me for the jobs of
the public, who would be left with me for their women, who would be
left with me for their children?" Then Muawiya sent two Quraishi
men from the tribe of `Abd-i-Shams called `Abdur Rahman bin Sumura
and `Abdullah bin 'Amir bin Kuraiz to Al-Hasan saying to them, "Go
to this man (i.e. Al-Hasan) and negotiate peace with him and talk
and appeal to him." So, they went to Al-Hasan and talked and
appealed to him to accept peace. Al-Hasan said, "We, the offspring
of `Abdul Muttalib, have got wealth and people have indulged in
killing and corruption (and money only will appease them)." They
said to Al-Hasan, "Muawiya offers you so and so, and appeals to you
and entreats you to accept peace." Al-Hasan said to them, "But who
will be responsible for what you have said?" They said, "We will be
responsible for it." So, whatever Al- Hasan asked they said, "We
will be responsible for it for you." So, Al-Hasan concluded a peace
treaty with Muawiya. Al-Hasan (Al-Basri) said: I heard Abu Bakr
saying, "I saw Allah's Apostle on the pulpit and Al-Hasan bin `Ali
was by his side. The Prophet was looking once at the people and
once at Al-Hasan bin `Ali saying, 'This son of mine is a Saiyid
(i.e. a noble) and may Allah make peace between two big groups of
Muslims through him."</english-text>
</hadith>
