<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2604</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>53</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2709</hadith-number>
<chapter>Peacemaking - كتاب الصلح</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20259, 11201, 11231, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن بشار، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا عبيد الله،
عن وهب بن كيسان، عن جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله عنهما قال توفي أبي
وعليه دين، فعرضت على غرمائه أن يأخذوا التمر بما عليه، فأبوا ولم
يروا أن فيه وفاء، فأتيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكرت ذلك له، فقال
‏"‏ إذا جددته فوضعته في المربد آذنت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏‏.‏ فجاء ومعه أبو بكر وعمر فجلس عليه، ودعا بالبركة ثم قال ‏"‏
ادع غرماءك، فأوفهم ‏"‏‏.‏ فما تركت أحدا له على أبي دين إلا قضيته،
وفضل ثلاثة عشر وسقا سبعة عجوة، وستة لون أو ستة عجوة وسبعة لون،
فوافيت مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المغرب فذكرت ذلك له فضحك
فقال ‏"‏ ائت أبا بكر وعمر فأخبرهما ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالا لقد علمنا إذ صنع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما صنع أن سيكون ذلك‏.‏ وقال هشام عن
وهب عن جابر صلاة العصر‏.‏ ولم يذكر أبا بكر ولا ضحك، وقال وترك أبي
عليه ثلاثين وسقا دينا‏.‏ وقال ابن إسحاق عن وهب عن جابر صلاة
الظهر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: My father died and was
in debt. I suggested that his creditors take the fruits (i.e.
dates) of my garden in lieu of the debt of my father, but they
refused the offer, as they thought that it would not cover the full
debt. So, I went to the Prophet and told him about it. He said (to
me), "When you pluck the dates and collect them in the Mirbad (i.e.
a place where dates are dried), call me (Allah's Apostle)." Finally
he came accompanied by Abu Bakr and `Umar and sat on the dates and
invoked Allah to bless them. Then he said, "Call your creditors and
give them their full rights." So, I paid all my father's creditors
in full and yet thirteen extra Wasqs of dates remained, seven of
which were 'Ajwa and six were Laun or six of which were Ajwa and
seven were Laun. I met Allah's Apostle at sunset and informed him
about it. On that he smiled and said, "Go to Abu Bakr and `Umar and
tell them about it." They said, "We perceived that was going to
happen, as Allah's Apostle did what he did."</english-text>
</hadith>
