<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2622</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2729</hadith-number>
<chapter>Conditions - كتاب الشروط</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، حدثنا مالك، عن هشام بن عروة، عن أبيه،
عن عائشة، قالت جاءتني بريرة فقالت كاتبت أهلي على تسع أواق في كل عام
أوقية، فأعينيني‏.‏ فقالت إن أحبوا أن أعدها لهم، ويكون ولاؤك لي
فعلت‏.‏ فذهبت بريرة إلى أهلها، فقالت لهم، فأبوا عليها، فجاءت من
عندهم ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم جالس، فقالت إني قد عرضت ذلك
عليهم فأبوا إلا أن يكون الولاء لهم‏.‏ فسمع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فأخبرت عائشة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ خذيها واشترطي لهم
الولاء، فإنما الولاء لمن أعتق ‏"‏‏.‏ ففعلت عائشة، ثم قام رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم في الناس، فحمد الله وأثنى عليه، ثم قال ‏"‏ ما
بال رجال يشترطون شروطا ليست في كتاب الله ما كان من شرط ليس في كتاب
الله فهو باطل، وإن كان مائة شرط، قضاء الله أحق، وشرط الله أوثق،
وإنما الولاء لمن أعتق ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa: Aisha said, "Buraira came to me and
said, 'My people (masters) have written the contract for my
emancipation for nine Awaq ) of gold) to be paid in yearly
installments, one Uqiyya per year; so help me." Aisha said (to
her), "If your masters agree, I will pay them the whole sum
provided the Wala will be for me." Buraira went to her masters and
told them about it, but they refused the offer and she returned
from them while Allah's Apostles was sitting. She said, "I
presented the offer to them, but they refused unless the Wala'
would be for them." When the Prophet heard that and `Aisha told him
about It, he said to her, "Buy Buraira and let them stipulate that
her Wala' will be for them, as the Wala' is for the manumitted."
`Aisha did so. After that Allah's Apostle got up amidst the people,
Glorified and Praised Allah and said, "What is wrong with some
people who stipulate things which are not in Allah's Laws? Any
condition which is not in Allah's Laws is invalid even if there
were a hundred such conditions. Allah's Rules are the most valid
and Allah's Conditions are the most solid. The Wala is for the
manumitted."</english-text>
</hadith>
