<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2623</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2730</hadith-number>
<chapter>Conditions - كتاب الشروط</chapter>
<chain-index>20355, 11222, 20001, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو أحمد، حدثنا محمد بن يحيى أبو غسان الكناني،
أخبرنا مالك، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما قال لما فدع أهل
خيبر عبد الله بن عمر، قام عمر خطيبا فقال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم كان عامل يهود خيبر على أموالهم، وقال ‏"‏ نقركم ما أقركم الله
‏"‏‏.‏ وإن عبد الله بن عمر خرج إلى ماله هناك فعدي عليه من الليل،
ففدعت يداه ورجلاه، وليس لنا هناك عدو غيرهم، هم عدونا وتهمتنا، وقد
رأيت إجلاءهم، فلما أجمع عمر على ذلك أتاه أحد بني أبي الحقيق، فقال
يا أمير المؤمنين، أتخرجنا وقد أقرنا محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم وعاملنا
على الأموال، وشرط ذلك لنا فقال عمر أظننت أني نسيت قول رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كيف بك إذا أخرجت من خيبر تعدو بك قلوصك، ليلة بعد
ليلة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال كانت هذه هزيلة من أبي القاسم‏.‏ قال كذبت يا عدو
الله‏.‏ فأجلاهم عمر وأعطاهم قيمة ما كان لهم من الثمر مالا وإبلا
وعروضا، من أقتاب وحبال وغير ذلك‏.‏ رواه حماد بن سلمة عن عبيد الله،
أحسبه عن نافع، عن ابن عمر، عن عمر، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم،
اختصره‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: When the people of Khaibar
dislocated `Abdullah bin `Umar's hands and feet, `Umar got up
delivering a sermon saying, "No doubt, Allah's Apostle made a
contract with the Jews concerning their properties, and said to
them, 'We allow you (to stand in your land) as long as Allah allows
you.' Now `Abdullah bin `Umar went to his land and was attacked at
night, and his hands and feet were dislocated, and as we have no
enemies there except those Jews, they are our enemies and the only
people whom we suspect, I have made up my mind to exile them." When
`Umar decided to carry out his decision, a son of Abu Al-Haqiq's
came and addressed `Umar, "O chief of the believers, will you exile
us although Muhammad allowed us to stay at our places, and made a
contract with us about our properties, and accepted the condition
of our residence in our land?" `Umar said, "Do you think that I
have forgotten the statement of Allah's Apostle, i.e.: What will
your condition be when you are expelled from Khaibar and your camel
will be carrying you night after night?" The Jew replied, "That was
joke from Abul-Qasim." `Umar said, "O the enemy of Allah! You are
telling a lie." `Umar then drove them out and paid them the price
of their properties in the form of fruits, money, camel saddles and
ropes, etc."</english-text>
</hadith>
