<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2624</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2732</hadith-number>
<chapter>Conditions - كتاب الشروط</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20121, 20115, 11013, 10511, 2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر،
قال أخبرني الزهري، قال أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، عن المسور بن مخرمة،
ومروان، يصدق كل واحد منهما حديث صاحبه قال خرج رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم زمن الحديبية، حتى كانوا ببعض الطريق قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن خالد بن الوليد بالغميم في خيل لقريش طليعة فخذوا
ذات اليمين ‏"‏‏.‏ فوالله ما شعر بهم خالد حتى إذا هم بقترة الجيش،
فانطلق يركض نذيرا لقريش، وسار النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى إذا كان
بالثنية التي يهبط عليهم منها، بركت به راحلته‏.‏ فقال الناس حل حل‏.‏
فألحت، فقالوا خلأت القصواء، خلأت القصواء‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما خلأت القصواء، وما ذاك لها بخلق، ولكن حبسها حابس
الفيل، ثم قال والذي نفسي بيده لا يسألوني خطة يعظمون فيها حرمات الله
إلا أعطيتهم إياها ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم زجرها فوثبت، قال فعدل عنهم حتى نزل
بأقصى الحديبية، على ثمد قليل الماء يتبرضه الناس تبرضا، فلم يلبثه
الناس حتى نزحوه، وشكي إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم العطش،
فانتزع سهما من كنانته، ثم أمرهم أن يجعلوه فيه، فوالله ما زال يجيش
لهم بالري حتى صدروا عنه، فبينما هم كذلك، إذ جاء بديل بن ورقاء
الخزاعي في نفر من قومه من خزاعة، وكانوا عيبة نصح رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم من أهل تهامة، فقال إني تركت كعب بن لؤى وعامر بن لؤى نزلوا
أعداد مياه الحديبية، ومعهم العوذ المطافيل، وهم مقاتلوك وصادوك عن
البيت‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنا لم نجئ لقتال
أحد، ولكنا جئنا معتمرين، وإن قريشا قد نهكتهم الحرب، وأضرت بهم، فإن
شاءوا ماددتهم مدة، ويخلوا بيني وبين الناس، فإن أظهر فإن شاءوا أن
يدخلوا فيما دخل فيه الناس فعلوا، وإلا فقد جموا، وإن هم أبوا فوالذي
نفسي بيده، لأقاتلنهم على أمري هذا حتى تنفرد سالفتي، ولينفذن الله
أمره ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال بديل سأبلغهم ما تقول‏.‏ قال فانطلق حتى أتى قريشا
قال إنا قد جئناكم من هذا الرجل، وسمعناه يقول قولا، فإن شئتم أن
نعرضه عليكم فعلنا، فقال سفهاؤهم لا حاجة لنا أن تخبرنا عنه بشىء‏.‏
وقال ذوو الرأى منهم هات ما سمعته يقول‏.‏ قال سمعته يقول كذا وكذا،
فحدثهم بما قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فقام عروة بن مسعود فقال
أى قوم ألستم بالوالد قالوا بلى‏.‏ قال أولست بالولد قالوا بلى‏.‏ قال
فهل تتهموني‏.‏ قالوا لا‏.‏ قال ألستم تعلمون أني استنفرت أهل عكاظ،
فلما بلحوا على جئتكم بأهلي وولدي ومن أطاعني قالوا بلى‏.‏ قال فإن
هذا قد عرض لكم خطة رشد، اقبلوها ودعوني آته‏.‏ قالوا ائته‏.‏ فأتاه
فجعل يكلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
نحوا من قوله لبديل، فقال عروة عند ذلك أى محمد، أرأيت إن استأصلت أمر
قومك هل سمعت بأحد من العرب اجتاح أهله قبلك وإن تكن الأخرى، فإني
والله لأرى وجوها، وإني لأرى أوشابا من الناس خليقا أن يفروا
ويدعوك‏.‏ فقال له أبو بكر امصص بظر اللات، أنحن نفر عنه وندعه فقال
من ذا قالوا أبو بكر‏.‏ قال أما والذي نفسي بيده لولا يد كانت لك عندي
لم أجزك بها لأجبتك‏.‏ قال وجعل يكلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فكلما
تكلم أخذ بلحيته، والمغيرة بن شعبة قائم على رأس النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ومعه السيف وعليه المغفر، فكلما أهوى عروة بيده إلى لحية النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم ضرب يده بنعل السيف، وقال له أخر يدك عن لحية رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فرفع عروة رأسه فقال من هذا قالوا المغيرة
بن شعبة‏.‏ فقال أى غدر، ألست أسعى في غدرتك وكان المغيرة صحب قوما في
الجاهلية، فقتلهم، وأخذ أموالهم، ثم جاء فأسلم فقال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما الإسلام فأقبل، وأما المال فلست منه في شىء ‏"‏‏.‏
ثم إن عروة جعل يرمق أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بعينيه‏.‏ قال
فوالله ما تنخم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نخامة إلا وقعت في كف
رجل منهم فدلك بها وجهه وجلده، وإذا أمرهم ابتدروا أمره، وإذا توضأ
كادوا يقتتلون على وضوئه، وإذا تكلم خفضوا أصواتهم عنده، وما يحدون
إليه النظر تعظيما له، فرجع عروة إلى أصحابه، فقال أى قوم، والله لقد
وفدت على الملوك، ووفدت على قيصر وكسرى والنجاشي والله إن رأيت ملكا
قط، يعظمه أصحابه ما يعظم أصحاب محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم محمدا، والله
إن تنخم نخامة إلا وقعت في كف رجل منهم، فدلك بها وجهه وجلده، وإذا
أمرهم ابتدروا أمره وإذا توضأ كادوا يقتتلون على وضوئه، وإذا تكلم
خفضوا أصواتهم عنده، وما يحدون إليه النظر تعظيما له، وإنه قد عرض
عليكم خطة رشد، فاقبلوها‏.‏ فقال رجل من بني كنانة دعوني آته‏.‏
فقالوا ائته‏.‏ فلما أشرف على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأصحابه، قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا فلان، وهو من قوم يعظمون البدن
فابعثوها له ‏"‏‏.‏ فبعثت له واستقبله الناس يلبون، فلما رأى ذلك قال
سبحان الله ما ينبغي لهؤلاء أن يصدوا عن البيت، فلما رجع إلى أصحابه
قال رأيت البدن قد قلدت وأشعرت، فما أرى أن يصدوا عن البيت‏.‏ فقام
رجل منهم يقال له مكرز بن حفص‏.‏ فقال دعوني آته‏.‏ فقالوا ائته‏.‏
فلما أشرف عليهم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هذا مكرز وهو رجل
فاجر ‏"‏‏.‏ فجعل يكلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، فبينما هو يكلمه إذ
جاء سهيل بن عمرو‏.‏ قال معمر فأخبرني أيوب عن عكرمة، أنه لما جاء
سهيل بن عمرو قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لقد سهل لكم من أمركم
‏"‏‏.‏ قال معمر قال الزهري في حديثه فجاء سهيل بن عمرو فقال هات،
اكتب بيننا وبينكم كتابا، فدعا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم الكاتب، فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سهيل
أما الرحمن فوالله ما أدري ما هو ولكن اكتب باسمك اللهم‏.‏ كما كنت
تكتب‏.‏ فقال المسلمون والله لا نكتبها إلا بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اكتب باسمك اللهم ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال
‏"‏ هذا ما قاضى عليه محمد رسول الله ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال سهيل والله لو كنا
نعلم أنك رسول الله ما صددناك عن البيت ولا قاتلناك، ولكن اكتب محمد
بن عبد الله‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والله إني لرسول
الله وإن كذبتموني‏.‏ اكتب محمد بن عبد الله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال الزهري وذلك
لقوله ‏"‏ لا يسألوني خطة يعظمون فيها حرمات الله إلا أعطيتهم إياها
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ على أن تخلوا بيننا وبين
البيت فنطوف به ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال سهيل والله لا تتحدث العرب أنا أخذنا ضغطة
ولكن ذلك من العام المقبل فكتب‏.‏ فقال سهيل وعلى أنه لا يأتيك منا
رجل، وإن كان على دينك، إلا رددته إلينا‏.‏ قال المسلمون سبحان الله
كيف يرد إلى المشركين وقد جاء مسلما فبينما هم كذلك إذ دخل أبو جندل
بن سهيل بن عمرو يرسف في قيوده، وقد خرج من أسفل مكة، حتى رمى بنفسه
بين أظهر المسلمين‏.‏ فقال سهيل هذا يا محمد أول ما أقاضيك عليه أن
ترده إلى‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنا لم نقض الكتاب بعد
‏"‏‏.‏ قال فوالله إذا لم أصالحك على شىء أبدا‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فأجزه لي ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ما أنا بمجيزه لك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ بلى،
فافعل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ما أنا بفاعل‏.‏ قال مكرز بل قد أجزناه لك‏.‏ قال
أبو جندل أى معشر المسلمين، أرد إلى المشركين وقد جئت مسلما ألا ترون
ما قد لقيت وكان قد عذب عذابا شديدا في الله‏.‏ قال فقال عمر بن
الخطاب فأتيت نبي الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت ألست نبي الله حقا قال
‏"‏ بلى ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت ألسنا على الحق وعدونا على الباطل قال ‏"‏ بلى
‏"‏‏.‏ قلت فلم نعطي الدنية في ديننا إذا قال ‏"‏ إني رسول الله، ولست
أعصيه وهو ناصري ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت أوليس كنت تحدثنا أنا سنأتي البيت فنطوف
به قال ‏"‏ بلى، فأخبرتك أنا نأتيه العام ‏"‏‏.‏ قال قلت لا‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ فإنك آتيه ومطوف به ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فأتيت أبا بكر فقلت يا أبا بكر،
أليس هذا نبي الله حقا قال بلى‏.‏ قلت ألسنا على الحق وعدونا على
الباطل قال بلى‏.‏ قلت فلم نعطي الدنية في ديننا إذا قال أيها الرجل،
إنه لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وليس يعصي ربه وهو ناصره، فاستمسك
بغرزه، فوالله إنه على الحق‏.‏ قلت أليس كان يحدثنا أنا سنأتي البيت
ونطوف به قال بلى، أفأخبرك أنك تأتيه العام قلت لا‏.‏ قال فإنك آتيه
ومطوف به‏.‏ قال الزهري قال عمر فعملت لذلك أعمالا‏.‏ قال فلما فرغ من
قضية الكتاب قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأصحابه ‏"‏ قوموا
فانحروا، ثم احلقوا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فوالله ما قام منهم رجل حتى قال ذلك
ثلاث مرات، فلما لم يقم منهم أحد دخل على أم سلمة، فذكر لها ما لقي من
الناس‏.‏ فقالت أم سلمة يا نبي الله، أتحب ذلك اخرج ثم لا تكلم أحدا
منهم كلمة حتى تنحر بدنك، وتدعو حالقك فيحلقك‏.‏ فخرج فلم يكلم أحدا
منهم، حتى فعل ذلك نحر بدنه، ودعا حالقه فحلقه‏.‏ فلما رأوا ذلك،
قاموا فنحروا، وجعل بعضهم يحلق بعضا، حتى كاد بعضهم يقتل بعضا غما، ثم
جاءه نسوة مؤمنات فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏يا أيها الذين آمنوا إذا جاءكم
المؤمنات مهاجرات فامتحنوهن‏}‏ حتى بلغ ‏{‏بعصم الكوافر‏}‏ فطلق عمر
يومئذ امرأتين كانتا له في الشرك، فتزوج إحداهما معاوية بن أبي سفيان،
والأخرى صفوان بن أمية، ثم رجع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى المدينة،
فجاءه أبو بصير رجل من قريش وهو مسلم فأرسلوا في طلبه رجلين، فقالوا
العهد الذي جعلت لنا‏.‏ فدفعه إلى الرجلين، فخرجا به حتى بلغا ذا
الحليفة، فنزلوا يأكلون من تمر لهم، فقال أبو بصير لأحد الرجلين والله
إني لأرى سيفك هذا يا فلان جيدا‏.‏ فاستله الآخر فقال أجل، والله إنه
لجيد، لقد جربت به ثم جربت‏.‏ فقال أبو بصير أرني أنظر إليه، فأمكنه
منه، فضربه حتى برد، وفر الآخر، حتى أتى المدينة، فدخل المسجد يعدو‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين رآه ‏"‏ لقد رأى هذا ذعرا
‏"‏‏.‏ فلما انتهى إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال قتل والله صاحبي
وإني لمقتول، فجاء أبو بصير فقال يا نبي الله، قد والله أوفى الله
ذمتك، قد رددتني إليهم ثم أنجاني الله منهم‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ويل أمه مسعر حرب، لو كان له أحد ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما سمع ذلك
عرف أنه سيرده إليهم، فخرج حتى أتى سيف البحر‏.‏ قال وينفلت منهم أبو
جندل بن سهيل، فلحق بأبي بصير، فجعل لا يخرج من قريش رجل قد أسلم إلا
لحق بأبي بصير، حتى اجتمعت منهم عصابة، فوالله ما يسمعون بعير خرجت
لقريش إلى الشأم إلا اعترضوا لها، فقتلوهم، وأخذوا أموالهم، فأرسلت
قريش إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم تناشده بالله والرحم لما أرسل، فمن
أتاه فهو آمن، فأرسل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إليهم، فأنزل الله
تعالى ‏{‏وهو الذي كف أيديهم عنكم وأيديكم عنهم ببطن مكة من بعد أن
أظفركم عليهم‏}‏ حتى بلغ ‏{‏الحمية حمية الجاهلية‏}‏ وكانت حميتهم
أنهم لم يقروا أنه نبي الله، ولم يقروا ببسم الله الرحمن الرحيم،
وحالوا بينهم وبين البيت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Miswar bin Makhrama and Marwan: (whose
narrations attest each other) Allah's Apostle set out at the time
of Al-Hudaibiya (treaty), and when they proceeded for a distance,
he said, "Khalid bin Al-Walid leading the cavalry of Quraish
constituting the front of the army, is at a place called Al-Ghamim,
so take the way on the right." By Allah, Khalid did not perceive
the arrival of the Muslims till the dust arising from the march of
the Muslim army reached him, and then he turned back hurriedly to
inform Quraish. The Prophet went on advancing till he reached the
Thaniya (i.e. a mountainous way) through which one would go to them
(i.e. people of Quraish). The she-camel of the Prophet sat down.
The people tried their best to cause the she-camel to get up but in
vain, so they said, "Al-Qaswa' (i.e. the she-camel's name) has
become stubborn! Al-Qaswa' has become stubborn!" The Prophet said,
"Al-Qaswa' has not become stubborn, for stubbornness is not her
habit, but she was stopped by Him Who stopped the elephant." Then
he said, "By the Name of Him in Whose Hands my soul is, if they
(i.e. the Quraish infidels) ask me anything which will respect the
ordinances of Allah, I will grant it to them." The Prophet then
rebuked the she-camel and she got up. The Prophet changed his way
till he dismounted at the farthest end of Al-Hudaibiya at a pit
(i.e. well) containing a little water which the people used in
small amounts, and in a short while the people used up all its
water and complained to Allah's Apostle; of thirst. The Prophet
took an arrow out of his arrow-case and ordered them to put the
arrow in that pit. By Allah, the water started and continued
sprouting out till all the people quenched their thirst and
returned with satisfaction. While they were still in that state,
Budail bin Warqa-al- Khuza`i came with some persons from his tribe
Khuza`a and they were the advisers of Allah's Apostle who would
keep no secret from him and were from the people of Tihama. Budail
said, "I left Ka`b bin Luai and 'Amir bin Luai residing at the
profuse water of Al-Hudaibiya and they had milch camels (or their
women and children) with them, and will wage war against you, and
will prevent you from visiting the Ka`ba." Allah's Apostle said,
"We have not come to fight anyone, but to perform the `Umra. No
doubt, the war has weakened Quraish and they have suffered great
losses, so if they wish, I will conclude a truce with them, during
which they should refrain from interfering between me and the
people (i.e. the 'Arab infidels other than Quraish), and if I have
victory over those infidels, Quraish will have the option to
embrace Islam as the other people do, if they wish; they will at
least get strong enough to fight. But if they do not accept the
truce, by Allah in Whose Hands my life is, I will fight with them
defending my Cause till I get killed, but (I am sure) Allah will
definitely make His Cause victorious." Budail said, "I will inform
them of what you have said." So, he set off till he reached Quraish
and said, "We have come from that man (i.e. Muhammad) whom we heard
saying something which we will disclose to you if you should like."
Some of the fools among Quraish shouted that they were not in need
of this information, but the wiser among them said, "Relate what
you heard him saying." Budail said, "I heard him saying so-and-so,"
relating what the Prophet had told him. `Urwa bin Mas`ud got up and
said, "O people! Aren't you the sons? They said, "Yes." He added,
"Am I not the father?" They said, "Yes." He said, "Do you mistrust
me?" They said, "No." He said, "Don't you know that I invited the
people of `Ukaz for your help, and when they refused I brought my
relatives and children and those who obeyed me (to help you)?" They
said, "Yes." He said, "Well, this man (i.e. the Prophet) has
offered you a reasonable proposal, you'd better accept it and allow
me to meet him." They said, "You may meet him." So, he went to the
Prophet and started talking to him. The Prophet told him almost the
same as he had told Budail. Then `Urwa said, "O Muhammad! Won't you
feel any scruple in extirpating your relations? Have you ever heard
of anyone amongst the Arabs extirpating his relatives before you?
On the other hand, if the reverse should happen, (nobody will aid
you, for) by Allah, I do not see (with you) dignified people, but
people from various tribes who would run away leaving you alone."
Hearing that, Abu Bakr abused him and said, "Do you say we would
run and leave the Prophet alone?" `Urwa said, "Who is that man?"
They said, "He is Abu Bakr." `Urwa said to Abu Bakr, "By Him in
Whose Hands my life is, were it not for the favor which you did to
me and which I did not compensate, I would retort on you." `Urwa
kept on talking to the Prophet and seizing the Prophet's beard as
he was talking while Al-Mughira bin Shu`ba was standing near the
head of the Prophet, holding a sword and wearing a helmet. Whenever
`Urwa stretched his hand towards the beard of the Prophet,
Al-Mughira would hit his hand with the handle of the sword and say
(to `Urwa), "Remove your hand from the beard of Allah's Apostle."
`Urwa raised his head and asked, "Who is that?" The people said,
"He is Al-Mughira bin Shu`ba." `Urwa said, "O treacherous! Am I not
doing my best to prevent evil consequences of your treachery?"
Before embracing Islam Al-Mughira was in the company of some
people. He killed them and took their property and came (to Medina)
to embrace Islam. The Prophet said (to him, "As regards your Islam,
I accept it, but as for the property I do not take anything of it.
(As it was taken through treason). `Urwa then started looking at
the Companions of the Prophet. By Allah, whenever Allah's Apostle
spat, the spittle would fall in the hand of one of them (i.e. the
Prophet's companions) who would rub it on his face and skin; if he
ordered them they would carry his orders immediately; if he
performed ablution, they would struggle to take the remaining
water; and when they spoke to him, they would lower their voices
and would not look at his face constantly out of respect. `Urwa
returned to his people and said, "O people! By Allah, I have been
to the kings and to Caesar, Khosrau and An- Najashi, yet I have
never seen any of them respected by his courtiers as much as
Muhammad is respected by his companions. By Allah, if he spat, the
spittle would fall in the hand of one of them (i.e. the Prophet's
companions) who would rub it on his face and skin; if he ordered
them, they would carry out his order immediately; if he performed
ablution, they would struggle to take the remaining water; and when
they spoke, they would lower their voices and would not look at his
face constantly out of respect." `Urwa added, "No doubt, he has
presented to you a good reasonable offer, so please accept it." A
man from the tribe of Bani Kinana said, "Allow me to go to him,"
and they allowed him, and when he approached the Prophet and his
companions, Allah's Apostle said, "He is so-and-so who belongs to
the tribe that respects the Budn (i.e. camels of the sacrifice).
So, bring the Budn in front of him." So, the Budn were brought
before him and the people received him while they were reciting
Talbiya. When he saw that scene, he said, "Glorified be Allah! It
is not fair to prevent these people from visiting the Ka`ba." When
he returned to his people, he said, 'I saw the Budn garlanded (with
colored knotted ropes) and marked (with stabs on their backs). I do
not think it is advisable to prevent them from visiting the Ka`ba."
Another person called Mikraz bin Hafs got up and sought their
permission to go to Muhammad, and they allowed him, too. When he
approached the Muslims, the Prophet said, "Here is Mikraz and he is
a vicious man." Mikraz started talking to the Prophet and as he was
talking, Suhail bin `Amr came. When Suhail bin `Amr came, the
Prophet said, "Now the matter has become easy." Suhail said to the
Prophet "Please conclude a peace treaty with us." So, the Prophet
called the clerk and said to him, "Write: By the Name of Allah, the
most Beneficent, the most Merciful." Suhail said, "As for
'Beneficent,' by Allah, I do not know what it means. So write: By
Your Name O Allah, as you used to write previously." The Muslims
said, "By Allah, we will not write except: By the Name of Allah,
the most Beneficent, the most Merciful." The Prophet said, "Write:
By Your Name O Allah." Then he dictated, "This is the peace treaty
which Muhammad, Allah's Apostle has concluded." Suhail said, "By
Allah, if we knew that you are Allah's Apostle we would not prevent
you from visiting the Ka`ba, and would not fight with you. So,
write: "Muhammad bin `Abdullah." The Prophet said, "By Allah! I am
Apostle of Allah even if you people do not believe me. Write:
Muhammad bin `Abdullah." (Az-Zuhri said, "The Prophet accepted all
those things, as he had already said that he would accept
everything they would demand if it respects the ordinance of Allah,
(i.e. by letting him and his companions perform `Umra.)" The
Prophet said to Suhail, "On the condition that you allow us to
visit the House (i.e. Ka`ba) so that we may perform Tawaf around
it." Suhail said, "By Allah, we will not (allow you this year) so
as not to give chance to the 'Arabs to say that we have yielded to
you, but we will allow you next year." So, the Prophet got that
written. Then Suhail said, "We also stipulate that you should
return to us whoever comes to you from us, even if he embraced your
religion." The Muslims said, "Glorified be Allah! How will such a
person be returned to the pagans after he has become a Muslim?
While they were in this state Abu- Jandal bin Suhail bin `Amr came
from the valley of Mecca staggering with his fetters and fell down
amongst the Muslims. Suhail said, "O Muhammad! This is the very
first term with which we make peace with you, i.e. you shall return
Abu Jandal to me." The Prophet said, "The peace treaty has not been
written yet." Suhail said, "I will never allow you to keep him."
The Prophet said, "Yes, do." He said, "I won't do.: Mikraz said,
"We allow you (to keep him)." Abu Jandal said, "O Muslims! Will I
be returned to the pagans though I have come as a Muslim? Don't you
see how much I have suffered?" (continued...) (continuing... 1):
-3.891:... ... Abu Jandal had been tortured severely for the Cause
of Allah. `Umar bin Al-Khattab said, "I went to the Prophet and
said, 'Aren't you truly the Apostle of Allah?' The Prophet said,
'Yes, indeed.' I said, 'Isn't our Cause just and the cause of the
enemy unjust?' He said, 'Yes.' I said, 'Then why should we be
humble in our religion?' He said, 'I am Allah's Apostle and I do
not disobey Him, and He will make me victorious.' I said, 'Didn't
you tell us that we would go to the Ka`ba and perform Tawaf around
it?' He said, 'Yes, but did I tell you that we would visit the
Ka`ba this year?' I said, 'No.' He said, 'So you will visit it and
perform Tawaf around it?' " `Umar further said, "I went to Abu Bakr
and said, 'O Abu Bakr! Isn't he truly Allah's Prophet?' He replied,
'Yes.' I said, 'Then why should we be humble in our religion?' He
said, 'Indeed, he is Allah's Apostle and he does not disobey his
Lord, and He will make him victorious. Adhere to him as, by Allah,
he is on the right.' I said, 'Was he not telling us that we would
go to the Ka`ba and perform Tawaf around it?' He said, 'Yes, but
did he tell you that you would go to the Ka`ba this year?' I said,
'No.' He said, "You will go to Ka`ba and perform Tawaf around it."
(Az-Zuhri said, " `Umar said, 'I performed many good deeds as
expiation for the improper questions I asked them.' ") When the
writing of the peace treaty was concluded, Allah's Apostle said to
his companions, "Get up and' slaughter your sacrifices and get your
head shaved." By Allah none of them got up, and the Prophet
repeated his order thrice. When none of them got up, he left them
and went to Um Salama and told her of the people's attitudes
towards him. Um Salama said, "O the Prophet of Allah! Do you want
your order to be carried out? Go out and don't say a word to
anybody till you have slaughtered your sacrifice and call your
barber to shave your head." So, the Prophet went out and did not
talk to anyone of them till he did that, i.e. slaughtered the
sacrifice and called his barber who shaved his head. Seeing that,
the companions of the Prophet got up, slaughtered their sacrifices,
and started shaving the heads of one another, and there was so much
rush that there was a danger of killing each other. Then some
believing women came (to the Prophet ); and Allah revealed the
following Divine Verses:-- "O you who believe, when the believing
women come to you as emigrants examine them . . ." (60.10) `Umar
then divorced two wives of his who were infidels. Later on Muawiya
bin Abu Sufyan married one of them, and Safwan bin Umaiya married
the other. When the Prophet returned to Medina, Abu Basir, a new
Muslim convert from Quraish came to him. The Infidels sent in his
pursuit two men who said (to the Prophet ), "Abide by the promise
you gave us." So, the Prophet handed him over to them. They took
him out (of the City) till they reached Dhul-Hulaifa where they
dismounted to eat some dates they had with them. Abu Basir said to
one of them, "By Allah, O so-and-so, I see you have a fine sword."
The other drew it out (of the scabbard) and said, "By Allah, it is
very fine and I have tried it many times." Abu Basir said, "Let me
have a look at it." When the other gave it to him, he hit him with
it till he died, and his companion ran away till he came to Medina
and entered the Mosque running. When Allah's Apostle saw him he
said, "This man appears to have been frightened." When he reached
the Prophet he said, "My companion has been murdered and I would
have been murdered too." Abu Basir came and said, "O Allah's
Apostle, by Allah, Allah has made you fulfill your obligations by
your returning me to them (i.e. the Infidels), but Allah has saved
me from them." The Prophet said, "Woe to his mother! what excellent
war kindler he would be, should he only have supporters." When Abu
Basir heard that he understood that the Prophet would return him to
them again, so he set off till he reached the seashore. Abu Jandal
bin Suhail got himself released from them (i.e. infidels) and
joined Abu Basir. So, whenever a man from Quraish embraced Islam he
would follow Abu Basir till they formed a strong group. By Allah,
whenever they heard about a caravan of Quraish heading towards
Sham, they stopped it and attacked and killed them (i.e. infidels)
and took their properties. The people of Quraish sent a message to
the Prophet requesting him for the Sake of Allah and Kith and kin
to send for (i.e. Abu Basir and his companions) promising that
whoever (amongst them) came to the Prophet would be secure. So the
Prophet sent for them (i.e. Abu Basir's companions) and Allah I
revealed the following Divine Verses: "And it is He Who Has
withheld their hands from you and your hands From them in the midst
of Mecca, After He made you the victorious over them. ... the
unbelievers had pride and haughtiness, in their hearts ... the
pride and haughtiness of the time of ignorance." (48.24-26) And
their pride and haughtiness was that they did not confess (write in
the treaty) that he (i.e. Muhammad) was the Prophet of Allah and
refused to write: "In the Name of Allah, the most Beneficent, the
Most Merciful," and they (the mushriks) prevented them (the
Muslims) from visiting the House (the Ka`bah).</english-text>
</hadith>
