<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2625</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>54</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2733</hadith-number>
<chapter>Conditions - كتاب الشروط</chapter>
<chain-index>11207, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وقال عقيل عن الزهري، قال عروة فأخبرتني عائشة، أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يمتحنهن، وبلغنا أنه لما أنزل الله تعالى
أن يردوا إلى المشركين ما أنفقوا على من هاجر من أزواجهم، وحكم على
المسلمين، أن لا يمسكوا بعصم الكوافر، أن عمر طلق امرأتين قريبة بنت
أبي أمية، وابنة جرول الخزاعي، فتزوج قريبة معاوية، وتزوج الأخرى أبو
جهم، فلما أبى الكفار أن يقروا بأداء ما أنفق المسلمون على أزواجهم،
أنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏وإن فاتكم شىء من أزواجكم إلى الكفار فعاقبتم‏}‏
والعقب ما يؤدي المسلمون إلى من هاجرت امرأته من الكفار، فأمر أن يعطى
من ذهب له زوج من المسلمين ما أنفق من صداق نساء الكفار اللائي هاجرن،
وما نعلم أحدا من المهاجرات ارتدت بعد إيمانها‏.‏ وبلغنا أن أبا بصير
بن أسيد الثقفي قدم على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مؤمنا مهاجرا في
المدة، فكتب الأخنس بن شريق إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يسأله أبا
بصير، فذكر الحديث‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Az-Zuhri: `Urwa said, "Aisha told me that
Allah's Apostle used to examine the women emigrants. We have been
told also that when Allah revealed the order that the Muslims
should return to the pagans what they had spent on their wives who
emigrated (after embracing Islam) and that the Mushriks should not.
keep unbelieving women as their wives, `Umar divorced two of his
wives, Qariba, the daughter of Abu Urhaiya and the daughter of
Jarwal Al-Khuza`i. Later on Mu'awiya married Qariba and Abu Jahm
married the other." When the pagans refused to pay what the Muslims
had spent on their wives, Allah revealed: "And if any of your wives
have gone from you to the unbelievers and you have an accession (By
the coming over of a woman from the other side) (Then pay to those
whose wives have gone) The equivalent of what they had spent (On
their Mahr)." (60.11) So, Allah ordered that the Muslim whose wife,
has gone, should be given, as a compensation of the Mahr he had
given to his wife, from the Mahr of the wives of the pagans who had
emigrated deserting their husbands. We do not know any of the women
emigrants who deserted Islam after embracing it. We have also been
told that Abu Basir bin Asid Ath-Thaqafi came to the Prophet as a
Muslim emigrant during the truce. Al-Akhnas bin Shariq wrote to the
Prophet requesting him to return Abu Basir.</english-text>
</hadith>
