<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2661</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2769</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wills and Testaments (Wasaayaa) - كتاب الوصايا</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد الله
بن أبي طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه يقول كان أبو طلحة
أكثر أنصاري بالمدينة مالا من نخل، وكان أحب ماله إليه بيرحاء مستقبلة
المسجد، وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يدخلها ويشرب من ماء فيها
طيب‏.‏ قال أنس فلما نزلت ‏{‏لن تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏
قام أبو طلحة فقال يا رسول الله إن الله يقول ‏{‏لن تنالوا البر حتى
تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏ وإن أحب أموالي إلى بيرحاء، وإنها صدقة لله أرجو
برها وذخرها عند الله، فضعها حيث أراك الله‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ بخ، ذلك مال
رابح أو رايح شك ابن مسلمة وقد سمعت ما قلت، وإني أرى أن تجعلها في
الأقربين ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو طلحة أفعل ذلك يا رسول الله‏.‏ فقسمها أبو
طلحة في أقاربه وفي بني عمه‏.‏ وقال إسماعيل وعبد الله بن يوسف ويحيى
بن يحيى عن مالك ‏"‏ رايح ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Abu Talha had the greatest
wealth of date-palms amongst the Ansar in Medina, and he prized
above all his wealth (his garden) Bairuha', which was situated
opposite the Mosque (of the Prophet ). The Prophet used to enter It
and drink from its fresh water. When the following Divine Verse
came:-- "By no means shall you attain piety until you spend of what
you love," (3.92) Abu Talha got up saying. "O Allah's Apostle!
Allah says, 'You will not attain piety until you spend of what you
love,' and I prize above al I my wealth, Bairuha' which I want to
give in charity for Allah's Sake, hoping for its reward from Allah.
So you can use it as Allah directs you." On that the Prophet said,
"Bravo! It is a profitable (or perishable) property. (Ibn Maslama
is not sure as to which word is right, i.e. profitable or
perishable.) I have heard what you have said, and I recommend that
you distribute this amongst your relatives." On that Abu Talha
said, "O Allah's Apostle! I will do (as you have suggested)." So,
Abu Talha distributed that garden amongst his relatives and
cousins.</english-text>
</hadith>
