<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2673</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>55</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2781</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wills and Testaments (Wasaayaa) - كتاب الوصايا</chapter>
<chain-index>30209, 20240, 11385, 11052, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سابق، أو الفضل بن يعقوب عنه حدثنا شيبان
أبو معاوية، عن فراس، قال قال الشعبي حدثني جابر بن عبد الله الأنصاري
رضى الله عنهما أن أباه استشهد يوم أحد، وترك ست بنات، وترك عليه
دينا، فلما حضر جداد النخل أتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت يا
رسول الله قد علمت أن والدي استشهد يوم أحد وترك عليه دينا كثيرا،
وإني أحب أن يراك الغرماء قال ‏"‏ اذهب فبيدر كل تمر على ناحيته
‏"‏‏.‏ ففعلت ثم دعوته، فلما نظروا إليه أغروا بي تلك الساعة، فلما
رأى ما يصنعون أطاف حول أعظمها بيدرا ثلاث مرات ثم جلس عليه ثم قال
‏"‏ ادع أصحابك ‏"‏‏.‏ فما زال يكيل لهم حتى أدى الله أمانة والدي،
وأنا والله راض أن يؤدي الله أمانة والدي ولا أرجع إلى أخواتي بتمرة،
فسلم والله البيادر كلها حتى أني أنظر إلى البيدر الذي عليه رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم كأنه لم ينقص تمرة واحدة‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله
أغروا بي يعني هيجوا بي فأغرينا بينهم العداوة والبغضاء</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah Al-Ansari: My father was
martyred on the day (of the Ghazwa) of Uhud and left six daughters
and some debts to be paid. When the time of plucking the
date-fruits came, I went to Allah's Apostle and said, "O Allah's
Apostle! you know that my father was martyred on Uhud's day and
owed much debt, and I wish that the creditors would see you." The
Prophet said, "Go and collect the various kinds of dates and place
them separately in heaps"' I did accordingly and called him. On
seeing him, the creditors started claiming their rights pressingly
at that time. When the Prophet saw how they behaved, he went round
the biggest heap for three times and sat over it and said, "Call
your companions (i.e. the creditors)." Then he kept on measuring
and giving them, till Allah cleared all my father's debts. By
Allah, it would have pleased me that Allah would clear the debts of
my father even though I had not taken a single date to my sisters.
But by Allah, all the heaps were complete, (as they were) and I
looked at the heap where Allah's Apostle was sitting and noticed as
if not a single date had been taken thereof.</english-text>
</hadith>
