<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2691</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2801</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>34062, 20297, 30312, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حفص بن عمر الحوضي، حدثنا همام، عن إسحاق، عن أنس
رضى الله عنه قال بعث النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أقواما من بني سليم
إلى بني عامر في سبعين، فلما قدموا، قال لهم خالي أتقدمكم، فإن أمنوني
حتى أبلغهم عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وإلا كنتم مني قريبا‏.‏
فتقدم، فأمنوه، فبينما يحدثهم عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ أومئوا
إلى رجل منهم، فطعنه فأنفذه فقال الله أكبر، فزت ورب الكعبة‏.‏ ثم
مالوا على بقية أصحابه فقتلوهم، إلا رجلا أعرج صعد الجبل‏.‏ قال همام
فأراه آخر معه، فأخبر جبريل عليه السلام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
أنهم قد لقوا ربهم، فرضي عنهم وأرضاهم، فكنا نقرأ أن بلغوا قومنا أن
قد لقينا ربنا فرضي عنا وأرضانا‏.‏ ثم نسخ بعد، فدعا عليهم أربعين
صباحا، على رعل وذكوان وبني لحيان وبني عصية الذين عصوا الله ورسوله
صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: The Prophet sent seventy men from the
tribe of Bani Salim to the tribe of Bani Amir. When they reached
there, my maternal uncle said to them, "I will go ahead of you, and
if they allow me to convey the message of Allah's Apostle (it will
be all right); otherwise you will remain close to me." So he went
ahead of them and the pagans granted him security But while he was
reporting the message of the Prophet , they beckoned to one of
their men who stabbed him to death. My maternal uncle said, "Allah
is Greater! By the Lord of the Ka`ba, I am successful." After that
they attached the rest of the party and killed them all except a
lame man who went up to the top of the mountain. (Hammam, a
sub-narrator said, "I think another man was saved along with him)."
Gabriel informed the Prophet that they (i.e the martyrs) met their
Lord, and He was pleased with them and made them pleased. We used
to recite, "Inform our people that we have met our Lord, He is
pleased with us and He has made us pleased " Later on this Qur'anic
Verse was cancelled. The Prophet invoked Allah for forty days to
curse the murderers from the tribe of Ral, Dhakwan, Bani Lihyan and
Bam Usaiya who disobeyed Allah and his Apostle.</english-text>
</hadith>
