<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2731</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2842</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>34207, 20169, 11229, 11020, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سنان، حدثنا فليح، حدثنا هلال، عن عطاء بن
يسار، عن أبي سعيد الخدري رضى الله عنه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قام على المنبر فقال ‏"‏ إنما أخشى عليكم من بعدي ما يفتح عليكم
من بركات الأرض ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم ذكر زهرة الدنيا، فبدأ بإحداهما وثنى
بالأخرى، فقام رجل فقال يا رسول الله أويأتي الخير بالشر فسكت عنه
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قلنا يوحى إليه‏.‏ وسكت الناس كأن على
رءوسهم الطير، ثم إنه مسح عن وجهه الرحضاء، فقال ‏"‏ أين السائل آنفا
أوخير هو ثلاثا إن الخير لا يأتي إلا بالخير، وإنه كل ما ينبت الربيع
ما يقتل حبطا أو يلم كلما أكلت، حتى إذا امتلأت خاصرتاها استقبلت
الشمس، فثلطت وبالت ثم رتعت، وإن هذا المال خضرة حلوة، ونعم صاحب
المسلم لمن أخذه بحقه، فجعله في سبيل الله واليتامى والمساكين، ومن لم
يأخذه بحقه فهو كالآكل الذي لا يشبع، ويكون عليه شهيدا يوم القيامة
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: Allah's Apostle
ascended the pulpit and said, "Nothing worries me as to what will
happen to you after me, except the temptation of worldly blessings
which will be conferred on you." Then he mentioned the worldly
pleasures. He started with the one (i.e. the blessings) and took up
the other (i.e. the pleasures). A man got up saying, "O Allah's
Apostle! Can the good bring about evil?" The Prophet remained
silent and we thought that he was being inspired divinely, so all
the people kept silent with awe. Then the Prophet wiped the sweat
off his face and asked, "Where is the present questioner?" "Do you
think wealth is good?" he repeated thrice, adding, "No doubt, good
produces nothing but good. Indeed it is like what grows on the
banks of a stream which either kills or nearly kills the grazing
animals because of gluttony except the vegetation-eating animal
which eats till both its flanks are full (i.e. till it gets
satisfied) and then stands in the sun and defecates and urinates
and again starts grazing. This worldly property is sweet
vegetation. How excellent the wealth of the Muslim is, if it is
collected through legal means and is spent in Allah's Cause and on
orphans, poor people and travelers. But he who does not take it
legally is like an eater who is never satisfied and his wealth will
be a witness against him on the Day of
Resurrection."</english-text>
</hadith>
