<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2750</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>2861</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>20285, 11297</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسلم، حدثنا أبو عقيل، حدثنا أبو المتوكل الناجي،
قال أتيت جابر بن عبد الله الأنصاري، فقلت له حدثني بما، سمعت من،
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال سافرت معه في بعض أسفاره قال أبو
عقيل لا أدري غزوة أو عمرة فلما أن أقبلنا قال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ من أحب أن يتعجل إلى أهله فليعجل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال جابر فأقبلنا
وأنا على جمل لي أرمك ليس فيه شية، والناس خلفي، فبينا أنا كذلك إذ
قام على، فقال لي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا جابر استمسك ‏"‏‏.‏
فضربه بسوطه ضربة، فوثب البعير مكانه‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أتبيع الجمل ‏"‏‏.‏
قلت نعم‏.‏ فلما قدمنا المدينة ودخل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم المسجد
في طوائف أصحابه، فدخلت إليه، وعقلت الجمل في ناحية البلاط‏.‏ فقلت له
هذا جملك‏.‏ فخرج، فجعل يطيف بالجمل ويقول ‏"‏ الجمل جملنا ‏"‏‏.‏
فبعث النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أواق من ذهب فقال ‏"‏ أعطوها جابرا
‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ استوفيت الثمن ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ الثمن
والجمل لك ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Muslim from Abu `Aqil from Abu Al-Mutawakkil
An-Naji: I called on Jabir bin `Abdullah Al-Ansari and said to him,
"Relate to me what you have heard from Allah's Apostle ." He said,
"I accompanied him on one of the journeys." (Abu `Aqil said, "I do
not know whether that journey was for the purpose of Jihad or
`Umra.") "When we were returning," Jabir continued, "the Prophet
said, 'Whoever wants to return earlier to his family, should hurry
up.' We set off and I was on a black red tainted camel having no
defect, and the people were behind me. While I was in that state
the camel stopped suddenly (because of exhaustion). On that the
Prophet said to me, 'O Jabir, wait!' Then he hit it once with his
lash and it started moving on a fast pace. He then said, 'Will you
sell the camel?' I replied in the affirmative when we reached
Medina, and the Prophet went to the Mosque along with his
companions. I, too, went to him after tying the camel on the
pavement at the Mosque gate. Then I said to him, 'This is your
camel.' He came out and started examining the camel and saying,
'The camel is ours.' Then the Prophet sent some Awaq (i.e. an
amount) of gold saying, 'Give it to Jabir.' Then he asked, 'Have
you taken the full price (of the camel)?' I replied in the
affirmative. He said, 'Both the price and the camel are for you.'
''</english-text>
</hadith>
