<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2900</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3018</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30457, 20299, 11015, 11047, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا معلى بن أسد، حدثنا وهيب، عن أيوب، عن أبي قلابة،
عن أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه أن رهطا، من عكل ثمانية قدموا على النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فاجتووا المدينة فقالوا يا رسول الله، ابغنا
رسلا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما أجد لكم إلا أن تلحقوا بالذود ‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلقوا
فشربوا من أبوالها وألبانها حتى صحوا وسمنوا، وقتلوا الراعي، واستاقوا
الذود، وكفروا بعد إسلامهم، فأتى الصريخ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم،
فبعث الطلب، فما ترجل النهار حتى أتي بهم، فقطع أيديهم وأرجلهم، ثم
أمر بمسامير فأحميت فكحلهم بها، وطرحهم بالحرة، يستسقون فما يسقون حتى
ماتوا‏.‏ قال أبو قلابة قتلوا وسرقوا وحاربوا الله ورسوله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وسعوا في الأرض فسادا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: A group of eight men from
the tribe of 'Ukil came to the Prophet and then they found the
climate of Medina unsuitable for them. So, they said, "O Allah's
Apostle! Provide us with some milk." Allah's Apostle said, "I
recommend that you should join the herd of camels." So they went
and drank the urine and the milk of the camels (as a medicine) till
they became healthy and fat. Then they killed the shepherd and
drove away the camels, and they became unbelievers after whey were
Muslims. When the Prophet was informed by a shouter for help, he
sent some men in their pursuit, and before the sun rose high, they
were brought, and he had their hands and feet cut off. Then he
ordered for nails which were heated and passed over their eyes, and
whey were left in the Harra (i.e. rocky land in Medina). They asked
for water, and nobody provided them with water till they died (Abu
Qilaba, a sub-narrator said, "They committed murder and theft and
fought against Allah and His Apostle, and spread evil in the
land.")</english-text>
</hadith>
