<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2918</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3039</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30237, 20321, 11049, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمرو بن خالد، حدثنا زهير، حدثنا أبو إسحاق، قال
سمعت البراء بن عازب رضى الله عنهما يحدث قال جعل النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم على الرجالة يوم أحد وكانوا خمسين رجلا عبد الله بن جبير فقال
‏"‏ إن رأيتمونا تخطفنا الطير، فلا تبرحوا مكانكم هذا حتى أرسل إليكم،
وإن رأيتمونا هزمنا القوم وأوطأناهم فلا تبرحوا حتى أرسل إليكم ‏"‏
فهزموهم‏.‏ قال فأنا والله رأيت النساء يشتددن قد بدت خلاخلهن وأسوقهن
رافعات ثيابهن، فقال أصحاب عبد الله بن جبير الغنيمة أى قوم الغنيمة،
ظهر أصحابكم فما تنتظرون فقال عبد الله بن جبير أنسيتم ما قال لكم
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالوا والله لنأتين الناس فلنصيبن من
الغنيمة‏.‏ فلما أتوهم صرفت وجوههم فأقبلوا منهزمين، فذاك إذ يدعوهم
الرسول في أخراهم، فلم يبق مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم غير اثنى عشر
رجلا، فأصابوا منا سبعين، وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وأصحابه أصاب
من المشركين يوم بدر أربعين ومائة سبعين أسيرا وسبعين قتيلا، فقال أبو
سفيان أفي القوم محمد ثلاث مرات، فنهاهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن
يجيبوه ثم قال أفي القوم ابن أبي قحافة ثلاث مرات، ثم قال أفي القوم
ابن الخطاب ثلاث مرات، ثم رجع إلى أصحابه فقال أما هؤلاء فقد قتلوا‏.‏
فما ملك عمر نفسه فقال كذبت والله يا عدو الله، إن الذين عددت لأحياء
كلهم، وقد بقي لك ما يسوؤك‏.‏ قال يوم بيوم بدر، والحرب سجال، إنكم
ستجدون في القوم مثلة لم آمر بها ولم تسؤني، ثم أخذ يرتجز أعل هبل،
أعل هبل‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ألا تجيبوا له ‏"‏‏.‏
قالوا يا رسول الله، ما نقول قال ‏"‏ قولوا الله أعلى وأجل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
إن لنا العزى ولا عزى لكم‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ألا
تجيبوا له ‏"‏‏.‏ قال قالوا يا رسول الله، ما نقول قال ‏"‏ قولوا الله
مولانا ولا مولى لكم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Bara bin Azib: The Prophet appointed
`Abdullah bin Jubair as the commander of the infantry men (archers)
who were fifty on the day (of the battle) of Uhud. He instructed
them, "Stick to your place, and don't leave it even if you see
birds snatching us, till I send for you; and if you see that we
have defeated the infidels and made them flee, even then you should
not leave your place till I send for you." Then the infidels were
defeated. By Allah, I saw the women fleeing lifting up their
clothes revealing their leg-bangles and their legs. So, the
companions of `Abdullah bin Jubair said, "The booty! O people, the
booty ! Your companions have become victorious, what are you
waiting for now?" `Abdullah bin Jubair said, "Have you forgotten
what Allah's Apostle said to you?" They replied, "By Allah! We will
go to the people (i.e. the enemy) and collect our share from the
war booty." But when they went to them, they were forced to turn
back defeated. At that time Allah's Apostle in their rear was
calling them back. Only twelve men remained with the Prophet and
the infidels martyred seventy men from us. On the day (of the
battle) of Badr, the Prophet and his companions had caused the
'Pagans to lose 140 men, seventy of whom were captured and seventy
were killed. Then Abu Sufyan asked thrice, "Is Muhammad present
amongst these people?" The Prophet ordered his companions not to
answer him. Then he asked thrice, "Is the son of Abu Quhafa present
amongst these people?" He asked again thrice, "Is the son of
Al-Khattab present amongst these people?" He then returned to his
companions and said, "As for these (men), they have been killed."
`Umar could not control himself and said (to Abu Sufyan), "You told
a lie, by Allah! O enemy of Allah! All those you have mentioned are
alive, and the thing which will make you unhappy is still there."
Abu Sufyan said, "Our victory today is a counterbalance to yours in
the battle of Badr, and in war (the victory) is always undecided
and is shared in turns by the belligerents, and you will find some
of your (killed) men mutilated, but I did not urge my men to do so,
yet I do not feel sorry for their deed" After that he started
reciting cheerfully, "O Hubal, be high! (1) On that the Prophet
said (to his companions), "Why don't you answer him back?" They
said, "O Allah's Apostle What shall we say?" He said, "Say, Allah
is Higher and more Sublime." (Then) Abu Sufyan said, "We have the
(idol) Al `Uzza, and you have no `Uzza." The Prophet said (to his
companions), "Why don't you answer him back?" They asked, "O
Allah's Apostle! What shall we say?" He said, "Says Allah is our
Helper and you have no helper."</english-text>
</hadith>
