<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2934</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3055</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20295, 20115, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا هشام، أخبرنا معمر، عن
الزهري، أخبرني سالم بن عبد الله، عن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما أنه
أخبره أن عمر انطلق في رهط من أصحاب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قبل ابن صياد حتى وجدوه يلعب مع الغلمان عند
أطم بني مغالة، وقد قارب يومئذ ابن صياد يحتلم، فلم يشعر حتى ضرب
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ظهره بيده ثم قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ أتشهد أني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏‏.‏ فنظر إليه ابن
صياد فقال أشهد أنك رسول الأميين‏.‏ فقال ابن صياد للنبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم أتشهد أني رسول الله‏.‏ قال له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ آمنت بالله ورسله ‏"‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ماذا ترى
‏"‏‏.‏ قال ابن صياد يأتيني صادق وكاذب‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ خلط عليك الأمر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني
قد خبأت لك خبيئا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ابن صياد هو الدخ‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اخسأ فلن تعدو قدرك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عمر يا رسول الله، ائذن
لي فيه أضرب عنقه‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن يكنه فلن
تسلط عليه، وإن لم يكنه فلا خير لك في قتله ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn 'Umar: Umar and a group of the
companions of the Prophet set out with the Prophet to Ibn Saiyad.
He found him playing with some boys near the hillocks of Bani
Maghala. Ibn Saiyad at that time was nearing his puberty. He did
not notice (the Prophet's presence) till the Prophet stroked him on
the back with his hand and said, "Ibn Saiyad! Do you testify that I
am Allah's Apostle?" Ibn Saiyad looked at him and said, "I testify
that you are the Apostle of the illiterates." Then Ibn Saiyad asked
the Prophet. "Do you testify that I am the apostle of Allah?" The
Prophet said to him, "I believe in Allah and His Apostles." Then
the Prophet said (to Ibn Saiyad). "What do you see?" Ibn Saiyad
replied, "True people and false ones visit me." The Prophet said,
"Your mind is confused as to this matter." The Prophet added, " I
have kept something (in my mind) for you." Ibn Saiyad said, "It is
Ad-Dukh." The Prophet said (to him), "Shame be on you! You cannot
cross your limits." On that 'Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow
me to chop his head off." The Prophet said, "If he should be him
(i.e. Ad-Dajjal) then you cannot overpower him, and should he not
be him, then you are not going to benefit by murdering
him."</english-text>
</hadith>
