<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>2941</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>56</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3062</hadith-number>
<chapter>Fighting for the Cause of Allah (Jihaad) - كتاب الجهاد
والسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 30277, 20121, 20115, 11013,
11002, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، ح وحدثني
محمود بن غيلان، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن الزهري، عن ابن
المسيب، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال شهدنا مع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال لرجل ممن يدعي الإسلام ‏"‏ هذا من أهل النار ‏"‏‏.‏
فلما حضر القتال قاتل الرجل قتالا شديدا، فأصابته جراحة فقيل يا رسول
الله، الذي قلت إنه من أهل النار فإنه قد قاتل اليوم قتالا شديدا وقد
مات‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إلى النار ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فكاد
بعض الناس أن يرتاب، فبينما هم على ذلك إذ قيل إنه لم يمت، ولكن به
جراحا شديدا‏.‏ فلما كان من الليل لم يصبر على الجراح، فقتل نفسه،
فأخبر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بذلك فقال ‏"‏ الله أكبر، أشهد أني
عبد الله ورسوله ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم أمر بلالا فنادى بالناس ‏"‏ إنه لا يدخل
الجنة إلا نفس مسلمة، وإن الله ليؤيد هذا الدين بالرجل الفاجر
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Az-Zuhri: as follows in Hadith 297.Narrated
Abu Huraira:We were in the company of Allah's Apostle in a Ghazwa,
and he remarked about a man who claimed to be a Muslim, saying,
"This (man) is from the people of the (Hell) Fire." When the battle
started, the man fought violently till he got wounded. Somebody
said, "O Allah's Apostle! The man whom you described as being from
the people of the (Hell) Fire fought violently today and died." The
Prophet said, "He will go to the (Hell) Fire." Some people were on
the point of doubting (the truth of what the Prophet had said)
while they were in this state, suddenly someone said that he was
still alive but severely wounded. When night fell, he lost patience
and committed suicide. The Prophet was informed of that, and he
said, "Allah is Greater! I testify that I am Allah's Slave and His
Apostle." Then he ordered Bilal to announce amongst the people:
'None will enter Paradise but a Muslim, and Allah may support this
religion (i.e. Islam) even with a disobedient man.'</english-text>
</hadith>
