<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3009</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>57</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3133</hadith-number>
<chapter>One-fifth of Booty to the Cause of Allah (Khumus) - كتاب
فرض الخمس</chapter>
<chain-index>30143, 20022, 11015, 11047, 11589</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن عبد الوهاب، حدثنا حماد، حدثنا أيوب،
عن أبي قلابة، قال وحدثني القاسم بن عاصم الكليبي وأنا لحديث القاسم،
أحفظ عن زهدم، قال كنا عند أبي موسى، فأتي ذكر دجاجة وعنده رجل من بني
تيم الله أحمر كأنه من الموالي، فدعاه للطعام فقال إني رأيته يأكل
شيئا، فقذرته، فحلفت لا آكل‏.‏ فقال هلم فلأحدثكم عن ذاك، إني أتيت
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في نفر من الأشعريين نستحمله فقال ‏"‏ والله
لا أحملكم، وما عندي ما أحملكم ‏"‏‏.‏ وأتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم بنهب إبل، فسأل عنا فقال ‏"‏ أين النفر الأشعريون ‏"‏‏.‏ فأمر
لنا بخمس ذود غر الذرى، فلما انطلقنا قلنا ما صنعنا لا يبارك لنا،
فرجعنا إليه فقلنا إنا سألناك أن تحملنا، فحلفت أن لا تحملنا أفنسيت
قال ‏"‏ لست أنا حملتكم، ولكن الله حملكم، وإني والله إن شاء الله لا
أحلف على يمين فأرى غيرها خيرا منها إلا أتيت الذي هو خير وتحللتها
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Zahdam: Once we were in the house of Abu
Musa who presented a meal containing cooked chicken. A man from the
tribe of Bani Taim Allah with red complexion as if he were from the
Byzantine war prisoners, was present. Abu Musa invited him to share
the meal but he (apologised) saying. "I saw chickens eating dirty
things and so I have had a strong aversion to eating them, and have
taken an oath that I will not eat chickens." Abu Musa said, "Come
along, I will tell you about this matter (i.e. how to cancel one's
oat ). I went to the Prophet in the company of a group of
Al-Ashariyin, asked him to provide us with means of conveyance. He
said, 'By Allah, I will not provide you with any means of
conveyance and I have nothing to make you ride on.' Then some
camels as booty were brought to Allah's Apostle and he asked for us
saying. 'Where are the group of Al-Ash`ariyun?' Then he ordered
that we should be given five camels with white humps. When we set
out we said, 'What have we done? We will never be blessed (with
what we have been given).' So, we returned to the Prophet and said,
'We asked you to provide us with means of conveyance, but you took
an oath that you would not provide us with any means of conveyance.
Did you forget (your oath when you gave us the camels)? He replied.
'I have not provided you with means of conveyance, but Allah has
provided you with it, and by Allah, Allah willing, if ever I take
an oath to do something, and later on I find that it is more
beneficial to do something different, I will do the thing which is
better, and give expiation for my oath."</english-text>
</hadith>
