<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3019</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>57</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3143</hadith-number>
<chapter>One-fifth of Booty to the Cause of Allah (Khumus) - كتاب
فرض الخمس</chapter>
<chain-index>30388, 20024, 11013, 11002, 10511, 423</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يوسف، حدثنا الأوزاعي، عن الزهري، عن سعيد
بن المسيب، وعروة بن الزبير، أن حكيم بن حزام رضى الله عنه قال سألت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأعطاني، ثم سألته فأعطاني، ثم قال لي
‏"‏ يا حكيم، إن هذا المال خضر حلو، فمن أخذه بسخاوة نفس بورك له فيه،
ومن أخذه بإشراف نفس لم يبارك له فيه، وكان كالذي يأكل ولا يشبع،
واليد العليا خير من اليد السفلى ‏"‏‏.‏ قال حكيم فقلت يا رسول الله،
والذي بعثك بالحق لا أرزأ أحدا بعدك شيئا حتى أفارق الدنيا‏.‏ فكان
أبو بكر يدعو حكيما ليعطيه العطاء، فيأبى أن يقبل منه شيئا، ثم إن عمر
دعاه ليعطيه فأبى أن يقبل فقال يا معشر المسلمين، إني أعرض عليه حقه
الذي قسم الله له من هذا الفىء، فيأبى أن يأخذه‏.‏ فلم يرزأ حكيم أحدا
من الناس بعد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى توفي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa bin Az-Zubair: Hakim bin Hizam said,
"I asked Allah's Apostle for something, and he gave me. I asked him
again, and he gave me, and said to me. 'O Hakim! This wealth is
like green sweet (i.e. fruit), and if one takes it without greed,
then one is blessed in it, and if one takes it with greediness,
then one is not blessed in it, and will be like the one who eats
without satisfaction. And an upper (i.e. giving) hand is better
than a lower (i.e. taking) hand,' I said, 'O Allah's Apostle! By
Him Who has sent you with the Truth. I will not ask anyone for
anything after you till I leave this world." So, when Abu Bakr
during his Caliphate, called Hakim to give him (some money), Hakim
refused to accept anything from him. Once `Umar called him (during
his Caliphate) in order to give him something, but Hakim refused to
accept it, whereupon `Umar said, "O Muslims! I give him (i.e.
Haklm) his right which Allah has assigned to him) from this Fai
'(booty), but he refuses to take it." So Haklm never took anything
from anybody after the Prophet till he died.</english-text>
</hadith>
