<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3023</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>57</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3147</hadith-number>
<chapter>One-fifth of Booty to the Cause of Allah (Khumus) - كتاب
فرض الخمس</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، حدثنا الزهري، قال
أخبرني أنس بن مالك، أن ناسا، من الأنصار قالوا لرسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم حين أفاء الله على رسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم من أموال هوازن
ما أفاء، فطفق يعطي رجالا من قريش المائة من الإبل فقالوا يغفر الله
لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطي قريشا ويدعنا، وسيوفنا تقطر من
دمائهم قال أنس فحدث رسول الله بمقالتهم، فأرسل إلى الأنصار، فجمعهم
في قبة من أدم، ولم يدع معهم أحدا غيرهم، فلما اجتمعوا جاءهم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ما كان حديث بلغني عنكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
له فقهاؤهم أما ذوو آرائنا يا رسول الله فلم يقولوا شيئا، وأما أناس
منا حديثة أسنانهم فقالوا يغفر الله لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يعطي قريشا ويترك الأنصار، وسيوفنا تقطر من دمائهم‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني أعطي رجالا حديث عهدهم بكفر، أما ترضون أن
يذهب الناس بالأموال وترجعون إلى رحالكم برسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم، فوالله ما تنقلبون به خير مما ينقلبون به ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا بلى يا
رسول الله قد رضينا‏.‏ فقال لهم ‏"‏ إنكم سترون بعدي أثرة شديدة،
فاصبروا حتى تلقوا الله ورسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم على الحوض ‏"‏‏.‏
قال أنس فلم نصبر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: When Allah favored His
Apostle with the properties of Hawazin tribe as Fai (booty), he
started giving to some Quarries men even up to one-hundred camels
each, whereupon some Ansari men said about Allah's Apostle, "May
Allah forgive His Apostle! He is giving to (men of) Quraish and
leaves us, in spite of the fact that our swords are still dropping
blood (of the infidels)" When Allah's Apostle was informed of what
they had said, he called the Ansar and gathered them in a leather
tent and did not call anybody else along, with them. When they
gathered, Allah's Apostle came to them and said, "What is the
statement which, I have been informed, and that which you have
said?" The learned ones among them replied," O Allah's Apostle! The
wise ones amongst us did not say anything, but the youngsters
amongst us said, 'May Allah forgive His Apostle; he gives the
Quarish and leaves the Ansar, in spite of the fact that our swords
are still dribbling (wet) with the blood of the infidels.' "
Allah's Apostle replied, I give to such people as are still close
to the period of Infidelity (i.e. they have recently embraced Islam
and Faith is still weak in their hearts). Won't you be pleased to
see people go with fortune, while you return with Allah's Apostle
to your houses? By Allah, what you will return with, is better than
what they are returning with." The Ansar replied, "Yes, O Allah's
Apostle, we are satisfied' Then the Prophet said to them." You will
find after me, others being preferred to you. Then be patient till
you meet Allah and meet His Apostle at Al-Kauthar (i.e. a fount in
Paradise)." (Anas added:) But we did not remain
patient.</english-text>
</hadith>
