<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3033</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>58</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3158</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jizyah and Mawaada'ah - كتاب الجزية والموادعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 2201, 30154</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال حدثني
عروة بن الزبير، عن المسور بن مخرمة، أنه أخبره أن عمرو بن عوف
الأنصاري وهو حليف لبني عامر بن لؤى وكان شهد بدرا أخبره أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث أبا عبيدة بن الجراح إلى البحرين يأتي
بجزيتها، وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هو صالح أهل البحرين وأمر
عليهم العلاء بن الحضرمي، فقدم أبو عبيدة بمال من البحرين، فسمعت
الأنصار بقدوم أبي عبيدة فوافت صلاة الصبح مع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم، فلما صلى بهم الفجر انصرف، فتعرضوا له، فتبسم رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم حين رآهم وقال ‏"‏ أظنكم قد سمعتم أن أبا عبيدة قد جاء
بشىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا أجل يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأبشروا وأملوا ما
يسركم، فوالله لا الفقر أخشى عليكم، ولكن أخشى عليكم أن تبسط عليكم
الدنيا كما بسطت على من كان قبلكم، فتنافسوها كما تنافسوها وتهلككم
كما أهلكتهم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amr bin `Auf Al-Ansari: (who was an ally of
Bam `Amr bin Lu'ai and one of those who had taken part in (the
Ghazwa of) Badr): Allah's Apostle sent Abu 'Ubaida bin Al-Jarreh to
Bahrain to collect the Jizya. Allah's Apostle had established peace
with the people of Bahrain and appointed Al-`Ala' bin Al-Hadrami as
their governor. When Abu 'Ubaida came from Bahrain with the money,
the Ansar heard of Abu 'Ubaida's arrival which coincided with the
time of the morning prayer with the Prophet. When Allah's Apostle
led them in the morning prayer and finished, the Ansar approached
him, and he looked at them and smiled on seeing them and said, "I
feel that you have heard that Abu. 'Ubaida has brought something?"
They said, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle' He said, "Rejoice and hope for
what will please you! By Allah, I am not afraid of your poverty but
I am afraid that you will lead a life of luxury as past nations
did, whereupon you will compete with each other for it, as they
competed for it, and it will destroy you as it destroyed
them."</english-text>
</hadith>
