<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3042</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>58</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3169</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jizyah and Mawaada'ah - كتاب الجزية والموادعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20023, 11168, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، حدثنا الليث، قال حدثني سعيد،
عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال لما فتحت خيبر أهديت للنبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم شاة فيها سم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اجمعوا إلى
من كان ها هنا من يهود ‏"‏‏.‏ فجمعوا له فقال ‏"‏ إني سائلكم عن شىء
فهل أنتم صادقي عنه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا نعم‏.‏ قال لهم النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ من أبوكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا فلان‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ كذبتم، بل أبوكم
فلان ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا صدقت‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فهل أنتم صادقي عن شىء إن سألت عنه
‏"‏ فقالوا نعم يا أبا القاسم، وإن كذبنا عرفت كذبنا كما عرفته في
أبينا‏.‏ فقال لهم ‏"‏ من أهل النار ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا نكون فيها يسيرا ثم
تخلفونا فيها‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اخسئوا فيها،
والله لا نخلفكم فيها أبدا ثم قال هل أنتم صادقي عن شىء إن سألتكم عنه
‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا نعم يا أبا القاسم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل جعلتم في هذه الشاة
سما ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ما حملكم على ذلك ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا أردنا
إن كنت كاذبا نستريح، وإن كنت نبيا لم يضرك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: When Khaibar was conquered, a
roasted poisoned sheep was presented to the Prophets as a gift (by
the Jews). The Prophet ordered, "Let all the Jews who have been
here, be assembled before me." The Jews were collected and the
Prophet said (to them), "I am going to ask you a question. Will you
tell the truth?'' They said, "Yes.' The Prophet asked, "Who is your
father?" They replied, "So-and-so." He said, "You have told a ie;
your father is so-and-so." They said, "You are right." He siad,
"Will you now tell me the truth, if I ask you about something?"
They replied, "Yes, O AbuAl-Qasim; and if we should tell a lie, you
can realize our lie as you have done regarding our father." On that
he asked, "Who are the people of the (Hell) Fire?" They said, "We
shall remain in the (Hell) Fire for a short period, and after that
you will replace us." The Prophet said, "You may be cursed and
humiliated in it! By Allah, we shall never replace you in it.''
Then he asked, "Will you now tell me the truth if I ask you a
question?" They said, "Yes, O Ab Li-AI-Qasim." He asked, "Have you
poisoned this sheep?" They said, "Yes." He asked, "What made you do
so?" They said, "We wanted to know if you were a liar in which case
we would get rid of you, and if you are a prophet then the poison
would not harm you."</english-text>
</hadith>
