<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3046</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>58</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3173</hadith-number>
<chapter>Jizyah and Mawaada'ah - كتاب الجزية والموادعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20212, 20031, 11810, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا بشر هو ابن المفضل حدثنا يحيى، عن
بشير بن يسار، عن سهل بن أبي حثمة، قال انطلق عبد الله بن سهل ومحيصة
بن مسعود بن زيد إلى خيبر، وهى يومئذ صلح، فتفرقا، فأتى محيصة إلى عبد
الله بن سهل وهو يتشحط في دم قتيلا، فدفنه ثم قدم المدينة، فانطلق عبد
الرحمن بن سهل ومحيصة وحويصة ابنا مسعود إلى النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم، فذهب عبد الرحمن يتكلم فقال ‏"‏ كبر كبر ‏"‏‏.‏ وهو أحدث القوم،
فسكت فتكلما فقال ‏"‏ أتحلفون وتستحقون قاتلكم أو صاحبكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا
وكيف نحلف ولم نشهد ولم نر قال ‏"‏ فتبريكم يهود بخمسين ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا
كيف نأخذ أيمان قوم كفار فعقله النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم من
عنده‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Abi Hathma: `Abdullah bin Sahl and
Muhaiyisa bin Mas`ud bin Zaid set out to Khaibar, the inhabitants
of which had a peace treaty with the Muslims at that time. They
parted and later on Muhaiyisa came upon `Abdullah bin Sah! and
found him murdered agitating in his blood. He buried him and
returned to Medina. `Abdur Rahman bin Sahl, Muhaiyisa and
Huwaiuisa, the sons of Mas`ud came to the Prophet and `Abdur Rahman
intended to talk, but the Prophet said (to him), "Let the eldest of
you speak." as `Abdur-Rahman was the youngest:. `Abdur-Rahman kept
silent and the other two spoke. The Prophet said, "If you swear as
to who has committed the murder, you will have the right to take
your right from the murderer." They said, "How should we swear if
we did not witness the murder or see the murderer?" The Prophet
said, "Then the Jews can clear themselves from the charge by taking
Alaska (an oath taken by men that it was not they who committed the
murder)." The!y said, "How should we believe in the oaths of
infidels?" So, the Prophet himself paid the blood money (of
`Abdullah). (See Hadith No. 36 Vol. 9.)</english-text>
</hadith>
