<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3139</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>59</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3268</hadith-number>
<chapter>Beginning of Creation - كتاب بدء الخلق</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20347, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن موسى، أخبرنا عيسى، عن هشام، عن أبيه،
عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت سحر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ وقال
الليث كتب إلى هشام أنه سمعه ووعاه عن أبيه عن عائشة قالت سحر النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى كان يخيل إليه أنه يفعل الشىء وما يفعله، حتى
كان ذات يوم دعا ودعا، ثم قال ‏"‏ أشعرت أن الله أفتاني فيما فيه
شفائي أتاني رجلان، فقعد أحدهما عند رأسي والآخر عند رجلى، فقال
أحدهما للآخر ما وجع الرجل قال مطبوب‏.‏ قال ومن طبه قال لبيد بن
الأعصم‏.‏ قال في ماذا قال في مشط ومشاقة وجف طلعة ذكر‏.‏ قال فأين هو
قال في بئر ذروان ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرج إليها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم رجع
فقال لعائشة حين رجع ‏"‏ نخلها كأنها رءوس الشياطين ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت
استخرجته فقال ‏"‏ لا أما أنا فقد شفاني الله، وخشيت أن يثير ذلك على
الناس شرا، ثم دفنت البئر ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Magic was worked on the Prophet so
that he began to fancy that he was doing a thing which he was not
actually doing. One day he invoked (Allah) for a long period and
then said, "I feel that Allah has inspired me as how to cure
myself. Two persons came to me (in my dream) and sat, one by my
head and the other by my feet. One of them asked the other, "What
is the ailment of this man?" The other replied, 'He has been
bewitched" The first asked, 'Who has bewitched him?' The other
replied, 'Lubaid bin Al-A'sam.' The first one asked, 'What material
has he used?' The other replied, 'A comb, the hair gathered on it,
and the outer skin of the pollen of the male date-palm.' The first
asked, 'Where is that?' The other replied, 'It is in the well of
Dharwan.' " So, the Prophet went out towards the well and then
returned and said to me on his return, "Its date-palms (the
date-palms near the well) are like the heads of the devils." I
asked, "Did you take out those things with which the magic was
worked?" He said, "No, for I have been cured by Allah and I am
afraid that this action may spread evil amongst the people." Later
on the well was filled up with earth.</english-text>
</hadith>
