<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3164</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>59</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3294</hadith-number>
<chapter>Beginning of Creation - كتاب بدء الخلق</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 10553</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا
أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عبد الحميد بن عبد الرحمن بن
زيد، أن محمد بن سعد بن أبي وقاص، أخبره أن أباه سعد بن أبي وقاص قال
استأذن عمر على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، وعنده نساء من قريش
يكلمنه ويستكثرنه، عالية أصواتهن، فلما استأذن عمر، قمن يبتدرن
الحجاب، فأذن له رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يضحك، فقال عمر أضحك الله سنك يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ عجبت
من هؤلاء اللاتي كن عندي، فلما سمعن صوتك ابتدرن الحجاب ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
عمر فأنت يا رسول الله كنت أحق أن يهبن‏.‏ ثم قال أى عدوات أنفسهن،
أتهبنني ولا تهبن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قلن نعم، أنت أفظ
وأغلظ من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده ما لقيك الشيطان قط سالكا فجا إلا سلك
فجا غير فجك ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`d bin Abi Waqqas: Once `Umar asked the
leave to see Allah's Apostle in whose company there were some
Quraishi women who were talking to him and asking him for more
financial support raising their voices. When `Umar asked permission
to enter the women got up (quickly) hurrying to screen themselves.
When Allah's Apostle admitted `Umar, Allah's Apostle was smiling,
`Umar asked, "O Allah's Apostle! May Allah keep you gay always."
Allah's Apostle said, "I am astonished at these women who were with
me. As soon as they heard your voice, they hastened to screen
themselves." `Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle! You have more right to
be feared by them." Then he addressed (those women) saying, "O
enemies of your own souls! Do you fear me and not Allah's Apostle
?" They replied. "Yes, for you are a fearful and fierce man as
compared with Allah's Apostle." On that Allah's Apostle said (to
`Umar), "By Him in Whose Hands my life is, whenever Satan sees you
taking a path, he follows a path other than yours."</english-text>
</hadith>
