<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3207</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3340</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30311, 30213, 11404, 11406, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق بن نصر، حدثنا محمد بن عبيد، حدثنا أبو
حيان، عن أبي زرعة، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال كنا مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم في دعوة، فرفع إليه الذراع، وكانت تعجبه، فنهس منها
نهسة وقال ‏"‏ أنا سيد القوم يوم القيامة، هل تدرون بمن يجمع الله
الأولين والآخرين في صعيد واحد فيبصرهم الناظر ويسمعهم الداعي، وتدنو
منهم الشمس، فيقول بعض الناس ألا ترون إلى ما أنتم فيه، إلى ما بلغكم،
ألا تنظرون إلى من يشفع لكم إلى ربكم فيقول بعض الناس أبوكم آدم،
فيأتونه فيقولون يا آدم أنت أبو البشر، خلقك الله بيده ونفخ فيك من
روحه، وأمر الملائكة فسجدوا لك، وأسكنك الجنة، ألا تشفع لنا إلى ربك
ألا ترى ما نحن فيه وما بلغنا فيقول ربي غضب غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله،
ولا يغضب بعده مثله، ونهاني عن الشجرة فعصيته، نفسي نفسي، اذهبوا إلى
غيري، اذهبوا إلى نوح‏.‏ فيأتون نوحا فيقولون يا نوح أنت أول الرسل
إلى أهل الأرض، وسماك الله عبدا شكورا، أما ترى إلى ما نحن فيه ألا
ترى إلى ما بلغنا ألا تشفع لنا إلى ربك فيقول ربي غضب اليوم غضبا لم
يغضب قبله مثله، ولا يغضب بعده مثله، نفسي نفسي، ائتوا النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم، فيأتوني، فأسجد تحت العرش فيقال يا محمد ارفع رأسك واشفع
تشفع، وسل تعطه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال محمد بن عبيد لا أحفظ
سائره‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: We were in the company of the
Prophet at a banquet and a cooked (mutton) forearm was set before
him, and he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, "I
will be the chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do
you know how Allah will gather all the first and the last (people)
in one level place where an observer will be able to see (all) of
them and they will be able to hear the announcer, and the sun will
come near to them. Some People will say: Don't you see, in what
condition you are and the state to which you have reached? Why
don't you look for a person who can intercede for you with your
Lord? Some people will say: Appeal to your father, Adam.' They will
go to him and say: 'O Adam! You are the father of all mankind, and
Allah created you with His Own Hands, and ordered the angels to
prostrate for you, and made you live in Paradise. Will you not
intercede for us with your Lord? Don't you see in what (miserable)
state we are, and to what condition we have reached?' On that Adam
will reply, 'My Lord is so angry as He has never been before and
will never be in the future; (besides), He forbade me (to eat from)
the tree, but I disobeyed (Him), (I am worried about) myself!
Myself! Go to somebody else; go to Noah.' They will go to Noah and
say; 'O Noah! You are the first amongst the messengers of Allah to
the people of the earth, and Allah named you a thankful slave.
Don't you see in what a (miserable) state we are and to what
condition we have reached? Will you not intercede for us with your
Lord? Noah will reply: 'Today my Lord has become so angry as he had
never been before and will never be in the future Myself! Myself!
Go to the Prophet (Muhammad). The people will come to me, and I
will prostrate myself underneath Allah's Throne. Then I will be
addressed: 'O Muhammad! Raise your head; intercede, for your
intercession will be accepted, and ask (for anything). for you will
be given. "</english-text>
</hadith>
