<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3220</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3348</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30311, 20318, 11060, 19291, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق بن نصر، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن الأعمش، حدثنا
أبو صالح، عن أبي سعيد الخدري رضى الله عنه عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ‏"‏ يقول الله تعالى يا آدم‏.‏ فيقول لبيك وسعديك والخير في
يديك‏.‏ فيقول أخرج بعث النار‏.‏ قال وما بعث النار قال من كل ألف
تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعين، فعنده يشيب الصغير، وتضع كل ذات حمل حملها،
وترى الناس سكارى، وما هم بسكارى، ولكن عذاب الله شديد ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا
يا رسول الله وأينا ذلك الواحد قال ‏"‏ أبشروا فإن منكم رجل، ومن
يأجوج ومأجوج ألف ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده، إني أرجو أن
تكونوا ربع أهل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أرجو أن تكونوا ثلث
أهل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أرجو أن تكونوا نصف أهل الجنة
‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ما أنتم في الناس إلا كالشعرة السوداء في
جلد ثور أبيض، أو كشعرة بيضاء في جلد ثور أسود ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: The Prophet said,
"Allah will say (on the Day of Resurrection), 'O Adam.' Adam will
reply, 'Labbaik wa Sa`daik', and all the good is in Your Hand.'
Allah will say: 'Bring out the people of the fire.' Adam will say:
'O Allah! How many are the people of the Fire?' Allah will reply:
'From every one thousand, take out nine-hundred-and ninety-nine.'
At that time children will become hoary headed, every pregnant
female will have a miscarriage, and one will see mankind as
drunken, yet they will not be drunken, but dreadful will be the
Wrath of Allah." The companions of the Prophet asked, "O Allah's
Apostle! Who is that (excepted) one?" He said, "Rejoice with glad
tidings; one person will be from you and one-thousand will be from
Gog and Magog." The Prophet further said, "By Him in Whose Hands my
life is, hope that you will be one-fourth of the people of
Paradise." We shouted, "Allahu Akbar!" He added, "I hope that you
will be one-third of the people of Paradise." We shouted, "Allahu
Akbar!" He said, "I hope that you will be half of the people of
Paradise." We shouted, "Allahu Akbar!" He further said, "You
(Muslims) (compared with non Muslims) are like a black hair in the
skin of a white ox or like a white hair in the skin of a black ox
(i.e. your number is very small as compared with
theirs).</english-text>
</hadith>
