<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>322</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>6</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>324</hadith-number>
<chapter>Menstrual Periods - كتاب الحيض</chapter>
<chain-index>30376, 20259, 11015, 11039</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد هو ابن سلام قال أخبرنا عبد الوهاب، عن أيوب،
عن حفصة، قالت كنا نمنع عواتقنا أن يخرجن في العيدين، فقدمت امرأة
فنزلت قصر بني خلف، فحدثت عن أختها، وكان زوج أختها غزا مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ثنتى عشرة، وكانت أختي معه في ست‏.‏ قالت كنا نداوي
الكلمى، ونقوم على المرضى، فسألت أختي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أعلى
إحدانا بأس إذا لم يكن لها جلباب أن لا تخرج قال ‏"‏ لتلبسها صاحبتها
من جلبابها، ولتشهد الخير ودعوة المسلمين ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما قدمت أم عطية
سألتها أسمعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت بأبي نعم وكانت لا تذكره
إلا قالت بأبي سمعته يقول ‏"‏ يخرج العواتق وذوات الخدور، أو العواتق
ذوات الخدور والحيض، وليشهدن الخير ودعوة المؤمنين، ويعتزل الحيض
المصلى ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت حفصة فقلت الحيض فقالت أليس تشهد عرفة وكذا
وكذا</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aiyub: Hafsa said, 'We used to forbid our
young women to go out for the two `Id prayers. A woman came and
stayed at the palace of Bani Khalaf and she narrated about her
sister whose husband took part in twelve holy battles along with
the Prophet and her sister was with her husband in six (out of
these twelve). She (the woman's sister) said, "We used to treat the
wounded, look after the patients and once I asked the Prophet, 'Is
there any harm for any of us to stay at home if she doesn't have a
veil?' He said, 'She should cover herself with the veil of her
companion and should participate in the good deeds and in the
religious gathering of the Muslims.' When Um `Atiya came I asked
her whether she had heard it from the Prophet. She replied, "Yes.
May my father be sacrificed for him (the Prophet)! (Whenever she
mentioned the Prophet she used to say, 'May my father be sacrificed
for him) I have heard the Prophet saying, 'The unmarried young
virgins and the mature girl who stay often screened or the young
unmarried virgins who often stay screened and the menstruating
women should come out and participate in the good deeds as well as
the religious gathering of the faithful believers but the
menstruating women should keep away from the Musalla (praying
place).' " Hafsa asked Um `Atiya surprisingly, "Do you say the
menstruating women?" She replied, "Doesn't a menstruating woman
attend `Arafat (Hajj) and such and such (other
deeds)?"</english-text>
</hadith>
