<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3230</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3358</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30171, 20022, 11015, 20278, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن محبوب، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن أيوب، عن
محمد، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال لم يكذب إبراهيم عليه السلام إلا
ثلاث كذبات ثنتين منهن في ذات الله عز وجل، قوله ‏{‏إني سقيم ‏}‏
وقوله ‏{‏بل فعله كبيرهم هذا‏}‏، وقال بينا هو ذات يوم وسارة إذ أتى
على جبار من الجبابرة فقيل له إن ها هنا رجلا معه امرأة من أحسن
الناس، فأرسل إليه، فسأله عنها‏.‏ فقال من هذه قال أختي، فأتى سارة
قال يا سارة، ليس على وجه الأرض مؤمن غيري وغيرك، وإن هذا سألني،
فأخبرته أنك أختي فلا تكذبيني‏.‏ فأرسل إليها، فلما دخلت عليه ذهب
يتناولها بيده، فأخذ فقال ادعي الله لي ولا أضرك‏.‏ فدعت الله فأطلق،
ثم تناولها الثانية، فأخذ مثلها أو أشد فقال ادعي الله لي ولا أضرك‏.‏
فدعت فأطلق‏.‏ فدعا بعض حجبته فقال إنكم لم تأتوني بإنسان، إنما
أتيتموني بشيطان‏.‏ فأخدمها هاجر فأتته، وهو قائم يصلي، فأومأ بيده
مهيا قالت رد الله كيد الكافر أو الفاجر في نحره، وأخدم هاجر‏.‏ قال
أبو هريرة تلك أمكم يا بني ماء السماء‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Abraham did not tell a lie
except on three occasion. Twice for the Sake of Allah when he said,
"I am sick," and he said, "(I have not done this but) the big idol
has done it." The (third was) that while Abraham and Sarah (his
wife) were going (on a journey) they passed by (the territory of) a
tyrant. Someone said to the tyrant, "This man (i.e. Abraham) is
accompanied by a very charming lady." So, he sent for Abraham and
asked him about Sarah saying, "Who is this lady?" Abraham said,
"She is my sister." Abraham went to Sarah and said, "O Sarah! There
are no believers on the surface of the earth except you and I. This
man asked me about you and I have told him that you are my sister,
so don't contradict my statement." The tyrant then called Sarah and
when she went to him, he tried to take hold of her with his hand,
but (his hand got stiff and) he was confounded. He asked Sarah.
"Pray to Allah for me, and I shall not harm you." So Sarah asked
Allah to cure him and he got cured. He tried to take hold of her
for the second time, but (his hand got as stiff as or stiffer than
before and) was more confounded. He again requested Sarah, "Pray to
Allah for me, and I will not harm you." Sarah asked Allah again and
he became alright. He then called one of his guards (who had
brought her) and said, "You have not brought me a human being but
have brought me a devil." The tyrant then gave Hajar as a
girl-servant to Sarah. Sarah came back (to Abraham) while he was
praying. Abraham, gesturing with his hand, asked, "What has
happened?" She replied, "Allah has spoiled the evil plot of the
infidel (or immoral person) and gave me Hajar for service." (Abu
Huraira then addressed his listeners saying, "That (Hajar) was your
mother, O Bani Ma-is-Sama (i.e. the Arabs, the descendants of
Ishmael, Hajar's son).</english-text>
</hadith>
