<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3254</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3388</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30376, 20356, 15097, 11353, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سلام، أخبرنا ابن فضيل، حدثنا حصين، عن
شقيق، عن مسروق، قال سألت أم رومان، وهى أم عائشة، عما قيل فيها ما
قيل قالت بينما أنا مع عائشة جالستان، إذ ولجت علينا امرأة من
الأنصار، وهى تقول فعل الله بفلان وفعل‏.‏ قالت فقلت لم قالت إنه نما
ذكر الحديث‏.‏ فقالت عائشة أى حديث فأخبرتها‏.‏ قالت فسمعه أبو بكر
ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت نعم‏.‏ فخرت مغشيا عليها، فما
أفاقت إلا وعليها حمى بنافض، فجاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏
ما لهذه ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت حمى أخذتها من أجل حديث تحدث به، فقعدت فقالت
والله لئن حلفت لا تصدقوني، ولئن اعتذرت لا تعذروني، فمثلي ومثلكم
كمثل يعقوب وبنيه، فالله المستعان على ما تصفون‏.‏ فانصرف النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأنزل الله ما أنزل، فأخبرها فقالت بحمد الله لا بحمد
أحد‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Masruq: I asked Um Ruman, `Aisha's mother
about the accusation forged against `Aisha. She said, "While I was
sitting with `Aisha, an Ansari woman came to us and said, 'Let
Allah condemn such-and-such person.' I asked her, 'Why do you say
so?' She replied, 'For he has spread the (slanderous) story.'
`Aisha said, 'What story?' The woman then told her the story.
`Aisha asked, 'Have Abu Bakr and Allah's Apostle heard about it ?'
She said, 'Yes.' `Aisha fell down senseless (on hearing that), and
when she came to her senses, she got fever and shaking of the body.
The Prophet came and asked, 'What is wrong with her?' I said, 'She
has got fever because of a story which has been rumored.' `Aisha
got up and said, 'By Allah! Even if I took an oath, you would not
believe me, and if I put forward an excuse, You would not excuse
me. My example and your example is just like that example of Jacob
and his sons. Against that which you assert, it is Allah (Alone)
Whose Help can be sought.' (12.18) The Prophet left and then Allah
revealed the Verses (concerning the matter), and on that `Aisha
said, 'Thanks to Allah (only) and not to anybody
else."</english-text>
</hadith>
