<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3265</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3400</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30263, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 11004,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمرو بن محمد، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، قال حدثني
أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، أخبره عن ابن
عباس، أنه تمارى هو والحر بن قيس الفزاري في صاحب موسى، قال ابن عباس
هو خضر، فمر بهما أبى بن كعب، فدعاه ابن عباس، فقال إني تماريت أنا
وصاحبي، هذا في صاحب موسى الذي سأل السبيل إلى لقيه، هل سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يذكر شأنه قال نعم سمعت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ بينما موسى في ملإ من بني إسرائيل جاءه رجل، فقال
هل تعلم أحدا أعلم منك قال لا‏.‏ فأوحى الله إلى موسى بلى عبدنا
خضر‏.‏ فسأل موسى السبيل إليه، فجعل له الحوت آية، وقيل له إذا فقدت
الحوت فارجع، فإنك ستلقاه‏.‏ فكان يتبع الحوت في البحر، فقال لموسى
فتاه أرأيت إذ أوينا إلى الصخرة، فإني نسيت الحوت، وما أنسانيه إلا
الشيطان أن أذكره‏.‏ فقال موسى ذلك ما كنا نبغ‏.‏ فارتدا على آثارهما
قصصا فوجدا خضرا، فكان من شأنهما الذي قص الله في كتابه
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: That he differed with Al-Hur bin
Qais Al-Fazari regarding the companion of Moses. Ibn `Abbas said
that he was Al-Khadir. Meanwhile Ubai bin Ka`b passed by them and
Ibn `Abbas called him saying, "My friend and I have differed
regarding Moses' companion whom Moses asked the way to meet. Have
you heard Allah's Apostle mentioning something about him?" He said,
"Yes, I heard Allah's Apostle saying, 'While Moses was sitting in
the company of some Israelites, a man came and asked (him), 'Do you
know anyone who is more learned than you?' Moses replied, 'No.' So,
Allah sent the Divine Inspiration to Moses: 'Yes, Our slave, Khadir
(is more learned than you).' Moses asked how to meet him (i.e.
Khadir). So, the fish, was made, as a sign for him, and he was told
that when the fish was lost, he should return and there he would
meet him. So, Moses went on looking for the sign of the fish in the
sea. The servant boy of Moses said to him, 'Do you know that when
we were sitting by the side of the rock, I forgot the fish, and t
was only Satan who made me forget to tell (you) about it.' Moses
said, That was what we were seeking after,' and both of them
returned, following their footmarks and found Khadir; and what
happened further to them, is mentioned in Allah's
Book."</english-text>
</hadith>
