<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3266</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3401</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11081, 11050, 39</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا عمرو بن
دينار، قال أخبرني سعيد بن جبير، قال قلت لابن عباس إن نوفا البكالي
يزعم أن موسى صاحب الخضر ليس هو موسى بني إسرائيل، إنما هو موسى
آخر‏.‏ فقال كذب عدو الله حدثنا أبى بن كعب عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أن موسى قام خطيبا في بني إسرائيل، فسئل أى الناس أعلم فقال
أنا‏.‏ فعتب الله عليه إذ لم يرد العلم إليه‏.‏ فقال له بلى، لي عبد
بمجمع البحرين هو أعلم منك‏.‏ قال أى رب ومن لي به وربما قال سفيان أى
رب وكيف لي به قال تأخذ حوتا، فتجعله في مكتل، حيثما فقدت الحوت فهو
ثم وربما قال فهو ثمه وأخذ حوتا، فجعله في مكتل، ثم انطلق هو وفتاه
يوشع بن نون، حتى أتيا الصخرة، وضعا رءوسهما فرقد موسى، واضطرب الحوت
فخرج فسقط في البحر، فاتخذ سبيله في البحر سربا، فأمسك الله عن الحوت
جرية الماء، فصار مثل الطاق، فقال هكذا مثل الطاق‏.‏ فانطلقا يمشيان
بقية ليلتهما ويومهما، حتى إذا كان من الغد قال لفتاه آتنا غداءنا لقد
لقينا من سفرنا هذا نصبا‏.‏ ولم يجد موسى النصب حتى جاوز حيث أمره
الله‏.‏ قال له فتاه أرأيت إذ أوينا إلى الصخرة فإني نسيت الحوت، وما
أنسانيه إلا الشيطان أن أذكره، واتخذ سبيله في البحر عجبا، فكان للحوت
سربا ولهما عجبا‏.‏ قال له موسى ذلك ما كنا نبغي، فارتدا على آثارهما
قصصا، رجعا يقصان آثارهما حتى انتهيا إلى الصخرة، فإذا رجل مسجى بثوب،
فسلم موسى، فرد عليه‏.‏ فقال وأنى بأرضك السلام‏.‏ قال أنا موسى‏.‏
قال موسى بني إسرائيل قال نعم، أتيتك لتعلمني مما علمت رشدا‏.‏ قال يا
موسى إني على علم من علم الله، علمنيه الله لا تعلمه وأنت على علم من
علم الله علمكه الله لا أعلمه‏.‏ قال هل أتبعك قال ‏{‏إنك لن تستطيع
معي صبرا * وكيف تصبر على ما لم تحط به خبرا‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏إمرا‏}‏
فانطلقا يمشيان على ساحل البحر، فمرت بهما سفينة، كلموهم أن يحملوهم،
فعرفوا الخضر، فحملوه بغير نول، فلما ركبا في السفينة جاء عصفور، فوقع
على حرف السفينة، فنقر في البحر نقرة أو نقرتين، قال له الخضر يا
موسى، ما نقص علمي وعلمك من علم الله إلا مثل ما نقص هذا العصفور
بمنقاره من البحر‏.‏ إذ أخذ الفأس فنزع لوحا، قال فلم يفجأ موسى إلا
وقد قلع لوحا بالقدوم‏.‏ فقال له موسى ما صنعت قوم حملونا بغير نول،
عمدت إلى سفينتهم فخرقتها لتغرق أهلها، لقد جئت شيئا إمرا‏.‏ قال ألم
أقل إنك لن تستطيع معي صبرا‏.‏ قال لا تؤاخذني بما نسيت ولا ترهقني من
أمري عسرا، فكانت الأولى من موسى نسيانا‏.‏ فلما خرجا من البحر مروا
بغلام يلعب مع الصبيان، فأخذ الخضر برأسه فقلعه بيده هكذا وأومأ سفيان
بأطراف أصابعه كأنه يقطف شيئا فقال له موسى أقتلت نفسا زكية بغير نفس
لقد جئت شيئا نكرا‏.‏ قال ألم أقل لك إنك لن تستطيع معي صبرا‏.‏ قال
إن سألتك عن شىء بعدها فلا تصاحبني، قد بلغت من لدني عذرا‏.‏ فانطلقا
حتى إذا أتيا أهل قرية استطعما أهلها فأبوا أن يضيفوهما فوجدا فيها
جدارا يريد أن ينقض مائلا أومأ بيده هكذا وأشار سفيان كأنه يمسح شيئا
إلى فوق، فلم أسمع سفيان يذكر مائلا إلا مرة قال قوم أتيناهم فلم
يطعمونا ولم يضيفونا عمدت إلى حائطهم لو شئت لاتخذت عليه أجرا‏.‏ قال
هذا فراق بيني وبينك، سأنبئك بتأويل ما لم تستطع عليه صبرا‏"‏‏.‏ قال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وددنا أن موسى كان صبر، فقص الله علينا
من خبرهما ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سفيان قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يرحم
الله موسى، لو كان صبر يقص علينا من أمرهما ‏"‏‏.‏ وقرأ ابن عباس
أمامهم ملك يأخذ كل سفينة صالحة غصبا، وأما الغلام فكان كافرا وكان
أبواه مؤمنين‏.‏ ثم قال لي سفيان سمعته منه مرتين وحفظته منه‏.‏ قيل
لسفيان حفظته قبل أن تسمعه من عمرو، أو تحفظته من إنسان فقال ممن
أتحفظه ورواه أحد عن عمرو غيري سمعته منه مرتين أو ثلاثا وحفظته
منه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id bin Jubair: I said to Ibn `Abbas,
"Nauf Al-Bukah claims that Moses, the companion of Al-Khadir was
not Moses (the prophet) of the children of Israel, but some other
Moses." Ibn `Abbas said, "Allah's enemy (i.e. Nauf) has told a lie.
Ubai bin Ka`b told us that the Prophet said, 'Once Moses stood up
and addressed Bani Israel. He was asked who was the most learned
man amongst the people. He said, 'I.' Allah admonished him as he
did not attribute absolute knowledge to Him (Allah). So, Allah said
to him, 'Yes, at the junction of the two seas there is a Slave of
Mine who is more learned than you.' Moses said, 'O my Lord! How can
I meet him?' Allah said, 'Take a fish and put it in a large basket
and you will find him at the place where you will lose the fish.'
Moses took a fish and put it in a basket and proceeded along with
his (servant) boy, Yusha` bin Noon, till they reached the rock
where they laid their heads (i.e. lay down). Moses slept, and the
fish, moving out of the basket, fell into the sea. It took its way
into the sea (straight) as in a tunnel. Allah stopped the flow of
water over the fish and it became like an arch (the Prophet pointed
out this arch with his hands). They travelled the rest of the
night, and the next day Moses said to his boy (servant), 'Give us
our food, for indeed, we have suffered much fatigue in this journey
of ours.' Moses did not feel tired till he crossed that place which
Allah had ordered him to seek after. His boy (servant) said to him,
'Do you know that when we were sitting near that rock, I forgot the
fish, and none but Satan caused me to forget to tell (you) about
it, and it took its course into the sea in an amazing way?.' So
there was a path for the fish and that astonished them. Moses said,
'That was what we were seeking after.' So, both of them retraced
their footsteps till they reached the rock. There they saw a man
Lying covered with a garment. Moses greeted him and he replied
saying, 'How do people greet each other in your land?' Moses said,
'I am Moses.' The man asked, 'Moses of Bani Israel?' Moses said,
'Yes, I have come to you so that you may teach me from those things
which Allah has taught you.' He said, 'O Moses! I have some of the
Knowledge of Allah which Allah has taught me, and which you do not
know, while you have some of the Knowledge of Allah which Allah has
taught you and which I do not know.' Moses asked, 'May I follow
you?' He said, 'But you will not be able to remain patient with me
for how can you be patient about things which you will not be able
to understand?' (Moses said, 'You will find me, if Allah so will,
truly patient, and I will not disobey you in aught.') So, both of
them set out walking along the sea-shore, a boat passed by them and
they asked the crew of the boat to take them on board. The crew
recognized Al-Khadir and so they took them on board without fare.
When they were on board the boat, a sparrow came and stood on the
edge of the boat and dipped its beak once or twice into the sea.
Al-Khadir said to Moses, 'O Moses! My knowledge and your knowledge
have not decreased Allah's Knowledge except as much as this sparrow
has decreased the water of the sea with its beak.' Then suddenly
Al-Khadir took an adze and plucked a plank, and Moses did not
notice it till he had plucked a plank with the adze. Moses said to
him, 'What have you done? They took us on board charging us
nothing; yet you I have intentionally made a hole in their boat so
as to drown its passengers. Verily, you have done a dreadful
thing.' Al-Khadir replied, 'Did I not tell you that you would not
be able to remain patient with me?' Moses replied, 'Do not blame me
for what I have forgotten, and do not be hard upon me for my
fault.' So the first excuse of Moses was that he had forgotten.
When they had left the sea, they passed by a boy playing with other
boys. Al-Khadir took hold of the boys head and plucked it with his
hand like this. (Sufyan, the sub narrator pointed with his
fingertips as if he was plucking some fruit.) Moses said to him,
"Have you killed an innocent person who has not killed any person?
You have really done a horrible thing." Al-Khadir said, "Did I not
tell you that you could not remain patient with me?' Moses said "If
I ask you about anything after this, don't accompany me. You have
received an excuse from me.' Then both of them went on till they
came to some people of a village, and they asked its inhabitant for
wood but they refused to entertain them as guests. Then they saw
therein a wall which was just going to collapse (and Al Khadir
repaired it just by touching it with his hands). (Sufyan, the
sub-narrator, pointed with his hands, illustrating how Al-Khadir
passed his hands over the wall upwards.) Moses said, "These are the
people whom we have called on, but they neither gave us food, nor
entertained us as guests, yet you have repaired their wall. If you
had wished, you could have taken wages for it." Al-Khadir said,
"This is the parting between you and me, and I shall tell you the
explanation of those things on which you could not remain patient."
The Prophet added, "We wished that Moses could have remained
patient by virtue of which Allah might have told us more about
their story. (Sufyan the sub-narrator said that the Prophet said,
"May Allah bestow His Mercy on Moses! If he had remained patient,
we would have been told further about their case.")</english-text>
</hadith>
