<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3269</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3404</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30123, 20229, 11298, 11016, 11035, 11283,
13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق بن إبراهيم، حدثنا روح بن عبادة، حدثنا عوف،
عن الحسن، ومحمد، وخلاس، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال قال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن موسى كان رجلا حييا ستيرا، لا يرى من جلده
شىء، استحياء منه، فآذاه من آذاه من بني إسرائيل، فقالوا ما يستتر هذا
التستر إلا من عيب بجلده، إما برص وإما أدرة وإما آفة‏.‏ وإن الله
أراد أن يبرئه مما قالوا لموسى فخلا يوما وحده فوضع ثيابه على الحجر
ثم اغتسل، فلما فرغ أقبل إلى ثيابه ليأخذها، وإن الحجر عدا بثوبه،
فأخذ موسى عصاه وطلب الحجر، فجعل يقول ثوبي حجر، ثوبي حجر، حتى انتهى
إلى ملإ من بني إسرائيل، فرأوه عريانا أحسن ما خلق الله، وأبرأه مما
يقولون، وقام الحجر فأخذ ثوبه فلبسه، وطفق بالحجر ضربا بعصاه، فوالله
إن بالحجر لندبا من أثر ضربه ثلاثا أو أربعا أو خمسا، فذلك قوله ‏{‏يا
أيها الذين آمنوا لا تكونوا كالذين آذوا موسى فبرأه الله مما قالوا
وكان عند الله وجيها‏}‏‏.‏‏"‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Allah's Apostle said, "(The
Prophet) Moses was a shy person and used to cover his body
completely because of his extensive shyness. One of the children of
Israel hurt him by saying, 'He covers his body in this way only
because of some defect in his skin, either leprosy or scrotal
hernia, or he has some other defect.' Allah wished to clear Moses
of what they said about him, so one day while Moses was in
seclusion, he took off his clothes and put them on a stone and
started taking a bath. When he had finished the bath, he moved
towards his clothes so as to take them, but the stone took his
clothes and fled; Moses picked up his stick and ran after the stone
saying, 'O stone! Give me my garment!' Till he reached a group of
Bani Israel who saw him naked then, and found him the best of what
Allah had created, and Allah cleared him of what they had accused
him of. The stone stopped there and Moses took and put his garment
on and started hitting the stone with his stick. By Allah, the
stone still has some traces of the hitting, three, four or five
marks. This was what Allah refers to in His Saying:-- "O you who
believe! Be you not like those Who annoyed Moses, But Allah proved
his innocence of that which they alleged, And he was honorable In
Allah's Sight." (33.69)</english-text>
</hadith>
