<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3318</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3459</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا ليث، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر
رضى الله عنهما عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ إنما أجلكم
في أجل من خلا من الأمم ما بين صلاة العصر إلى مغرب الشمس، وإنما
مثلكم ومثل اليهود والنصارى كرجل استعمل عمالا فقال من يعمل لي إلى
نصف النهار على قيراط قيراط فعملت اليهود إلى نصف النهار على قيراط
قيراط، ثم قال من يعمل لي من نصف النهار إلى صلاة العصر على قيراط
قيراط فعملت النصارى من نصف النهار إلى صلاة العصر، على قيراط قيراط،
ثم قال من يعمل لي من صلاة العصر إلى مغرب الشمس على قيراطين قيراطين
ألا فأنتم الذين يعملون من صلاة العصر إلى مغرب الشمس على قيراطين
قيراطين، ألا لكم الأجر مرتين، فغضبت اليهود والنصارى، فقالوا نحن
أكثر عملا وأقل عطاء، قال الله هل ظلمتكم من حقكم شيئا قالوا لا‏.‏
قال فإنه فضلي أعطيه من شئت ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: Allah's Apostle said, "Your
period (i.e. the Muslims' period) in comparison to the periods of
the previous nations, is like the period between the `Asr prayer
and sunset. And your example in comparison to the Jews and the
Christians is like the example of a person who employed some
laborers and asked them, 'Who will work for me till midday for one
Qirat each?' The Jews worked for half a day for one Qirat each. The
person asked, 'Who will do the work for me from midday to the time
of the `Asr (prayer) for one Qirat each?' The Christians worked
from midday till the `Asr prayer for one Qirat. Then the person
asked, 'Who will do the work for me from the `Asr till sunset for
two Qirats each?' " The Prophet added, "It is you (i.e. Muslims)
who are doing the work from the `Asr till sunset, so you will have
a double reward. The Jews and the Christians got angry and said,
'We have done more work but got less wages.' Allah said, 'Have I
been unjust to you as regards your rights?' They said, 'No.' So
Allah said, 'Then it is My Blessing which I bestow on whomever I
like. "</english-text>
</hadith>
