<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3324</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3465</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30186, 20345, 11201, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل بن خليل، أخبرنا علي بن مسهر، عن عبيد
الله بن عمر، عن نافع، عن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما أن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ بينما ثلاثة نفر ممن كان قبلكم يمشون إذ
أصابهم مطر، فأووا إلى غار، فانطبق عليهم، فقال بعضهم لبعض إنه والله
يا هؤلاء لا ينجيكم إلا الصدق، فليدع كل رجل منكم بما يعلم أنه قد صدق
فيه‏.‏ فقال واحد منهم اللهم إن كنت تعلم أنه كان لي أجير عمل لي على
فرق من أرز، فذهب وتركه، وأني عمدت إلى ذلك الفرق فزرعته، فصار من
أمره أني اشتريت منه بقرا، وأنه أتاني يطلب أجره فقلت اعمد إلى تلك
البقر‏.‏ فسقها، فقال لي إنما لي عندك فرق من أرز‏.‏ فقلت له اعمد إلى
تلك البقر فإنها من ذلك الفرق، فساقها، فإن كنت تعلم أني فعلت ذلك من
خشيتك، ففرج عنا‏.‏ فانساحت عنهم الصخرة‏.‏ فقال الآخر اللهم إن كنت
تعلم أنه كان لي أبوان شيخان كبيران، فكنت آتيهما كل ليلة بلبن غنم
لي، فأبطأت عليهما ليلة فجئت وقد رقدا وأهلي وعيالي يتضاغون من الجوع،
فكنت لا أسقيهم حتى يشرب أبواى، فكرهت أن أوقظهما، وكرهت أن أدعهما،
فيستكنا لشربتهما، فلم أزل أنتظر حتى طلع الفجر، فإن كنت تعلم أني
فعلت ذلك من خشيتك، ففرج عنا‏.‏ فانساحت عنهم الصخرة، حتى نظروا إلى
السماء‏.‏ فقال الآخر اللهم إن كنت تعلم أنه كان لي ابنة عم من أحب
الناس إلى، وأني راودتها عن نفسها فأبت إلا أن آتيها بمائة دينار،
فطلبتها حتى قدرت، فأتيتها بها فدفعتها إليها، فأمكنتني من نفسها،
فلما قعدت بين رجليها، فقالت اتق الله ولا تفض الخاتم إلا بحقه‏.‏
فقمت وتركت المائة دينار، فإن كنت تعلم أني فعلت ذلك من خشيتك ففرج
عنا‏.‏ ففرج الله عنهم فخرجوا ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: Allah's Apostle said, "Once three
persons (from the previous nations) were traveling, and suddenly it
started raining and they took shelter in a cave. The entrance of
the cave got closed while they were inside. They said to each
other, 'O you! Nothing can save you except the truth, so each of
you should ask Allah's Help by referring to such a deed as he
thinks he did sincerely (i.e. just for gaining Allah's Pleasure).'
So one of them said, 'O Allah! You know that I had a laborer who
worked for me for one Faraq (i.e. three Sas) of rice, but he
departed, leaving it (i.e. his wages). I sowed that Faraq of rice
and with its yield I bought cows (for him). Later on when he came
to me asking for his wages, I said (to him), 'Go to those cows and
drive them away.' He said to me, 'But you have to pay me only a
Faraq of rice,' I said to him, 'Go to those cows and take them, for
they are the product of that Faraq (of rice).' So he drove them. O
Allah! If you consider that I did that for fear of You, then please
remove the rock.' The rock shifted a bit from the mouth of the
cave. The second one said, 'O Allah, You know that I had old
parents whom I used to provide with the milk of my sheep every
night. One night I was delayed and when I came, they had slept,
while my wife and children were crying with hunger. I used not to
let them (i.e. my family) drink unless my parents had drunk first.
So I disliked to wake them up and also disliked that they should
sleep without drinking it, I kept on waiting (for them to wake)
till it dawned. O Allah! If You consider that I did that for fear
of you, then please remove the rock.' So the rock shifted and they
could see the sky through it. The (third) one said, 'O Allah! You
know that I had a cousin (i.e. my paternal uncle's daughter) who
was most beloved to me and I sought to seduce her, but she refused,
unless I paid her one-hundred Dinars (i.e. gold pieces). So I
collected the amount and brought it to her, and she allowed me to
sleep with her. But when I sat between her legs, she said, 'Be
afraid of Allah, and do not deflower me but legally. 'I got up and
left the hundred Dinars (for her). O Allah! If You consider that I
did that for fear of you than please remove the rock. So Allah
saved them and they came out (of the cave)." [It has been flasely
argued that "This Hadith indicates that one can ONLY ask Allah for
help directly or through his performed good deeds." [In fact this
hadith does account the request of those three men based on their
good deeds, but nowhere within this hadith's text is it mentioned -
as claimed - that this is the ONLY way that Allah may be asked. The
reader is requested to review our holy Prophets words for himself,
and not to allow others to falsely interject their own opinions in
them. [It has also been wrongly (and vehemently) added that "But to
ask Allah through dead or absent prophets, saints, spirits, holy
men, angels etc. is absolutely forbidden in Islam and it is a kind
of disbelief." Such statements are extremely inflamatory and
un-islamically accusative. They purport to deny intercession, even
though it was affirmed by the majority of Muslim scholars. The
authentis hadeeth where one of the the Companions asks the Prophet:
"I ask you to be in your company in Jannah" is enough proof for the
wise. As for debative persons who prefer their own opinions, they
will not accept even volumes of proofs. Addition by Dar Al
Hadeeth]</english-text>
</hadith>
