<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3330</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>60</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3471</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophets - كتاب أحاديث الأنبياء</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11061, 11197, 10567, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا أبو الزناد،
عن الأعرج، عن أبي سلمة، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال صلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم صلاة الصبح، ثم أقبل على الناس، فقال ‏"‏ بينا رجل
يسوق بقرة إذ ركبها فضربها فقالت إنا لم نخلق لهذا، إنما خلقنا للحرث
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال الناس سبحان الله بقرة تكلم‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ فإني أومن بهذا
أنا وأبو بكر وعمر وما هما ثم وبينما رجل في غنمه إذ عدا الذئب فذهب
منها بشاة، فطلب حتى كأنه استنقذها منه، فقال له الذئب هذا استنقذتها
مني فمن لها يوم السبع، يوم لا راعي لها غيري ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال الناس سبحان
الله ذئب يتكلم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإني أومن بهذا أنا وأبو بكر وعمر ‏"‏‏.‏
وما هما ثم‏.‏ وحدثنا علي، حدثنا سفيان، عن مسعر، عن سعد بن إبراهيم،
عن أبي سلمة، عن أبي هريرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بمثله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Once Allah's Apostle; offered
the morning prayer and then faced the people and said, "While a man
was driving a cow, he suddenly rode over it and beat it. The cow
said, "We have not been created for this, but we have been created
for sloughing." On that the people said astonishingly, "Glorified
be Allah! A cow speaks!" The Prophet said, "I believe this, and Abu
Bakr and `Umar too, believe it, although neither of them was
present there. While a person was amongst his sheep, a wolf
attacked and took one of the sheep. The man chased the wolf till he
saved it from the wolf, where upon the wolf said, 'You have saved
it from me; but who will guard it on the day of the wild beasts
when there will be no shepherd to guard them except me (because of
riots and afflictions)? ' " The people said surprisingly,
"Glorified be Allah! A wolf speaks!" The Prophet said, "But I
believe this, and Abu Bakr and `Umar too, believe this, although
neither of them was present there." (See the Foot-note of page No.
10 Vol.5)</english-text>
</hadith>
