<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3374</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3558</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20462, 11070, 11081, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد، أخبرنا مخلد بن يزيد، أخبرنا ابن جريج، قال
أخبرني عمرو بن دينار، أنه سمع جابرا رضى الله عنه يقول غزونا مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وقد ثاب معه ناس من المهاجرين حتى كثروا،
وكان من المهاجرين رجل لعاب فكسع أنصاريا، فغضب الأنصاري غضبا شديدا،
حتى تداعوا، وقال الأنصاري يا للأنصار‏.‏ وقال المهاجري يا
للمهاجرين‏.‏ فخرج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ما بال دعوى أهل
الجاهلية ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال ‏"‏ ما شأنهم ‏"‏‏.‏ فأخبر بكسعة المهاجري
الأنصاري قال فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ دعوها فإنها خبيثة
‏"‏‏.‏ وقال عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول أقد تداعوا علينا، لئن رجعنا
إلى المدينة ليخرجن الأعز منها الأذل‏.‏ فقال عمر ألا نقتل يا رسول
الله هذا الخبيث لعبد الله‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا
يتحدث الناس أنه كان يقتل أصحابه ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir: We were in the company of the Prophet
in a Ghazwa. A large number of emigrants joined him and among the
emigrants there was a person who used to play jokes (or play with
spears); so he (jokingly) stroked an Ansari man on the hip. The
Ans-ari got so angry that both of them called their people. The
Ansari said, "Help, O Ansar!" And the emigrant said "Help, O
emigrants!" The Prophet came out and said, "What is wrong with the
people (as they are calling) this call of the period of Ignorance?
"Then he said, "What is the matter with them?" So he was told about
the stroke of the emigrant to the Ansari. The Prophet said, "Stop
this (i.e. appeal for help) for it is an evil call. "Abdullah bin
Ubai bin Salul (a hypocrite) said, "The emigrants have called and
(gathered against us); so when we return to Medina, surely, the
more honorable people will expel therefrom the meaner," Upon that
`Umar said, "O Allah's Prophet! Shall we not kill this evil person
(i.e. `Abdullah bin Ubai bin Salul) ?" The Prophet) said, "(No),
lest the people should say that Muhammad used to kill his
companions."</english-text>
</hadith>
