<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3434</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3619</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد
الله بن أبي طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول قال أبو طلحة لأم سليم
لقد سمعت صوت، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضعيفا، أعرف فيه الجوع
فهل عندك من شىء قالت نعم‏.‏ فأخرجت أقراصا من شعير، ثم أخرجت خمارا
لها فلفت الخبز ببعضه، ثم دسته تحت يدي ولاثتني ببعضه، ثم أرسلتني إلى
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال فذهبت به، فوجدت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في المسجد ومعه الناس، فقمت عليهم فقال لي رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ آرسلك أبو طلحة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم‏.‏ قال بطعام‏.‏
فقلت نعم‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمن معه ‏"‏ قوموا
‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلق وانطلقت بين أيديهم حتى جئت أبا طلحة فأخبرته‏.‏ فقال
أبو طلحة يا أم سليم، قد جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالناس،
وليس عندنا ما نطعمهم‏.‏ فقالت الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فانطلق أبو طلحة
حتى لقي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، فأقبل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأبو طلحة معه، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هلمي يا
أم سليم ما عندك ‏"‏‏.‏ فأتت بذلك الخبز، فأمر به رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ففت، وعصرت أم سليم عكة فأدمته، ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فيه ما شاء الله أن يقول، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏
فأذن لهم، فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏
فأذن لهم، فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏
فأذن لهم، فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم خرجوا ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏
فأكل القوم كلهم وشبعوا، والقوم سبعون أو ثمانون
رجلا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Abu Talha said to Um Sulaim,
"I have noticed feebleness in the voice of Allah's Apostle which I
think, is caused by hunger. Have you got any food?" She said,
"Yes." She brought out some loaves of barley and took out a veil
belonging to her, and wrapped the bread in part of it and put it
under my arm and wrapped part of the veil round me and sent me to
Allah's Apostle. I went carrying it and found Allah's Apostle in
the Mosque sitting with some people. When I stood there, Allah's
Apostle asked, "Has Abu Talha sent you?" I said, "Yes". He asked,
"With some food? I said, "Yes" Allah's Apostle then said to the men
around him, "Get up!" He set out (accompanied by them) and I went
ahead of them till I reached Abu Talha and told him (of the
Prophet's visit). Abu Talha said, "O Um Sulaim! Allah's Apostle is
coming with the people and we have no food to feed them." She said,
"Allah and His Apostle know better." So Abu Talha went out to
receive Allah's Apostle. Allah's Apostle came along with Abu Talha.
Allah's Apostle said, "O Um Sulaim! Bring whatever you have." She
brought the bread which Allah's Apostle ordered to be broken into
pieces. Um Sulaim poured on them some butter from an oilskin. Then
Allah's Apostle recited what Allah wished him to recite, and then
said, "Let ten persons come (to share the meal)." Ten persons were
admitted, ate their fill and went out. Then he again said, "Let
another ten do the same." They were admitted, ate their fill and
went out. Then he again said, '"'Let another ten persons (do the
same.)" They were admitted, ate their fill and went out. Then he
said, "Let another ten persons come." In short, all of them ate
their fill, and they were seventy or eighty men.</english-text>
</hadith>
