<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3437</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3622</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20288, 11289, 11113, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا معتمر، عن أبيه، حدثنا أبو
عثمان، أنه حدثه عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر رضى الله عنهما أن أصحاب،
الصفة كانوا أناسا فقراء، وأن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال مرة ‏"‏
من كان عنده طعام اثنين فليذهب بثالث، ومن كان عنده طعام أربعة فليذهب
بخامس أو سادس ‏"‏‏.‏ أو كما قال، وأن أبا بكر جاء بثلاثة وانطلق
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بعشرة، وأبو بكر وثلاثة، قال فهو أنا وأبي
وأمي ولا أدري هل قال امرأتي وخادمي بين بيتنا وبين بيت أبي بكر، وأن
أبا بكر تعشى عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم لبث حتى صلى العشاء، ثم
رجع فلبث حتى تعشى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجاء بعد ما مضى من
الليل ما شاء الله، قالت له امرأته ما حبسك عن أضيافك أو ضيفك‏.‏ قال
أو عشيتهم قالت أبوا حتى تجيء، قد عرضوا عليهم فغلبوهم، فذهبت
فاختبأت، فقال يا غنثر‏.‏ فجدع وسب وقال كلوا وقال لا أطعمه أبدا‏.‏
قال وايم الله ما كنا نأخذ من اللقمة إلا ربا من أسفلها أكثر منها حتى
شبعوا، وصارت أكثر مما كانت قبل، فنظر أبو بكر فإذا شىء أو أكثر قال
لامرأته يا أخت بني فراس‏.‏ قالت لا وقرة عيني لهى الآن أكثر مما قبل
بثلاث مرات‏.‏ فأكل منها أبو بكر، وقال إنما كان الشيطان يعني يمينه
ثم أكل منها لقمة، ثم حملها إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأصبحت
عنده‏.‏ وكان بيننا وبين قوم عهد، فمضى الأجل، فتفرقنا اثنا عشر رجلا
مع كل رجل منهم أناس‏.‏ الله أعلم كم مع كل رجل، غير أنه بعث معهم،
قال أكلوا منها أجمعون‏.‏ أو كما قال‏.‏ وغيره يقول فعرفنا من
العرافة</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdur-Rahman bin Abi Bakr: The companions
of Suffa were poor people. The Prophet once said, "Whoever has food
enough for two persons, should take a third one (from among them),
and whoever has food enough for four persons, should take a fifth
or a sixth (or said something similar)." Abu Bakr brought three
persons while the Prophet took ten. And Abu Bakr with his three
family member (who were I, my father and my mother) (the
sub-narrator is in doubt whether `Abdur-Rahman said, "My wife and
my servant who was common for both my house and Abu Bakr's house.")
Abu Bakr took his supper with the Prophet and stayed there till he
offered the `Isha' prayers. He returned and stayed till Allah's
Apostle took his supper. After a part of the night had passed, he
returned to his house. His wife said to him, "What has detained you
from your guests?" He said, "Have you served supper to them?" She
said, "They refused to take supper until you come. They (i.e. some
members of the household) presented the meal to them but they
refused (to eat)" I went to hide myself and he said, "O Ghunthar!"
He invoked Allah to cause my ears to be cut and he rebuked me. He
then said (to them): Please eat!" and added, I will never eat the
meal." By Allah, whenever we took a handful of the meal, the meal
grew from underneath more than that handful till everybody ate to
his satisfaction; yet the remaining food was more than the original
meal. Abu Bakr saw that the food was as much or more than the
original amount. He called his wife, "O sister of Bani Firas!" She
said, "O pleasure of my eyes. The food has been tripled in
quantity." Abu Bakr then started eating thereof and said, "It (i.e.
my oath not to eat) was because of Sa all." He took a handful from
it, and carried the rest to the Prophet. So that food was with the
Prophet . There was a treaty between us and some people, and when
the period of that treaty had elapsed, he divided US into twelve
groups, each being headed by a man. Allah knows how many men were
under the command of each leader. Anyhow, the Prophet surely sent a
leader with each group. Then all of them ate of that
meal.</english-text>
</hadith>
