<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3449</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3637</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>20291, 20311, 11651, 212</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن الحكم، أخبرنا النضر، أخبرنا إسرائيل،
أخبرنا سعد الطائي، أخبرنا محل بن خليفة، عن عدي بن حاتم، قال بينا
أنا عند النبي، صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ أتاه رجل فشكا إليه الفاقة، ثم
أتاه آخر، فشكا قطع السبيل‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ يا عدي هل رأيت الحيرة ‏"‏‏.‏
قلت لم أرها وقد أنبئت عنها‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن طالت بك حياة لترين
الظعينة ترتحل من الحيرة، حتى تطوف بالكعبة، لا تخاف أحدا إلا الله
‏"‏ قلت فيما بيني وبين نفسي فأين دعار طيئ الذين قد سعروا البلاد ‏"‏
ولئن طالت بك حياة لتفتحن كنوز كسرى ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت كسرى بن هرمز قال ‏"‏
كسرى بن هرمز، ولئن طالت بك حياة، لترين الرجل يخرج ملء كفه من ذهب أو
فضة، يطلب من يقبله منه، فلا يجد أحدا يقبله منه، وليلقين الله أحدكم
يوم يلقاه، وليس بينه وبينه ترجمان يترجم له‏.‏ فيقولن ألم أبعث إليك
رسولا فيبلغك فيقول بلى‏.‏ فيقول ألم أعطك مالا وأفضل عليك فيقول
بلى‏.‏ فينظر عن يمينه فلا يرى إلا جهنم، وينظر عن يساره فلا يرى إلا
جهنم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عدي سمعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ اتقوا
النار ولو بشقة تمرة، فمن لم يجد شقة تمرة فبكلمة طيبة ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عدي
فرأيت الظعينة ترتحل من الحيرة حتى تطوف بالكعبة، لا تخاف إلا الله،
وكنت فيمن افتتح كنوز كسرى بن هرمز، ولئن طالت بكم حياة لترون ما قال
النبي أبو القاسم صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يخرج ملء كفه
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Adi bin Hatim: While I was in the city of
the Prophet, a man came and complained to him (the Prophet, ) of
destitution and poverty. Then another man came and complained of
robbery (by highwaymen). The Prophet said, "Adi! Have you been to
Al-Hira?" I said, "I haven't been to it, but I was informed about
it." He said, "If you should live for a long time, you will
certainly see that a lady in a Howdah traveling from Al-Hira will
(safely reach Mecca and) perform the Tawaf of the Ka`ba, fearing
none but Allah." I said to myself, "What will happen to the robbers
of the tribe of Tai who have spread evil through out the country?"
The Prophet further said. "If you should live long, the treasures
of Khosrau will be opened (and taken as spoils)." I asked, "You
mean Khosrau, son of Hurmuz?" He said, "Khosrau, son of Hurmuz; and
if you should live long, you will see that one will carry a handful
of gold or silver and go out looking for a person to accept it from
him, but will find none to accept it from him. And any of you, when
meeting Allah, will meet Him without needing an interpreter between
him and Allah to interpret for him, and Allah will say to him:
'Didn't I send a messenger to teach you?' He will say: 'Yes.' Allah
will say: 'Didn't I give you wealth and do you favors?' He will
say: 'Yes.' Then he will look to his right and see nothing but
Hell, and look to his left and see nothing but Hell." `Adi further
said: I heard the Prophet saying, "Save yourself from the (Hell)
Fire even with half a date (to be given in charity) and if you do
not find a half date, then with a good pleasant word." `Adi added:
(later on) I saw a lady in a Howdah traveling from Al-Hira till she
performed the Tawaf of the Ka`ba, fearing none but Allah. And I was
one of those who opened (conquered) the treasures of Khosrau, son
of Hurmuz. If you should live long, you will see what the Prophet
Abu-l-Qasim had said: 'A person will come out with a handful. of
gold...etc.</english-text>
</hadith>
