<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3464</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3653</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10567, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
أبو سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، أن أبا سعيد الخدري رضى الله عنه قال بينما
نحن عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو يقسم قسما أتاه ذو الخويصرة
وهو رجل من بني تميم فقال يا رسول الله اعدل‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ويلك، ومن
يعدل إذا لم أعدل قد خبت وخسرت إن لم أكن أعدل ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال عمر يا
رسول الله ائذن لي فيه، فأضرب عنقه‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ دعه فإن له أصحابا،
يحقر أحدكم صلاته مع صلاتهم وصيامه مع صيامهم، يقرءون القرآن لا يجاوز
تراقيهم، يمرقون من الدين كما يمرق السهم من الرمية، ينظر إلى نصله
فلا يوجد فيه شىء، ثم ينظر إلى رصافه فما يوجد فيه شىء، ثم ينظر إلى
نضيه وهو قدحه فلا يوجد فيه شىء، ثم ينظر إلى قذذه فلا يوجد فيه شىء،
قد سبق الفرث والدم، آيتهم رجل أسود إحدى عضديه مثل ثدى المرأة، أو
مثل البضعة تدردر ويخرجون على حين فرقة من الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد
فأشهد أني سمعت هذا الحديث من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم، وأشهد أن
علي بن أبي طالب قاتلهم وأنا معه، فأمر بذلك الرجل، فالتمس فأتي به
حتى نظرت إليه على نعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم الذي
نعته‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: While we were with
Allah's Apostle who was distributing (i.e. some property), there
came Dhu-l- Khuwaisira, a man from the tribe of Bani Tamim and
said, "O Allah's Apostle! Do Justice." The Prophet said, "Woe to
you! Who could do justice if I did not? I would be a desperate
loser if I did not do justice." `Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle!
Allow me to chop his head off." The Prophet said, "Leave him, for
he has companions who pray and fast in such a way that you will
consider your fasting negligible in comparison to theirs. They
recite Qur'an but it does not go beyond their throats (i.e. they do
not act on it) and they will desert Islam as an arrow goes through
a victim's body, so that the hunter, on looking at the arrow's
blade, would see nothing on it; he would look at its Risaf and see
nothing: he would look at its Na,di and see nothing, and he would
look at its Qudhadh ( 1 ) and see nothing (neither meat nor blood),
for the arrow has been too fast even for the blood and excretions
to smear. The sign by which they will be recognized is that among
them there will be a black man, one of whose arms will resemble a
woman's breast or a lump of meat moving loosely. Those people will
appear when there will be differences amongst the people." I
testify that I heard this narration from Allah's Apostle and I
testify that `Ali bin Abi Talib fought with such people, and I was
in his company. He ordered that the man (described by the Prophet )
should be looked for. The man was brought and I looked at him and
noticed that he looked exactly as the Prophet had described
him.</english-text>
</hadith>
