<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3476</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3666</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>20348, 11338, 11385, 11052, 11018, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا زكرياء، عن فراس، عن عامر، عن
مسروق، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت أقبلت فاطمة تمشي، كأن مشيتها مشى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ مرحبا
بابنتي ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم أجلسها عن يمينه أو عن شماله، ثم أسر إليها حديثا،
فبكت فقلت لها لم تبكين ثم أسر إليها حديثا فضحكت فقلت ما رأيت كاليوم
فرحا أقرب من حزن، فسألتها عما قال‏.‏ فقالت ما كنت لأفشي سر رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى قبض النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فسألتها
فقالت أسر إلى ‏"‏ إن جبريل كان يعارضني القرآن كل سنة مرة، وإنه
عارضني العام مرتين، ولا أراه إلا حضر أجلي، وإنك أول أهل بيتي لحاقا
بي ‏"‏‏.‏ فبكيت فقال ‏"‏ أما ترضين أن تكوني سيدة نساء أهل الجنة أو
نساء المؤمنين ‏"‏‏.‏ فضحكت لذلك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Once Fatima came walking and her
gait resembled the gait of the Prophet . The Prophet said,
"Welcome, O my daughter!" Then he made her sit on his right or on
his left side, and then he told her a secret and she started
weeping. I asked her, "Why are you weeping?" He again told her a
secret and she started laughing. I said, "I never saw happiness so
near to sadness as I saw today." I asked her what the Prophet had
told her. She said, "I would never disclose the secret of Allah's
Apostle ." When the Prophet died, I asked her about it. She
replied. "The Prophet said.) 'Every year Gabriel used to revise the
Qur'an with me once only, but this year he has done so twice. I
think this portends my death, and you will be the first of my
family to follow me.' So I started weeping. Then he said. 'Don't
you like to be the mistress of all the ladies of Paradise or the
mistress of all the lady believers? So I laughed for
that."</english-text>
</hadith>
