<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3496</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>61</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3689</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues and Merits of the Prophet (pbuh) and his
Companions - كتاب المناقب</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11163, 11161, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن
أبي صالح السمان، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه عن النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ‏"‏ الخيل لثلاثة لرجل أجر، ولرجل ستر وعلى رجل وزر‏.‏ فأما
الذي له أجر، فرجل ربطها في سبيل الله، فأطال لها في مرج أو روضة، وما
أصابت في طيلها من المرج أو الروضة كانت له حسنات، ولو أنها قطعت
طيلها، فاستنت شرفا أو شرفين، كانت أرواثها حسنات له، ولو أنها مرت
بنهر فشربت، ولم يرد أن يسقيها، كان ذلك له حسنات، ورجل ربطها تغنيا
وسترا وتعففا، لم ينس حق الله في رقابها وظهورها، فهي له كذلك ستر‏.‏
ورجل ربطها فخرا ورياء، ونواء لأهل الإسلام فهى وزر‏.‏ وسئل النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم عن الحمر فقال ‏"‏ ما أنزل على فيها إلا هذه الآية
الجامعة الفاذة ‏{‏فمن يعمل مثقال ذرة خيرا يره * ومن يعمل مثقال ذرة
شرا يره‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: The Prophet said, "A horse may
be kept for one of three purposes: for a man it may be a source of
reward; for another it may be a means of living; and for a third it
may be a burden (a source of committing sins). As for the one for
whom it is a source of reward, he is the one who keeps his horse
for the sake of Jihad in Allah's Cause; he ties it with a long rope
on a pasture or in a garden. So whatever its rope allows it to eat,
will be regarded as good rewardable deeds (for its owner). And if
it breaks off its rope and jumps over one or two hillocks, even its
dung will be considered amongst his good deeds. And if it passes by
a river and drinks water from it, that will be considered as good
deeds for his benefit) even if he has had no intention of watering
it. A horse is a shelter for the one who keeps it so that he may
earn his living honestly and takes it as a refuge to keep him from
following illegal ways (of gaining money), and does not forget the
rights of Allah (i.e. paying the Zakat and allowing others to use
it for Allah's Sake). But a horse is a burden (and a source of
committing sins for him who keeps it out of pride and pretense and
with the intention of harming the Muslims." The Prophet was asked
about donkeys. He replied, "Nothing has been revealed to be
concerning them except this comprehensive Verse (which covers
everything) :--'Then whosoever has done good equal to the weight of
an atom (or a small ant), Shall see it (its reward) And whosoever
has done evil equal to the weight of an atom (or a small ) ant),
Shall see it (Its punishment)." (99.7-8)</english-text>
</hadith>
