<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3511</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3705</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30288, 20398, 11671, 11412, 37</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني هشام بن عمار، حدثنا صدقة بن خالد، حدثنا زيد بن
واقد، عن بسر بن عبيد الله، عن عائذ الله أبي إدريس، عن أبي الدرداء
رضى الله عنه قال كنت جالسا عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إذ أقبل أبو
بكر آخذا بطرف ثوبه حتى أبدى عن ركبته، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ أما صاحبكم فقد غامر ‏"‏‏.‏ فسلم، وقال إني كان بيني وبين ابن
الخطاب شىء فأسرعت إليه ثم ندمت، فسألته أن يغفر لي فأبى على، فأقبلت
إليك فقال ‏"‏ يغفر الله لك يا أبا بكر ‏"‏‏.‏ ثلاثا، ثم إن عمر ندم
فأتى منزل أبي بكر فسأل أثم أبو بكر فقالوا لا‏.‏ فأتى إلى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم، فسلم فجعل وجه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يتمعر حتى
أشفق أبو بكر، فجثا على ركبتيه فقال يا رسول الله، والله أنا كنت أظلم
مرتين‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن الله بعثني إليكم
فقلتم كذبت‏.‏ وقال أبو بكر صدق‏.‏ وواساني بنفسه وماله، فهل أنتم
تاركو لي صاحبي ‏"‏‏.‏ مرتين فما أوذي بعدها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Ad-Darda: While I was sitting with the
Prophet, Abu Bakr came, lifting up one corner of h is garment
uncovering h is knee. The Prophet said, "Your companion has had a
quarrel." Abu Bakr greeted (the Prophet ) and said, "O Allah's
Apostle! There was something (i.e. quarrel) between me and the Son
of Al-Khattab. I talked to him harshly and then regretted that, and
requested him to forgive me, but he refused. This is why I have
come to you." The Prophet said thrice, "O Abu Bakr! May Allah
forgive you." In the meanwhile, `Umar regretted (his refusal of Abu
Bakr's excuse) and went to Abu Bakr's house and asked if Abu Bakr
was there. They replied in the negative. So he came to the Prophet
and greeted him, but signs of displeasure appeared on the face of
the Prophet till Abu Bakr pitied (`Umar), so he knelt and said
twice, "O Allah's Apostle! By Allah! I was more unjust to him (than
he to me)." The Prophet said, "Allah sent me (as a Prophet) to you
(people) but you said (to me), 'You are telling a lie,' while Abu
Bakr said, 'He has said the truth,' and consoled me with himself
and his money." He then said twice, "Won't you then give up harming
my companion?" After that nobody harmed Abu Bakr.</english-text>
</hadith>
