<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3517</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3711</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20160, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل بن عبد الله، حدثنا سليمان بن بلال، عن
هشام بن عروة، عن عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها زوج النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مات وأبو بكر
بالسنح قال إسماعيل يعني بالعالية فقام عمر يقول والله ما مات رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ قالت وقال عمر والله ما كان يقع في نفسي
إلا ذاك وليبعثنه الله فليقطعن أيدي رجال وأرجلهم‏.‏ فجاء أبو بكر
فكشف عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقبله قال بأبي أنت وأمي طبت
حيا وميتا، والذي نفسي بيده لا يذيقك الله الموتتين أبدا‏.‏ ثم خرج
فقال أيها الحالف على رسلك‏.‏ فلما تكلم أبو بكر جلس عمر‏.‏ فحمد الله
أبو بكر وأثنى عليه وقال ألا من كان يعبد محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم
فإن محمدا قد مات، ومن كان يعبد الله فإن الله حى لا يموت‏.‏ وقال
‏{‏إنك ميت وإنهم ميتون‏}‏ وقال ‏{‏وما محمد إلا رسول قد خلت من قبله
الرسل أفإن مات أو قتل انقلبتم على أعقابكم ومن ينقلب على عقبيه فلن
يضر الله شيئا وسيجزي الله الشاكرين‏}‏ قال فنشج الناس يبكون قال
واجتمعت الأنصار إلى سعد بن عبادة في سقيفة بني ساعدة فقالوا منا أمير
ومنكم أمير، فذهب إليهم أبو بكر وعمر بن الخطاب وأبو عبيدة بن الجراح،
فذهب عمر يتكلم فأسكته أبو بكر، وكان عمر يقول والله ما أردت بذلك إلا
أني قد هيأت كلاما قد أعجبني خشيت أن لا يبلغه أبو بكر، ثم تكلم أبو
بكر فتكلم أبلغ الناس فقال في كلامه نحن الأمراء وأنتم الوزراء‏.‏
فقال حباب بن المنذر لا والله لا نفعل، منا أمير ومنكم أمير‏.‏ فقال
أبو بكر لا، ولكنا الأمراء وأنتم الوزراء هم أوسط العرب دارا، وأعربهم
أحسابا فبايعوا عمر أو أبا عبيدة‏.‏ فقال عمر بل نبايعك أنت، فأنت
سيدنا وخيرنا وأحبنا إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فأخذ عمر
بيده فبايعه، وبايعه الناس، فقال قائل قتلتم سعد بن عبادة‏.‏ فقال عمر
قتله الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Aisha: (the wife of the Prophet) Allah's
Apostle died while Abu Bakr was at a place called As-Sunah
(Al-'Aliya) 'Umar stood up and said, "By Allah! Allah's Apostle is
not dead!" 'Umar (later on) said, "By Allah! Nothing occurred to my
mind except that." He said, "Verily! Allah will resurrect him and
he will cut the hands and legs of some men." Then Abu Bakr came and
uncovered the face of Allah's Apostle, kissed him and said, "Let my
mother and father be sacrificed for you, (O Allah's Apostle), you
are good in life and in death. By Allah in Whose Hands my life is,
Allah will never make you taste death twice." Then he went out and
said, "O oath-taker! Don't be hasty." When Abu Bakr spoke, 'Umar
sat down. Abu Bakr praised and glorified Allah and said, No doubt!
Whoever worshipped Muhammad, then Muhammad is dead, but whoever
worshipped Allah, then Allah is Alive and shall never die." Then he
recited Allah's Statement.:-- "(O Muhammad) Verily you will die,
and they also will die." (39.30) He also recited:-- "Muhammad is no
more than an Apostle; and indeed many Apostles have passed away,
before him, If he dies Or is killed, will you then Turn back on
your heels? And he who turns back On his heels, not the least Harm
will he do to Allah And Allah will give reward to those Who are
grateful." (3.144) The people wept loudly, and the Ansar were
assembled with Sad bin 'Ubada in the shed of Bani Saida. They said
(to the emigrants). "There should be one 'Amir from us and one from
you." Then Abu Bakr, Umar bin Al-Khattab and Abu 'baida bin
Al-Jarrah went to them. 'Umar wanted to speak but Abu Bakr stopped
him. 'Umar later on used to say, "By Allah, I intended only to say
something that appealed to me and I was afraid that Abu Bakr would
not speak so well. Then Abu Bakr spoke and his speech was very
eloquent. He said in his statement, "We are the rulers and you
(Ansars) are the ministers (i.e. advisers)," Hubab bin Al-Mundhir
said, "No, by Allah we won't accept this. But there must be a ruler
from us and a ruler from you." Abu Bakr said, "No, we will be the
rulers and you will be the ministers, for they (i.e. Quarish) are
the best family amongst the 'Arabs and of best origin. So you
should elect either 'Umar or Abu 'Ubaida bin Al-Jarrah as your
ruler." 'Umar said (to Abu Bakr), "No but we elect you, for you are
our chief and the best amongst us and the most beloved of all of us
to Allah's Apostle." So 'Umar took Abu Bakr's hand and gave the
pledge of allegiance and the people too gave the pledge of
allegiance to Abu Bakr. Someone said, "You have killed Sad bin
Ubada." 'Umar said, "Allah has killed him."</english-text>
</hadith>
