<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3520</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3716</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20001, 10530, 10535, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، عن مالك، عن عبد الرحمن بن القاسم،
عن أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أنها قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم في بعض أسفاره، حتى إذا كنا بالبيداء أو بذات الجيش
انقطع عقد لي، فأقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على التماسه، وأقام
الناس معه، وليسوا على ماء وليس معهم ماء، فأتى الناس أبا بكر، فقالوا
ألا ترى ما صنعت عائشة أقامت برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وبالناس
معه، وليسوا على ماء وليس معهم ماء، فجاء أبو بكر ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم واضع رأسه على فخذي قد نام، فقال حبست رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم والناس، وليسوا على ماء وليس معهم ماء قالت فعاتبني، وقال
ما شاء الله أن يقول، وجعل يطعنني بيده في خاصرتي، فلا يمنعني من
التحرك إلا مكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على فخذي، فنام رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى أصبح على غير ماء فأنزل الله آية التيمم،
فتيمموا، فقال أسيد بن الحضير ما هي بأول بركتكم يا آل أبي بكر‏.‏
فقالت عائشة فبعثنا البعير الذي كنت عليه فوجدنا العقد
تحته‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: We went out with Allah's Apostle on
one of his journeys till we reached Al-Baida or Dhatul-Jaish where
my necklace got broken (and lost). Allah's Apostle stopped to
search for it and the people too stopped with him. There was no
water at that place and they had no water with them. So they went
to Abu Bakr and said, "Don't you see what `Aisha has done? She has
made Allah's Apostle and the people stop where there is no water
and they have no water with them. Abu Bakr came while Allah's
Apostle was sleeping with his head on my thigh and said, "You
detained Allah Apostle and the people where there is no water and
they have no water." He then admonished me and said what Allah
wished and pinched me at my flanks with his hands, but I did not
move because the head of Allah's Apostle was on my thigh . Allah's
Apostle kept on sleeping till be got up in the morning and found no
water. Then Allah revealed the Divine Verse of Tayammum, and the
people performed Tayammum. Usaid bin AlHudair said. "O family of
Abu Bakr! This is not the first blessings of yours." We urged the
camel on which I was sitting to get up from its place and the
necklace was found under it.</english-text>
</hadith>
