<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3539</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3737</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30140, 20208, 11015, 11090, 2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الصلت بن محمد، حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، حدثنا
أيوب، عن ابن أبي مليكة، عن المسور بن مخرمة، قال لما طعن عمر جعل
يألم، فقال له ابن عباس وكأنه يجزعه يا أمير المؤمنين، ولئن كان ذاك
لقد صحبت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأحسنت صحبته، ثم فارقته وهو
عنك راض، ثم صحبت أبا بكر فأحسنت صحبته، ثم فارقته وهو عنك راض، ثم
صحبت صحبتهم فأحسنت صحبتهم، ولئن فارقتهم لتفارقنهم وهم عنك راضون‏.‏
قال أما ما ذكرت من صحبة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورضاه، فإنما
ذاك من من الله تعالى من به على، وأما ما ذكرت من صحبة أبي بكر ورضاه،
فإنما ذاك من من الله جل ذكره من به على، وأما ما ترى من جزعي، فهو من
أجلك وأجل أصحابك، والله لو أن لي طلاع الأرض ذهبا لافتديت به من عذاب
الله عز وجل قبل أن أراه‏.‏ قال حماد بن زيد حدثنا أيوب، عن ابن أبي
مليكة، عن ابن عباس، دخلت على عمر بهذا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Miswar bin Makhrama: When `Umar was
stabbed, he showed signs of agony. Ibn `Abbas, as if intending to
encourage `Umar, said to him, "O Chief of the believers! Never mind
what has happened to you, for you have been in the company of
Allah's Apostle and you kept good relations with him and you parted
with him while he was pleased with you. Then you were in the
company of Abu Bakr and kept good relations with him and you parted
with him (i.e. he died) while he was pleased with you. Then you
were in the company of the Muslims, and you kept good relations
with them, and if you leave them, you will leave them while they
are pleased with you." `Umar said, (to Ibn "Abbas), "As for what
you have said about the company of Allah's Apostle and his being
pleased with me, it is a favor, Allah did to me; and as for what
you have said about the company of Abu Bakr and his being pleased
with me, it is a favor Allah did to me; and concerning my
impatience which you see, is because of you and your companions. By
Allah! If (at all) I had gold equal to the earth, I would have
ransomed myself with it from the Punishment of Allah before I meet
Him."</english-text>
</hadith>
