<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3543</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3743</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30120, 20238, 20475, 11013, 10511, 880,
2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أحمد بن شبيب بن سعيد، قال حدثني أبي، عن يونس،
قال ابن شهاب أخبرني عروة، أن عبيد الله بن عدي بن الخيار، أخبره أن
المسور بن مخرمة وعبد الرحمن بن الأسود بن عبد يغوث قالا ما يمنعك أن
تكلم عثمان لأخيه الوليد فقد أكثر الناس فيه‏.‏ فقصدت لعثمان حتى خرج
إلى الصلاة، قلت إن لي إليك حاجة، وهي نصيحة لك‏.‏ قال يا أيها المرء
قال معمر أراه قال أعوذ بالله منك‏.‏ فانصرفت، فرجعت إليهم إذ جاء
رسول عثمان فأتيته، فقال ما نصيحتك فقلت إن الله سبحانه بعث محمدا صلى
الله عليه وسلم بالحق، وأنزل عليه الكتاب، وكنت ممن استجاب لله
ولرسوله، فهاجرت الهجرتين، وصحبت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورأيت
هديه، وقد أكثر الناس في شأن الوليد‏.‏ قال أدركت رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم قلت لا ولكن خلص إلى من علمه ما يخلص إلى العذراء في
سترها‏.‏ قال أما بعد فإن الله بعث محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم بالحق،
فكنت ممن استجاب لله ولرسوله وآمنت بما بعث به، وهاجرت الهجرتين كما
قلت، وصحبت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وبايعته، فوالله ما عصيته
ولا غششته حتى توفاه الله، ثم أبو بكر مثله، ثم عمر مثله، ثم استخلفت،
أفليس لي من الحق مثل الذي لهم قلت بلى‏.‏ قال فما هذه الأحاديث التي
تبلغني عنكم أما ما ذكرت من شأن الوليد، فسنأخذ فيه بالحق إن شاء
الله، ثم دعا عليا فأمره أن يجلده فجلده ثمانين‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah bin `Adi bin Al-Khiyar:
Al-Miswar bin Makhrama and `Abdur-Rahman bin Al-Aswad bin 'Abu
Yaghuth said (to me), "What forbids you to talk to `Uthman about
his brother Al-Walid because people have talked much about him?" So
I went to `Uthman and when he went out for prayer I said (to him),
"I have something to say to you and it is a piece of advice for you
" `Uthman said, "O man, from you." (`Umar said: I see that he said,
"I seek Refuge with Allah from you.") So I left him and went to
them. Then the messenger of `Uthman came and I went to him (i.e.
`Uthman), `Uthman asked, "What is your advice?" I replied, "Allah
sent Muhammad with the Truth, and revealed the Divine Book (i.e.
Qur'an) to him; and you were amongst those who followed Allah and
His Apostle, and you participated in the two migrations (to
Ethiopia and to Medina) and enjoyed the company of Allah's Apostle
and saw his way. No doubt, the people are talking much about
Al-Walid." `Uthman said, "Did you receive your knowledge directly
from Allah's Apostle ?" I said, "No, but his knowledge did reach me
and it reached (even) to a virgin in her seclusion." `Uthman said,
"And then Allah sent Muhammad with the Truth and I was amongst
those who followed Allah and His Apostle and I believed in what
ever he (i.e. the Prophet) was sent with, and participated in two
migrations, as you have said, and I enjoyed the company of Allah's
Apostle and gave the pledge of allegiance him. By Allah! I never
disobeyed him, nor did I cheat him till Allah took him unto Him.
Then I treated Abu Bakr and then `Umar similarly and then I was
made Caliph. So, don't I have rights similar to theirs?" I said,
"Yes." He said, "Then what are these talks reaching me from you
people? Now, concerning what you mentioned about the question of
Al-Walid, Allah willing, I shall deal with him according to what is
right." Then he called `Ali and ordered him to flog him, and `Ali
flogged him (i.e. Al-Walid) eighty lashes.</english-text>
</hadith>
