<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3545</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3745</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 18716</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو عوانة، حدثنا عثمان هو
ابن موهب قال جاء رجل من أهل مصر حج البيت فرأى قوما جلوسا، فقال من
هؤلاء القوم قال هؤلاء قريش‏.‏ قال فمن الشيخ فيهم قالوا عبد الله بن
عمر‏.‏ قال يا ابن عمر إني سائلك عن شىء فحدثني هل تعلم أن عثمان فر
يوم أحد قال نعم‏.‏ قال تعلم أنه تغيب عن بدر ولم يشهد قال نعم‏.‏ قال
تعلم أنه تغيب عن بيعة الرضوان فلم يشهدها قال نعم‏.‏ قال الله
أكبر‏.‏ قال ابن عمر تعال أبين لك أما فراره يوم أحد فأشهد أن الله
عفا عنه وغفر له، وأما تغيبه عن بدر، فإنه كانت تحته بنت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم وكانت مريضة، فقال له رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إن لك أجر رجل ممن شهد بدرا وسهمه ‏"‏‏.‏ وأما تغيبه عن بيعة
الرضوان فلو كان أحد أعز ببطن مكة من عثمان لبعثه مكانه فبعث رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عثمان وكانت بيعة الرضوان بعد ما ذهب عثمان
إلى مكة، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بيده اليمنى ‏"‏ هذه يد
عثمان ‏"‏‏.‏ فضرب بها على يده، فقال ‏"‏ هذه لعثمان ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال له
ابن عمر اذهب بها الآن معك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Uthman: (the son of Muhib) An Egyptian who
came and performed the Hajj to the Ka`ba saw some people sitting.
He enquire, "Who are these people?" Somebody said, "They are the
tribe of Quraish." He said, "Who is the old man sitting amongst
them?" The people replied, "He is `Abdullah bin `Umar." He said, "O
Ibn `Umar! I want to ask you about something; please tell me about
it. Do you know that `Uthman fled away on the day (of the battle)
of Uhud?" Ibn `Umar said, "Yes." The (Egyptian) man said, "Do you
know that `Uthman was absent on the day (of the battle) of Badr and
did not join it?" Ibn `Umar said, "Yes." The man said, "Do you know
that he failed to attend the Ar Ridwan pledge and did not witness
it (i.e. Hudaibiya pledge of allegiance)?" Ibn `Umar said, "Yes."
The man said, "Allahu Akbar!" Ibn `Umar said, "Let me explain to
you (all these three things). As for his flight on the day of Uhud,
I testify that Allah has excused him and forgiven him; and as for
his absence from the battle of Badr, it was due to the fact that
the daughter of Allah's Apostle was his wife and she was sick then.
Allah's Apostle said to him, "You will receive the same reward and
share (of the booty) as anyone of those who participated in the
battle of Badr (if you stay with her).' As for his absence from the
Ar-Ridwan pledge of allegiance, had there been any person in Mecca
more respectable than `Uthman (to be sent as a representative).
Allah's Apostle would have sent him instead of him. No doubt,
Allah's Apostle had sent him, and the incident of the Ar-Ridwan
pledge of Allegiance happened after `Uthman had gone to Mecca.
Allah's Apostle held out his right hand saying, 'This is `Uthman's
hand.' He stroke his (other) hand with it saying, 'This (pledge of
allegiance) is on the behalf of `Uthman.' Then Ibn `Umar said to
the man, 'Bear (these) excuses in mind with you.'</english-text>
</hadith>
