<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3549</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3748</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20167, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا عبد العزيز، عن أبي حازم، عن
سهل بن سعد رضى الله عنه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏
لأعطين الراية غدا رجلا يفتح الله على يديه ‏"‏ قال فبات الناس يدوكون
ليلتهم أيهم يعطاها فلما أصبح الناس، غدوا على رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم كلهم يرجو أن يعطاها فقال ‏"‏ أين علي بن أبي طالب ‏"‏‏.‏
فقالوا يشتكي عينيه يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأرسلوا إليه فأتوني به
‏"‏‏.‏ فلما جاء بصق في عينيه، ودعا له، فبرأ حتى كأن لم يكن به وجع،
فأعطاه الراية‏.‏ فقال علي يا رسول الله أقاتلهم حتى يكونوا مثلنا
فقال ‏"‏ انفذ على رسلك حتى تنزل بساحتهم، ثم ادعهم إلى الإسلام،
وأخبرهم بما يجب عليهم من حق الله فيه، فوالله لأن يهدي الله بك رجلا
واحدا خير لك من أن يكون لك حمر النعم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: Allah's Apostle said,
"Tomorrow I will give the flag to a man with whose leadership Allah
will grant (the Muslim) victory." So the people kept on thinking
the whole night as to who would be given the flag. The next morning
the people went to Allah's Apostle and every one of them hoped that
he would be given the flag. The Prophet said, "Where is `Ali bin
Abi Talib?" The people replied, "He is suffering from eye trouble,
O Allah's Apostle." He said, "Send for him and bring him to me." So
when `Ali came, the Prophet spat in his eyes and invoked good on
him, and be became alright as if he had no ailment. The Prophet
then gave him the flag. `Ali said, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall I
fight them (i.e. enemy) till they become like us?" The Prophet
said, "Proceed to them steadily till you approach near to them and
then invite them to Islam and inform them of their duties towards
Allah which Islam prescribes for them, for by Allah, if one man is
guided on the right path (i.e. converted to Islam) through you, it
would be better for you than (a great number of) red
camels."</english-text>
</hadith>
