<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3559</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>62</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3758</hadith-number>
<chapter>Companions of the Prophet - كتاب فضائل أصحاب النبى صلى
الله عليه وسلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال حدثني
عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة، أن فاطمة عليها السلام أرسلت إلى أبي بكر
تسأله ميراثها من النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فيما أفاء الله على رسوله
صلى الله عليه وسلم، تطلب صدقة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم التي
بالمدينة وفدك وما بقي من خمس خيبر‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر إن رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ لا نورث، ما تركنا فهو صدقة، إنما يأكل آل
محمد من هذا المال يعني مال الله ليس لهم أن يزيدوا على المأكل ‏"‏‏.‏
وإني والله لا أغير شيئا من صدقات النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم التي كانت
عليها في عهد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، ولأعملن فيها بما عمل فيها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ فتشهد علي، ثم قال إنا قد عرفنا يا
أبا بكر فضيلتك‏.‏ وذكر قرابتهم من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وحقهم‏.‏ فتكلم أبو بكر فقال والذي نفسي بيده، لقرابة رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أحب إلى أن أصل من قرابتي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Aisha: Fatima sent somebody to Abu Bakr
asking him to give her her inheritance from the Prophet from what
Allah had given to His Apostle through Fai (i.e. booty gained
without fighting). She asked for the Sadaqa (i.e. wealth assigned
for charitable purposes) of the Prophet at Medina, and Fadak, and
what remained of the Khumus (i.e., one-fifth) of the Khaibar booty.
Abu Bakr said, "Allah's Apostle said, 'We (Prophets), our property
is not inherited, and whatever we leave is Sadaqa, but Muhammad's
Family can eat from this property, i.e. Allah's property, but they
have no right to take more than the food they need.' By Allah! I
will not bring any change in dealing with the Sadaqa of the Prophet
(and will keep them) as they used to be observed in his (i.e. the
Prophet's) life-time, and I will dispose with it as Allah's Apostle
used to do," Then 'Ali said, "I testify that None has the right to
be worshipped but Allah, and that Muhammad is His Apostle," and
added, "O Abu Bakr! We acknowledge your superiority." Then he (i.e.
'Ali) mentioned their own relationship to Allah's Apostle and their
right. Abu Bakr then spoke saying, "By Allah in Whose Hands my life
is. I love to do good to the relatives of Allah's Apostle rather
than to my own relatives"</english-text>
</hadith>
