<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3646</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3845</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20330, 20349, 11349, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا عبد الله بن داود، عن فضيل بن غزوان،
عن أبي حازم، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه أن رجلا، أتى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فبعث إلى نسائه فقلن ما معنا إلا الماء‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من يضم، أو يضيف هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رجل من
الأنصار أنا‏.‏ فانطلق به إلى امرأته، فقال أكرمي ضيف رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقالت ما عندنا إلا قوت صبياني‏.‏ فقال هيئي طعامك،
وأصبحي سراجك، ونومي صبيانك إذا أرادوا عشاء‏.‏ فهيأت طعامها وأصبحت
سراجها، ونومت صبيانها، ثم قامت كأنها تصلح سراجها فأطفأته، فجعلا
يريانه أنهما يأكلان، فباتا طاويين، فلما أصبح، غدا إلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ضحك الله الليلة أو عجب من فعالكما ‏"‏ فأنزل
الله ‏{‏ويؤثرون على أنفسهم ولو كان بهم خصاصة ومن يوق شح نفسه فأولئك
هم المفلحون‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: A man came to the Prophet. The
Prophet sent a messenger to his wives (to bring something for that
man to eat) but they said that they had nothing except water. Then
Allah's Apostle said, "Who will take this (person) or entertain him
as a guest?" An Ansar man said, "I." So he took him to his wife and
said to her, "Entertain generously the guest of Allah's Apostle "
She said, "We have got nothing except the meals of my children." He
said, "Prepare your meal, light your lamp and let your children
sleep if they ask for supper." So she prepared her meal, lighted
her lamp and made her children sleep, and then stood up pretending
to mend her lamp, but she put it off. Then both of them pretended
to be eating, but they really went to bed hungry. In the morning
the Ansari went to Allah's Apostle who said, "Tonight Allah laughed
or wondered at your action." Then Allah revealed: "But give them
(emigrants) preference over themselves even though they were in
need of that And whosoever is saved from the covetousness Such are
they who will be successful." (59.9)</english-text>
</hadith>
