<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3660</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3858</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30315, 20258, 11295, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو معمر، حدثنا عبد الوارث، حدثنا عبد العزيز، عن
أنس رضى الله عنه قال لما كان يوم أحد انهزم الناس عن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأبو طلحة بين يدى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مجوب به عليه
بحجفة له، وكان أبو طلحة رجلا راميا شديد القد، يكسر يومئذ قوسين أو
ثلاثا، وكان الرجل يمر معه الجعبة من النبل فيقول انشرها لأبي طلحة‏.‏
فأشرف النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ينظر إلى القوم، فيقول أبو طلحة يا
نبي الله بأبي أنت وأمي، لا تشرف يصيبك سهم من سهام القوم، نحري دون
نحرك‏.‏ ولقد رأيت عائشة بنت أبي بكر وأم سليم وإنهما لمشمرتان، أرى
خدم سوقهما، تنقزان القرب على متونهما، تفرغانه في أفواه القوم، ثم
ترجعان فتملآنها، ثم تجيآن فتفرغانه في أفواه القوم، ولقد وقع السيف
من يدى أبي طلحة إما مرتين، وإما ثلاثا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: On the day of the battle of Uhud, the
people ran away, leaving the Prophet , but Abu- Talha was shielding
the Prophet with his shield in front of him. Abu Talha was a
strong, experienced archer who used to keep his arrow bow strong
and well stretched. On that day he broke two or three arrow bows.
If any man passed by carrying a quiver full of arrows, the Prophet
would say to him, "Empty it in front of Abu Talha." When the
Prophet stated looking at the enemy by raising his head, Abu Talha
said, "O Allah's Prophet! Let my parents be sacrificed for your
sake! Please don't raise your head and make it visible, lest an
arrow of the enemy should hit you. Let my neck and chest be wounded
instead of yours." (On that day) I saw `Aisha, the daughter of Abu
Bakr and Um Sulaim both lifting their dresses up so that I was able
to see the ornaments of their legs, and they were carrying the
water skins of their arms to pour the water into the mouths of the
thirsty people and then go back and fill them and come to pour the
water into the mouths of the people again. (On that day) Abu
Talha's sword fell from his hand twice or thrice.</english-text>
</hadith>
