<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3662</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3860</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20206, 11071, 11035, 11609, 103</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا أزهر السمان، عن ابن عون،
عن محمد، عن قيس بن عباد، قال كنت جالسا في مسجد المدينة، فدخل رجل
على وجهه أثر الخشوع، فقالوا هذا رجل من أهل الجنة‏.‏ فصلى ركعتين
تجوز فيهما ثم خرج، وتبعته فقلت إنك حين دخلت المسجد قالوا هذا رجل من
أهل الجنة‏.‏ قال والله ما ينبغي لأحد أن يقول ما لا يعلم وسأحدثك لم
ذاك رأيت رؤيا على عهد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقصصتها عليه، ورأيت
كأني في روضة ذكر من سعتها وخضرتها وسطها عمود من حديد، أسفله في
الأرض وأعلاه في السماء، في أعلاه عروة فقيل له ارقه‏.‏ قلت لا
أستطيع‏.‏ فأتاني منصف فرفع ثيابي من خلفي، فرقيت حتى كنت في أعلاها،
فأخذت بالعروة، فقيل له استمسك‏.‏ فاستيقظت وإنها لفي يدي، فقصصتها
على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ تلك الروضة الإسلام، وذلك
العمود عمود الإسلام، وتلك العروة عروة الوثقى، فأنت على الإسلام حتى
تموت ‏"‏‏.‏ وذاك الرجل عبد الله بن سلام‏.‏ وقال لي خليفة حدثنا
معاذ، حدثنا ابن عون، عن محمد، حدثنا قيس بن عباد، عن ابن سلام، قال
وصيف مكان منصف‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Qais bin Ubad: While I was sitting in the
Mosque of Medina, there entered a man (Abdullah bin Salam) with
signs of solemnity over his face. The people said, "He is one of
the people of Paradise." He prayed two light rak`at and then left.
I followed him and said, "When you entered the Mosque, the people
said, 'He is one of the people of Paradise.' " He said, "By Allah,
one ought not say what he does not know; and I will tell you why.
In the lifetime of the Prophet I had a dream which I narrated to
him. I saw as if I were in a garden." He then described its
extension and greenery. He added: In its center there was an iron
pillar whose lower end was fixed in the earth and the upper end was
in the sky, and at its upper end there was a (ring-shaped)
hand-hold. I was told to climb it. I said, "I can't." "Then a
servant came to me and lifted my clothes from behind and I climbed
till I reached the top (of the pillar). Then I got hold of the
hand-hold, and I was told to hold it tightly, then I woke up and
(the effect of) the handhold was in my hand. I narrated al I that
to the Prophet who said, 'The garden is Islam, and the handhold is
the Most Truth-worthy Hand-Hold. So you will remain as a Muslim
till you die." The narrator added: "The man was `Abdullah bin
Salam."</english-text>
</hadith>
