<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3723</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3920</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20295, 20115, 11013, 10511, 880,
2201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد الجعفي، حدثنا هشام، أخبرنا
معمر، عن الزهري، حدثنا عروة بن الزبير، أن عبيد الله بن عدي بن
الخيار، أخبره أن المسور بن مخرمة وعبد الرحمن بن الأسود بن عبد يغوث
قالا له ما يمنعك أن تكلم خالك عثمان في أخيه الوليد بن عقبة وكان
أكثر الناس فيما فعل به‏.‏ قال عبيد الله فانتصبت لعثمان حين خرج إلى
الصلاة فقلت له إن لي إليك حاجة وهى نصيحة‏.‏ فقال أيها المرء، أعوذ
بالله منك، فانصرفت، فلما قضيت الصلاة جلست إلى المسور وإلى ابن عبد
يغوث، فحدثتهما بالذي قلت لعثمان وقال لي‏.‏ فقالا قد قضيت الذي كان
عليك‏.‏ فبينما أنا جالس معهما، إذ جاءني رسول عثمان، فقالا لي قد
ابتلاك الله‏.‏ فانطلقت حتى دخلت عليه، فقال ما نصيحتك التي ذكرت آنفا
قال فتشهدت ثم قلت إن الله بعث محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم وأنزل عليه
الكتاب، وكنت ممن استجاب لله ورسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم وآمنت به،
وهاجرت الهجرتين الأوليين، وصحبت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورأيت
هديه، وقد أكثر الناس في شأن الوليد بن عقبة، فحق عليك أن تقيم عليه
الحد‏.‏ فقال لي يا ابن أخي أدركت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
قلت لا، ولكن قد خلص إلى من علمه ما خلص إلى العذراء في سترها‏.‏ قال
فتشهد عثمان فقال إن الله قد بعث محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم بالحق
وأنزل عليه الكتاب، وكنت ممن استجاب لله ورسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وآمنت بما بعث به محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ وهاجرت الهجرتين
الأوليين كما قلت، وصحبت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وبايعته، والله
ما عصيته ولا غششته حتى توفاه الله، ثم استخلف الله أبا بكر فوالله ما
عصيته ولا غششته، ثم استخلف عمر، فوالله ما عصيته ولا غششته، ثم
استخلفت، أفليس لي عليكم مثل الذي كان لهم على قال بلى‏.‏ قال فما هذه
الأحاديث التي تبلغني عنكم فأما ما ذكرت من شأن الوليد بن عقبة،
فسنأخذ فيه إن شاء الله بالحق قال فجلد الوليد أربعين جلدة، وأمر عليا
أن يجلده، وكان هو يجلده‏.‏ وقال يونس وابن أخي الزهري عن الزهري
أفليس لي عليكم من الحق مثل الذي كان لهم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah bin `Adi bin Al-Khiyar: That
Al-Miswar bin Makhrama and `Abdur-Rahman bin Al-Aswad bin 'Abu
Yaghuth had said to him, "What prevents you from speaking to your
uncle `Uthman regarding his brother Al-Walid bin `Uqba?" The people
were speaking against the latter for what he had done. 'Ubaidullah
said, "So I kept waiting for `Uthman, and when he went out for the
prayer, I said to him, 'I have got something to say to you as a
piece of advice.' `Uthman said, 'O man! I seek Refuge with Allah
from you. So I went away. When I finished my prayer, I sat with
Al-Miswar and Ibn 'Abu Yaghutb and talked to both of them of what I
had said to `Uthman and what he had said to me. They said, 'You
have done your duty.' So while I was sitting with them. `Uthman's
Messenger came to me. They said, 'Allah has put you to trial." I
set out and when I reached `Uthman, he said, 'What is your advice
which you mentioned a while ago?' I recited Tashahhud and added,
'Allah has sent Muhammad and has revealed the Holy Book (i.e.
Qur'an) to him. You (O `Uthman!) were amongst those who responded
to the call of Allah and His Apostle and had faith in him. And you
took part in the first two migrations (to Ethiopia and to Medina),
and you enjoyed the company of Allah's Apostle and learned his
traditions and advice. Now the people are talking much about
Al-Walid bin `Uqba and so it is your duty to impose on him the
legal punishment.' `Uthman then said to me, 'O my nephew! Did you
ever meet Allah's Apostle ?' I said, 'No, but his knowledge has
reached me as it has reached the virgin in her seclusion.' `Uthman
then recited Tashahhud and said, 'No doubt, Allah has sent Muhammad
with the Truth and has revealed to him His Holy Book (i.e. Qur'an)
and I was amongst those who responded to the call of Allah and His
Apostle and I had faith in Muhammad's Mission, and I had performed
the first two migrations as you have said, and I enjoyed the
company of Allah's Apostle and gave the pledge of allegiance to
him. By Allah, I never disobeyed him and never cheated him till
Allah caused him to die. Then Allah made Abu Bakr Caliph, and by
Allah, I was never disobedient to him, nor did I cheat him. Then
`Umar became Caliph, and by Allah, I was never disobedient to him,
nor did I cheat him. Then I became Caliph. Have I not then the same
rights over you as they had over me?' I replied in the affirmative.
`Uthman further said, 'The what are these talks which are reaching
me from you? As for what you ha mentioned about Al-Walid bin 'Uqb;
Allah willing, I shall give him the leg; punishment justly. Then
`Uthman ordered that Al-Walid be flogged fort lashes. He ordered
`Ali to flog him an he himself flogged him as well."</english-text>
</hadith>
