<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3739</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3935</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>20294, 20297, 11019, 19, 1335</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا هدبة بن خالد، حدثنا همام بن يحيى، حدثنا قتادة،
عن أنس بن مالك، عن مالك بن صعصعة رضى الله عنهما أن نبي الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم حدثهم عن ليلة أسري به ‏"‏ بينما أنا في الحطيم وربما
قال في الحجر مضطجعا، إذ أتاني آت فقد قال وسمعته يقول فشق ما بين هذه
إلى هذه فقلت للجارود وهو إلى جنبي ما يعني به قال من ثغرة نحره إلى
شعرته، وسمعته يقول من قصه إلى شعرته فاستخرج قلبي، ثم أتيت بطست من
ذهب مملوءة إيمانا، فغسل قلبي ثم حشي، ثم أوتيت بدابة دون البغل وفوق
الحمار أبيض ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال له الجارود هو البراق يا أبا حمزة قال أنس
نعم، يضع خطوه عند أقصى طرفه ‏"‏ فحملت عليه، فانطلق بي جبريل حتى أتى
السماء الدنيا فاستفتح، فقيل من هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال
محمد‏.‏ قيل وقد أرسل إليه قال نعم‏.‏ قيل مرحبا به، فنعم المجيء جاء
ففتح، فلما خلصت، فإذا فيها آدم، فقال هذا أبوك آدم فسلم عليه‏.‏
فسلمت عليه فرد السلام ثم قال مرحبا بالابن الصالح والنبي الصالح‏.‏
ثم صعد حتى أتى السماء الثانية فاستفتح، قيل من هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل
ومن معك قال محمد‏.‏ قيل وقد أرسل إليه قال نعم‏.‏ قيل مرحبا به فنعم
المجيء جاء‏.‏ ففتح، فلما خلصت، إذا يحيى وعيسى، وهما ابنا الخالة قال
هذا يحيى وعيسى فسلم عليهما‏.‏ فسلمت فردا، ثم قالا مرحبا بالأخ
الصالح والنبي الصالح‏.‏ ثم صعد بي إلى السماء الثالثة، فاستفتح قيل
من هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد‏.‏ قيل وقد أرسل إليه قال
نعم‏.‏ قيل مرحبا به، فنعم المجيء جاء‏.‏ ففتح، فلما خلصت إذا يوسف‏.‏
قال هذا يوسف فسلم عليه‏.‏ فسلمت عليه فرد، ثم قال مرحبا بالأخ الصالح
والنبي الصالح، ثم صعد بي حتى أتى السماء الرابعة، فاستفتح، قيل من
هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد‏.‏ قيل أوقد أرسل إليه قال
نعم‏.‏ قيل مرحبا به، فنعم المجيء جاء‏.‏ ففتح، فلما خلصت إلى إدريس
قال هذا إدريس فسلم عليه‏.‏ فسلمت عليه فرد ثم قال مرحبا بالأخ الصالح
والنبي الصالح‏.‏ ثم صعد بي حتى أتى السماء الخامسة، فاستفتح، قيل من
هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل ومن معك قال محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ قيل وقد
أرسل إليه قال نعم‏.‏ قيل مرحبا به، فنعم المجيء جاء‏.‏ فلما خلصت
فإذا هارون قال هذا هارون فسلم عليه‏.‏ فسلمت عليه فرد ثم قال مرحبا
بالأخ الصالح والنبي الصالح‏.‏ ثم صعد بي حتى أتى السماء السادسة،
فاستفتح، قيل من هذا قال جبريل‏.‏ قيل من معك قال محمد‏.‏ قيل وقد
أرسل إليه قال نعم‏.‏ قال مرحبا به، فنعم المجيء جاء، فلما خلصت، فإذا
موسى قال هذا موسى فسلم عليه، فسلمت عليه فرد ثم قال مرحبا بالأخ
الصالح والنبي الصالح‏.‏ فلما تجاوزت بكى، قيل له ما يبكيك قال أبكي
لأن غلاما بعث بعدي، يدخل الجنة من أمته أكثر من يدخلها من أمتي‏.‏ ثم
صعد بي إلى السماء السابعة، فاستفتح جبريل، قيل من هذا قال جبريل‏.‏
قيل ومن معك قال محمد‏.‏ قيل وقد بعث إليه‏.‏ قال نعم‏.‏ قال مرحبا
به، فنعم المجيء جاء فلما خلصت، فإذا إبراهيم قال هذا أبوك فسلم
عليه‏.‏ قال فسلمت عليه، فرد السلام قال مرحبا بالابن الصالح والنبي
الصالح‏.‏ ثم رفعت لي سدرة المنتهى، فإذا نبقها مثل قلال هجر، وإذا
ورقها مثل آذان الفيلة قال هذه سدرة المنتهى، وإذا أربعة أنهار نهران
باطنان، ونهران ظاهران‏.‏ فقلت ما هذان يا جبريل قال أما الباطنان،
فنهران في الجنة، وأما الظاهران فالنيل والفرات‏.‏ ثم رفع لي البيت
المعمور، ثم أتيت بإناء من خمر، وإناء من لبن وإناء من عسل، فأخذت
اللبن، فقال هي الفطرة أنت عليها وأمتك‏.‏ ثم فرضت على الصلوات خمسين
صلاة كل يوم‏.‏ فرجعت فمررت على موسى، فقال بما أمرت قال أمرت بخمسين
صلاة كل يوم‏.‏ قال إن أمتك لا تستطيع خمسين صلاة كل يوم، وإني والله
قد جربت الناس قبلك، وعالجت بني إسرائيل أشد المعالجة، فارجع إلى ربك
فاسأله التخفيف لأمتك‏.‏ فرجعت، فوضع عني عشرا، فرجعت إلى موسى فقال
مثله، فرجعت فوضع عني عشرا، فرجعت إلى موسى فقال مثله، فرجعت فوضع عني
عشرا، فرجعت إلى موسى فقال مثله، فرجعت فأمرت بعشر صلوات كل يوم،
فرجعت فقال مثله، فرجعت فأمرت بخمس صلوات كل يوم، فرجعت إلى موسى،
فقال بما أمرت قلت أمرت بخمس صلوات كل يوم‏.‏ قال إن أمتك لا تستطيع
خمس صلوات كل يوم، وإني قد جربت الناس قبلك، وعالجت بني إسرائيل أشد
المعالجة، فارجع إلى ربك فاسأله التخفيف لأمتك‏.‏ قال سألت ربي حتى
استحييت، ولكن أرضى وأسلم قال فلما جاوزت نادى مناد أمضيت فريضتي
وخففت عن عبادي ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abbas bin Malik: Malik bin Sasaa said that
Allah's Apostle described to them his Night Journey saying, "While
I was lying in Al-Hatim or Al-Hijr, suddenly someone came to me and
cut my body open from here to here." I asked Al-Jarud who was by my
side, "What does he mean?" He said, "It means from his throat to
his pubic area," or said, "From the top of the chest." The Prophet
further said, "He then took out my heart. Then a gold tray of
Belief was brought to me and my heart was washed and was filled
(with Belief) and then returned to its original place. Then a white
animal which was smaller than a mule and bigger than a donkey was
brought to me." (On this Al-Jarud asked, "Was it the Buraq, O Abu
Hamza?" I (i.e. Anas) replied in the affirmative). The Prophet
said, "The animal's step (was so wide that it) reached the farthest
point within the reach of the animal's sight. I was carried on it,
and Gabriel set out with me till we reached the nearest heaven.
When he asked for the gate to be opened, it was asked, 'Who is it?'
Gabriel answered, 'Gabriel.' It was asked, 'Who is accompanying
you?' Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked, 'Has Muhammad been
called?' Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, 'He
is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!' The gate was opened,
and when I went over the first heaven, I saw Adam there. Gabriel
said (to me). 'This is your father, Adam; pay him your greetings.'
So I greeted him and he returned the greeting to me and said, 'You
are welcomed, O pious son and pious Prophet.' Then Gabriel ascended
with me till we reached the second heaven. Gabriel asked for the
gate to be opened. It was asked, 'Who is it?' Gabriel answered,
'Gabriel.' It was asked, 'Who is accompanying you?' Gabriel
replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked, 'Has he been called?' Gabriel
answered in the affirmative. Then it was said, 'He is welcomed.
What an excellent visit his is!' The gate was opened. When I went
over the second heaven, there I saw Yahya (i.e. John) and `Isa
(i.e. Jesus) who were cousins of each other. Gabriel said (to me),
'These are John and Jesus; pay them your greetings.' So I greeted
them and both of them returned my greetings to me and said, 'You
are welcomed, O pious brother and pious Prophet.' Then Gabriel
ascended with me to the third heaven and asked for its gate to be
opened. It was asked, 'Who is it?' Gabriel replied, 'Gabriel.' It
was asked, 'Who is accompanying you?' Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.'
It was asked, 'Has he been called?' Gabriel replied in the
affirmative. Then it was said, 'He is welcomed, what an excellent
visit his is!' The gate was opened, and when I went over the third
heaven there I saw Joseph. Gabriel said (to me), 'This is Joseph;
pay him your greetings.' So I greeted him and he returned the
greeting to me and said, 'You are welcomed, O pious brother and
pious Prophet.' Then Gabriel ascended with me to the fourth heaven
and asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, 'Who is it?'
Gabriel replied, 'Gabriel' It was asked, 'Who is accompanying you?'
Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked, 'Has he been called?'
Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, 'He is
welcomed, what an excel lent visit his is!' The gate was opened,
and when I went over the fourth heaven, there I saw Idris. Gabriel
said (to me), 'This is Idris; pay him your greetings.' So I greeted
him and he returned the greeting to me and said, 'You are welcomed,
O pious brother and pious Prophet.' Then Gabriel ascended with me
to the fifth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was
asked, 'Who is it?' Gabriel replied, 'Gabriel.' It was asked. 'Who
is accompanying you?' Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked,
'Has he been called?' Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it
was said He is welcomed, what an excellent visit his is! So when I
went over the fifth heaven, there I saw Harun (i.e. Aaron), Gabriel
said, (to me). This is Aaron; pay him your greetings.' I greeted
him and he returned the greeting to me and said, 'You are welcomed,
O pious brother and pious Prophet.' Then Gabriel ascended with me
to the sixth heaven and asked for its gate to be opened. It was
asked. 'Who is it?' Gabriel replied, 'Gabriel.' It was asked, 'Who
is accompanying you?' Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked,
'Has he been called?' Gabriel replied in the affirmative. It was
said, 'He is welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!' When I went
(over the sixth heaven), there I saw Moses. Gabriel said (to me),'
This is Moses; pay him your greeting. So I greeted him and he
returned the greetings to me and said, 'You are welcomed, O pious
brother and pious Prophet.' When I left him (i.e. Moses) he wept.
Someone asked him, 'What makes you weep?' Moses said, 'I weep
because after me there has been sent (as Prophet) a young man whose
followers will enter Paradise in greater numbers than my
followers.' Then Gabriel ascended with me to the seventh heaven and
asked for its gate to be opened. It was asked, 'Who is it?' Gabriel
replied, 'Gabriel.' It was asked,' Who is accompanying you?'
Gabriel replied, 'Muhammad.' It was asked, 'Has he been called?'
Gabriel replied in the affirmative. Then it was said, 'He is
welcomed. What an excellent visit his is!' So when I went (over the
seventh heaven), there I saw Abraham. Gabriel said (to me), 'This
is your father; pay your greetings to him.' So I greeted him and he
returned the greetings to me and said, 'You are welcomed, O pious
son and pious Prophet.' Then I was made to ascend to
Sidrat-ul-Muntaha (i.e. the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary)
Behold! Its fruits were like the jars of Hajr (i.e. a place near
Medina) and its leaves were as big as the ears of elephants.
Gabriel said, 'This is the Lote Tree of the utmost boundary) .
Behold ! There ran four rivers, two were hidden and two were
visible, I asked, 'What are these two kinds of rivers, O Gabriel?'
He replied,' As for the hidden rivers, they are two rivers in
Paradise and the visible rivers are the Nile and the Euphrates.'
Then Al-Bait-ul-Ma'mur (i.e. the Sacred House) was shown to me and
a container full of wine and another full of milk and a third full
of honey were brought to me. I took the milk. Gabriel remarked,
'This is the Islamic religion which you and your followers are
following.' Then the prayers were enjoined on me: They were fifty
prayers a day. When I returned, I passed by Moses who asked (me),
'What have you been ordered to do?' I replied, 'I have been ordered
to offer fifty prayers a day.' Moses said, 'Your followers cannot
bear fifty prayers a day, and by Allah, I have tested people before
you, and I have tried my level best with Bani Israel (in vain). Go
back to your Lord and ask for reduction to lessen your followers'
burden.' So I went back, and Allah reduced ten prayers for me. Then
again I came to Moses, but he repeated the same as he had said
before. Then again I went back to Allah and He reduced ten more
prayers. When I came back to Moses he said the same, I went back to
Allah and He ordered me to observe ten prayers a day. When I came
back to Moses, he repeated the same advice, so I went back to Allah
and was ordered to observe five prayers a day. When I came back to
Moses, he said, 'What have you been ordered?' I replied, 'I have
been ordered to observe five prayers a day.' He said, 'Your
followers cannot bear five prayers a day, and no doubt, I have got
an experience of the people before you, and I have tried my level
best with Bani Israel, so go back to your Lord and ask for
reduction to lessen your follower's burden.' I said, 'I have
requested so much of my Lord that I feel ashamed, but I am
satisfied now and surrender to Allah's Order.' When I left, I heard
a voice saying, 'I have passed My Order and have lessened the
burden of My Worshipers."</english-text>
</hadith>
