<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3766</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3963</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30483, 20229, 11298, 11306, 11901</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بشر، حدثنا روح، حدثنا عوف، عن معاوية بن
قرة، قال حدثني أبو بردة بن أبي موسى الأشعري، قال قال لي عبد الله بن
عمر هل تدري ما قال أبي لأبيك قال قلت لا‏.‏ قال فإن أبي قال لأبيك يا
أبا موسى، هل يسرك إسلامنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهجرتنا
معه، وجهادنا معه، وعملنا كله معه، برد لنا، وأن كل عمل عملناه بعده
نجونا منه كفافا رأسا برأس فقال أبي لا والله، قد جاهدنا بعد رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وصلينا، وصمنا، وعملنا خيرا كثيرا، وأسلم على
أيدينا بشر كثير، وإنا لنرجو ذلك‏.‏ فقال أبي لكني أنا والذي نفس عمر
بيده لوددت أن ذلك برد لنا، وأن كل شىء عملناه بعد نجونا منه كفافا
رأسا برأس‏.‏ فقلت إن أباك والله خير من أبي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Burda Bin Abi Musa Al-Ash`ari: `Abdullah
bin `Umar said to me, "Do you know what my father said to your
father once?" I said, "No." He said, "My father said to your
father, 'O Abu Musa, will it please you that we will be rewarded
for our conversion to Islam with Allah's Apostle and our migration
with him, and our Jihad with him and all our good deeds which we
did, with him, and that all the deeds we did after his death will
be disregarded whether good or bad?' Your father (i.e. Abu Musa)
said, 'No, by Allah, we took part in Jihad after Allah's Apostle ,
prayed and did plenty of good deeds, and many people have embraced
Islam at our hands, and no doubt, we expect rewards from Allah for
these good deeds.' On that my father (i.e. `Umar) said, 'As for
myself, By Him in Whose Hand `Umar's soul is, I wish that the deeds
done by us at the time of the Prophet remain rewardable while
whatsoever we did after the death of the Prophet be enough to save
us from Punishment in that the good deeds compensate for the bad
ones.' " On that I said (to Ibn `Umar), "By Allah, your father was
better than my father!"</english-text>
</hadith>
