<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3768</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3965</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30185, 20427, 20406, 20473, 11049, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن عثمان، حدثنا شريح بن مسلمة، حدثنا
إبراهيم بن يوسف، عن أبيه، عن أبي إسحاق، قال سمعت البراء، يحدث قال
ابتاع أبو بكر من عازب رحلا فحملته معه قال فسأله عازب عن مسير رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال أخذ علينا بالرصد، فخرجنا ليلا، فأحثثنا
ليلتنا ويومنا حتى قام قائم الظهيرة، ثم رفعت لنا صخرة، فأتيناها ولها
شىء من ظل قال ففرشت لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فروة معي، ثم
اضطجع عليها النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فانطلقت أنفض ما حوله، فإذا أنا
براع قد أقبل في غنيمة يريد من الصخرة مثل الذي أردنا فسألته لمن أنت
يا غلام فقال أنا لفلان‏.‏ فقلت له هل في غنمك من لبن قال نعم‏.‏ قلت
له هل أنت حالب قال نعم‏.‏ فأخذ شاة من غنمه فقلت له انفض الضرع‏.‏
قال فحلب كثبة من لبن، ومعي إداوة من ماء عليها خرقة قد روأتها لرسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصببت على اللبن حتى برد أسفله، ثم أتيت به
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت اشرب يا رسول الله‏.‏ فشرب رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى رضيت، ثم ارتحلنا والطلب في
إثرنا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Bara: Abu Bakr bought a (camel's) saddle
from `Azib, and I carried it for him. `Azib (i.e. my father) asked
Abu Bakr regarding the journey of the migration of Allah's Apostle.
Abu Bakr said, "Close observers were appointed by our enemies to
watch us. So we went out at night and travelled throughout the
night and the following day till it was noon, then we perceived a
rock and went towards it, and there was some shade under it. I
spread a cloak I had with me for Allah's Apostle and then the
Prophet layed on it. I went out to guard him and all of a sudden I
saw a shepherd coming with his sheep looking for the same, the
shade of the rock as we did, I asked him, 'O boy, to whom do you
belong?' He replied, 'I belong to so-and-so.' I asked him, 'Is
there some milk in your sheep?' He replied in the affirmative. I
asked him, 'Will you milk?' He replied in the affirmative. Then he
got hold of one of his sheep. I said to him, 'Remove the dust from
its udder.' Then he milked a little milk. I had a water-skin with
me which was tied with a piece of cloth. I had prepared the
water-skin for Allah's Apostle . So I poured some water over the
milk (container) till its bottom became cold. Then I brought the
milk to the Prophet and said, 'Drink, O Allah's Apostle.' Allah's
Apostle drank till I became pleased. Then we departed and the
pursuers were following us." Al-Bara added: I then went with Abu
Bakr into his home (carrying that saddle) and there I saw his
daughter `Aisha Lying in a bed because of heavy fever and I saw her
father Abu Bakr kissing her cheek and saying, "How are you, little
daughter?"</english-text>
</hadith>
