<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3780</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3977</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20150, 11013, 11006</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد، أخبرنا
ابن شهاب، عن خارجة بن زيد بن ثابت، أن أم العلاء امرأة من نسائهم
بايعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرته أن عثمان بن مظعون طار لهم في
السكنى حين اقترعت الأنصار على سكنى المهاجرين، قالت أم العلاء فاشتكى
عثمان عندنا، فمرضته حتى توفي، وجعلناه في أثوابه، فدخل علينا النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت رحمة الله عليك أبا السائب، شهادتي عليك لقد
أكرمك الله‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وما يدريك أن الله
أكرمه ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت قلت لا أدري بأبي أنت وأمي يا رسول الله فمن قال
‏"‏ أما هو فقد جاءه والله اليقين، والله إني لأرجو له الخير، وما
أدري والله وأنا رسول الله ما يفعل بي ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فوالله لا أزكي
أحدا بعده قالت فأحزنني ذلك فنمت فأريت لعثمان بن مظعون عينا تجري،
فجئت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخبرته‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ذلك عمله
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Um Al-`Ala: An Ansari woman who gave the
pledge of allegiance to the Prophet that the Ansar drew lots
concerning the dwelling of the Emigrants. `Uthman bin Maz'un was
decided to dwell with them (i.e. Um Al-`Ala's family), `Uthman fell
ill and I nursed him till he died, and we covered him with his
clothes. Then the Prophet came to us and I (addressing the dead
body) said, "O Abu As-Sa'ib, may Allah's Mercy be on you! I bear
witness that Allah has honored you." On that the Prophet said, "How
do you know that Allah has honored him?" I replied, "I do not know.
May my father and my mother be sacrificed for you, O Allah's
Apostle! But who else is worthy of it (if not `Uthman)?" He said,
"As to him, by Allah, death has overtaken him, and I hope the best
for him. By Allah, though I am the Apostle of Allah, yet I do not
know what Allah will do to me," By Allah, I will never assert the
piety of anyone after him. That made me sad, and when I slept I saw
in a dream a flowing stream for `Uthman bin Maz'un. I went to
Allah's Apostle and told him of it. He remarked, "That symbolizes
his (good) deeds."</english-text>
</hadith>
