<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3783</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3980</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 30313, 20250, 20258, 11317, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا عبد الوارث،‏.‏ وحدثنا إسحاق بن
منصور، أخبرنا عبد الصمد، قال سمعت أبي يحدث، حدثنا أبو التياح، يزيد
بن حميد الضبعي قال حدثني أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه قال لما قدم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المدينة، نزل في علو المدينة في حى يقال لهم
بنو عمرو بن عوف قال فأقام فيهم أربع عشرة ليلة، ثم أرسل إلى ملإ بني
النجار قال فجاءوا متقلدي سيوفهم، قال وكأني أنظر إلى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم على راحلته، وأبو بكر ردفه، وملأ بني النجار حوله حتى
ألقى بفناء أبي أيوب، قال فكان يصلي حيث أدركته الصلاة، ويصلي في
مرابض الغنم، قال ثم إنه أمر ببناء المسجد، فأرسل إلى ملإ بني النجار،
فجاءوا فقال ‏"‏ يا بني النجار، ثامنوني حائطكم هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا لا،
والله لا نطلب ثمنه إلا إلى الله‏.‏ قال فكان فيه ما أقول لكم كانت
فيه قبور المشركين، وكانت فيه خرب، وكان فيه نخل، فأمر رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم بقبور المشركين فنبشت، وبالخرب فسويت، وبالنخل فقطع،
قال فصفوا النخل قبلة المسجد قال وجعلوا عضادتيه حجارة‏.‏ قال قال
جعلوا ينقلون ذاك الصخر وهم يرتجزون، ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
معهم يقولون اللهم إنه لا خير إلا خير الآخره فانصر الأنصار
والمهاجره‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: When Allah's Apostle arrived
at Medina, he alighted at the upper part of Medina among the people
called Bani `Amr bin `Auf and he stayed with them for fourteen
nights. Then he sent for the chiefs of Bani An-Najjar, and they
came, carrying their swords. As if I am just now looking at Allah's
Apostle on his she-camel with Abu Bakr riding behind him (on the
same camel) and the chiefs of Bani An- Najjar around him till he
dismounted in the courtyard of Abu Aiyub's home. The Prophet used
to offer the prayer wherever the prayer was due, and he would pray
even in sheepfolds. Then he ordered that the mosque be built. He
sent for the chiefs of Banu An-Najjar, and when they came, he said,
"O Banu An-Najjar! Suggest to me the price of this garden of
yours." They replied "No! By Allah, we do not demand its price
except from Allah." In that garden there were the (following)
things that I will tell you: Graves of pagans, unleveled land with
holes and pits etc., and date-palm trees. Allah's Apostle ordered
that the graves of the pagans be dug up and, the unleveled land be
leveled and the date-palm trees be cut down. The trunks of the
trees were arranged so as to form the wall facing the Qibla. The
Stone pillars were built at the sides of its gate. The companions
of the Prophet were carrying the stones and reciting some lyrics,
and Allah's Apostle . . was with them and they were saying, "O
Allah! There is no good Excel the good of the Hereafter, so bestow
victory on the Ansar and the Emigrants. "</english-text>
</hadith>
