<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3787</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3984</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30119, 20150, 11013, 10554, 9</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن قزعة، حدثنا إبراهيم، عن الزهري، عن عامر
بن سعد بن مالك، عن أبيه، قال عادني النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عام حجة
الوداع من مرض أشفيت منه على الموت، فقلت يا رسول الله، بلغ بي من
الوجع ما ترى، وأنا ذو مال ولا يرثني إلا ابنة لي واحدة، أفأتصدق
بثلثى مالي قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فأتصدق بشطره قال ‏"‏ الثلث يا سعد،
والثلث كثير، إنك أن تذر ذريتك أغنياء خير من أن تذرهم عالة يتكففون
الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أحمد بن يونس عن إبراهيم ‏"‏ أن تذر ذريتك، ولست
بنافق نفقة تبتغي بها وجه الله إلا آجرك الله بها، حتى اللقمة تجعلها
في في امرأتك ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت يا رسول الله، أخلف بعد أصحابي قال ‏"‏ إنك
لن تخلف فتعمل عملا تبتغي به وجه الله إلا ازددت به درجة ورفعة، ولعلك
تخلف حتى ينتفع بك أقوام، ويضر بك آخرون، اللهم أمض لأصحابي هجرتهم،
ولا تردهم على أعقابهم، لكن البائس سعد ابن خولة يرثي له رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم أن توفي بمكة ‏"‏‏.‏ وقال أحمد بن يونس وموسى عن
إبراهيم ‏"‏ أن تذر ورثتك ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`d bin Malik: In the year of
Hajjat-ul-Wada` the Prophet visited me when I fell ill and was
about to die because of that illness. I said, "O Allah's Apostle! I
am very ill as you see, and I am a rich man and have no heir except
my only daughter. Shall I give 2/3 of my property in charity?" He
said, "No." I said, "Shall I then give one half of it in charity?"
He said, "O Sa`d! Give 1/3 (in charity) and even 1/3 is too much.
No doubt, it is better to leave your children rich than to leave
them poor, reduced to begging from others. And Allah will reward
you for whatever you spend with the intention of gaining Allah's
Pleasure even if it were a mouthful of food you put into your wives
mouth." I said, "O Allah's Apostle! Am I to be left behind (in
Mecca) after my companions have gone?" He said, "If you should be
left behind, you will be upgraded and elevated for every deed you
will do with a desire to achieve Allah's Pleasure. I hope that you
will live long so that some people will benefit by you while others
will be harmed. O Allah! Please fulfill the migration of my
companions and do not make them turn back on their heels. But (we
feel sorry for) the unlucky Sa`d bin Khaulah." Allah's Apostle
lamented his death in Mecca.</english-text>
</hadith>
