<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3789</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>63</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3986</hadith-number>
<chapter>Merits of the Helpers in Madinah (Ansaar) - كتاب مناقب
الأنصار</chapter>
<chain-index>30128, 20212, 11279, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني حامد بن عمر، عن بشر بن المفضل، حدثنا حميد، حدثنا
أنس، أن عبد الله بن سلام، بلغه مقدم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
المدينة، فأتاه يسأله عن أشياء، فقال إني سائلك عن ثلاث لا يعلمهن إلا
نبي ما أول أشراط الساعة وما أول طعام يأكله أهل الجنة وما بال الولد
ينزع إلى أبيه أو إلى أمه قال ‏"‏ أخبرني به جبريل آنفا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
ابن سلام ذاك عدو اليهود من الملائكة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أما أول أشراط الساعة
فنار تحشرهم من المشرق إلى المغرب، وأما أول طعام يأكله أهل الجنة،
فزيادة كبد الحوت، وأما الولد، فإذا سبق ماء الرجل ماء المرأة نزع
الولد، وإذا سبق ماء المرأة ماء الرجل نزعت الولد ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أشهد أن
لا إله إلا الله وأنك رسول الله‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله، إن اليهود قوم
بهت، فاسألهم عني قبل أن يعلموا بإسلامي، فجاءت اليهود فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أى رجل عبد الله بن سلام فيكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا خيرنا
وابن خيرنا وأفضلنا وابن أفضلنا‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
أرأيتم إن أسلم عبد الله بن سلام ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا أعاذه الله من ذلك‏.‏
فأعاد عليهم، فقالوا مثل ذلك، فخرج إليهم عبد الله فقال أشهد أن لا
إله إلا الله وأن محمدا رسول الله‏.‏ قالوا شرنا وابن شرنا‏.‏
وتنقصوه‏.‏ قال هذا كنت أخاف يا رسول الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: When the news of the arrival of the
Prophet at Medina reached `Abdullah bin Salam, he went to him to
ask him about certain things, He said, "I am going to ask you about
three things which only a Prophet can answer: What is the first
sign of The Hour? What is the first food which the people of
Paradise will eat? Why does a child attract the similarity to his
father or to his mother?" The Prophet replied, "Gabriel has just
now informed me of that." Ibn Salam said, "He (i.e. Gabriel) is the
enemy of the Jews amongst the angels. The Prophet said, "As for the
first sign of The Hour, it will be a fire that will collect the
people from the East to the West. As for the first meal which the
people of Paradise will eat, it will be the caudate (extra) lobe of
the fish-liver. As for the child, if the man's discharge proceeds
the woman's discharge, the child attracts the similarity to the
man, and if the woman's discharge proceeds the man's, then the
child attracts the similarity to the woman." On this, `Abdullah bin
Salam said, "I testify that None has the right to be worshipped
except Allah, and that you are the Apostle of Allah." and added, "O
Allah's Apostle! Jews invent such lies as make one astonished, so
please ask them about me before they know about my conversion to I
slam . " The Jews came, and the Prophet said, "What kind of man is
`Abdullah bin Salam among you?" They replied, "The best of us and
the son of the best of us and the most superior among us, and the
son of the most superior among us. "The Prophet said, "What would
you think if `Abdullah bin Salam should embrace Islam?" They said,
"May Allah protect him from that." The Prophet repeated his
question and they gave the same answer. Then `Abdullah came out to
them and said, "I testify that None has the right to be worshipped
except Allah and that Muhammad is the Apostle of Allah!" On this,
the Jews said, "He is the most wicked among us and the son of the
most wicked among us." So they degraded him. On this, he (i.e.
`Abdullah bin Salam) said, "It is this that I was afraid of, O
Allah's Apostle.</english-text>
</hadith>
