<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3801</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>3998</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30185, 20427, 20406, 20473, 11049, 11382,
16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أحمد بن عثمان، حدثنا شريح بن مسلمة، حدثنا
إبراهيم بن يوسف، عن أبيه، عن أبي إسحاق، قال حدثني عمرو بن ميمون،
أنه سمع عبد الله بن مسعود رضى الله عنه حدث عن سعد بن معاذ، أنه قال
كان صديقا لأمية بن خلف، وكان أمية إذا مر بالمدينة نزل على سعد، وكان
سعد إذا مر بمكة نزل على أمية، فلما قدم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
المدينة انطلق سعد معتمرا، فنزل على أمية بمكة، فقال لأمية انظر لي
ساعة خلوة لعلي أن أطوف بالبيت‏.‏ فخرج به قريبا من نصف النهار
فلقيهما أبو جهل فقال يا أبا صفوان، من هذا معك فقال هذا سعد‏.‏ فقال
له أبو جهل ألا أراك تطوف بمكة آمنا، وقد أويتم الصباة، وزعمتم أنكم
تنصرونهم وتعينونهم، أما والله لولا أنك مع أبي صفوان ما رجعت إلى
أهلك سالما‏.‏ فقال له سعد ورفع صوته عليه أما والله لئن منعتني هذا
لأمنعنك ما هو أشد عليك منه طريقك على المدينة‏.‏ فقال له أمية لا
ترفع صوتك يا سعد على أبي الحكم سيد أهل الوادي‏.‏ فقال سعد دعنا عنك
يا أمية، فوالله لقد سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول إنهم
قاتلوك‏.‏ قال بمكة قال لا أدري‏.‏ ففزع لذلك أمية فزعا شديدا، فلما
رجع أمية إلى أهله قال يا أم صفوان، ألم ترى ما قال لي سعد قالت وما
قال لك قال زعم أن محمدا أخبرهم أنهم قاتلي، فقلت له بمكة قال لا
أدري‏.‏ فقال أمية والله لا أخرج من مكة، فلما كان يوم بدر استنفر أبو
جهل الناس قال أدركوا عيركم‏.‏ فكره أمية أن يخرج، فأتاه أبو جهل فقال
يا أبا صفوان، إنك متى ما يراك الناس قد تخلفت وأنت سيد أهل الوادي
تخلفوا معك، فلم يزل به أبو جهل حتى قال أما إذ غلبتني، فوالله
لأشترين أجود بعير بمكة ثم قال أمية يا أم صفوان جهزيني‏.‏ فقالت له
يا أبا صفوان وقد نسيت ما قال لك أخوك اليثربي قال لا، ما أريد أن
أجوز معهم إلا قريبا‏.‏ فلما خرج أمية أخذ لا ينزل منزلا إلا عقل
بعيره، فلم يزل بذلك حتى قتله الله عز وجل ببدر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin Mas`ud: From Sa`d bin Mu`adh:
Sa`d bin Mu`adh was an intimate friend of Umaiya bin Khalaf and
whenever Umaiya passed through Medina, he used to stay with Sa`d,
and whenever Sa`d went to Mecca, he used to stay with Umaiya. When
Allah's Apostle arrived at Medina, Sa`d went to perform `Umra and
stayed at Umaiya's home in Mecca. He said to Umaiya, "Tell me of a
time when (the Mosque) is empty so that I may be able to perform
Tawaf around the Ka`ba." So Umaiya went with him about midday. Abu
Jahl met them and said, "O Abu Safwan! Who is this man accompanying
you?" He said, "He is Sa`d." Abu Jahl addressed Sa`d saying, "I see
you wandering about safely in Mecca inspite of the fact that you
have given shelter to the people who have changed their religion
(i.e. became Muslims) and have claimed that you will help them and
support them. By Allah, if you were not in the company of Abu
Safwan, you would not be able to go your family safely." Sa`d,
raising his voice, said to him, "By Allah, if you should stop me
from doing this (i.e. performing Tawaf) I would certainly prevent
you from something which is more valuable for you, that is, your
passage through Medina." On this, Umaiya said to him, "O Sa`d do
not raise your voice before Abu-l-Hakam, the chief of the people of
the Valley (of Mecca)." Sa`d said, "O Umaiya, stop that! By Allah,
I have heard Allah's Apostle predicting that the Muslim will kill
you." Umaiya asked, "In Mecca?" Sa`d said, "I do not know." Umaiya
was greatly scared by that news. When Umaiya returned to his
family, he said to his wife, "O Um Safwan! Don't you know what Sa`d
told me? "She said, "What has he told you?" He replied, "He claims
that Muhammad has informed them (i.e. companions that they will
kill me. I asked him, 'In Mecca?' He replied, 'I do not know." Then
Umaiya added, "By Allah, I will never go out of Mecca." But when
the day of (the Ghazwa of) Badr came, Abu Jahl called the people to
war, saying, "Go and protect your caravan." But Umaiya disliked to
go out (of Mecca). Abu Jahl came to him and said, "O Abu Safwan! If
the people see you staying behind though you are the chief of the
people of the Valley, then they will remain behind with you." Abu
Jahl kept on urging him to go until he (i.e. Umaiya) said, "As you
have forced me to change my mind, by Allah, I will buy the best
camel in Mecca. Then Umaiya said (to his wife). "O Um Safwan,
prepare what I need (for the journey)." She said to him, "O Abu
Safwan! Have you forgotten what your Yathribi brother told you?" He
said, "No, but I do not want to go with them but for a short
distance." So when Umaiya went out, he used to tie his camel
wherever he camped. He kept on doing that till Allah caused him to
be killed at Badr.</english-text>
</hadith>
