<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3869</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4064</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 20025, 20115, 20475, 11013, 10511, 2201,
30154</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا معمر، ويونس، عن
الزهري، عن عروة بن الزبير، أنه أخبره أن المسور بن مخرمة أخبره أن
عمرو بن عوف وهو حليف لبني عامر بن لؤى، وكان شهد بدرا مع النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث أبا عبيدة بن
الجراح إلى البحرين يأتي بجزيتها، وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
هو صالح أهل البحرين، وأمر عليهم العلاء بن الحضرمي، فقدم أبو عبيدة
بمال من البحرين فسمعت الأنصار بقدوم أبي عبيدة، فوافوا صلاة الفجر مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، فلما انصرف تعرضوا له، فتبسم رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم حين رآهم ثم قال ‏"‏ أظنكم سمعتم أن أبا عبيدة قدم
بشىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا أجل يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأبشروا وأملوا ما
يسركم، فوالله ما الفقر أخشى عليكم، ولكني أخشى أن تبسط عليكم الدنيا
كما بسطت على من قبلكم، فتنافسوها كما تنافسوها، وتهلككم كما أهلكتهم
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Miswar bin Makhrama: That `Amr bin `Auf,
who was an ally of Bani 'Amir bin Luai and one of those who fought
at Badr in the company of the Prophet , said, "Allah's Apostle sent
Abu 'Ubaida bin Al-Jarrah to Bahrain to bring the Jizya taxation
from its people, for Allah's Apostle had made a peace treaty with
the people of Bahrain and appointed Al-`Ala' bin Al-Hadrami as
their ruler. So, Abu 'Ubaida arrived with the money from Bahrain.
When the Ansar heard of the arrival of Abu 'Ubaida (on the next
day) they offered the morning prayer with the Prophet and when the
morning prayer had finished, they presented themselves before him.
On seeing the Ansar, Allah's Apostle smiled and said, "I think you
have heard that Abu 'Ubaida has brought something?" They replied,
"Indeed, it is so, O Allah's Apostle!" He said, "Be happy, and hope
for what will please you. By Allah, I am not afraid that you will
be poor, but I fear that worldly wealth will be bestowed upon you
as it was bestowed upon those who lived before you. So you will
compete amongst yourselves for it, as they competed for it and it
will destroy you as it did them."</english-text>
</hadith>
