<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3872</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4068</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20241, 11070, 11013, 11206, 163, 30312, 20184, 20176,
11206, 880</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عاصم، عن ابن جريج، عن الزهري، عن عطاء بن
يزيد، عن عبيد الله بن عدي، عن المقداد بن الأسود، حدثني إسحاق، حدثنا
يعقوب بن إبراهيم بن سعد، حدثنا ابن أخي ابن شهاب، عن عمه، قال أخبرني
عطاء بن يزيد الليثي، ثم الجندعي أن عبيد، الله بن عدي بن الخيار
أخبره أن المقداد بن عمرو الكندي، وكان حليفا لبني زهرة، وكان ممن شهد
بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبره أنه قال لرسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أرأيت إن لقيت رجلا من الكفار فاقتتلنا، فضرب إحدى يدى
بالسيف فقطعها، ثم لاذ مني بشجرة فقال أسلمت لله‏.‏ آأقتله يا رسول
الله بعد أن قالها فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقتله
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال يا رسول الله، إنه قطع إحدى يدى، ثم قال ذلك بعد ما
قطعها‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقتله، فإن قتلته
فإنه بمنزلتك قبل أن تقتله، وإنك بمنزلته قبل أن يقول كلمته التي قال
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah bin `Adi bin Al-Khiyar: That
Al-Miqdad bin `Amr Al-Kindi, who was an ally of Bani Zuhra and one
of those who fought the battle of Badr together with Allah's
Apostle told him that he said to Allah's Apostle, "Suppose I met
one of the infidels and we fought, and he struck one of my hands
with his sword and cut it off and then took refuge in a tree and
said, "I surrender to Allah (i.e. I have become a Muslim),' could I
kill him, O Allah's Apostle, after he had said this?" Allah's
Apostle said, "You should not kill him." Al- Miqdad said, "O
Allah's Apostle! But he had cut off one of my two hands, and then
he had uttered those words?" Allah's Apostle replied, "You should
not kill him, for if you kill him, he would be in your position
where you had been before killing him, and you would be in his
position where he had been before uttering those
words."</english-text>
</hadith>
