<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3895</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4093</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20340, 20311, 11049, 400</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد الله بن موسى، عن إسرائيل، عن أبي إسحاق، عن
البراء رضى الله عنه قال لقينا المشركين يومئذ، وأجلس النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم جيشا من الرماة، وأمر عليهم عبد الله وقال ‏"‏ لا تبرحوا،
إن رأيتمونا ظهرنا عليهم فلا تبرحوا وإن رأيتموهم ظهروا علينا فلا
تعينونا ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما لقينا هربوا حتى رأيت النساء يشتددن في الجبل،
رفعن عن سوقهن قد بدت خلاخلهن، فأخذوا يقولون الغنيمة الغنيمة‏.‏ فقال
عبد الله عهد إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن لا تبرحوا‏.‏ فأبوا،
فلما أبوا صرف وجوههم، فأصيب سبعون قتيلا، وأشرف أبو سفيان فقال أفي
القوم محمد فقال ‏"‏ لا تجيبوه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أفي القوم ابن أبي قحافة
قال ‏"‏ لا تجيبوه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أفي القوم ابن الخطاب فقال إن هؤلاء
قتلوا، فلو كانوا أحياء لأجابوا، فلم يملك عمر نفسه فقال كذبت يا عدو
الله، أبقى الله عليك ما يخزيك‏.‏ قال أبو سفيان أعل هبل‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أجيبوه ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا ما نقول قال ‏"‏
قولوا الله أعلى وأجل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو سفيان لنا العزى ولا عزى لكم‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أجيبوه ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا ما نقول قال
‏"‏ قولوا الله مولانا ولا مولى لكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو سفيان يوم بيوم
بدر، والحرب سجال، وتجدون مثلة لم آمر بها ولم تسؤني‏.‏ أخبرني عبد
الله بن محمد، حدثنا سفيان، عن عمرو، عن جابر، قال اصطبح الخمر يوم
أحد ناس ثم قتلوا شهداء‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Bara: We faced the pagans on that day (of
the battle of Uhud) and the Prophet placed a batch of archers (at a
special place) and appointed `Abdullah (bin Jubair) as their
commander and said, "Do not leave this place; and if you should see
us conquering the enemy, do not leave this place, and if you should
see them conquering us, do not (come to) help us," So, when we
faced the enemy, they took to their heel till I saw their women
running towards the mountain, lifting up their clothes from their
legs, revealing their leg-bangles. The Muslims started saying, "The
booty, the booty!" `Abdullah bin Jubair said, "The Prophet had
taken a firm promise from me not to leave this place." But his
companions refused (to stay). So when they refused (to stay there),
(Allah) confused them so that they could not know where to go, and
they suffered seventy casualties. Abu Sufyan ascended a high place
and said, "Is Muhammad present amongst the people?" The Prophet
said, "Do not answer him." Abu Sufyan said, "Is the son of Abu
Quhafa present among the people?" The Prophet said, "Do not answer
him." `Abd Sufyan said, "Is the son of Al-Khattab amongst the
people?" He then added, "All these people have been killed, for,
were they alive, they would have replied." On that, `Umar could not
help saying, "You are a liar, O enemy of Allah! Allah has kept what
will make you unhappy." Abu Safyan said, "Superior may be Hubal!"
On that the Prophet said (to his companions), "Reply to him." They
asked, "What may we say?" He said, "Say: Allah is More Elevated and
More Majestic!" Abu Sufyan said, "We have (the idol) Al-`Uzza,
whereas you have no `Uzza!" The Prophet said (to his companions),
"Reply to him." They said, "What may we say?" The Prophet said,
"Say: Allah is our Helper and you have no helper." Abu Sufyan said,
"(This) day compensates for our loss at Badr and (in) the battle
(the victory) is always undecided and shared in turns by the
belligerents. You will see some of your dead men mutilated, but
neither did I urge this action, nor am I sorry for it." Narrated
Jabir: Some people took wine in the morning of the day of Uhud and
were then killed as martyrs.</english-text>
</hadith>
