<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3922</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4121</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20382, 20026, 11187, 11005, 11501</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني أبو جعفر، محمد بن عبد الله حدثنا حجين بن المثنى،
حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله بن أبي سلمة، عن عبد الله بن الفضل، عن
سليمان بن يسار، عن جعفر بن عمرو بن أمية الضمري، قال خرجت مع عبيد
الله بن عدي بن الخيار، فلما قدمنا حمص قال لي عبيد الله هل لك في
وحشي نسأله عن قتل حمزة قلت نعم‏.‏ وكان وحشي يسكن حمص فسألنا عنه
فقيل لنا هو ذاك في ظل قصره، كأنه حميت‏.‏ قال فجئنا حتى وقفنا عليه
بيسير، فسلمنا، فرد السلام، قال وعبيد الله معتجر بعمامته، ما يرى
وحشي إلا عينيه ورجليه، فقال عبيد الله يا وحشي أتعرفني قال فنظر إليه
ثم قال لا والله إلا أني أعلم أن عدي بن الخيار تزوج امرأة يقال لها
أم قتال بنت أبي العيص، فولدت له غلاما بمكة، فكنت أسترضع له، فحملت
ذلك الغلام مع أمه، فناولتها إياه، فلكأني نظرت إلى قدميك‏.‏ قال فكشف
عبيد الله عن وجهه ثم قال ألا تخبرنا بقتل حمزة قال نعم، إن حمزة قتل
طعيمة بن عدي بن الخيار ببدر، فقال لي مولاى جبير بن مطعم إن قتلت
حمزة بعمي فأنت حر، قال فلما أن خرج الناس عام عينين وعينين جبل بحيال
أحد، بينه وبينه واد خرجت مع الناس إلى القتال، فلما اصطفوا للقتال
خرج سباع فقال هل من مبارز قال فخرج إليه حمزة بن عبد المطلب فقال يا
سباع يا ابن أم أنمار مقطعة البظور، أتحاد الله ورسوله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال ثم شد عليه فكان كأمس الذاهب قال وكمنت لحمزة تحت صخرة فلما
دنا مني رميته بحربتي، فأضعها في ثنته حتى خرجت من بين وركيه قال فكان
ذاك العهد به، فلما رجع الناس رجعت معهم فأقمت بمكة، حتى فشا فيها
الإسلام، ثم خرجت إلى الطائف، فأرسلوا إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم رسولا، فقيل لي إنه لا يهيج الرسل قال فخرجت معهم حتى قدمت على
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما رآني قال ‏"‏ آنت وحشي ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت
نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أنت قتلت حمزة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت قد كان من الأمر ما بلغك‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فهل تستطيع أن تغيب وجهك عني ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فخرجت، فلما قبض رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرج مسيلمة الكذاب قلت لأخرجن إلى مسيلمة
لعلي أقتله فأكافئ به حمزة قال فخرجت مع الناس، فكان من أمره ما كان
قال فإذا رجل قائم في ثلمة جدار، كأنه جمل أورق ثائر الرأس قال فرميته
بحربتي، فأضعها بين ثدييه حتى خرجت من بين كتفيه قال ووثب إليه رجل من
الأنصار، فضربه بالسيف على هامته‏.‏ قال قال عبد الله بن الفضل
فأخبرني سليمان بن يسار أنه سمع عبد الله بن عمر يقول فقالت جارية على
ظهر بيت وا أمير المؤمنين، قتله العبد الأسود‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jafar bin `Amr bin Umaiya: I went out with
'Ubaidullah bin `Adi Al-Khaiyar. When we reached Hims (i.e. a town
in Syria), 'Ubaidullah bin `Adi said (to me), "Would you like to
see Wahshi so that we may ask him about the killing of Hamza?" I
replied, "Yes." Wahshi used to live in Hims. We enquired about him
and somebody said to us, "He is that in the shade of his palace, as
if he were a full water skin." So we went up to him, and when we
were at a short distance from him, we greeted him and he greeted us
in return. 'Ubaidullah was wearing his turban and Wahshi could not
see except his eyes and feet. 'Ubaidullah said, "O Wahshi! Do you
know me?" Wahshi looked at him and then said, "No, by Allah! But I
know that `Adi bin Al-Khiyar married a woman called Um Qital, the
daughter of Abu Al-Is, and she delivered a boy for him at Mecca,
and I looked for a wet nurse for that child. (Once) I carried that
child along with his mother and then I handed him over to her, and
your feet resemble that child's feet." Then 'Ubaidullah uncovered
his face and said (to Wahshi), "Will you tell us (the story of) the
killing of Hamza?" Wahshi replied "Yes, Hamza killed Tuaima bin
`Adi bin Al-Khaiyar at Badr (battle) so my master, Jubair bin
Mut`im said to me, 'If you kill Hamza in revenge for my uncle, then
you will be set free." When the people set out (for the battle of
Uhud) in the year of 'Ainain ..'Ainain is a mountain near the
mountain of Uhud, and between it and Uhud there is a valley.. I
went out with the people for the battle. When the army aligned for
the fight, Siba' came out and said, 'Is there any (Muslim) to
accept my challenge to a duel?' Hamza bin `Abdul Muttalib came out
and said, 'O Siba'. O Ibn Um Anmar, the one who circumcises other
ladies! Do you challenge Allah and His Apostle?' Then Hamza
attacked and killed him, causing him to be non-extant like the
bygone yesterday. I hid myself under a rock, and when he (i.e.
Hamza) came near me, I threw my spear at him, driving it into his
umbilicus so that it came out through his buttocks, causing him to
die. When all the people returned to Mecca, I too returned with
them. I stayed in (Mecca) till Islam spread in it (i.e. Mecca).
Then I left for Taif, and when the people (of Taif) sent their
messengers to Allah's Apostle, I was told that the Prophet did not
harm the messengers; So I too went out with them till I reached
Allah's Apostle. When he saw me, he said, 'Are you Wahshi?' I said,
'Yes.' He said, 'Was it you who killed Hamza?' I replied, 'What
happened is what you have been told of.' He said, 'Can you hide
your face from me?' So I went out when Allah's Apostle died, and
Musailamah Al-Kadhdhab appeared (claiming to be a prophet). I said,
'I will go out to Musailamah so that I may kill him, and make
amends for killing Hamza. So I went out with the people (to fight
Musailamah and his followers) and then famous events took place
concerning that battle. Suddenly I saw a man (i.e. Musailamah)
standing near a gap in a wall. He looked like an ash-colored camel
and his hair was dishevelled. So I threw my spear at him, driving
it into his chest in between his breasts till it passed out through
his shoulders, and then an Ansari man attacked him and struck him
on the head with a sword. `Abdullah bin `Umar said, 'A slave girl
on the roof of a house said: Alas! The chief of the believers (i.e.
Musailamah) has been killed by a black slave."</english-text>
</hadith>
