<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3942</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4143</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت استأذن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
أبو بكر في الخروج حين اشتد عليه الأذى، فقال له ‏"‏ أقم ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال
يا رسول الله أتطمع أن يؤذن لك، فكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يقول ‏"‏ إني لأرجو ذلك ‏"‏ قالت فانتظره أبو بكر فأتاه رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ذات يوم ظهرا فناداه فقال ‏"‏ أخرج من عندك ‏"‏‏.‏
فقال أبو بكر إنما هما ابنتاى‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أشعرت أنه قد أذن لي في
الخروج ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال يا رسول الله الصحبة‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ الصحبة ‏"‏‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله عندي ناقتان قد كنت أعددتهما
للخروج‏.‏ فأعطى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إحداهما وهى الجدعاء، فركبا
فانطلقا حتى أتيا الغار، وهو بثور، فتواريا فيه، فكان عامر بن فهيرة
غلاما لعبد الله بن الطفيل بن سخبرة أخو عائشة لأمها، وكانت لأبي بكر
منحة، فكان يروح بها ويغدو عليهم، ويصبح فيدلج إليهما ثم يسرح، فلا
يفطن به أحد من الرعاء، فلما خرج خرج معهما يعقبانه حتى قدما المدينة،
فقتل عامر بن فهيرة يوم بئر معونة‏.‏ وعن أبي أسامة قال قال هشام بن
عروة فأخبرني أبي قال لما قتل الذين ببئر معونة وأسر عمرو بن أمية
الضمري قال له عامر بن الطفيل من هذا فأشار إلى قتيل، فقال له عمرو بن
أمية هذا عامر بن فهيرة‏.‏ فقال لقد رأيته بعد ما قتل رفع إلى السماء
حتى إني لأنظر إلى السماء بينه وبين الأرض، ثم وضع‏.‏ فأتى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم خبرهم فنعاهم فقال ‏"‏ إن أصحابكم قد أصيبوا، وإنهم قد
سألوا ربهم، فقالوا ربنا أخبر عنا إخواننا بما رضينا عنك ورضيت عنا‏.‏
فأخبرهم عنهم ‏"‏‏.‏ وأصيب يومئذ فيهم عروة بن أسماء بن الصلت، فسمي
عروة به، ومنذر بن عمرو سمي به منذرا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Abu Bakr asked the Prophet to allow
him to go out (of Mecca) when he was greatly annoyed (by the
infidels). But the Prophet said to him, ''Wait." Abu Bakr said, O
Allah's Apostle! Do you hope that you will be allowed (to
migrate)?" Allah's Apostle replied, "I hope so." So Abu Bakr waited
for him till one day Allah's Apostle came at noon time and
addressed him saying "Let whoever is present with you, now leave
you." Abu Bakr said, "None is present but my two daughters." The
Prophet said, "Have you noticed that I have been allowed to go out
(to migrate)?" Abu Bakr said, "O Allah's Apostle, I would like to
accompany you." The Prophet said, "You will accompany me." Abu Bakr
said, "O Allah's Apostle! I have got two she-camels which I had
prepared and kept ready for (our) going out." So he gave one of the
two (she-camels) to the Prophet and it was Al-Jad`a . They both
rode and proceeded till they reached the Cave at the mountain of
Thaur where they hid themselves. Amir bin Fuhaira was the slave of
`Abdullah bin at-Tufail bin Sakhbara `Aisha's brother from her
mother's side. Abu Bakr had a milch she-camel. Amir used to go with
it (i.e. the milch she-camel) in the afternoon and come back to
them before noon by setting out towards them in the early morning
when it was still dark and then he would take it to the pasture so
that none of the shepherds would be aware of his job. When the
Prophet (and Abu Bakr) went away (from the Cave), he (i.e. 'Amir)
too went along with them and they both used to make him ride at the
back of their camels in turns till they reached Medina. 'Amir bin
Fuhaira was martyred on the day of Bir Ma'una. Narrated `Urwa: When
those (Muslims) at Bir Ma'una were martyred and `Amr bin Umaiya Ad-
Damri was taken prisoner, 'Amir bin at-Tufail, pointing at a killed
person, asked `Amr, "Who is this?" `Amr bin Umaiya said to him, "He
is 'Amir bin Fuhaira." 'Amir bin at-Tufail said, "I saw him lifted
to the sky after he was killed till I saw the sky between him and
the earth, and then he was brought down upon the earth. Then the
news of the killed Muslims reached the Prophet and he announced the
news of their death saying, "Your companions (of Bir Ma'una) have
been killed, and they have asked their Lord saying, 'O our Lord!
Inform our brothers about us as we are pleased with You and You are
pleased with us." So Allah informed them (i.e. the Prophet and his
companions) about them (i.e. martyrs of Bir Mauna). On that day,
`Urwa bin Asma bin As-Salt who was one of them, was killed, and
`Urwa (bin Az- Zubair) was named after `Urwa bin Asma and Mundhir
(bin AzZubair) was named after Mundhir bin `Amr (who had also been
martyred on that day).</english-text>
</hadith>
