<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3950</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4151</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20191, 11560, 11556</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا خلاد بن يحيى، حدثنا عبد الواحد بن أيمن، عن أبيه،
قال أتيت جابرا رضى الله عنه فقال إنا يوم الخندق نحفر فعرضت كدية
شديدة، فجاءوا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا هذه كدية عرضت في
الخندق، فقال ‏"‏ أنا نازل ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قام وبطنه معصوب بحجر، ولبثنا
ثلاثة أيام لا نذوق ذواقا، فأخذ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم المعول
فضرب، فعاد كثيبا أهيل أو أهيم، فقلت يا رسول الله ائذن لي إلى
البيت‏.‏ فقلت لامرأتي رأيت بالنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم شيئا، ما كان
في ذلك صبر، فعندك شىء قالت عندي شعير وعناق‏.‏ فذبحت العناق وطحنت
الشعير، حتى جعلنا اللحم في البرمة، ثم جئت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
والعجين قد انكسر، والبرمة بين الأثافي قد كادت أن تنضج فقلت طعيم لي،
فقم أنت يا رسول الله ورجل أو رجلان‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ كم هو ‏"‏‏.‏ فذكرت
له، قال ‏"‏ كثير طيب ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ قل لها لا تنزع البرمة ولا الخبز
من التنور حتى آتي ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ قوموا ‏"‏‏.‏ فقام المهاجرون
والأنصار، فلما دخل على امرأته قال ويحك جاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بالمهاجرين والأنصار ومن معهم‏.‏ قالت هل سألك قلت نعم‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
ادخلوا ولا تضاغطوا ‏"‏‏.‏ فجعل يكسر الخبز ويجعل عليه اللحم، ويخمر
البرمة والتنور إذا أخذ منه، ويقرب إلى أصحابه ثم ينزع، فلم يزل يكسر
الخبز ويغرف حتى شبعوا وبقي بقية قال ‏"‏ كلي هذا وأهدي، فإن الناس
أصابتهم مجاعة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir: We were digging (the trench) on the
day of (Al-Khandaq ( i.e. Trench )) and we came across a big solid
rock. We went to the Prophet and said, "Here is a rock appearing
across the trench." He said, "I am coming down." Then he got up,
and a stone was tied to his belly for we had not eaten anything for
three days. So the Prophet took the spade and struck the big solid
rock and it became like sand. I said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow me
to go home." (When the Prophet allowed me) I said to my wife, "I
saw the Prophet in a state that I cannot treat lightly. Have you
got something (for him to eat?" She replied, "I have barley and a
she goat." So I slaughtered the she-kid and she ground the barley;
then we put the meat in the earthenware cooking pot. Then I came to
the Prophet when the dough had become soft and fermented and (the
meat in) the pot over the stone trivet had nearly been well-cooked,
and said, "I have got a little food prepared, so get up O Allah's
Apostle, you and one or two men along with you (for the food)." The
Prophet asked, "How much is that food?" I told him about it. He
said, "It is abundant and good. Tell your wife not to remove the
earthenware pot from the fire and not to take out any bread from
the oven till I reach there." Then he said (to all his companions),
"Get up." So the Muhajirn (i.e. Emigrants) and the Ansar got up.
When I came to my wife, I said, "Allah's Mercy be upon you! The
Prophet came along with the Muhajirin and the Ansar and those who
were present with them." She said, "Did the Prophet ask you (how
much food you had)?" I replied, "Yes." Then the Prophet said,
"Enter and do not throng." The Prophet started cutting the bread
(into pieces) and put the cooked meat over it. He covered the
earthenware pot and the oven whenever he took something out of
them. He would give the food to his companions and take the meat
out of the pot. He went on cutting the bread and scooping the meat
(for his companions) till they all ate their fill, and even then,
some food remained. Then the Prophet said (to my wife), "Eat and
present to others as the people are struck with
hunger."</english-text>
</hadith>
