<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3951</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4152</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30153, 20241, 11243, 11510, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عمرو بن علي، حدثنا أبو عاصم، أخبرنا حنظلة بن أبي
سفيان، أخبرنا سعيد بن ميناء، قال سمعت جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله
عنهما قال لما حفر الخندق رأيت بالنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم خمصا شديدا،
فانكفأت إلى امرأتي فقلت هل عندك شىء فإني رأيت برسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم خمصا شديدا‏.‏ فأخرجت إلى جرابا فيه صاع من شعير، ولنا
بهيمة داجن فذبحتها، وطحنت الشعير ففرغت إلى فراغي، وقطعتها في
برمتها، ثم وليت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالت لا تفضحني
برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وبمن معه‏.‏ فجئته فساررته فقلت يا
رسول الله ذبحنا بهيمة لنا وطحنا صاعا من شعير كان عندنا، فتعال أنت
ونفر معك‏.‏ فصاح النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ يا أهل الخندق،
إن جابرا قد صنع سورا فحى هلا بكم ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تنزلن برمتكم، ولا تخبزن عجينكم حتى أجيء ‏"‏‏.‏
فجئت وجاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقدم الناس حتى جئت امرأتي،
فقالت بك وبك‏.‏ فقلت قد فعلت الذي قلت‏.‏ فأخرجت له عجينا، فبصق فيه
وبارك، ثم عمد إلى برمتنا فبصق وبارك ثم قال ‏"‏ ادع خابزة فلتخبز معي
واقدحي من برمتكم ولا تنزلوها‏"‏، وهم ألف، فأقسم بالله لقد أكلوا حتى
تركوه وانحرفوا، وإن برمتنا لتغط كما هي، وإن عجيننا ليخبز كما
هو‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: When the Trench was
dug, I saw the Prophet in the state of severe hunger. So I returned
to my wife and said, "Have you got anything (to eat), for I have
seen Allah's Apostle in a state of severe hunger." She brought out
for me, a bag containing one Sa of barley, and we had a domestic
she animal (i.e. a kid) which I slaughtered then, and my wife
ground the barley and she finished at the time I finished my job
(i.e. slaughtering the kid). Then I cut the meat into pieces and
put it in an earthenware (cooking) pot, and returned to Allah's
Apostle . My wife said, "Do not disgrace me in front of Allah's
Apostle and those who are with him." So I went to him and said to
him secretly, "O Allah's Apostle! I have slaughtered a she-animal
(i.e. kid) of ours, and we have ground a Sa of barley which was
with us. So please come, you and another person along with you."
The Prophet raised his voice and said, "O people of Trench ! Jabir
has prepared a meal so let us go." Allah's Apostle said to me,
"Don't put down your earthenware meat pot (from the fireplace) or
bake your dough till I come." So I came (to my house) and Allah's
Apostle too, came, proceeding before the people. When I came to my
wife, she said, "May Allah do so-and-so to you." I said, "I have
told the Prophet of what you said." Then she brought out to him
(i.e. the Prophet the dough, and he spat in it and invoked for
Allah's Blessings in it. Then he proceeded towards our earthenware
meat-pot and spat in it and invoked for Allah's Blessings in it.
Then he said (to my wife). Call a lady-baker to bake along with you
and keep on taking out scoops from your earthenware meat-pot, and
do not put it down from its fireplace." They were onethousand (who
took their meals), and by Allah they all ate, and when they left
the food and went away, our earthenware pot was still bubbling
(full of meat) as if it had not decreased, and our dough was still
being baked as if nothing had been taken from it.</english-text>
</hadith>
