<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3971</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4172</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30193, 20331, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا زكرياء بن يحيى، حدثنا عبد الله بن نمير، حدثنا
هشام، عن أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت أصيب سعد يوم الخندق،
رماه رجل من قريش يقال له حبان ابن العرقة، رماه في الأكحل، فضرب
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم خيمة في المسجد ليعوده من قريب، فلما رجع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من الخندق وضع السلاح واغتسل، فأتاه
جبريل عليه السلام وهو ينفض رأسه من الغبار فقال قد وضعت السلاح والله
ما وضعته، اخرج إليهم‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فأين
‏"‏‏.‏ فأشار إلى بني قريظة، فأتاهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فنزلوا على حكمه، فرد الحكم إلى سعد، قال فإني أحكم فيهم أن تقتل
المقاتلة، وأن تسبى النساء والذرية، وأن تقسم أموالهم‏.‏ قال هشام
فأخبرني أبي عن عائشة أن سعدا قال اللهم إنك تعلم أنه ليس أحد أحب إلى
أن أجاهدهم فيك من قوم كذبوا رسولك صلى الله عليه وسلم وأخرجوه، اللهم
فإني أظن أنك قد وضعت الحرب بيننا وبينهم، فإن كان بقي من حرب قريش
شىء، فأبقني له حتى أجاهدهم فيك، وإن كنت وضعت الحرب فافجرها، واجعل
موتتي فيها‏.‏ فانفجرت من لبته، فلم يرعهم وفي المسجد خيمة من بني
غفار إلا الدم يسيل إليهم فقالوا يا أهل الخيمة ما هذا الذي يأتينا من
قبلكم فإذا سعد يغذو جرحه دما، فمات منها رضى الله
عنه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Sa`d was wounded on the day of
Khandaq (i.e. Trench) when a man from Quraish, called Hibban bin
Al-`Araqa hit him (with an arrow). The man was Hibban bin Qais from
(the tribe of) Bani Mais bin 'Amir bin Lu'ai who shot an arrow at
Sa`d's medial arm vein (or main artery of the arm). The Prophet
pitched a tent (for Sa`d) in the Mosque so that he might be near to
the Prophet to visit. When the Prophet returned from the (battle)
of Al-Khandaq (i.e. Trench) and laid down his arms and took a bath
Gabriel came to him while he (i.e. Gabriel) was shaking the dust
off his head, and said, "You have laid down the arms?" By Allah, I
have not laid them down. Go out to them (to attack them)." The
Prophet said, "Where?" Gabriel pointed towards Bani Quraiza. So
Allah's Apostle went to them (i.e. Banu Quraiza) (i.e. besieged
them). They then surrendered to the Prophet's judgment but he
directed them to Sa`d to give his verdict concerning them. Sa`d
said, "I give my judgment that their warriors should be killed,
their women and children should be taken as captives, and their
properties distributed." Narrated Hisham: My father informed me
that `Aisha said, "Sa`d said, "O Allah! You know that there is
nothing more beloved to me than to fight in Your Cause against
those who disbelieved Your Apostle and turned him out (of Mecca). O
Allah! I think you have put to an end the fight between us and them
(i.e. Quraish infidels). And if there still remains any fight with
the Quraish (infidels), then keep me alive till I fight against
them for Your Sake. But if you have brought the war to an end, then
let this wound burst and cause my death thereby.' So blood gushed
from the wound. There was a tent in the Mosque belonging to Banu
Ghifar who were surprised by the blood flowing towards them . They
said, 'O people of the tent! What is this thing which is coming to
us from your side?' Behold! Blood was flowing profusely out of
Sa`d's wound. Sa`d then died because of that."</english-text>
</hadith>
