<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>3986</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4187</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20436, 20160, 11013, 11511, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني أخي، عن سليمان، عن محمد بن
أبي عتيق، عن ابن شهاب، عن سنان بن أبي سنان الدؤلي، عن جابر بن عبد
الله رضى الله عنهما أخبره أنه، غزا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قبل نجد، فلما قفل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قفل معه، فأدركتهم
القائلة في واد كثير العضاه، فنزل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم،
وتفرق الناس في العضاه يستظلون بالشجر، ونزل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم تحت سمرة، فعلق بها سيفه، قال جابر فنمنا نومة، ثم إذا رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يدعونا، فجئناه فإذا عنده أعرابي جالس فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن هذا اخترط سيفي، وأنا نائم فاستيقظت،
وهو في يده صلتا، فقال لي من يمنعك مني قلت الله‏.‏ فها هو ذا جالس
‏"‏‏.‏ ثم لم يعاقبه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: That he fought in a
Ghazwa towards Najd along with Allah's Apostle and when Allah's
Apostle returned, he too, returned along with him. The time of the
afternoon nap overtook them when they were in a valley full of
thorny trees. Allah's Apostle dismounted and the people dispersed
amongst the thorny trees, seeking the shade of the trees. Allah's
Apostle took shelter under a Samura tree and hung his sword on it.
We slept for a while when Allah's Apostle suddenly called us, and
we went to him, to find a bedouin sitting with him. Allah's Apostle
said, "This (bedouin) took my sword out of its sheath while I was
asleep. When I woke up, the naked sword was in his hand and he said
to me, 'Who can save you from me?, I replied, 'Allah.' Now here he
is sitting." Allah's Apostle did not punish him (for that). Through
another group of narrators, Jabir said, "We were in the company of
the Prophet (during the battle of) Dhat-ur-Riqa', and we came
across a shady tree and we left it for the Prophet (to take rest
under its shade). A man from the pagans came while the Prophet's
sword was hanging on the tree. He took it out of its sheath
secretly and said (to the Prophet ), 'Are you afraid of me?' The
Prophet said, 'No.' He said, 'Who can save you from me?' The
Prophet said, Allah.' The companions of the Prophet threatened him,
then the Iqama for the prayer was announced and the Prophet offered
a two rak`at Fear prayer with one of the two batches, and that
batch went aside and he offered two rak`a-t with the other batch.
So the Prophet offered four rak`at but the people offered two
rak`at only." (The subnarrator) Abu Bishr added, "The man was
Ghaurath bin Al-Harith and the battle was waged against Muharib
Khasafa." Jabir added, "We were with the Prophet at Nakhl and he
offered the Fear prayer." Abu Huraira said, "I offered the Fear
prayer with the Prophet during the Ghazwa (i.e. the battle) of
Najd." Abu Huraira came to the Prophet during the day of
Khaibar.</english-text>
</hadith>
