<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4028</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4229</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20005, 10511, 2201, 858</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا سفيان، قال سمعت الزهري،
حين حدث هذا الحديث،، حفظت بعضه، وثبتني معمر عن عروة بن الزبير، عن
المسور بن مخرمة، ومروان بن الحكم، يزيد أحدهما على صاحبه قالا خرج
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عام الحديبية في بضع عشرة مائة من أصحابه،
فلما أتى ذا الحليفة قلد الهدى، وأشعره، وأحرم منها بعمرة، وبعث عينا
له من خزاعة، وسار النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى كان بغدير الأشطاط،
أتاه عينه قال إن قريشا جمعوا لك جموعا، وقد جمعوا لك الأحابيش، وهم
مقاتلوك وصادوك عن البيت ومانعوك‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أشيروا أيها الناس على،
أترون أن أميل إلى عيالهم وذراري هؤلاء الذين يريدون أن يصدونا عن
البيت، فإن يأتونا كان الله عز وجل قد قطع عينا من المشركين، وإلا
تركناهم محروبين ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو بكر يا رسول الله، خرجت عامدا لهذا
البيت، لا تريد قتل أحد ولا حرب أحد، فتوجه له، فمن صدنا عنه
قاتلناه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ امضوا على اسم الله ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Miswar bin Makhrama and Marwan bin
Al-Hakam: (one of them said more than his friend): The Prophet set
out in the company of more than onethousand of his companions in
the year of Al-Hudaibiya, and when he reached Dhul-Hulaifa, he
garlanded his Hadi (i.e. sacrificing animal), assumed the state of
Ihram for `Umra from that place and sent a spy of his from Khuzi'a
(tribe). The Prophet proceeded on till he reached (a village
called) Ghadir-al-Ashtat. There his spy came and said, "The Quraish
(infidels) have collected a great number of people against you, and
they have collected against you the Ethiopians, and they will fight
with you, and will stop you from entering the Ka`ba and prevent
you." The Prophet said, "O people! Give me your opinion. Do you
recommend that I should destroy the families and offspring of those
who want to stop us from the Ka`ba? If they should come to us (for
peace) then Allah will destroy a spy from the pagans, or otherwise
we will leave them in a miserable state." On that Abu Bakr said, "O
Allah Apostle! You have come with the intention of visiting this
House (i.e. Ka`ba) and you do not want to kill or fight anybody. So
proceed to it, and whoever should stop us from it, we will fight
him." On that the Prophet said, "Proceed on, in the Name of Allah
!"</english-text>
</hadith>
