<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4033</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4234</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30144, 20216, 11014, 11004, 20040, 20216,
11014</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد بن أسماء، حدثنا جويرية، عن
نافع، أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله، وسالم بن عبد الله، أخبراه أنهما،
كلما عبد الله بن عمر‏.‏ وحدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا جويرية، عن
نافع، أن بعض بني عبد الله، قال له لو أقمت العام، فإني أخاف أن لا
تصل إلى البيت‏.‏ قال خرجنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فحال كفار
قريش دون البيت، فنحر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم هداياه، وحلق وقصر
أصحابه، وقال ‏"‏ أشهدكم أني أوجبت عمرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فإن خلي بيني وبين
البيت طفت، وإن حيل بيني وبين البيت صنعت كما صنع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فسار ساعة ثم قال ما أرى شأنهما إلا واحدا، أشهدكم أني قد
أوجبت حجة مع عمرتي‏.‏ فطاف طوافا واحدا وسعيا واحدا، حتى حل منهما
جميعا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Nafi`: One of `Abdullah's sons said to
`Abdullah (bin `Umar) "I wish you would stay this year (and not
perform Hajj) as I am afraid that you will not be able to reach the
Ka`ba." On that he (i.e. `Abdullah bin `Umar) said, "We went out
with the Prophet (for `Umra), and when the Quraish infidel
intervened between us and the Ka`ba, the Prophet slaughtered his
Hadi and shaved (his head), and his companions cut short their
hair." Then `Abdullah bin `Umar said, "I make you witness that I
have intended to perform `Umra and if I am allowed to reach the
Ka`ba, I will perform the Tawaf, and if something (i.e. obstacles)
intervene between me and the Ka`ba, then I will do what Allah's
Apostle did." Then after going for a while, he said, "I consider
the ceremonies (of both `Umra and Hajj as one and the same, so I
would like you to witness that I have intended to perform Hajj
along with my `Umra." So he performed only one Tawaf and one Sai
(between Safa and Marwa) and finished the Ihram of both Umra and
Hajj).</english-text>
</hadith>
