<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4042</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4243</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20159, 11450, 237</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا حاتم، عن يزيد بن أبي عبيد،
قال سمعت سلمة بن الأكوع، يقول خرجت قبل أن يؤذن، بالأولى، وكانت لقاح
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ترعى بذي قرد قال فلقيني غلام لعبد
الرحمن بن عوف فقال أخذت لقاح رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قلت من
أخذها قال غطفان‏.‏ قال فصرخت ثلاث صرخات يا صباحاه قال فأسمعت ما بين
لابتى المدينة، ثم اندفعت على وجهي حتى أدركتهم وقد أخذوا يستقون من
الماء، فجعلت أرميهم بنبلي، وكنت راميا، وأقول أنا ابن الأكوع، اليوم
يوم الرضع‏.‏ وأرتجز حتى استنقذت اللقاح منهم، واستلبت منهم ثلاثين
بردة، قال وجاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس فقلت يا نبي الله قد
حميت القوم الماء وهم عطاش، فابعث إليهم الساعة‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ يا ابن
الأكوع، ملكت فأسجح ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ثم رجعنا ويردفني رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم على ناقته حتى دخلنا المدينة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Salama bin Al-Akwa`: Once I went (from
Medina) towards (Al-Ghaba) before the first Adhan of the Fajr
Prayer. The shecamels of Allah's Apostle used to graze at a place
called Dhi-Qarad. A slave of `Abdur-Rahman bin `Auf met me (on the
way) and said, "The she-camels of Allah's Apostle had been taken
away by force." I asked, "Who had taken them?" He replied "(The
people of) Ghatafan." I made three loud cries (to the people of
Medina) saying, "O Sabahah!" I made the people between the two
mountains of Medina hear me. Then I rushed onward and caught up
with the robbers while they were watering the camels. I started
throwing arrows at them as I was a good archer and I was saying, "I
am the son of Al-Akwa`, and today will perish the wicked people." I
kept on saying like that till I restored the shecamels (of the
Prophet), I also snatched thirty Burda (i.e. garments) from them.
Then the Prophet and the other people came there, and I said, "O
Allah's Prophet! I have stopped the people (of Ghatafan) from
taking water and they are thirsty now. So send (some people) after
them now." On that the Prophet said, "O the son of Al-Akwa`! You
have over-powered them, so forgive them." Then we all came back and
Allah's Apostle seated me behind him on his she-camel till we
entered Medina.</english-text>
</hadith>
