<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4058</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4259</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20185, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا يعقوب بن عبد الرحمن، عن أبي
حازم، قال أخبرني سهل بن سعد رضى الله عنه أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال يوم خيبر ‏"‏ لأعطين هذه الراية غدا رجلا، يفتح الله على
يديه، يحب الله ورسوله، ويحبه الله ورسوله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فبات الناس
يدوكون ليلتهم أيهم يعطاها فلما أصبح الناس غدوا على رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم، كلهم يرجو أن يعطاها فقال ‏"‏ أين علي بن أبي طالب
‏"‏‏.‏ فقيل هو يا رسول الله يشتكي عينيه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأرسلوا إليه
‏"‏‏.‏ فأتي به فبصق رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في عينيه، ودعا له،
فبرأ حتى كأن لم يكن به وجع، فأعطاه الراية، فقال علي يا رسول الله
أقاتلهم حتى يكونوا مثلنا، فقال ‏"‏ انفذ على رسلك حتى تنزل بساحتهم،
ثم ادعهم إلى الإسلام، وأخبرهم بما يجب عليهم من حق الله فيه، فوالله
لأن يهدي الله بك رجلا واحدا خير لك من أن يكون لك حمر النعم
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: On the day of Khaibar,
Allah's Apostle said, "Tomorrow I will give this flag to a man
through whose hands Allah will give us victory. He loves Allah and
His Apostle, and he is loved by Allah and His Apostle." The people
remained that night, wondering as to who would be given it. In the
morning the people went to Allah's Apostle and everyone of them was
hopeful to receive it (i.e. the flag). The Prophet said, "Where is
`Ali bin Abi Talib?" It was said, "He is suffering from eye trouble
O Allah's Apostle." He said, "Send for him." `Ali was brought and
Allah's Apostle spat in his eye and invoked good upon him. So `Ali
was cured as if he never had any trouble. Then the Prophet gave him
the flag. `Ali said "O Allah's Apostle! I will fight with them till
they become like us." Allah's Apostle said, "Proceed and do not
hurry. When you enter their territory, call them to embrace Islam
and inform them of Allah's Rights which they should observe, for by
Allah, even if a single man is led on the right path (of Islam) by
Allah through you, then that will be better for you than the nice
red camels.</english-text>
</hadith>
