<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4076</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4277</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20318, 11325, 11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن العلاء، حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا بريد بن
عبد الله، عن أبي بردة، عن أبي موسى رضى الله عنه قال بلغنا مخرج
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ونحن باليمن، فخرجنا مهاجرين إليه أنا،
وأخوان لي أنا أصغرهم، أحدهما أبو بردة، والآخر أبو رهم إما قال بضع
وإما قال في ثلاثة وخمسين أو اثنين وخمسين رجلا من قومي، فركبنا
سفينة، فألقتنا سفينتنا إلى النجاشي بالحبشة، فوافقنا جعفر بن أبي
طالب فأقمنا معه حتى قدمنا جميعا، فوافقنا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
حين افتتح خيبر، وكان أناس من الناس يقولون لنا يعني لأهل السفينة
سبقناكم بالهجرة، ودخلت أسماء بنت عميس، وهى ممن قدم معنا، على حفصة
زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زائرة، وقد كانت هاجرت إلى النجاشي فيمن
هاجر، فدخل عمر على حفصة وأسماء عندها، فقال عمر حين رأى أسماء من هذه
قالت أسماء بنت عميس‏.‏ قال عمر الحبشية هذه البحرية هذه قالت أسماء
نعم‏.‏ قال سبقناكم بالهجرة، فنحن أحق برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
منكم‏.‏ فغضبت وقالت كلا والله، كنتم مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يطعم جائعكم، ويعظ جاهلكم، وكنا في دار أو في أرض البعداء البغضاء
بالحبشة، وذلك في الله وفي رسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم وايم الله، لا
أطعم طعاما، ولا أشرب شرابا حتى أذكر ما قلت لرسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ونحن كنا نؤذى ونخاف، وسأذكر ذلك للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وأسأله، والله لا أكذب ولا أزيغ ولا أزيد عليه‏.‏ فلما جاء النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قالت يا نبي الله إن عمر قال كذا وكذا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فما
قلت له ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت قلت له كذا وكذا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ليس بأحق بي منكم، وله
ولأصحابه هجرة واحدة، ولكم أنتم أهل السفينة هجرتان ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فلقد
رأيت أبا موسى وأصحاب السفينة يأتوني أرسالا، يسألوني عن هذا الحديث،
ما من الدنيا شىء هم به أفرح ولا أعظم في أنفسهم مما قال لهم النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم.</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa: The news of the migration of the
Prophet (from Mecca to Medina) reached us while we were in Yemen.
So we set out as emigrants towards him. We were (three) I and my
two brothers. I was the youngest of them, and one of the two was
Abu Burda, and the other, Abu Ruhm, and our total number was either
53 or 52 men from my people. We got on board a boat and our boat
took us to Negus in Ethiopia. There we met Ja`far bin Abi Talib and
stayed with him. Then we all came (to Medina) and met the Prophet
at the time of the conquest of Khaibar. Some of the people used to
say to us, namely the people of the ship, "We have migrated before
you." Asma' bint 'Umais who was one of those who had come with us,
came as a visitor to Hafsa, the wife the Prophet . She had migrated
along with those other Muslims who migrated to Negus. `Umar came to
Hafsa while Asma' bint 'Umais was with her. `Umar, on seeing Asma,'
said, "Who is this?" She said, "Asma' bint 'Umais," `Umar said, "Is
she the Ethiopian? Is she the sea-faring lady?" Asma' replied,
"Yes." `Umar said, "We have migrated before you (people of the
boat), so we have got more right than you over Allah's Apostle " On
that Asma' became angry and said, "No, by Allah, while you were
with Allah's Apostle who was feeding the hungry ones amongst you,
and advised the ignorant ones amongst you, we were in the far-off
hated land of Ethiopia, and all that was for the sake of Allah's
Apostle . By Allah, I will neither eat any food nor drink anything
till I inform Allah's Apostle of all that you have said. There we
were harmed and frightened. I will mention this to the Prophet and
will not tell a lie or curtail your saying or add something to it."
So when the Prophet came, she said, "O Allah's Prophet `Umar has
said so-and-so." He said (to Asma'), "What did you say to him?"
Asma's aid, "I told him so-and-so." The Prophet said, "He (i.e.
`Umar) has not got more right than you people over me, as he and
his companions have (the reward of) only one migration, and you,
the people of the boat, have (the reward of) two migrations." Asma'
later on said, "I saw Abu Musa and the other people of the boat
coming to me in successive groups, asking me about this narration,,
and to them nothing in the world was more cheerful and greater than
what the Prophet had said about them." Narrated Abu Burda: Asma'
said, "I saw Abu Musa requesting me to repeat this narration again
and again." Narrated Abu Burda: Abu Musa said, "The Prophet said,
"I recognize the voice of the group of Al- Ashariyun, when they
recite the Qur'an, when they enter their homes at night, and I
recognize their houses by (listening) to their voices when they are
reciting the Qur'an at night although I have not seen their houses
when they came to them during the day time. Amongst them is Hakim
who, on meeting the cavalry or the enemy, used to say to them (i.e.
the enemy). My companions order you to wait for them.'
"</english-text>
</hadith>
