<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4080</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4281</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20389, 11049, 20001, 11155, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا معاوية بن عمرو، حدثنا
أبو إسحاق، عن مالك بن أنس، قال حدثني ثور، قال حدثني سالم، مولى ابن
مطيع أنه سمع أبا هريرة رضى الله عنه يقول افتتحنا خيبر، ولم نغنم
ذهبا ولا فضة، إنما غنمنا البقر والإبل والمتاع والحوائط، ثم انصرفنا
مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى وادي القرى، ومعه عبد له يقال له
مدعم، أهداه له أحد بني الضباب، فبينما هو يحط رحل رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم إذ جاءه سهم عائر حتى أصاب ذلك العبد، فقال الناس هنيئا له
الشهادة‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بلى والذي نفسي
بيده، إن الشملة التي أصابها يوم خيبر من المغانم لم تصبها المقاسم
لتشتعل عليه نارا ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاء رجل حين سمع ذلك من النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم بشراك أو بشراكين، فقال هذا شىء كنت أصبته‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ شراك أو شراكان من نار ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: When we conquered Khaibar, we
gained neither gold nor silver as booty, but we gained cows,
camels, goods and gardens. Then we departed with Allah's Apostle to
the valley of Al-Qira, and at that time Allah's Apostle had a slave
called Mid`am who had been presented to him by one of Banu
Ad-Dibbab. While the slave was dismounting the saddle of Allah's
Apostle an arrow the thrower of which was unknown, came and hit
him. The people said, "Congratulations to him for the martyrdom."
Allah's Apostle said, "No, by Him in Whose Hand my soul is, the
sheet (of cloth) which he had taken (illegally) on the day of
Khaibar from the booty before the distribution of the booty, has
become a flame of Fire burning him." On hearing that, a man brought
one or two leather straps of shoes to the Prophet and said, "These
are things I took (illegally)." On that Allah's Apostle said, "This
is a strap, or these are two straps of Fire."</english-text>
</hadith>
