<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4122</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4325</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، قال لما سار رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عام الفتح فبلغ ذلك
قريشا، خرج أبو سفيان بن حرب وحكيم بن حزام وبديل بن ورقاء يلتمسون
الخبر عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأقبلوا يسيرون حتى أتوا مر
الظهران، فإذا هم بنيران كأنها نيران عرفة، فقال أبو سفيان ما هذه
لكأنها نيران عرفة‏.‏ فقال بديل بن ورقاء نيران بني عمرو‏.‏ فقال أبو
سفيان عمرو أقل من ذلك‏.‏ فرآهم ناس من حرس رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فأدركوهم فأخذوهم، فأتوا بهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأسلم
أبو سفيان، فلما سار قال للعباس ‏"‏ احبس أبا سفيان عند حطم الخيل حتى
ينظر إلى المسلمين ‏"‏‏.‏ فحبسه العباس، فجعلت القبائل تمر مع النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم تمر كتيبة كتيبة على أبي سفيان، فمرت كتيبة قال يا
عباس من هذه قال هذه غفار‏.‏ قال ما لي ولغفار ثم مرت جهينة، قال مثل
ذلك، ثم مرت سعد بن هذيم، فقال مثل ذلك، ومرت سليم، فقال مثل ذلك، حتى
أقبلت كتيبة لم ير مثلها، قال من هذه قال هؤلاء الأنصار عليهم سعد بن
عبادة معه الراية‏.‏ فقال سعد بن عبادة يا أبا سفيان اليوم يوم
الملحمة، اليوم تستحل الكعبة‏.‏ فقال أبو سفيان يا عباس حبذا يوم
الذمار‏.‏ ثم جاءت كتيبة، وهى أقل الكتائب، فيهم رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأصحابه، وراية النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم مع الزبير بن
العوام، فلما مر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بأبي سفيان قال ألم
تعلم ما قال سعد بن عبادة قال ‏"‏ ما قال ‏"‏‏.‏ قال كذا وكذا‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ كذب سعد، ولكن هذا يوم يعظم الله فيه الكعبة، ويوم تكسى فيه
الكعبة ‏"‏‏.‏ قال وأمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن تركز رايته
بالحجون‏.‏ قال عروة وأخبرني نافع بن جبير بن مطعم قال سمعت العباس
يقول للزبير بن العوام يا أبا عبد الله، ها هنا أمرك رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم أن تركز الراية، قال وأمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يومئذ خالد بن الوليد أن يدخل من أعلى مكة من كداء، ودخل النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم من كدا، فقتل من خيل خالد يومئذ رجلان حبيش بن
الأشعر وكرز بن جابر الفهري‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Hisham's father: When Allah's Apostle set
out (towards Mecca) during the year of the Conquest (of Mecca) and
this news reached (the infidels of Quraish), Abu Sufyan, Hakim bin
Hizam and Budail bin Warqa came out to gather information about
Allah's Apostle , They proceeded on their way till they reached a
place called Marr-az-Zahran (which is near Mecca). Behold! There
they saw many fires as if they were the fires of `Arafat. Abu
Sufyan said, "What is this? It looked like the fires of `Arafat."
Budail bin Warqa' said, "Banu `Amr are less in number than that."
Some of the guards of Allah's Apostle saw them and took them over,
caught them and brought them to Allah's Apostle. Abu Sufyan
embraced Islam. When the Prophet proceeded, he said to Al-Abbas,
"Keep Abu Sufyan standing at the top of the mountain so that he
would look at the Muslims. So Al-`Abbas kept him standing (at that
place) and the tribes with the Prophet started passing in front of
Abu Sufyan in military batches. A batch passed and Abu Sufyan said,
"O `Abbas Who are these?" `Abbas said, "They are (Banu) Ghifar."
Abu Sufyan said, I have got nothing to do with Ghifar." Then (a
batch of the tribe of) Juhaina passed by and he said similarly as
above. Then (a batch of the tribe of) Sa`d bin Huzaim passed by and
he said similarly as above. then (Banu) Sulaim passed by and he
said similarly as above. Then came a batch, the like of which Abu
Sufyan had not seen. He said, "Who are these?" `Abbas said, "They
are the Ansar headed by Sa`d bin Ubada, the one holding the flag."
Sa`d bin Ubada said, "O Abu Sufyan! Today is the day of a great
battle and today (what is prohibited in) the Ka`ba will be
permissible." Abu Sufyan said., "O `Abbas! How excellent the day of
destruction is! "Then came another batch (of warriors) which was
the smallest of all the batches, and in it there was Allah's
Apostle and his companions and the flag of the Prophet was carried
by Az-Zubair bin Al Awwam. When Allah's Apostle passed by Abu
Sufyan, the latter said, (to the Prophet), "Do you know what Sa`d
bin 'Ubada said?" The Prophet said, "What did he say?" Abu Sufyan
said, "He said so-and-so." The Prophet said, "Sa`d told a lie, but
today Allah will give superiority to the Ka`ba and today the Ka`ba
will be covered with a (cloth) covering." Allah's Apostle ordered
that his flag be fixed at Al-Hajun. Narrated `Urwa: Nafi` bin
Jubair bin Mut`im said, "I heard Al-Abbas saying to Az-Zubair bin
Al- `Awwam, 'O Abu `Abdullah ! Did Allah's Apostle order you to fix
the flag here?' " Allah's Apostle ordered Khalid bin Al-Walid to
enter Mecca from its upper part from Ka'da while the Prophet
himself entered from Kuda. Two men from the cavalry of Khalid bin
Al-Wahd named Hubaish bin Al-Ash'ar and Kurz bin Jabir Al-Fihri
were martyred on that day.</english-text>
</hadith>
