<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4135</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4339</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20283, 20469, 11419, 11050, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو النعمان، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن أبي بشر، عن
سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال كان عمر يدخلني مع
أشياخ بدر، فقال بعضهم لم تدخل هذا الفتى معنا، ولنا أبناء مثله فقال
إنه ممن قد علمتم‏.‏ قال فدعاهم ذات يوم، ودعاني معهم قال وما رئيته
دعاني يومئذ إلا ليريهم مني فقال ما تقولون ‏{‏إذا جاء نصر الله
والفتح * ورأيت الناس يدخلون‏}‏ حتى ختم السورة، فقال بعضهم أمرنا أن
نحمد الله ونستغفره، إذا نصرنا وفتح علينا‏.‏ وقال بعضهم لا ندري‏.‏
أو لم يقل بعضهم شيئا‏.‏ فقال لي يا ابن عباس أكذاك تقول قلت لا‏.‏
قال فما تقول قلت هو أجل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أعلمه الله له
‏{‏إذا جاء نصر الله والفتح‏}‏ فتح مكة، فذاك علامة أجلك ‏{‏فسبح بحمد
ربك واستغفره إنه كان توابا‏}‏ قال عمر ما أعلم منها إلا ما
تعلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: `Umar used to admit me (into his
house) along with the old men who had fought in the Badr battle.
Some of them said (to `Umar), "Why do you allow this young man to
enter with us, while we have sons of his own age? " `Umar said,
"You know what person he is." One day `Umar called them and called
me along with them, I had thought he called me on that day to show
them something about me (i.e. my knowledge). `Umar asked them,
"What do you say about (the Sura): "When comes the help of Allah
and the Conquest (of Mecca) And you see mankind entering the
Religion of Allah (i.e. Islam) in crowds. 'So celebrate the Praises
Of your Lord and ask for His forgiveness, Truly, He is the One Who
accepts repentance and forgives." (110.1-3) Some of them replied,
"We are ordered to praise Allah and repent to Him if we are helped
and granted victory." Some said, "We do not know." Others kept
quiet. `Umar then said to me, "Do you say similarly?" I said, "No."
`Umar said "What do you say then?" I said, "This Verse indicates
the approaching of the death of Allah's Apostle of which Allah
informed him. When comes the help of Allah and the Conquest, i.e.
the Conquest of Mecca, that will be the sign of your Prophet's)
approaching death, so testify the uniqueness of your Lord (i.e.
Allah) and praise Him and repent to Him as He is ready to forgive."
On that, `Umar said, "I do not know about it anything other than
what you know."</english-text>
</hadith>
