<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4136</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4340</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30194, 20023, 11168, 5355</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن شرحبيل، حدثنا الليث، عن المقبري، عن أبي
شريح العدوي، أنه قال لعمرو بن سعيد وهو يبعث البعوث إلى مكة ائذن لي
أيها الأمير أحدثك قولا قام به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم الغد يوم
الفتح، سمعته أذناى ووعاه قلبي، وأبصرته عيناى، حين تكلم به حمد الله
وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ إن مكة حرمها الله ولم يحرمها الناس، لا يحل
لامرئ يؤمن بالله واليوم الآخر أن يسفك بها دما، ولا يعضد بها شجرا،
فإن أحد ترخص لقتال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيها فقولوا له إن
الله أذن لرسوله، ولم يأذن لكم‏.‏ وإنما أذن لي فيها ساعة من نهار،
وقد عادت حرمتها اليوم كحرمتها بالأمس، وليبلغ الشاهد الغائب ‏"‏‏.‏
فقيل لأبي شريح ماذا قال لك عمرو قال قال أنا أعلم بذلك منك يا أبا
شريح، إن الحرم لا يعيذ عاصيا، ولا فارا بدم، ولا فارا
بخربة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Shuraih: Al-Adawi that he said to `Amr
bin Sa`id while the latter was sending troops in batches to Mecca,
"O chief! Allow me to tell you a statement which Allah's Apostle
said on the second day of the Conquest of Mecca. My two ears heard
it and my heart remembered it and my two eyes saw him when he said
it. He (i.e. the Prophet) praised Allah and then said, 'Mecca has
been made a sanctuary by Allah and not by the people, so it is not
lawful for a person, who believes in Allah and the Last Day to shed
blood in it, or to cut its trees and if someone asks the permission
to fight in Mecca because Allah's Apostle was allowed to fight in
it, say to him; Allah permitted His Apostle and did not allow you,
and even he (i.e. the Apostle) was allowed for a short period of
the day, and today its (Mecca's sanctity has become the same as it
was before (of old) so those who are present should inform those
who are absent (this Hadith)." Then Abu Shuraih, was asked, "What
did `Amr say to you? Abu Shuraih said, "He said, "I knew that
better than you, O Abu Shuraih! The Haram (i.e. Mecca) does not
give refuge to a sinner or a fleeing murderer or a person running
away after causing destruction."</english-text>
</hadith>
