<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4170</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4373</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20184, 20208, 11070, 11029, 11248, 20372</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم، حدثنا إسماعيل، حدثنا ابن جريج،
قال أخبرني عطاء، أن صفوان بن يعلى بن أمية، أخبر أن يعلى كان يقول
ليتني أرى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حين ينزل عليه‏.‏ قال فبينا
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالجعرانة وعليه ثوب قد أظل به، معه فيه ناس
من أصحابه، إذ جاءه أعرابي عليه جبة متضمخ بطيب فقال يا رسول الله كيف
ترى في رجل أحرم بعمرة في جبة بعد ما تضمخ بالطيب فأشار عمر إلى يعلى
بيده أن تعال‏.‏ فجاء يعلى فأدخل رأسه، فإذا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
محمر الوجه، يغط كذلك ساعة، ثم سري عنه فقال ‏"‏ أين الذي يسألني عن
العمرة آنفا ‏"‏‏.‏ فالتمس الرجل فأتي به فقال ‏"‏ أما الطيب الذي بك
فاغسله ثلاث مرات، وأما الجبة فانزعها، ثم اصنع في عمرتك كما تصنع في
حجك ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Safwan bin Ya`la bin Umaiya: Ya`la used to
say, "I wish I could see Allah's Apostle at the time when he is
being inspired divinely." Ya`la added "While the Prophet was at
Al-Ja'rana, shaded with a cloth sheet (in the form of a tent) and
there were staying with him, some of his companions under it,
suddenly there came to him a bedouin wearing a cloak and perfumed
extravagantly. He said, "O Allah's Apostle ! What is your opinion
regarding a man who assumes the state of Ihram for `Umra wearing a
cloak after applying perfume to his body?" `Umar signalled with his
hand to Ya`la to come (near). Ya`la came and put his head
(underneath that cloth sheet) and saw the Prophet red-faced and
when that state (of the Prophet ) was over, he said, "Where is he
who as already asked me about the `Umra?" The man was looked for
and brought to the Prophet The Prophet said (to him), "As for the
perfume you have applied to your body, wash it off your body)
thrice, and take off your cloak, and then do in your `Umra the
rites you do in your Hajj."</english-text>
</hadith>
