<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4172</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4375</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 20295, 20115, 11013, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا هشام، أخبرنا معمر، عن
الزهري، قال أخبرني أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه قال قال ناس من الأنصار
حين أفاء الله على رسوله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما أفاء من أموال هوازن،
فطفق النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطي رجالا المائة من الإبل فقالوا
يغفر الله لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطي قريشا ويتركنا، وسيوفنا
تقطر من دمائهم‏.‏ قال أنس فحدث رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
بمقالتهم، فأرسل إلى الأنصار فجمعهم في قبة من أدم ولم يدع معهم
غيرهم، فلما اجتمعوا قام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ما حديث
بلغني عنكم ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال فقهاء الأنصار أما رؤساؤنا يا رسول الله فلم
يقولوا شيئا، وأما ناس منا حديثة أسنانهم فقالوا يغفر الله لرسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يعطي قريشا ويتركنا، وسيوفنا تقطر من دمائهم‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فإني أعطي رجالا حديثي عهد بكفر،
أتألفهم، أما ترضون أن يذهب الناس بالأموال وتذهبون بالنبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم إلى رحالكم، فوالله لما تنقلبون به خير مما ينقلبون به
‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله قد رضينا‏.‏ فقال لهم النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ ستجدون أثرة شديدة، فاصبروا حتى تلقوا الله ورسوله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فإني على الحوض ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أنس فلم يصبروا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas Bin Malik: When Allah gave Allah's
Apostle what he gave of the properties of the Hawazin tribe as a
war booty, the Prophet started giving some men 100 camels each. The
Ansar (then) said, "May Allah forgive Allah's Apostles as he gives
to Quraish and leaves us although our swords are still dribbling
with the blood of Quraish." Allah Apostle was informed of their
statement, so he sent for the Ansar and gathered them in a leather
tent, and did not call anybody else along with them. When they al I
gathered, the Prophet got up and said, "What is this talk being
informed to me about you?" The learned men amongst the Ansar said,
"O Allah's Apostle! Our chiefs did not say anything, but some
people amongst us who are younger in age said. 'May Allah forgive
Allah's Apostle as he gives (of the booty) to Quraish and leaves us
though our swords are still dribbling with their blood." The
Prophet said, "I give to these men who have newly deserted
heathenism (and embraced Islam) so as to attract their hearts.
Won't you be happy that the people take the wealth while you take
the Prophet with you to your homes? By Allah, what you are taking
is better than whatever they are taking." They (i.e. the Ansar)
said, "O Allah's Apostle! We are satisfied." The Prophet then said
to them. "You will find others favored over you greatly, so be
patient till you meet Allah and His Apostle and I will be at the
Tank then." Anas added: But they did not remain
patient.</english-text>
</hadith>
