<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4174</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4377</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20206, 11071, 11228, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا أزهر، عن ابن عون، أنبأنا
هشام بن زيد بن أنس، عن أنس رضى الله عنه قال لما كان يوم حنين التقى
هوازن ومع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عشرة آلاف والطلقاء فأدبروا قال
‏"‏ يا معشر الأنصار ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لبيك يا رسول الله وسعديك، لبيك نحن
بين يديك، فنزل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أنا عبد الله
ورسوله ‏"‏‏.‏ فانهزم المشركون، فأعطى الطلقاء والمهاجرين ولم يعط
الأنصار شيئا فقالوا، فدعاهم فأدخلهم في قبة فقال ‏"‏ أما ترضون أن
يذهب الناس بالشاة والبعير، وتذهبون برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏لو سلك الناس واديا وسلكت
الأنصار شعبا لاخترت شعب الأنصار ‏"‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: When it was the day of (the battle of)
Hunain, the Prophet confronted the tribe of Hawazin while there
were ten-thousand (men) besides the Tulaqa' (i.e. those who had
embraced Islam on the day of the Conquest of Mecca) with the
Prophet. When they (i.e. Muslims) fled, the Prophet said, "O the
group of Ansari" They replied, "Labbaik, O Allah's Apostle and
Sadaik! We are under your command." Then the Prophet got down (from
his mule) and said, "I am Allah's Slave and His Apostle." Then the
pagans were defeated. The Prophet distributed the war booty amongst
the Tulaqa and Muhajirin (i.e. Emigrants) and did not give anything
to the Ansar. So the Ansar spoke (i.e. were dissatisfied) and he
called them and made them enter a leather tent and said, Won't you
be pleased that the people take the sheep and camels, and you take
Allah's Apostle along with you?" The Prophet added, "If the people
took their way through a valley and the Ansar took their way
through a mountain pass, then I would choose a mountain pass of the
Ansar."</english-text>
</hadith>
