<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4178</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4381</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20286, 11071, 11228, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا معاذ بن معاذ، حدثنا ابن عون،
عن هشام بن زيد بن أنس بن مالك، عن أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه قال لما
كان يوم حنين أقبلت هوازن وغطفان وغيرهم بنعمهم وذراريهم، ومع النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم عشرة آلاف ومن الطلقاء، فأدبروا عنه حتى بقي وحده،
فنادى يومئذ نداءين لم يخلط بينهما، التفت عن يمينه، فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر
الأنصار ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لبيك يا رسول الله، أبشر نحن معك‏.‏ ثم التفت عن
يساره، فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر الأنصار ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لبيك يا رسول الله،
أبشر نحن معك‏.‏ وهو على بغلة بيضاء، فنزل فقال ‏"‏ أنا عبد الله
ورسوله ‏"‏، فانهزم المشركون، فأصاب يومئذ غنائم كثيرة، فقسم في
المهاجرين والطلقاء ولم يعط الأنصار شيئا، فقالت الأنصار إذا كانت
شديدة فنحن ندعى، ويعطى الغنيمة غيرنا‏.‏ فبلغه ذلك، فجمعهم في قبة،
فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر الأنصار ما حديث بلغني عنكم ‏"‏‏.‏ فسكتوا فقال ‏"‏
يا معشر الأنصار ألا ترضون أن يذهب الناس بالدنيا، وتذهبون برسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم تحوزونه إلى بيوتكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا بلى‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو سلك الناس واديا، وسلكت الأنصار شعبا
لأخذت شعب الأنصار ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال هشام يا أبا حمزة، وأنت شاهد ذاك قال
وأين أغيب عنه</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas Bin Malik: When it was the day (of the
battle) of Hunain, the tributes of Hawazin and Ghatafan and others,
along with their animals and offspring (and wives) came to fight
against the Prophet The Prophet had with him, ten thousand men and
some of the Tulaqa. The companions fled, leaving the Prophet alone.
The Prophet then made two calls which were clearly distinguished
from each other. He turned right and said, "O the group of Ansar!"
They said, "Labbaik, O Allah's Apostle! Rejoice, for we are with
you!" Then he turned left and said, "O the group of Ansar!" They
said, "Labbaik! O Allah's Apostle! Rejoice, for we are with you!"
The Prophet at that time, was riding on a white mule; then he
dismounted and said, "I am Allah's Slave and His Apostle." The
infidels then were defeated, and on that day the Prophet gained a
large amount of booty which he distributed amongst the Muhajirin
and the Tulaqa and did not give anything to the Ansar. The Ansar
said, "When there is a difficulty, we are called, but the booty is
given to other than us." The news reached the Prophet and he
gathered them in a leather tent and said, "What is this news
reaching me from you, O the group of Ansar?" They kept silent, He
added," O the group of Ansar! Won't you be happy that the people
take the worldly things and you take Allah's Apostle to your homes
reserving him for yourself?" They said, "Yes." Then the Prophet
said, "If the people took their way through a valley, and the Ansar
took their way through a mountain pass, surely, I would take the
Ansar's mountain pass." Hisham said, "O Abu Hamza (i.e. Anas)! Did
you witness that? " He replied, "And how could I be absent from
him?"</english-text>
</hadith>
