<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4191</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4394</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20256, 11379, 11366, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد الواحد، عن عمارة بن القعقاع بن
شبرمة، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن أبي نعم، قال سمعت أبا سعيد الخدري، يقول
بعث علي بن أبي طالب رضى الله عنه إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
من اليمن بذهيبة في أديم مقروظ لم تحصل من ترابها، قال فقسمها بين
أربعة نفر بين عيينة بن بدر، وأقرع بن حابس وزيد الخيل، والرابع إما
علقمة وإما عامر بن الطفيل، فقال رجل من أصحابه كنا نحن أحق بهذا من
هؤلاء‏.‏ قال فبلغ ذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ ألا تأمنوني
وأنا أمين من في السماء، يأتيني خبر السماء صباحا ومساء ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
فقام رجل غائر العينين، مشرف الوجنتين، ناشز الجبهة، كث اللحية، محلوق
الرأس، مشمر الإزار، فقال يا رسول الله، اتق الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ويلك
أولست أحق أهل الأرض أن يتقي الله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ثم ولى الرجل، قال خالد
بن الوليد يا رسول الله، ألا أضرب عنقه قال ‏"‏ لا، لعله أن يكون يصلي
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال خالد وكم من مصل يقول بلسانه ما ليس في قلبه‏.‏ قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني لم أومر أن أنقب قلوب الناس، ولا أشق
بطونهم ‏"‏ قال ثم نظر إليه وهو مقف فقال ‏"‏ إنه يخرج من ضئضئ هذا
قوم يتلون كتاب الله رطبا، لا يجاوز حناجرهم، يمرقون من الدين كما
يمرق السهم من الرمية ‏"‏‏.‏ وأظنه قال ‏"‏ لئن أدركتهم لأقتلنهم قتل
ثمود ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: `Ali bin Abi Talib sent
a piece of gold not yet taken out of its ore, in a tanned leather
container to Allah's Apostle . Allah's Apostle distributed that
amongst four Persons: 'Uyaina bin Badr, Aqra bin H`Abis, Zaid
Al-Khail and the fourth was either Alqama or Amir bin at-Tufail. On
that, one of his companions said, "We are more deserving of this
(gold) than these (persons)." When that news reached the Prophet ,
he said, "Don't you trust me though I am the truth worthy man of
the One in the Heavens, and I receive the news of Heaven (i.e.
Divine Inspiration) both in the morning and in the evening?" There
got up a man with sunken eyes, raised cheek bones, raised forehead,
a thick beard, a shaven head and a waist sheet that was tucked up
and he said, "O Allah's Apostle! Be afraid of Allah." The Prophet
said, "Woe to you! Am I not of all the people of the earth the most
entitled to fear Allah?" Then that man went away. Khalid bin
Al-Wahd said, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall I chop his neck off?" The
Prophet said, "No, for he may offer prayers." Khalid said,
"Numerous are those who offer prayers and say by their tongues
(i.e. mouths) what is not in their hearts." Allah's Apostle said,
"I have not been ordered (by Allah) to search the hearts of the
people or cut open their bellies." Then the Prophet looked at him
(i.e. that man) while the latter was going away and said, "From the
offspring of this (man there will come out (people) who will recite
the Qur'an continuously and elegantly but it will not exceed their
throats. (They will neither understand it nor act upon it). They
would go out of the religion (i.e. Islam) as an arrow goes through
a game's body." I think he also said, "If I should be present at
their time I would kill them as the nations a Thamud were
killed."</english-text>
</hadith>
