<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4197</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4400</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30224, 20318, 11418, 11046, 4057</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يوسف بن موسى، أخبرنا أبو أسامة، عن إسماعيل بن
أبي خالد، عن قيس، عن جرير، قال قال لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ ألا تريحني من ذي الخلصة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت بلى‏.‏ فانطلقت في خمسين
ومائة فارس من أحمس وكانوا أصحاب خيل وكنت لا أثبت على الخيل، فذكرت
ذلك للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فضرب يده على صدري حتى رأيت أثر يده في
صدري وقال ‏"‏ اللهم ثبته واجعله هاديا مهديا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فما وقعت عن
فرس بعد‏.‏ قال وكان ذو الخلصة بيتا باليمن لخثعم وبجيلة، فيه نصب
تعبد، يقال له الكعبة‏.‏ قال فأتاها فحرقها بالنار وكسرها‏.‏ قال ولما
قدم جرير اليمن كان بها رجل يستقسم بالأزلام فقيل له إن رسول رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ها هنا فإن قدر عليك ضرب عنقك‏.‏ قال فبينما
هو يضرب بها إذ وقف عليه جرير فقال لتكسرنها ولتشهدن أن لا إله إلا
الله أو لأضربن عنقك‏.‏ قال فكسرها وشهد، ثم بعث جرير رجلا من أحمس
يكنى أبا أرطاة إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يبشره بذلك، فلما أتى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال يا رسول الله والذي بعثك بالحق ما جئت
حتى تركتها كأنها جمل أجرب‏.‏ قال فبرك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم على
خيل أحمس ورجالها خمس مرات‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Qais: Jarir said "Allah's Apostle said to
me, "Won't you relieve me from Dhul-Khalasa?" I replied, "Yes, (I
will relieve you)." So I proceeded along with one-hundred and fifty
cavalry from Ahmas tribe who were skillful in riding horses. I used
not to sit firm over horses, so I informed the Prophet of that, and
he stroke my chest with his hand till I saw the marks of his hand
over my chest and he said, O Allah! Make him firm and one who
guides others and is guided (on the right path).' Since then I have
never fallen from a horse. Dhul-l--Khulasa was a house in Yemen
belonging to the tribe of Khatham and Bajaila, and in it there were
idols which were worshipped, and it was called Al-Ka`ba." Jarir
went there, burnt it with fire and dismantled it. When Jarir
reached Yemen, there was a man who used to foretell and give good
omens by casting arrows of divination. Someone said to him. "The
messenger of Allah's Apostle is present here and if he should get
hold of you, he would chop off your neck." One day while he was
using them (i.e. arrows of divination), Jarir stopped there and
said to him, "Break them (i.e. the arrows) and testify that None
has the right to be worshipped except Allah, or else I will chop
off your neck." So the man broke those arrows and testified that
none has the right to be worshipped except Allah. Then Jarir sent a
man called Abu Artata from the tribe of Ahmas to the Prophet to
convey the good news (of destroying Dhu-l-Khalasa). So when the
messenger reached the Prophet, he said, "O Allah's Apostle! By Him
Who sent you with the Truth, I did not leave it till it was like a
scabby camel." Then the Prophet blessed the horses of Ahmas and
their men five times.</english-text>
</hadith>
