<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4199</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4402</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>20102, 11418, 11046, 4057</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبد الله بن أبي شيبة العبسي، حدثنا ابن إدريس، عن
إسماعيل بن أبي خالد، عن قيس، عن جرير، قال كنت بالبحر فلقيت رجلين من
أهل اليمن ذا كلاع وذا عمرو، فجعلت أحدثهم عن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال له ذو عمرو لئن كان الذي تذكر من أمر صاحبك، لقد مر على
أجله منذ ثلاث‏.‏ وأقبلا معي حتى إذا كنا في بعض الطريق رفع لنا ركب
من قبل المدينة فسألناهم فقالوا قبض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
واستخلف أبو بكر والناس صالحون‏.‏ فقالا أخبر صاحبك أنا قد جئنا
ولعلنا سنعود إن شاء الله، ورجعا إلى اليمن فأخبرت أبا بكر بحديثهم
قال أفلا جئت بهم‏.‏ فلما كان بعد قال لي ذو عمرو يا جرير إن بك على
كرامة، وإني مخبرك خبرا، إنكم معشر العرب لن تزالوا بخير ما كنتم إذا
هلك أمير تأمرتم في آخر، فإذا كانت بالسيف كانوا ملوكا يغضبون غضب
الملوك ويرضون رضا الملوك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jarir: While I was at Yemen, I met two men
from Yemen called Dhu Kala and Dhu `Amr, and I started telling them
about Allah's Apostle. Dhu `Amr said to me, "If what you are saying
about your friend (i.e. the Prophet) is true, then he has died
three days ago." Then both of them accompanied me to Medina, and
when we had covered some distance on the way to Medina, we saw some
riders coming from Medina. We asked them and they said, "Allah's
Apostle has died and Abu Bakr has been appointed as the Caliph and
the people are in a good state.' Then they said, "Tell your friend
(Abu Bakr) that we have come (to visit him), and if Allah will, we
will come again." So they both returned to Yemen. When I told Abu
Bakr their statement, he said to me, "I wish you had brought them
(to me)." Afterwards I met Dhu `Amr, and he said to me, "O Jarir!
You have done a favor to me and I am going to tell you something,
i.e. you, the nation of 'Arabs, will remain prosperous as long as
you choose and appoint another chief whenever a former one is dead.
But if authority is obtained by the power of the sword, then the
rulers will become kings who will get angry, as kings get angry,
and will be delighted as kings get delighted."</english-text>
</hadith>
