<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4201</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4404</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، قال الذي حفظناه من
عمرو بن دينار قال سمعت جابر بن عبد الله، يقول بعثنا رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ثلاثمائة راكب أميرنا أبو عبيدة بن الجراح نرصد عير
قريش، فأقمنا بالساحل نصف شهر فأصابنا جوع شديد حتى أكلنا الخبط، فسمي
ذلك الجيش جيش الخبط، فألقى لنا البحر دابة يقال لها العنبر، فأكلنا
منه نصف شهر وادهنا من ودكه حتى ثابت إلينا أجسامنا، فأخذ أبو عبيدة
ضلعا من أضلاعه فنصبه فعمد إلى أطول رجل معه قال سفيان مرة ضلعا من
أعضائه فنصبه وأخذ رجلا وبعيرا فمر تحته قال جابر وكان رجل من القوم
نحر ثلاث جزائر، ثم نحر ثلاث جزائر، ثم نحر ثلاث جزائر، ثم إن أبا
عبيدة نهاه‏.‏ وكان عمرو يقول أخبرنا أبو صالح أن قيس بن سعد قال
لأبيه كنت في الجيش فجاعوا‏.‏ قال انحر‏.‏ قال نحرت‏.‏ قال ثم جاعوا
قال انحر‏.‏ قال نحرت‏.‏ قال ثم جاعوا قال انحر‏.‏ قال نحرت ثم جاعوا
قال انحر‏.‏ قال نهيت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: Allah's Apostle sent us
who were three-hundred riders under the command of Abu Ubaida bin
Al- Jarrah in order to watch the caravan of the Quraish pagans. We
stayed at the seashore for half a month and were struck with such
severe hunger that we ate even the Khabt (i.e. the leaves of the
Salam, a thorny desert tree), and because of that, the army was
known as Jaish-ul-Khabt. Then the sea threw out, an animal (i.e. a
fish) called Al-`Anbar and we ate of that for half a month, and
rubbed its fat on our bodies till our bodies returned to their
original state (i.e. became strong and healthy). Abu Ubaida took
one of its ribs, fixed it on the ground; then he went to the
tallest man of his companions (to let him pass under the rib). Once
Sufyan said, "He took a rib from its parts and fixed it, and then
took a man and camel and they passed from underneath it (without
touching it). " Jabir added: There was a man amongst the people who
slaughtered three camels and then slaughtered another three camels
and then slaughtered other three camels, and then Abu 'Ubaida
forbade him to do so. Narrated Abu Salih: Qais bin Sa`d said to his
father. "I was present in the army and the people were struck with
severe hunger." He said, "You should have slaughtered (camels) (for
them)." Qais said, "I did slaughter camels but they were hungry
again. He said, "You should have slaughtered (camels) again." Qais
said, "I did slaughter (camels) again but the people felt hungry
again." He said, "You should have slaughtered (camels) again." Qais
said, "I did slaughter (camels) again, but the people again felt
hungry." He said, "You should have slaughtered (camels) again."
Qais said, "But I was forbidden (by Abu 'Ubaida this
time).</english-text>
</hadith>
