<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4213</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4417</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11251, 11059, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن عبد الله بن أبي
حسين، حدثنا نافع بن جبير، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال قدم مسيلمة
الكذاب على عهد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجعل يقول إن جعل لي
محمد من بعده تبعته‏.‏ وقدمها في بشر كثير من قومه، فأقبل إليه رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ومعه ثابت بن قيس بن شماس، وفي يد رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قطعة جريد حتى وقف على مسيلمة في أصحابه، فقال ‏"‏
لو سألتني هذه القطعة ما أعطيتكها ولن تعدو أمر الله فيك، ولئن أدبرت
ليعقرنك الله، وإني لأراك الذي أريت فيه ما رأيت، وهذا ثابت يجيبك عني
‏"‏‏.‏ ثم انصرف عنه‏.‏ قال ابن عباس فسألت عن قول، رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنك أرى الذي أريت فيه ما أريت ‏"‏‏.‏ فأخبرني أبو
هريرة أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ بينا أنا نائم رأيت في
يدى سوارين من ذهب، فأهمني شأنهما، فأوحي إلى في المنام أن انفخهما،
فنفختهما فطارا فأولتهما كذابين يخرجان بعدي، أحدهما العنسي، والآخر
مسيلمة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: Musailima Al-Kadhdhab came
during the lifetime of the Prophet and started saying, "If Muhammad
gives me the rule after him, I will follow him." And he came to
Medina with a great number of the people of his tribe. Allah's
Apostle went to him in the company of Thabit bin Qais bin Shammas,
and at that time, Allah's Apostle had a stick of a date-palm tree
in his hand. When he (i.e. the Prophet ) stopped near Musailima
while the latter was amidst his companions, he said to him, "If you
ask me for this piece (of stick), I will not give it to you, and
Allah's Order you cannot avoid, (but you will be destroyed), and if
you turn your back from this religion, then Allah will destroy you.
And I think you are the same person who was shown to me in my
dream, and this is Thabit bin Qais who will answer your questions
on my behalf." Then the Prophet went away from him. I asked about
the statement of Allah's Apostle : "You seem to be the same person
who was shown to me in my dream," and Abu Huraira informed me that
Allah's Apostle said, "When I was sleeping, I saw (in a dream) two
bangles of gold on my hands and that worried me. And then I was
inspired Divinely in the dream that I should blow on them, so I
blew on them and both the bangles flew away. And I interpreted it
that two liars (who would claim to be prophets) would appear after
me. One of them has proved to be Al Ansi and the other,
Musailima."</english-text>
</hadith>
