<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4216</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4421</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30195, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن محمد الجرمي، حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم،
حدثنا أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن عبيدة بن نشيط وكان في موضع آخر اسمه عبد
الله أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة قال بلغنا أن مسيلمة الكذاب
قدم المدينة، فنزل في دار بنت الحارث، وكان تحته بنت الحارث بن كريز،
وهى أم عبد الله بن عامر، فأتاه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ومعه
ثابت بن قيس بن شماس، وهو الذي يقال له خطيب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وفي يد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قضيب، فوقف عليه فكلمه فقال
له مسيلمة إن شئت خليت بيننا وبين الأمر، ثم جعلته لنا بعدك‏.‏ فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو سألتني هذا القضيب ما أعطيتكه وإني
لأراك الذي أريت فيه ما أريت، وهذا ثابت بن قيس وسيجيبك عني ‏"‏‏.‏
فانصرف النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ قال عبيد الله بن عبد الله سألت
عبد الله بن عباس عن رؤيا، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم التي ذكر
فقال ابن عباس ذكر لي أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ بينا
أنا نائم أريت أنه وضع في يدى سواران من ذهب، ففظعتهما وكرهتهما، فأذن
لي فنفختهما فطارا، فأولتهما كذابين يخرجان ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال عبيد الله
أحدهما العنسي الذي قتله فيروز باليمن، والآخر مسيلمة
الكذاب‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ubaidullah bin `Abdullah bin `Utba: We were
informed that Musailima Al-Kadhdhab had arrived in Medina and
stayed in the house of the daughter of Al-Harith. The daughter of
Al-Harith bin Kuraiz was his wife and she was the mother of
`Abdullah bin 'Amir. There came to him Allah's Apostle accompanied
by Thabit bin Qais bin Shammas who was called the orator of Allah's
Apostle. Allah's Apostle had a stick in his hand then. The Prophet
stopped before Musailima and spoke to him. Musailima said to him,
"If you wish, we would not interfere between you and the rule, on
condition that the rule will be ours after you... The Prophet said,
"If you asked me for this stick, I would not give it to you. I
think you are the same person who was shown to me in a dream. And
this is Thabit bin Al-Qais who will answer you on my behalf." The
Prophet then went away. I asked Ibn `Abbas about the dream Allah's
Apostle had mentioned. Ibn `Abbas said, "Someone told me that the
Prophet said, "When I was sleeping, I saw in a dream that two gold
bangles were put in my hands, and that frightened me and made me
dislike them. Then I was allowed to blow on them, and when I blew
at them, both of them flew. Then I interpreted them as two liars
who would appear.' One of them was Al-`Ansi who was killed by
Fairuz in Yemen and the other was Musailima
Al-Kadhdbab."</english-text>
</hadith>
