<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4220</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4426</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20005</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا سفيان، سمع ابن المنكدر،
جابر بن عبد الله رضى الله عنهما يقول قال لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ لو قد جاء مال البحرين لقد أعطيتك هكذا وهكذا ثلاثا ‏"‏‏.‏
فلم يقدم مال البحرين حتى قبض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما قدم
على أبي بكر أمر مناديا فنادى من كان له عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
دين أو عدة فليأتني‏.‏ قال جابر فجئت أبا بكر، فأخبرته أن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ لو جاء مال البحرين أعطيتك هكذا وهكذا ثلاثا
‏"‏‏.‏ قال فأعطاني‏.‏ قال جابر فلقيت أبا بكر بعد ذلك فسألته، فلم
يعطني، ثم أتيته فلم يعطني، ثم أتيته الثالثة فلم يعطني، فقلت له قد
أتيتك فلم تعطني، ثم أتيتك فلم تعطني، ثم أتيتك فلم تعطني، فإما أن
تعطيني، وإما أن تبخل عني‏.‏ فقال أقلت تبخل عني وأى داء أدوأ من
البخل قالها ثلاثا ما منعتك من مرة إلا وأنا أريد أن أعطيك‏.‏ وعن
عمرو عن محمد بن علي سمعت جابر بن عبد الله يقول جئته، فقال لي أبو
بكر عدها‏.‏ فعددتها فوجدتها خمسمائة، فقال خذ مثلها
مرتين‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: Allah's Apostle said to
me, "If the revenue of Al-Bahrain should come, I will give you so
much and so much," repeating "so much" thrice. But the revenue of
Al-Bahrain did not come till Allah's Apostle had died. When the
revenue came during the rule of Abu Bakr. Abu Bakr ordered an
announcer to announce, "Whoever had any debt or promise due upon
the Prophet, should present himself to me (i.e. Abu Bakr). I came
to Abu Bakr and informed him that the Prophet had said (to me), "If
the revenue of Al-Bahrain should come, I will give you so-much and
so much," repeating "so much" thrice. So Abu Bakr gave me (in
another narration Jaibir said,). I met Abu Bakr after that and
asked him (to give me what the Prophet had promised me) but he did
not give me. I again went to him but he did not give me. I again
went to him (for the third time) but he did not give me; On that I
said to him, "I came to you but you did not give me, then I came to
you and you did not give me, and then again I came to you, but you
did not give me; so you should either give me or else you are like
a miserly to me, on that, Abu Bakr said, "Do you say, 'You are like
a miserly to me?' There is no worse disease than miserliness." Abu
Bakr said it thrice and added, "Whenever I refused to give you, I
had the intention of giving you." (In another narration) Jabir bin
`Abdullah said, "I went to Abu Bakr (and he gave me a handful of
money) and told me to count it, I counted and found it
five-hundred, and then Abu Bakr said (to me), "Take the same amount
twice."</english-text>
</hadith>
