<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4229</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4435</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 20458, 11060, 11051, 11017</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، عن أبي حمزة، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، عن
علقمة، قال كنا جلوسا مع ابن مسعود، فجاء خباب فقال يا أبا عبد
الرحمن، أيستطيع هؤلاء الشباب أن يقرءوا كما تقرأ قال أما إنك لو شئت
أمرت بعضهم يقرأ عليك قال أجل‏.‏ قال اقرأ يا علقمة‏.‏ فقال زيد بن
حدير أخو زياد بن حدير أتأمر علقمة أن يقرأ وليس بأقرئنا قال أما إنك
إن شئت أخبرتك بما قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في قومك وقومه‏.‏
فقرأت خمسين آية من سورة مريم، فقال عبد الله كيف ترى قال قد أحسن‏.‏
قال عبد الله ما أقرأ شيئا إلا وهو يقرؤه، ثم التفت إلى خباب وعليه
خاتم من ذهب فقال ألم يأن لهذا الخاتم أن يلقى قال أما إنك لن تراه
على بعد اليوم، فألقاه‏.‏ رواه غندر عن شعبة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Alqama: We were sitting with Ibn Masud when
Khabbab came and said, "O Abu `Abdur-Rahman! Can these young
fellows recite Qur'an as you do?" Ibn Mas`ud said, "If you wish I
can order one of them to recite (Qur'an) for you ." Khabbab
replied, "Yes. "Ibn Mas`ud said, "Recite, O 'Alqama!" On that, Zaid
bin Hudair, the brother of Ziyad bin Hudair said, (to Ibn Mas`ud),
"Why have you ordered 'Alqama to recite though he does not recite
better than we?" Ibn Mas`ud said, "If you like, I would tell you
what the Prophet said about your nation and his (i.e. 'Alqama's)
nation." So I recited fifty Verses from Sura-Maryam. `Abdullah (bin
Mas`ud) said to Khabbab, "What do you think (about 'Alqama's
recitation)?" Khabbab said, "He has recited well." `Abdullah said,
"Whatever I recite, 'Alqama recites." Then `Abdullah turned towards
Khabbab and saw that he was wearing a gold ring, whereupon he said,
"Hasn't the time for its throwing away come yet?" Khabbab said,
"You will not see me wearing it after today," and he throw it
away.</english-text>
</hadith>
