<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4240</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4446</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30220, 20029, 11530, 11217, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن سليمان، قال أخبرني ابن وهب، قال حدثني
عمر بن محمد، أن أباه، حدثه عن ابن عمر رضى الله عنهما قال كنا نتحدث
بحجة الوداع والنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بين أظهرنا، ولا ندري ما حجة
الوداع، فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم ذكر المسيح الدجال فأطنب في ذكره
وقال ‏"‏ ما بعث الله من نبي إلا أنذر أمته، أنذره نوح والنبيون من
بعده، وإنه يخرج فيكم، فما خفي عليكم من شأنه فليس يخفى عليكم أن ربكم
ليس على ما يخفى عليكم ثلاثا، إن ربكم ليس بأعور، وإنه أعور عين
اليمنى، كأن عينه عنبة طافية ‏"‏‏.‏ ‏"‏ ألا إن الله حرم عليكم دماءكم
وأموالكم، كحرمة يومكم هذا، في بلدكم هذا، في شهركم هذا، ألا هل بلغت
‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اللهم اشهد، ثلاثا، ويلكم، أو ويحكم،
انظروا لا ترجعوا بعدي كفارا، يضرب بعضكم رقاب بعض
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: We were talking about
Hajjat-ul-Wada`, while the Prophet was amongst us. We did not know
what Hajjat-ul-Wada` signified. The Prophet praised Allah and then
mentioned Al-Masih Ad-Dajjal and described him extensively, saying,
"Allah did not send any prophet but that prophet warned his nation
of Al-Masih Ad-Dajjal. Noah and the prophets following him warned
(their people) of him. He will appear amongst you (O Muhammad's
followers), and if it happens that some of his qualities may be
hidden from you, but your Lord's State is clear to you and not
hidden from you. The Prophet said it thrice. Verily, your Lord is
not blind in one eye, while he (i.e. Ad-Dajjal) is blind in the
right eye which looks like a grape bulging out (of its cluster). No
doubt,! Allah has made your blood and your properties sacred to one
another like the sanctity of this day of yours, in this town of
yours, in this month of yours." The Prophet added: No doubt!
Haven't I conveyed Allah's Message to you? " They replied, "Yes,"
The Prophet said thrice, "O Allah! Be witness for it." The Prophet
added, "Woe to you!" (or said), "May Allah be merciful to you! Do
not become infidels after me (i.e. my death) by cutting the necks
(throats) of one another."</english-text>
</hadith>
