<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4243</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4450</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20259, 11015, 20278, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا أيوب، عن
محمد، عن ابن أبي بكرة، عن أبي بكرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ الزمان قد استدار كهيئة يوم خلق السموات والأرض، السنة اثنا عشر
شهرا منها أربعة حرم ثلاثة متواليات ذو القعدة وذو الحجة والمحرم،
ورجب مضر الذي بين جمادى وشعبان، أى شهر هذا ‏"‏ قلنا الله ورسوله
أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس ذو الحجة
‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأى بلد هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله
أعلم، فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس البلدة
‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأى يوم هذا ‏"‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم،
فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أليس يوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏
قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم قال محمد وأحسبه قال
وأعراضكم عليكم حرام كحرمة يومكم هذا، في بلدكم هذا، في شهركم هذا
وستلقون ربكم، فسيسألكم عن أعمالكم، ألا فلا ترجعوا بعدي ضلالا، يضرب
بعضكم رقاب بعض، ألا ليبلغ الشاهد الغائب، فلعل بعض من يبلغه أن يكون
أوعى له من بعض من سمعه فكان محمد إذا ذكره يقول صدق محمد صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم قال ألا هل بلغت‏.‏ مرتين ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Bakra: The Prophet said, "Time has taken
its original shape which it had when Allah created the Heavens and
the Earth. The year is of twelve months, four of which are sacred,
and out of these (four) three are in succession, i.e. Dhul-Qa'da,
Dhul-Hijja and Al-Muharram, and the fourth is Rajab which is named
after the Mudar tribe, between (the month of) Jumaida (ath-thania)
and Sha'ban." Then the Prophet asked, "Which is this month?" We
said, "Allah and His Apostle know better." On that the Prophet kept
quiet so long that we thought that he might name it with another
name. Then the Prophet said, "Isn't it the month of Dhul-Hijja?" We
replied, "Yes." Then he said, "Which town is this?" "We replied,
"Allah and His Apostle know better." On that he kept quiet so long
that we thought that he might name it with another name. Then he
said, "Isn't it the town of Mecca?" We replied, "Yes, " Then he
said, "Which day is today?" We replied, "Allah and His Apostle know
better." He kept quiet so long that we thought that he might name
it with another name. Then he said, "Isn't it the day of An- Nahr
(i.e. sacrifice)?" We replied, "Yes." He said, "So your blood, your
properties, (The sub-narrator Muhammad said, 'I think the Prophet
also said: And your honor..) are sacred to one another like the
sanctity of this day of yours, in this city of yours, in this month
of yours; and surely, you will meet your Lord, and He will ask you
about your deeds. Beware! Do not become infidels after me, cutting
the throats of one another. It is incumbent on those who are
present to convey this message (of mine) to those who are absent.
May be that some of those to whom it will be conveyed will
understand it better than those who have actually heard it." (The
sub-narrator, Muhammad, on remembering that narration, used to say,
"Muhammad spoke the truth!") He (i.e. Prophet) then added twice,
"No doubt! Haven't I conveyed (Allah's Message) to
you?"</english-text>
</hadith>
