<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4254</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4459</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30216, 20318, 11325, 11901, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن العلاء، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن بريد بن عبد
الله بن أبي بردة، عن أبي بردة، عن أبي موسى رضى الله عنه قال أرسلني
أصحابي إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أسأله الحملان لهم، إذ هم
معه في جيش العسرة وهى غزوة تبوك فقلت يا نبي الله، إن أصحابي أرسلوني
إليك لتحملهم‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ والله لا أحملكم على شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ ووافقته،
وهو غضبان ولا أشعر، ورجعت حزينا من منع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم،
ومن مخافة أن يكون النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وجد في نفسه على، فرجعت
إلى أصحابي فأخبرتهم الذي قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، فلم ألبث إلا
سويعة إذ سمعت بلالا ينادي أى عبد الله بن قيس‏.‏ فأجبته، فقال أجب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يدعوك، فلما أتيته، قال ‏"‏ خذ هذين
القرينين وهذين القرينين لستة أبعرة ابتاعهن حينئذ من سعد فانطلق بهن
إلى أصحابك فقل إن الله أو قال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يحملكم على هؤلاء فاركبوهن ‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلقت إليهم بهن، فقلت إن النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم يحملكم على هؤلاء ولكني والله لا أدعكم حتى ينطلق
معي بعضكم إلى من سمع مقالة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا تظنوا
أني حدثتكم شيئا لم يقله رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا لي إنك
عندنا لمصدق، ولنفعلن ما أحببت‏.‏ فانطلق أبو موسى بنفر منهم حتى أتوا
الذين سمعوا قول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منعه إياهم، ثم إعطاءهم
بعد، فحدثوهم بمثل ما حدثهم به أبو موسى‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa: My Companions sent me to Allah's
Apostle to ask him for some animals to ride on as they were
accompanying him in the army of Al-Usra, and that was the Ghazwa
(Battle) of Tabuk, I said, "O Allah's Prophet! My companions have
sent me to you to provide them with means of transportation." He
said, "By Allah! I will not make you ride anything." It happened
that when I reached him, he was in an angry mood, and I didn't
notice it. So I returned in a sad mood because of the refusal the
Prophet and for the fear that the Prophet might have become 'angry
with me. So I returned to my companions and informed them of what
the Prophet had said. Only a short while had passed when I heard
Bilal calling, "O `Abdullah bin Qais!" I replied to his call. Bilal
said, "Respond to Allah's Apostle who is calling you." When I went
to him (i.e. the Prophet), he said, "Take these two camels tied
together and also these two camels tied together,"' referring to
six camels he had brought them from Sa`d at that time. The Prophet
added, "Take them to your companions and say, 'Allah (or Allah's
Apostle ) allows you to ride on these,' so ride on them." So I took
those camels to them and said, "The Prophet allows you to ride on
these (camels) but by Allah, I will not leave you till some of you
proceed with me to somebody who heard the statement of Allah's
Apostle. Do not think that I narrate to you a thing which Allah's
Apostle has not said." They said to me, "We consider you truthful,
and we will do what you like." The sub-narrator added: So Abu Musa
proceeded along with some of them till they came to those who have
heard the statement of Allah's Apostle wherein he denied them (some
animals to ride on) and (his statement) whereby he gave them the
same. So these people told them the same information as Abu Musa
had told them.</english-text>
</hadith>
