<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4288</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4490</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30021, 30317, 20428, 11013, 1131, 17, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسحاق، أخبرنا بشر بن شعيب بن أبي حمزة، قال حدثني
أبي، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني عبد الله بن كعب بن مالك الأنصاري وكان
كعب بن مالك أحد الثلاثة الذين تيب عليهم أن عبد الله بن عباس أخبره
أن علي بن أبي طالب رضى الله عنه خرج من عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في وجعه الذي توفي فيه، فقال الناس يا أبا حسن، كيف أصبح رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال أصبح بحمد الله بارئا، فأخذ بيده عباس
بن عبد المطلب، فقال له أنت والله بعد ثلاث عبد العصا، وإني والله
لأرى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سوف يتوفى من وجعه هذا، إني لأعرف
وجوه بني عبد المطلب عند الموت، اذهب بنا إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فلنسأله فيمن هذا الأمر، إن كان فينا علمنا ذلك، وإن كان في
غيرنا علمناه فأوصى بنا‏.‏ فقال علي إنا والله لئن سألناها رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فمنعناها لا يعطيناها الناس بعده، وإني والله لا
أسألها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: `Ali bin Abu Talib
came out of the house of Allah's Apostle during his fatal illness.
The people asked, "O Abu Hasan (i.e. `Ali)! How is the health of
Allah's Apostle this morning?" `Ali replied, "He has recovered with
the Grace of Allah." `Abbas bin `Abdul Muttalib held him by the
hand and said to him, "In three days you, by Allah, will be ruled
(by somebody else ), And by Allah, I feel that Allah's Apostle will
die from this ailment of his, for I know how the faces of the
offspring of `Abdul Muttalib look at the time of their death. So
let us go to Allah's Apostle and ask him who will take over the
Caliphate. If it is given to us we will know as to it, and if it is
given to somebody else, we will inform him so that he may tell the
new ruler to take care of us." `Ali said, "By Allah, if we asked
Allah's Apostle for it (i.e. the Caliphate) and he denied it us,
the people will never give it to us after that. And by Allah, I
will not ask Allah's Apostle for it."</english-text>
</hadith>
