<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4290</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>64</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4492</hadith-number>
<chapter>Military Expeditions led by the Prophet (pbuh)
(Al-Maghaazi) - كتاب المغازى</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20347, 10652, 11090</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن عبيد، حدثنا عيسى بن يونس، عن عمر بن
سعيد، قال أخبرني ابن أبي مليكة، أن أبا عمرو، ذكوان مولى عائشة أخبره
أن عائشة كانت تقول إن من نعم الله على أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم توفي في بيتي وفي يومي، وبين سحري ونحري، وأن الله جمع بين ريقي
وريقه عند موته، دخل على عبد الرحمن وبيده السواك وأنا مسندة رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فرأيته ينظر إليه، وعرفت أنه يحب السواك فقلت
آخذه لك فأشار برأسه أن نعم، فتناولته فاشتد عليه وقلت ألينه لك فأشار
برأسه أن نعم، فلينته، وبين يديه ركوة أو علبة يشك عمر فيها ماء، فجعل
يدخل يديه في الماء فيمسح بهما وجهه يقول ‏"‏ لا إله إلا الله، إن
للموت سكرات ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم نصب يده فجعل يقول ‏"‏ في الرفيق الأعلى ‏"‏‏.‏
حتى قبض ومالت يده‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha: It was one of the favors of Allah
towards me that Allah's Apostle expired in my house on the day of
my turn while he was leaning against my chest and Allah made my
saliva mix with his saliva at his death. `Abdur-Rahman entered upon
me with a Siwak in his hand and I was supporting (the back of)
Allah's Apostle (against my chest ). I saw the Prophet looking at
it (i.e. Siwak) and I knew that he loved the Siwak, so I said ( to
him ), "Shall I take it for you ? " He nodded in agreement. So I
took it and it was too stiff for him to use, so I said, "Shall I
soften it for you ?" He nodded his approval. So I softened it and
he cleaned his teeth with it. In front of him there was a jug or a
tin, (The sub-narrator, `Umar is in doubt as to which was right)
containing water. He started dipping his hand in the water and
rubbing his face with it, he said, "None has the right to be
worshipped except Allah. Death has its agonies." He then lifted his
hands (towards the sky) and started saying, "With the highest
companion," till he expired and his hand dropped
down.</english-text>
</hadith>
