<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>433</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>439</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayers (Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، قال حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام،
عن أبيه، عن عائشة، أن وليدة، كانت سوداء لحى من العرب، فأعتقوها،
فكانت معهم قالت فخرجت صبية لهم عليها وشاح أحمر من سيور قالت فوضعته
أو وقع منها، فمرت به حدياة وهو ملقى، فحسبته لحما فخطفته قالت
فالتمسوه فلم يجدوه قالت فاتهموني به قالت فطفقوا يفتشون حتى فتشوا
قبلها قالت والله إني لقائمة معهم، إذ مرت الحدياة فألقته قالت فوقع
بينهم قالت فقلت هذا الذي اتهمتموني به زعمتم وأنا منه بريئة، وهو ذا
هو قالت فجاءت إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأسلمت‏.‏ قالت عائشة
فكان لها خباء في المسجد أو حفش قالت فكانت تأتيني فتحدث عندي قالت
فلا تجلس عندي مجلسا إلا قالت ويوم الوشاح من أعاجيب ربنا ألا إنه من
بلدة الكفر أنجاني قالت عائشة فقلت لها ما شأنك لا تقعدين معي مقعدا
إلا قلت هذا قالت فحدثتني بهذا الحديث‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: There was a black slave girl
belonging to an 'Arab tribe and they manumitted her but she
remained with them. The slave girl said, "Once one of their girls
(of that tribe) came out wearing a red leather scarf decorated with
precious stones. It fell from her or she placed it somewhere. A
kite passed by that place, saw it Lying there and mistaking it for
a piece of meat, flew away with it. Those people searched for it
but they did not find it. So they accused me of stealing it and
started searching me and even searched my private parts." The slave
girl further said, "By Allah! while I was standing (in that state)
with those people, the same kite passed by them and dropped the red
scarf and it fell amongst them. I told them, 'This is what you
accused me of and I was innocent and now this is it.' " `Aisha
added: That slave girl came to Allah's Apostle and embraced Islam.
She had a tent or a small room with a low roof in the mosque.
Whenever she called on me, she had a talk with me and whenever she
sat with me, she would recite the following: "The day of the scarf
(band) was one of the wonders of our Lord, verily He rescued me
from the disbelievers' town. `Aisha added: "Once I asked her, 'What
is the matter with you? Whenever you sit with me, you always recite
these poetic verses.' On that she told me the whole story.
"</english-text>
</hadith>
