<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4356</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4562</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30161, 20271, 11106, 11211, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن أبي بكر، حدثنا فضيل بن سليمان، حدثنا
موسى بن عقبة، أخبرني كريب، عن ابن عباس، قال يطوف الرجل بالبيت ما
كان حلالا حتى يهل بالحج، فإذا ركب إلى عرفة فمن تيسر له هدية من
الإبل أو البقر أو الغنم، ما تيسر له من ذلك أى ذلك شاء، غير إن لم
يتيسر له فعليه ثلاثة أيام في الحج، وذلك قبل يوم عرفة، فإن كان آخر
يوم من الأيام الثلاثة يوم عرفة فلا جناح عليه، ثم لينطلق حتى يقف
بعرفات من صلاة العصر إلى أن يكون الظلام، ثم ليدفعوا من عرفات إذا
أفاضوا منها حتى يبلغوا جمعا الذي يتبرر فيه، ثم ليذكروا الله كثيرا،
أو أكثروا التكبير والتهليل قبل أن تصبحوا ثم أفيضوا، فإن الناس كانوا
يفيضون، وقال الله تعالى ‏{‏ثم أفيضوا من حيث أفاض الناس واستغفروا
الله إن الله غفور رحيم‏}‏ حتى ترموا الجمرة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: A man who wants to perform the
Hajj (from Mecca) can perform the Tawaf around the Ka`ba as long as
he is not in the state of Ihram till he assumes the Ihram for Hajj.
Then, if he rides and proceeds to `Arafat, he should take a Hadi
(i.e. animal for sacrifice), either a camel or a cow or a sheep,
whatever he can afford; but if he cannot afford it, he should fast
for three days during the Hajj before the day of `Arafat, but if
the third day of his fasting happens to be the day of `Arafat (i.e.
9th of Dhul-Hijja) then it is no sin for him (to fast on it). Then
he should proceed to `Arafat and stay there from the time of the
`Asr prayer till darkness falls. Then the pilgrims should proceed
from `Arafat, and when they have departed from it, they reach Jam'
(i.e. Al-Muzdalifa) where they ask Allah to help them to be
righteous and dutiful to Him, and there they remember Allah greatly
or say Takbir (i.e. Allah is Greater) and Tahlil (i.e. None has the
right to be worshipped but Allah) repeatedly before dawn breaks.
Then, after offering the morning (Fajr) prayer you should pass on
(to Mina) for the people used to do so and Allah said:-- "Then
depart from the place whence all the people depart. And ask for
Allah's Forgiveness. Truly! Allah is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful."
(2.199) Then you should go on doing so till you throw pebbles over
the Jamra.</english-text>
</hadith>
