<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4387</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4595</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20295, 20115, 30351, 20121, 20115, 11013,
11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إبراهيم بن موسى، عن هشام، عن معمر،‏.‏ وحدثني عبد
الله بن محمد، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، قال حدثني ابن عباس، قال حدثني أبو
سفيان، من فيه إلى في قال انطلقت في المدة التي كانت بيني وبين رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال فبينا أنا بالشأم إذ جيء بكتاب من النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى هرقل قال وكان دحية الكلبي جاء به فدفعه إلى
عظيم بصرى، فدفعه عظيم بصرى إلى هرقل قال فقال هرقل هل ها هنا أحد من
قوم هذا الرجل الذي يزعم أنه نبي فقالوا نعم‏.‏ قال فدعيت في نفر من
قريش فدخلنا على هرقل، فأجلسنا بين يديه فقال أيكم أقرب نسبا من هذا
الرجل الذي يزعم أنه نبي فقال أبو سفيان فقلت أنا‏.‏ فأجلسوني بين
يديه، وأجلسوا أصحابي خلفي، ثم دعا بترجمانه فقال قل لهم إني سائل هذا
عن هذا الرجل الذي يزعم أنه نبي، فإن كذبني فكذبوه‏.‏ قال أبو سفيان
وايم الله، لولا أن يؤثروا على الكذب لكذبت‏.‏ ثم قال لترجمانه سله
كيف حسبه فيكم قال قلت هو فينا ذو حسب‏.‏ قال فهل كان من آبائه ملك
قال قلت لا‏.‏ قال فهل كنتم تتهمونه بالكذب قبل أن يقول ما قال قلت
لا‏.‏ قال أيتبعه أشراف الناس أم ضعفاؤهم قال قلت بل ضعفاؤهم‏.‏ قال
يزيدون أو ينقصون قال قلت لا بل يزيدون‏.‏ قال هل يرتد أحد منهم عن
دينه، بعد أن يدخل فيه، سخطة له قال قلت لا‏.‏ قال فهل قاتلتموه قال
قلت نعم‏.‏ قال فكيف كان قتالكم إياه قال قلت تكون الحرب بيننا وبينه
سجالا، يصيب منا ونصيب منه‏.‏ قال فهل يغدر قال قلت لا ونحن منه في
هذه المدة لا ندري ما هو صانع فيها‏.‏ قال والله ما أمكنني من كلمة
أدخل فيها شيئا غير هذه‏.‏ قال فهل قال هذا القول أحد قبله قلت لا‏.‏
ثم قال لترجمانه قل له إني سألتك عن حسبه فيكم، فزعمت أنه فيكم ذو
حسب، وكذلك الرسل تبعث في أحساب قومها، وسألتك هل كان في آبائه ملك
فزعمت أن لا فقلت لو كان من آبائه ملك قلت رجل يطلب ملك آبائه، وسألتك
عن أتباعه أضعفاؤهم أم أشرافهم فقلت بل ضعفاؤهم، وهم أتباع الرسل،
وسألتك هل كنتم تتهمونه بالكذب قبل أن يقول ما قال فزعمت أن لا، فعرفت
أنه لم يكن ليدع الكذب على الناس ثم يذهب فيكذب على الله، وسألتك هل
يرتد أحد منهم عن دينه بعد أن يدخل فيه سخطة له فزعمت أن لا، وكذلك
الإيمان إذا خالط بشاشة القلوب، وسألتك هل يزيدون أم ينقصون فزعمت
أنهم يزيدون، وكذلك الإيمان حتى يتم، وسألتك هل قاتلتموه فزعمت أنكم
قاتلتموه فتكون الحرب بينكم وبينه سجالا، ينال منكم وتنالون منه،
وكذلك الرسل تبتلى، ثم تكون لهم العاقبة، وسألتك هل يغدر فزعمت أنه لا
يغدر، وكذلك الرسل لا تغدر، وسألتك هل قال أحد هذا القول قبله فزعمت
أن لا، فقلت لو كان قال هذا القول أحد قبله قلت رجل ائتم بقول قيل
قبله‏.‏ قال ثم قال بم يأمركم قال قلت يأمرنا بالصلاة والزكاة والصلة
والعفاف‏.‏ قال إن يك ما تقول فيه حقا فإنه نبي، وقد كنت أعلم أنه
خارج، ولم أك أظنه منكم، ولو أني أعلم أني أخلص إليه لأحببت لقاءه،
ولو كنت عنده لغسلت عن قدميه، وليبلغن ملكه ما تحت قدمى‏.‏ قال ثم دعا
بكتاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقرأه، فإذا فيه ‏"‏ بسم الله
الرحمن الرحيم من محمد رسول الله، إلى هرقل عظيم الروم، سلام على من
اتبع الهدى، أما بعد، فإني أدعوك بدعاية الإسلام، أسلم تسلم، وأسلم
يؤتك الله أجرك مرتين، فإن توليت فإن عليك إثم الأريسيين، و‏{‏يا أهل
الكتاب تعالوا إلى كلمة سواء بيننا وبينكم أن لا نعبد إلا الله‏}‏ إلى
قوله ‏{‏اشهدوا بأنا مسلمون‏}‏‏"‏‏.‏ فلما فرغ من قراءة الكتاب ارتفعت
الأصوات عنده، وكثر اللغط، وأمر بنا فأخرجنا قال فقلت لأصحابي حين
خرجنا لقد أمر أمر ابن أبي كبشة، أنه ليخافه ملك بني الأصفر فما زلت
موقنا بأمر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنه سيظهر حتى أدخل الله على
الإسلام‏.‏ قال الزهري فدعا هرقل عظماء الروم فجمعهم في دار له فقال
يا معشر الروم، هل لكم في الفلاح والرشد آخر الأبد، وأن يثبت لكم
ملككم قال فحاصوا حيصة حمر الوحش إلى الأبواب، فوجدوها قد غلقت، فقال
على بهم‏.‏ فدعا بهم فقال إني إنما اختبرت شدتكم على دينكم، فقد رأيت
منكم الذي أحببت‏.‏ فسجدوا له ورضوا عنه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: Abu Sufyan narrated to me
personally, saying, "I set out during the Truce that had been
concluded between me and Allah's Apostle. While I was in Sham, a
letter sent by the Prophet was brought to Heraclius. Dihya Al-Kalbi
had brought and given it to the governor of Busra, and the latter
forwarded it to Heraclius. Heraclius said, 'Is there anyone from
the people of this man who claims to be a prophet?' The people
replied, 'Yes.' So I along with some of Quraishi men were called
and we entered upon Heraclius, and we were seated in front of him.
Then he said, 'Who amongst you is the nearest relative to the man
who claims to be a prophet?' So they made me sit in front of him
and made my companions sit behind me. Then he called upon his
translator and said (to him). 'Tell them ( i.e. Abu Sufyan's
companions) that I am going to ask him (i.e. Abu Sufyan) regarding
that man who claims to be a prophet. So, if he tell me a lie, they
should contradict him (instantly).' By Allah, had I not been afraid
that my companions would consider me a liar, I would have told
lies. Heraclius then said to his translator, 'Ask him: What is his
(i.e. the Prophet's) family status amongst you? I said, 'He belongs
to a noble family amongst us." Heraclius said, 'Was any of his
ancestors a king?' I said, 'No.' He said, 'Did you ever accuse him
of telling lies before his saying what he has said?' I said, 'No.'
He said, 'Do the nobles follow him or the poor people?' I said, 'It
is the poor who followed him.' He said, 'Is the number of his
follower increasing or decreasing?' I said, 'The are increasing.'
He said, 'Does anyone renounce his religion (i.e. Islam) after
embracing it, being displeased with it?' I said, 'No.' He said,
'Did you fight with him?' I replied, 'Yes.' He said, 'How was your
fighting with him?' I said, 'The fighting between us was undecided
and victory was shared by him and us by turns. He inflicts
casualties upon us and we inflict casualties upon him.' He said,
'Did he ever betray?' I said, 'No, but now we are away from him in
this truce and we do not know what he will do in it" Abu Sufyan
added, "By Allah, I was not able to insert in my speech a word
(against him) except that. Heraclius said, 'Did anybody else
(amongst you) ever claimed the same (i.e. Islam) before him? I
said, 'No.' Then Heraclius told his translator to tell me (i.e. Abu
Sufyan), 'I asked you about his family status amongst you, and you
told me that he comes from a noble family amongst you Verily, all
Apostles come from the noblest family among their people. Then I
asked you whether any of his ancestors was a king, and you denied
that. Thereupon I thought that had one of his fore-fathers been a
king, I would have said that he (i.e. Muhammad) was seeking to rule
the kingdom of his fore-fathers. Then I asked you regarding his
followers, whether they were the noble or the poor among the
people, and you said that they were only the poor (who follow him).
In fact, such are the followers of the Apostles. Then I asked you
whether you have ever accused him of telling lies before saying
what he said, and your reply was in the negative. Therefore, I took
for granted that a man who did not tell a lie about others, could
ever tell a lie about Allah. Then I asked you whether anyone of his
followers had renounced his religion (i.e. Islam) after embracing
it, being displeased with it, and you denied that. And such is
Faith when it mixes with the cheerfulness of the hearts. Then I
asked you whether his followers were increasing or decreasing. You
claimed that they were increasing. That is the way of true faith
till it is complete. Then I asked you whether you had ever fought
with him, and you claimed that you had fought with him and the
battle between you and him was undecided and the victory was shared
by you and him in turns; he inflicted casual ties upon you and you
inflicted casualties upon them. Such is the case with the Apostles;
they are out to test and the final victory is for them. Then I
asked you whether he had ever betrayed; you claimed that he had
never betrayed. I need, Apostles never betray. Then I asked you
whether anyone had said this statement before him; and you denied
that. Thereupon I thought if somebody had said that statement
before him, then I would have said that he was but a man copying
some sayings said before him." Abu Safyan said, "Heraclius then
asked me, 'What does he order you to do?' I said, 'He orders us (to
offer) prayers and (to pay) Zakat and to keep good relationship
with the Kith and kin and to be chaste.' Then Heraclius said, 'If
whatever you have said, is true, he is really a prophet, and I knew
that he ( i.e. the Prophet ) was going to appear, but I never
thought that he would be from amongst you. If I were certain that I
can reach him, I would like to meet him and if I were with him, I
would wash his feet; and his kingdom will expand (surely to what is
under my feet.' Then Heraclius asked for the letter of Allah's
Apostle and read it wherein was written: "In the Name of Allah, the
Most Beneficent, the Most Merciful. This letter is) from Muhammad,
Apostle of Allah, to Heraclius, the sovereign of Byzantine........
Peace be upon him who follows the Right Path. Now then, I call you
to embrace Islam. Embrace Islam and you will be saved (from Allah's
Punishment); embrace Islam, and Allah will give you a double
reward, but if you reject this, you will be responsible for the
sins of all the people of your kingdom (Allah's Statement):--"O the
people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Come to a word
common to you and us that we worship None but Allah....bear witness
that we are Muslims.' (3.64) When he finished reading the letter,
voices grew louder near him and there was a great hue and cry, and
we were ordered to go out." Abu Sufyan added, "While coming out, I
said to my companions, 'The situation of Ibn Abu Kabsha (i.e.
Muhammad) has become strong; even the king of Banu Al14 Asfar is
afraid of him.' So I continued to believe that Allah's Apostle
would be victorious, till Allah made me embrace Islam." Az-Zuhri
said, "Heraclius then invited all the chiefs of the Byzantines and
had them assembled in his house and said, 'O group of Byzantines!
Do you wish to have a permanent success and guidance and that your
kingdom should remain with you?' (Immediately after hearing that),
they rushed towards the gate like onagers, but they found them
closed. Heraclius then said, 'Bring them back to me.' So he called
them and said, 'I just wanted to test the strength of your
adherence to your religion. Now I have observed of you that which I
like.' Then the people fell in prostration before him and became
pleased with him." (See Hadith No. 6,Vol 1)</english-text>
</hadith>
