<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4401</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4608</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
عروة بن الزبير، أن أسامة بن زيد رضى الله عنهما أخبره أن رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ركب على حمار على قطيفة فدكية، وأردف أسامة بن زيد
وراءه، يعود سعد بن عبادة في بني الحارث بن الخزرج قبل وقعة بدر قال
حتى مر بمجلس فيه عبد الله بن أبى، ابن سلول، وذلك قبل أن يسلم عبد
الله بن أبى فإذا في المجلس أخلاط من المسلمين والمشركين عبدة الأوثان
واليهود والمسلمين، وفي المجلس عبد الله بن رواحة، فلما غشيت المجلس
عجاجة الدابة خمر عبد الله بن أبى أنفه بردائه، ثم قال لا تغبروا
علينا‏.‏ فسلم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عليهم ثم وقف فنزل فدعاهم
إلى الله، وقرأ عليهم القرآن، فقال عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول أيها
المرء، إنه لا أحسن مما تقول، إن كان حقا، فلا تؤذينا به في مجلسنا،
ارجع إلى رحلك، فمن جاءك فاقصص عليه‏.‏ فقال عبد الله بن رواحة بلى يا
رسول الله، فاغشنا به في مجالسنا، فإنا نحب ذلك‏.‏ فاستب المسلمون
والمشركون واليهود حتى كادوا يتثاورون، فلم يزل النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم يخفضهم حتى سكنوا، ثم ركب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم دابته فسار
حتى دخل على سعد بن عبادة، فقال له النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يا
سعد ألم تسمع ما قال أبو حباب ‏"‏‏.‏ يريد عبد الله بن أبى ‏"‏ قال
كذا وكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سعد بن عبادة يا رسول الله، اعف عنه واصفح عنه،
فوالذي أنزل عليك الكتاب، لقد جاء الله بالحق الذي أنزل عليك، لقد
اصطلح أهل هذه البحيرة على أن يتوجوه فيعصبونه بالعصابة، فلما أبى
الله ذلك بالحق الذي أعطاك الله شرق بذلك، فذلك فعل به ما رأيت‏.‏
فعفا عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وأصحابه يعفون عن المشركين وأهل الكتاب كما أمرهم الله، ويصبرون على
الأذى قال الله عز وجل ‏{‏ولتسمعن من الذين أوتوا الكتاب من قبلكم ومن
الذين أشركوا أذى كثيرا ‏}‏ الآية، وقال الله ‏{‏ود كثير من أهل
الكتاب لو يردونكم من بعد إيمانكم كفارا حسدا من عند أنفسهم‏}‏ إلى
آخر الآية، وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يتأول العفو ما أمره الله
به، حتى أذن الله فيهم، فلما غزا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بدرا،
فقتل الله به صناديد كفار قريش قال ابن أبى ابن سلول، ومن معه من
المشركين، وعبدة الأوثان هذا أمر قد توجه‏.‏ فبايعوا الرسول صلى الله
عليه وسلم على الإسلام فأسلموا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Usama bin Zaid: Allah's Apostle rode a
donkey, equipped with a thick cloth-covering made in Fadak and was
riding behind him. He was going to pay visit to Sa`d bin Ubada in
Banu Al-Harith bin Al-Khazraj; and this incident happened before
the battle of Badr. The Prophet passed by a gathering in which
`Abdullah bin Ubai bin Salul was present, and that was before
`Abdullah bin Ubai embraced Islam. Behold in that gathering there
were people of different religions: there were Muslims, pagans,
idol-worshippers and Jews, and in that gathering `Abdullah bin
Rawaha was also present. When a cloud of dust raised by the donkey
reached that gathering, `Abdullah bin Ubai covered his nose with
his garment and then said, "Do not cover us with dust." Then
Allah's Apostle greeted them and stopped and dismounted and invited
them to Allah (i.e. to embrace Islam) and recited to them the Holy
Qur'an. On that, `Abdullah bin Ubai bin Saluil said, "O man ! There
is nothing better than that what you say. If it is the truth, then
do not trouble us with it in our gatherings. Return to your mount
(or residence) and if somebody comes to you, relate (your tales) to
him." On that `Abdullah bin Rawaha said, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle!
Bring it (i.e. what you want to say) to us in our gathering, for we
love that." So the Muslims, the pagans and the Jews started abusing
one another till they were on the point of fighting with one
another. The Prophet kept on quietening them till they became
quiet, whereupon the Prophet rode his animal (mount) and proceeded
till he entered upon Sa`d bin Ubada. The Prophet said to Sa`d, "Did
you not hear what 'Abu Hub-b said?" He meant `Abdullah bin Ubai.
"He said so-andso." On that Sa`d bin Ubada said, "O Allah's
Apostle! Excuse and forgive him, for by Him Who revealed the Book
to you, Allah brought the Truth which was sent to you at the time
when the people of this town (i.e. Medina) had decided unanimously
to crown him and tie a turban on his head (electing him as chief).
But when Allah opposed that (decision) through the Truth which
Allah gave to you, he (i.e. `Abdullah bin Ubai) was grieved with
jealously. and that caused him to do what you have seen." So
Allah's Apostle excused him, for the Prophet and his companions
used to forgive the pagans and the people of Scripture as Allah had
ordered them, and they used to put up with their mischief with
patience. Allah said: "And you shall certainly hear much that will
grieve you from those who received the Scripture before you and
from the pagans........'(3.186) And Allah also said:--"Many of the
people of the Scripture wish if they could turn you away as
disbelievers after you have believed, from selfish envy.." (2.109)
So the Prophet used to stick to the principle of forgiveness for
them as long as Allah ordered him to do so till Allah permitted
fighting them. So when Allah's Apostle fought the battle of Badr
and Allah killed the nobles of Quraish infidels through him, Ibn
Ubai bin Salul and the pagans and idolaters who were with him,
said, "This matter (i.e. Islam) has appeared (i.e. became
victorious)." So they gave the pledge of allegiance (for embracing
Islam) to Allah's Apostle and became Muslims.</english-text>
</hadith>
