<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4407</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4614</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 30112, 20001, 11223, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا معن بن عيسى، حدثنا مالك،
عن مخرمة بن سليمان، عن كريب، مولى عبد الله بن عباس أن عبد الله بن
عباس، أخبره أنه، بات عند ميمونة زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وهى
خالته قال فاضطجعت في عرض الوسادة، واضطجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأهله في طولها، فنام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى انتصف
الليل، أو قبله بقليل، أو بعده بقليل، ثم استيقظ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فجعل يمسح النوم عن وجهه بيديه، ثم قرأ العشر الآيات
الخواتم من سورة آل عمران، ثم قام إلى شن معلقة فتوضأ منها، فأحسن
وضوءه، ثم قام يصلي، فصنعت مثل ما صنع، ثم ذهبت فقمت إلى جنبه، فوضع
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده اليمنى على رأسي، وأخذ بأذني بيده
اليمنى يفتلها، فصلى ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم
ركعتين، ثم ركعتين، ثم أوتر، ثم اضطجع حتى جاءه المؤذن، فقام فصلى
ركعتين خفيفتين، ثم خرج فصلى الصبح‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: That once he stayed
overnight (in the house) of his aunt Maimuna. the wife of the
Prophet. He added: I lay on the cushion transversely and Allah's
Apostle lay along with his wife in the lengthwise direction of the
pillow. Allah's Apostle slept till the middle of the night, either
a bit before or a bit after it, and then woke up rubbing the traces
of sleep off his face with his hands and then he recited the last
ten Verses of Surat-al-`Imran, got up and went to a hanging water
skin. He then performed the ablution from it, and it was perfect
ablution, and then stood up to offer the prayer. I too did the same
as he had done, and then went to stand beside him. Allah's Apostle
put his right hand on my head and held and twisted my right ear. He
then offered two rak`at, then two rak`at, then two rak`at, then two
rak`at, then two rak`at. then two rak`at, and finally one rak`a,
the witr. Then he lay down again till the Muadhdhin (i.e. the
call-maker) came to him, whereupon he got up and offered a light
two-rak`at prayer, and went out (to the Mosque) and offered the
(compulsory congregational) Fajr prayer.</english-text>
</hadith>
