<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4410</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4617</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20150, 11176, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله، حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد، عن
صالح بن كيسان، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أنه سأل
عائشة عن قول الله، تعالى ‏{‏وإن خفتم أن لا تقسطوا في اليتامى‏}‏‏.‏
فقالت يا ابن أختي، هذه اليتيمة تكون في حجر وليها، تشركه في ماله
ويعجبه مالها وجمالها، فيريد وليها أن يتزوجها، بغير أن يقسط في
صداقها، فيعطيها مثل ما يعطيها غيره، فنهوا عن أن ينكحوهن، إلا أن
يقسطوا لهن، ويبلغوا لهن أعلى سنتهن في الصداق، فأمروا أن ينكحوا ما
طاب لهم من النساء سواهن‏.‏ قال عروة قالت عائشة وإن الناس استفتوا
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعد هذه الآية فأنزل الله ‏{‏ويستفتونك
في النساء‏}‏ قالت عائشة وقول الله تعالى في آية أخرى ‏{‏وترغبون أن
تنكحوهن‏}‏ رغبة أحدكم عن يتيمته حين تكون قليلة المال والجمال قالت
فنهوا أن ينكحوا عن من رغبوا في ماله وجماله في يتامى النساء، إلا
بالقسط، من أجل رغبتهم عنهن إذا كن قليلات المال
والجمال‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa bin Az-Zubair: That he asked `Aisha
regarding the Statement of Allah: "If you fear that you shall not
be able to deal justly with the orphan girls..." (4.3) She said, "O
son of my sister! An Orphan girl used to be under the care of a
guardian with whom she shared property. Her guardian, being
attracted by her wealth and beauty, would intend to marry her
without giving her a just Mahr, i.e. the same Mahr as any other
person might give her (in case he married her). So such guardians
were forbidden to do that unless they did justice to their female
wards and gave them the highest Mahr their peers might get. They
were ordered (by Allah, to marry women of their choice other than
those orphan girls." `Aisha added," The people asked Allah's
Apostle his instructions after the revelation of this Divine Verse
whereupon Allah revealed: "They ask your instruction regarding
women " (4.127) `Aisha further said, "And the Statement of Allah:
"And yet whom you desire to marry." (4.127) as anyone of you
refrains from marrying an orphan girl (under his guardianship) when
she is lacking in property and beauty." `Aisha added, "So they were
forbidden to marry those orphan girls for whose wealth and beauty
they had a desire unless with justice, and that was because they
would refrain from marrying them if they were lacking in property
and beauty."</english-text>
</hadith>
