<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4443</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4650</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 10530, 10535, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن عبد الرحمن بن
القاسم، عن أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها زوج النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم قالت خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في بعض أسفاره، حتى
إذا كنا بالبيداء أو بذات الجيش انقطع عقد لي، فأقام رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم على التماسه، وأقام الناس معه، وليسوا على ماء، وليس
معهم ماء فأتى الناس إلى أبي بكر الصديق فقالوا ألا ترى ما صنعت عائشة
أقامت برسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وبالناس، وليسوا على ماء، وليس
معهم ماء، فجاء أبو بكر ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم واضع رأسه على
فخذي قد نام، فقال حبست رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس، وليسوا
على ماء، وليس معهم ماء قالت عائشة فعاتبني أبو بكر، وقال ما شاء الله
أن يقول، وجعل يطعنني بيده في خاصرتي، ولا يمنعني من التحرك إلا مكان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على فخذي، فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حتى أصبح على غير ماء، فأنزل الله آية التيمم فقال أسيد بن حضير
ما هي بأول بركتكم يا آل أبي بكر‏.‏ قالت فبعثنا البعير الذي كنت عليه
فإذا العقد تحته‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Aisha: The wife of the Prophet : We set out
with Allah's Apostle on one of his journeys, and when we were at
Baida' or at Dhat-al-Jaish, a necklace of mine was broken (and
lost). Allah's Apostle stayed there to look for it, and so did the
people along with him. Neither were they at a place of water, nor
did they have any water with them. So the people went to Abu Bakr
As-Siddiq and said, "Don't you see what `Aisha has done? She has
made Allah's Apostle and the people, stay where there is no water
and they have no water with them." Abu Bakr came while Allah's
Apostle was sleeping with his head on my thigh. He said (to me),
"You have detained Allah's Apostle and the people where there is no
water, and they have no water with them." So he admonished me and
said what Allah wished him to say, and he hit me on my flanks with
his hand. Nothing prevented me from moving (because of pain! but
the position of Allah's Apostle on my thigh. So Allah's Apostle got
up when dawn broke and there was no water, so Allah revealed the
Verse of Tayammum. Usaid bin Hudair said, "It is not the first
blessing of yours, O the family of Abu Bakr." Then we made the
camel on which I was riding, got up, and found the necklace under
it.</english-text>
</hadith>
