<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4478</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4685</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>20025, 30587, 30218, 20733, 20399, 11412,
11027</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله، حدثنا سليمان بن عبد الرحمن، وموسى بن
هارون، قالا حدثنا الوليد بن مسلم، حدثنا عبد الله بن العلاء بن زبر،
قال حدثني بسر بن عبيد الله، قال حدثني أبو إدريس الخولاني، قال سمعت
أبا الدرداء، يقول كانت بين أبي بكر وعمر محاورة، فأغضب أبو بكر عمر،
فانصرف عنه عمر مغضبا، فاتبعه أبو بكر يسأله أن يستغفر له، فلم يفعل
حتى أغلق بابه في وجهه، فأقبل أبو بكر إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم فقال أبو الدرداء ونحن عنده فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ أما صاحبكم هذا فقد غامر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال وندم عمر على ما كان منه
فأقبل حتى سلم وجلس إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وقص على رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم الخبر‏.‏ قال أبو الدرداء وغضب رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وجعل أبو بكر يقول والله يا رسول الله لأنا كنت أظلم فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هل أنتم تاركو لي صاحبي هل أنتم
تاركو لي صاحبي إني قلت يا أيها الناس إني رسول الله إليكم جميعا
فقلتم كذبت‏.‏ وقال أبو بكر صدقت ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Ad-Darda: There was a dispute between
Abu Bakr and `Umar, and Abu Bakr made `Umar angry. So `Umar left
angrily. Abu Bakr followed him, requesting him to ask forgiveness
(of Allah) for him, but `Umar refused to do so and closed his door
in Abu Bakr's face. So Abu Bakr went to Allah's Apostle while we
were with him. Allah's Apostle said, "This friend of yours must
have quarrelled (with somebody)." In the meantime `Umar repented
and felt sorry for what he had done, so he came, greeted (those who
were present) and sat with the Prophet and related the story to
him. Allah's Apostle became angry and Abu Bakr started saying, "O
Allah's Apostle! By Allah, I was more at fault (than `Umar)."
Allah's Apostle said, "Are you (people) leaving for me my
companion? (Abu Bakr), Are you (people) leaving for me my
companion? When I said, 'O people I am sent to you all as the
Apostle of Allah,' you said, 'You tell a lie.' while Abu Bakr said,
'You have spoken the truth ."</english-text>
</hadith>
