<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4480</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4687</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، أن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال قدم
عيينة بن حصن بن حذيفة فنزل على ابن أخيه الحر بن قيس، وكان من النفر
الذين يدنيهم عمر، وكان القراء أصحاب مجالس عمر ومشاورته كهولا كانوا
أو شبانا‏.‏ فقال عيينة لابن أخيه يا ابن أخي، لك وجه عند هذا الأمير
فاستأذن لي عليه‏.‏ قال سأستأذن لك عليه‏.‏ قال ابن عباس فاستأذن الحر
لعيينة فأذن له عمر، فلما دخل عليه قال هي يا ابن الخطاب، فوالله ما
تعطينا الجزل، ولا تحكم بيننا بالعدل‏.‏ فغضب عمر حتى هم به، فقال له
الحر يا أمير المؤمنين إن الله تعالى قال لنبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏{‏خذ العفو وأمر بالعرف وأعرض عن الجاهلين‏}‏ وإن هذا من الجاهلين‏.‏
والله ما جاوزها عمر حين تلاها عليه، وكان وقافا عند كتاب
الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: 'Uyaina bin Hisn bin Hudhaifa
came and stayed with his nephew Al-Hurr bin Qais who was one of
those whom `Umar used to keep near him, as the Qurra' (learned men
knowing Qur'an by heart) were the people of `Umar's meetings and
his advisors whether they were old or young. 'Uyaina said to his
nephew, "O son of my brother! You have an approach to this chief,
so get for me the permission to see him." Al-Hurr said, "I will get
the permission for you to see him." So Al-Hurr asked the permission
for 'Uyaina and `Umar admitted him. When 'Uyaina entered upon him,
he said, "Beware! O the son of Al-Khattab! By Allah, you neither
give us sufficient provision nor judge among us with justice."
Thereupon `Umar became so furious that he intended to harm him, but
Al-Hurr said, "O chief of the Believers! Allah said to His Prophet:
"Hold to forgiveness; command what is right; and leave (don't
punish) the foolish." (7.199) and this (i.e. 'Uyaina) is one of the
foolish." By Allah, `Umar did not overlook that Verse when Al-Hurr
recited it before him; he observed (the orders of) Allah's Book
strictly.</english-text>
</hadith>
