<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4535</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4741</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20150, 11176, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله، حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد، عن
صالح، عن ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة رضى الله
عنها قالت له وهو يسألها عن قول الله تعالى ‏{‏حتى إذا استيأس
الرسل‏}‏ قال قلت أكذبوا أم كذبوا قالت عائشة كذبوا‏.‏ قلت فقد
استيقنوا أن قومهم كذبوهم فما هو بالظن قالت أجل لعمري لقد استيقنوا
بذلك‏.‏ فقلت لها وظنوا أنهم قد كذبوا قالت معاذ الله لم تكن الرسل
تظن ذلك بربها‏.‏ قلت فما هذه الآية‏.‏ قالت هم أتباع الرسل الذين
آمنوا بربهم وصدقوهم، فطال عليهم البلاء، واستأخر عنهم النصر حتى
استيأس الرسل ممن كذبهم من قومهم وظنت الرسل أن أتباعهم قد كذبوهم
جاءهم نصر الله عند ذلك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Urwa bin Az-Zubair: That when he asked
`Aisha about the statement of Allah "Until when the Apostles gave
up hope (of their people)." (12.110) she told him (its meaning),
`Urwa added, "I said, 'Did they (Apostles) suspect that they were
betrayed (by Allah) or that they were treated as liars by (their
people)?' `Aisha said, '(They suspected) that they were treated as
liars by (their people),' I said, 'But they were sure that their
people treated them as liars and it was not a matter of suspicion.'
She said, 'Yes, upon my life they were sure about it.' I said to
her. 'So they (Apostles) suspected that they were betrayed (by
Allah).' She said, "Allah forbid! The Apostles never suspected
their Lord of such a thing.' I said, 'What about this Verse then?'
She said, 'It is about the Apostles' followers who believed in
their Lord and trusted their Apostles, but the period of trials was
prolonged and victory was delayed till the Apostles gave up all
hope of converting those of the people who disbelieved them and the
Apostles thought that their followers treated them as liars;
thereupon Allah's help came to them.</english-text>
</hadith>
