<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4554</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4759</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30118, 20025, 11404, 11406, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن مقاتل، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا أبو حيان
التيمي، عن أبي زرعة بن عمرو بن جرير، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال
أتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بلحم، فرفع إليه الذراع، وكانت
تعجبه، فنهس منها نهسة ثم قال ‏"‏ أنا سيد الناس يوم القيامة، وهل
تدرون مم ذلك يجمع الناس الأولين والآخرين في صعيد واحد، يسمعهم
الداعي، وينفذهم البصر، وتدنو الشمس، فيبلغ الناس من الغم والكرب ما
لا يطيقون ولا يحتملون فيقول الناس ألا ترون ما قد بلغكم ألا تنظرون
من يشفع لكم إلى ربكم فيقول بعض الناس لبعض عليكم بآدم فيأتون آدم
عليه السلام فيقولون له أنت أبو البشر خلقك الله بيده‏.‏ ونفخ فيك من
روحه، وأمر الملائكة فسجدوا لك، اشفع لنا إلى ربك، ألا ترى إلى ما نحن
فيه ألا ترى إلى ما قد بلغنا فيقول آدم إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم
يغضب قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله، وإنه نهاني عن الشجرة فعصيته،
نفسي نفسي نفسي، اذهبوا إلى غيري، اذهبوا إلى نوح، فيأتون نوحا
فيقولون يا نوح إنك أنت أول الرسل إلى أهل الأرض، وقد سماك الله عبدا
شكورا اشفع لنا إلى ربك، ألا ترى إلى ما نحن فيه فيقول إن ربي عز وجل
قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله، ولن يغضب بعده مثله، وإنه قد
كانت لي دعوة دعوتها على قومي نفسي نفسي نفسي اذهبوا إلى غيري، اذهبوا
إلى إبراهيم، فيأتون إبراهيم، فيقولون يا إبراهيم، أنت نبي الله
وخليله من أهل الأرض اشفع لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى إلى ما نحن فيه فيقول
لهم إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله ولن يغضب بعده مثله،
وإني قد كنت كذبت ثلاث كذبات فذكرهن أبو حيان في الحديث نفسي نفسي
نفسي، اذهبوا إلى غيري اذهبوا إلى موسى، فيأتون موسى، فيقولون يا موسى
أنت رسول الله، فضلك الله برسالته وبكلامه على الناس، اشفع لنا إلى
ربك ألا ترى إلى ما نحن فيه فيقول إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب
قبله مثله، ولن يغضب بعده مثله، وإني قد قتلت نفسا لم أومر بقتلها،
نفسي نفسي نفسي، اذهبوا إلى غيري، اذهبوا إلى عيسى، فيأتون عيسى
فيقولون يا عيسى أنت رسول الله وكلمته ألقاها إلى مريم وروح منه،
وكلمت الناس في المهد صبيا اشفع لنا ألا ترى إلى ما نحن فيه فيقول
عيسى إن ربي قد غضب اليوم غضبا لم يغضب قبله مثله، ولن يغضب بعده مثله
ولم يذكر ذنبا نفسي نفسي نفسي، اذهبوا إلى غيري اذهبوا إلى محمد صلى
الله عليه وسلم فيأتون محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم فيقولون يا محمد أنت
رسول الله وخاتم الأنبياء، وقد غفر الله لك ما تقدم من ذنبك وما تأخر،
اشفع لنا إلى ربك ألا ترى إلى ما نحن فيه فأنطلق فآتي تحت العرش، فأقع
ساجدا لربي عز وجل ثم يفتح الله على من محامده وحسن الثناء عليه شيئا
لم يفتحه على أحد قبلي ثم يقال يا محمد ارفع رأسك، سل تعطه، واشفع
تشفع، فأرفع رأسي، فأقول أمتي يا رب، أمتي يا رب فيقال يا محمد أدخل
من أمتك من لا حساب عليهم من الباب الأيمن من أبواب الجنة وهم شركاء
الناس فيما سوى ذلك من الأبواب، ثم قال والذي نفسي بيده إن ما بين
المصراعين من مصاريع الجنة كما بين مكة وحمير، أو كما بين مكة وبصرى
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Some (cooked) meat was brought
to Allah Apostle and the meat of a forearm was presented to him as
he used to like it. He ate a morsel of it and said, "I will be the
chief of all the people on the Day of Resurrection. Do you know the
reason for it? Allah will gather all the human being of early
generations as well as late generation on one plain so that the
announcer will be able to make them all-hear his voice and the
watcher will be able to see all of them. The sun will come so close
to the people that they will suffer such distress and trouble as
they will not be able to bear or stand. Then the people will say,
'Don't you see to what state you have reached? Won't you look for
someone who can intercede for you with your Lord' Some people will
say to some others, 'Go to Adam.' So they will go to Adam and say
to him. 'You are the father of mankind; Allah created you with His
Own Hand, and breathed into you of His Spirit (meaning the spirit
which he created for you); and ordered the angels to prostrate
before you; so (please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you
see in what state we are? Don't you see what condition we have
reached?' Adam will say, 'Today my Lord has become angry as He has
never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. He forbade me
(to eat of the fruit of) the tree, but I disobeyed Him . Myself!
Myself! Myself! (I am preoccuied with my own problems). Go to
someone else; go to Noah.' So they will go to Noah and say (to
him), 'O Noah! You are the first (of Allah's Messengers) to the
people of the earth, and Allah has named you a thankful slave;
please intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what state
we are?' He will say.' Today my Lord has become angry as He has
never become nor will ever become thereafter. I had (in the world)
the right to make one definitely accepted invocation, and I made it
against my nation. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go
to Abraham.' They will go to Abraham and say, 'O Abraham! You are
Allah's Apostle and His Khalil from among the people of the earth;
so please intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in what
state we are?' He will say to them, 'My Lord has today become angry
as He has never become before, nor will ever become thereafter. I
had told three lies (Abu Haiyan (the sub-narrator) mentioned them
in the Hadith) Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to
Moses.' The people will then go to Moses and say, 'O Moses! You art
Allah's Apostle and Allah gave you superiority above the others
with this message and with His direct Talk to you; (please)
intercede for us with your Lord Don't you see in what state we
are?' Moses will say, 'My Lord has today become angry as He has
never become before, nor will become thereafter, I killed a person
whom I had not been ordered to kill. Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to
someone else; go to Jesus.' So they will go to Jesus and say, 'O
Jesus! You are Allah's Apostle and His Word which He sent to Mary,
and a superior soul created by Him, and you talked to the people
while still young in the cradle. Please intercede for us with your
Lord. Don't you see in what state we are?' Jesus will say. 'My Lord
has today become angry as He has never become before nor will ever
become thereafter. Jesus will not mention any sin, but will say,
'Myself! Myself! Myself! Go to someone else; go to Muhammad.' So
they will come to me and say, 'O Muhammad ! You are Allah's Apostle
and the last of the prophets, and Allah forgave your early and late
sins. (Please) intercede for us with your Lord. Don't you see in
what state we are?" The Prophet added, "Then I will go beneath
Allah's Throne and fall in prostration before my Lord. And then
Allah will guide me to such praises and glorification to Him as He
has never guided anybody else before me. Then it will be said, 'O
Muhammad Raise your head. Ask, and it will be granted. Intercede
and It (your intercession) will be accepted.' So I will raise my
head and Say, 'My followers, O my Lord! My followers, O my Lord'.
It will be said, 'O Muhammad! Let those of your followers who have
no accounts, enter through such a gate of the gates of Paradise as
lies on the right; and they will share the other gates with the
people." The Prophet further said, "By Him in Whose Hand my soul
is, the distance between every two gate-posts of Paradise is like
the distance between Mecca and Busra (in Sham).</english-text>
</hadith>
