<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4583</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4788</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30204, 20317, 11060, 19291, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمر بن حفص، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا الأعمش، حدثنا أبو
صالح، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يقول
الله عز وجل يوم القيامة يا آدم‏.‏ يقول لبيك ربنا وسعديك، فينادى
بصوت إن الله يأمرك أن تخرج من ذريتك بعثا إلى النار‏.‏ قال يا رب وما
بعث النار قال من كل ألف أراه قال تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعين فحينئذ تضع
الحامل حملها ويشيب الوليد ‏{‏وترى الناس سكارى وما هم بسكارى ولكن
عذاب الله شديد‏}‏ ‏"‏‏.‏ فشق ذلك على الناس حتى تغيرت وجوههم، فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من يأجوج ومأجوج تسعمائة وتسعة وتسعين،
ومنكم واحد، ثم أنتم في الناس كالشعرة السوداء في جنب الثور الأبيض،
أو كالشعرة البيضاء في جنب الثور الأسود، وإني لأرجو أن تكونوا ربع
أهل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا ثم قال ‏"‏ ثلث أهل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا ثم
قال ‏"‏ شطر أهل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فكبرنا‏.‏ قال أبو أسامة عن الأعمش
‏{‏ترى الناس سكارى وما هم بسكارى‏}‏ وقال من كل ألف تسعمائة وتسعة
وتسعين‏.‏ وقال جرير وعيسى بن يونس وأبو معاوية ‏{‏سكرى وما هم
بسكرى‏}‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: The Prophet said, "On
the day of Resurrection Allah will say, 'O Adam!' Adam will reply,
'Labbaik our Lord, and Sa`daik ' Then there will be a loud call
(saying), Allah orders you to take from among your offspring a
mission for the (Hell) Fire.' Adam will say, 'O Lord! Who are the
mission for the (Hell) Fire?' Allah will say, 'Out of each
thousand, take out 999.' At that time every pregnant female shall
drop her load (have a miscarriage) and a child will have grey hair.
And you shall see mankind as in a drunken state, yet not drunk, but
severe will be the torment of Allah." (22.2) (When the Prophet
mentioned this), the people were so distressed (and afraid) that
their faces got changed (in color) whereupon the Prophet said,
"From Gog and Magog nine-hundred ninety-nine will be taken out and
one from you. You Muslims (compared to the large number of other
people) will be like a black hair on the side of a white ox, or a
white hair on the side of a black ox, and I hope that you will be
onefourth of the people of Paradise." On that, we said,
"Allahu-Akbar!" Then he said, "I hope that you will be) one-third
of the people of Paradise." We again said, "Allahu-Akbar!" Then he
said, "(I hope that you will be) one-half of the people of
Paradise." So we said, Allahu Akbar."</english-text>
</hadith>
