<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4587</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4792</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30312, 30388, 20024, 11013, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق، حدثنا محمد بن يوسف، حدثنا الأوزاعي، قال
حدثني الزهري، عن سهل بن سعد، أن عويمرا، أتى عاصم بن عدي وكان سيد
بني عجلان فقال كيف تقولون في رجل وجد مع امرأته رجلا، أيقتله
فتقتلونه أم كيف يصنع سل لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن ذلك فأتى
عاصم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله، فكره رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم المسائل، فسأله عويمر فقال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم كره المسائل وعابها، قال عويمر والله لا أنتهي حتى أسأل رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عن ذلك فجاء عويمر فقال يا رسول الله رجل وجد
مع امرأته رجلا، أيقتله فتقتلونه أم كيف يصنع فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد أنزل الله القرآن فيك وفي صاحبتك ‏"‏‏.‏ فأمرهما
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالملاعنة بما سمى الله في كتابه،
فلاعنها ثم قال يا رسول الله، إن حبستها فقد ظلمتها، فطلقها، فكانت
سنة لمن كان بعدهما في المتلاعنين، ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ انظروا فإن جاءت به أسحم أدعج العينين عظيم الأليتين خدلج
الساقين فلا أحسب عويمرا إلا قد صدق عليها، وإن جاءت به أحيمر كأنه
وحرة فلا أحسب عويمرا، إلا قد كذب عليها ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاءت به على النعت
الذي نعت به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من تصديق عويمر، فكان بعد
ينسب إلى أمه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Saud: 'Uwaimir came to `Asim bin
`Adi who was the chief of Bani Ajlan and said, "What do you say
about a man who has found another man with his wife? Should he kill
him whereupon you would kill him (i.e. the husband), or what should
he do? Please ask Allah's Apostle about this matter on my behalf."
`Asim then went to the Prophet and said, "O Allah's Apostle! (And
asked him that question) but Allah's Apostle disliked the
question," When 'Uwaimir asked `Asim (about the Prophet's answer)
`Asim replied that Allah's Apostle disliked such questions and
considered it shameful. "Uwaimir then said, "By Allah, I will not
give up asking unless I ask Allah's Apostle about it." Uwaimir came
(to the Prophet ) and said, "O Allah's Apostle! A man has found
another man with his wife! Should he kill him whereupon you would
kill him (the husband, in Qisas) or what should he do?" Allah's
Apostle said, "Allah has revealed regarding you and your wife's
case in the Qur'an "So Allah's Apostle ordered them to perform the
measures of Mula'ana according to what Allah had mentioned in His
Book. So 'Uwaimir did Mula'ana with her and said, "O Allah's
Apostle! If I kept her I would oppress her." So 'Uwaimir divorced
her and so divorce became a tradition after them for those who
happened to be involved in a case of Mula'ana. Allah's Apostle then
said, "Look! If she (Uwaimir's wife) delivers a black child with
deep black large eyes, big hips and fat legs, then I will be of the
opinion that 'Uwaimir has spoken the truth; but if she delivers a
red child looking like a Wahra then we will consider that 'Uwaimir
has told a lie against her." Later on she delivered a child
carrying the qualities which Allah's Apostle had mentioned as a
proof for 'Uwaimir's claim; therefore the child was ascribed to its
mother henceforth.</english-text>
</hadith>
