<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4616</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4821</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>28531, 20012, 11067, 11060, 11392, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن كثير، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا منصور، والأعمش،
عن أبي الضحى، عن مسروق، قال بينما رجل يحدث في كندة فقال يجيء دخان
يوم القيامة فيأخذ بأسماع المنافقين وأبصارهم، يأخذ المؤمن كهيئة
الزكام‏.‏ ففزعنا، فأتيت ابن مسعود، وكان متكئا، فغضب فجلس فقال من
علم فليقل، ومن لم يعلم فليقل الله أعلم‏.‏ فإن من العلم أن يقول لما
لا يعلم لا أعلم‏.‏ فإن الله قال لنبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏{‏قل ما
أسألكم عليه من أجر وما أنا من المتكلفين‏}‏ وإن قريشا أبطئوا عن
الإسلام فدعا عليهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ اللهم أعني
عليهم بسبع كسبع يوسف، فأخذتهم سنة حتى هلكوا فيها، وأكلوا الميتة
والعظام ويرى الرجل ما بين السماء والأرض كهيئة الدخان ‏"‏، فجاءه أبو
سفيان فقال يا محمد جئت تأمرنا بصلة الرحم، وإن قومك قد هلكوا فادع
الله، فقرأ ‏{‏فارتقب يوم تأتي السماء بدخان مبين‏}‏ إلى قوله
‏{‏عائدون‏}‏ أفيكشف عنهم عذاب الآخرة إذا جاء ثم عادوا إلى كفرهم
فذلك قوله تعالى ‏{‏يوم نبطش البطشة الكبرى‏}‏ يوم بدر ولزاما يوم بدر
‏{‏الم * غلبت الروم‏}‏ إلى ‏{‏سيغلبون‏}‏ والروم قد
مضى‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Masruq: While a man was delivering a speech
in the tribe of Kinda, he said, "Smoke will prevail on the Day of
Resurrection and will deprive the hypocrites their faculties of
hearing and seeing. The believers will be afflicted with something
like cold only thereof." That news scared us, so I went to
(Abdullah) Ibn Mas`ud while he was reclining (and told him the
story) whereupon he became angry, sat up and said, "He who knows a
thing can say, it, but if he does not know, he should say, 'Allah
knows best,' for it is an aspect of knowledge to say, 'I do not
know,' if you do not know a certain thing. Allah said to His
prophet. 'Say (O Muhammad): No wage do I ask of you for this
(Qur'an), nor I am one of the pretenders (a person who pretends
things which do not exist.)' (38.86) The Qur'aish delayed in
embracing Islam for a period, so the Prophet invoked evil on them,
saying, 'O Allah! Help me against them by sending seven years of
(famine) like those of Joseph.' So they were afflicted with such a
severe year of famine that they were destroyed therein and ate dead
animals and bones. They started seeing something like smoke between
the sky and the earth (because of severe hunger). Abu Sufyan then
came (to the Prophet) and said, "O Muhammad! You came to order us
for to keep good relations with Kith and kin, and your kinsmen have
now perished, so please invoke Allah (to relieve them).' Then Ibn
Mas`ud recited:-- 'Then watch you for the day that the sky will
bring forth a kind of smoke plainly visible....but truly you will
return! (to disbelief) (44.10-15) Ibn Mas`ud added, Then the
punishment was stopped, but truly, they reverted to heathenism
(their old way). So Allah (threatened them thus): 'On the day when
we shall seize you with a mighty grasp.' (44.16) And that was the
day of the Battle of Badr. Allah's saying- "Lizama" (the
punishment) refers to the day of Badr Allah's Statement:
Alif-Lam-Mim, the Romans have been defeated, and they, after their
defeat, will be victorious,' (30.1- 3) (This verse): Indicates that
the defeat of Byzantine has already passed.</english-text>
</hadith>
