<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4665</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4870</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30020, 20354, 11060, 20285, 11018</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى، حدثنا أبو معاوية، عن الأعمش، عن مسلم، عن
مسروق، قال قال عبد الله إنما كان هذا لأن قريشا لما استعصوا على
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم دعا عليهم بسنين كسني يوسف، فأصابهم قحط
وجهد حتى أكلوا العظام، فجعل الرجل ينظر إلى السماء فيرى ما بينه
وبينها كهيئة الدخان من الجهد، فأنزل الله تعالى ‏{‏فارتقب يوم تأتي
السماء بدخان مبين * يغشى الناس هذا عذاب أليم‏}‏ قال فأتي رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقيل يا رسول الله استسق الله لمضر، فإنها قد
هلكت‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لمضر إنك لجريء ‏"‏‏.‏ فاستسقى فسقوا‏.‏ فنزلت
‏{‏إنكم عائدون‏}‏ فلما أصابتهم الرفاهية عادوا إلى حالهم حين أصابتهم
الرفاهية‏.‏ فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏يوم نبطش البطشة الكبرى إنا
منتقمون‏}‏ قال يعني يوم بدر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah: It (i.e., the imagined smoke) was
because, when the Quraish refused to obey the Prophet, he asked
Allah to afflict them with years of famine similar to those of
(Prophet) Joseph. So they were stricken with famine and fatigue, so
much so that they ate even bones. A man would look towards the sky
and imagine seeing something like smoke between him and the sky
because of extreme fatigue. So Allah revealed:-- 'Then watch you
for the Day that the sky will bring forth a kind of smoke plainly
visible, covering the people; this is a painfull of torment.'
(44.10-11) Then someone (Abu Sufyan) came to Allah's Apostle and
said, "O Allah's Apostle! Invoke Allah to send rain for the tribes
of Mudar for they are on the verge of destruction." On that the
Prophet said (astonishingly) "Shall I invoke Allah) for the tribes
of Mudar? Verily, you are a brave man!" But the Prophet prayed for
rain and it rained for them. Then the Verse was revealed. 'But
truly you will return (to disbelief).' (44.15) (When the famine was
over and) they restored prosperity and welfare, they reverted to
their ways (of heathenism) whereupon Allah revealed: 'On the Day
when We shall seize you with a Mighty Grasp. We will indeed (then)
exact retribution.' (44.16) The narrator said, "That was the day of
the Battle of Badr."</english-text>
</hadith>
