<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4668</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4873</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30126, 20278, 20020, 11060, 11067, 11392, 11018,
16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا بشر بن خالد، أخبرنا محمد، عن شعبة، عن سليمان،
ومنصور، عن أبي الضحى، عن مسروق، قال قال عبد الله إن الله بعث محمدا
صلى الله عليه وسلم وقال ‏{‏قل ما أسألكم عليه من أجر وما أنا من
المتكلفين‏}‏ فإن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لما رأى قريشا استعصوا
عليه فقال ‏"‏ اللهم أعني عليهم بسبع كسبع يوسف ‏"‏‏.‏ فأخذتهم السنة
حتى حصت كل شىء حتى أكلوا العظام والجلود فقال أحدهم حتى أكلوا الجلود
والميتة وجعل يخرج من الأرض كهيئة الدخان فأتاه أبو سفيان فقال أى
محمد إن قومك قد هلكوا فادع الله أن يكشف عنهم فدعا ثم قال ‏"‏ تعودوا
بعد هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ في حديث منصور ثم قرأ ‏{‏فارتقب يوم تأتي السماء بدخان
مبين‏}‏ إلى ‏{‏عائدون‏}‏ أيكشف عذاب الآخرة فقد مضى الدخان والبطشة
واللزام وقال أحدهم القمر وقال الآخر الروم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah: Allah sent (the Prophet) Muhammad
and said:-- 'Say, No wage do I ask of you for this (Qur'an) nor am
I one of the pretenders (i.e. a person who pretends things which do
not exist). (38.68) When Allah's Apostle saw Quraish standing
against him, he said, "O Allah! Help me against them by afflicting
them with seven years of famine similar to the seven years (of
famine) of Joseph. So they were afflicted with a year of drought
that destroyed everything, and they ate bones and hides. (One of
them said), "And they ate hides and dead animals, and (it seemed to
them that) something like smoke was coming out of the earth. So Abu
Sufyan came to the Prophet and said, "O Muhammad! Your people are
on the verge of destruction! Please invoke Allah to relieve them."
So the Prophet invoked Allah for them (and the famine disappeared).
He said to them. "You will revert (to heathenism) after that."
`Abdullah then recited: 'Then watch you for the Day that the sky
will bring forth a kind of smoke plainly visible.......but truly
you will revert (to disbelief).' He added, "Will the punishment be
removed from them in the Hereafter? The smoke and the grasp and the
Al-Lizam have all passed." One of the sub-narrater said, "The
splitting of the moon." And another said, "The defeat of the Romans
(has passed).</english-text>
</hadith>
