<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4728</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4935</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30388, 20005, 11067, 11051, 11017, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن يوسف، حدثنا سفيان، عن منصور، عن إبراهيم،
عن علقمة، عن عبد الله، قال لعن الله الواشمات والموتشمات والمتنمصات
والمتفلجات للحسن المغيرات خلق الله‏.‏ فبلغ ذلك امرأة من بني أسد
يقال لها أم يعقوب، فجاءت فقالت إنه بلغني أنك لعنت كيت وكيت‏.‏ فقال
وما لي لا ألعن من لعن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ومن هو في كتاب
الله فقالت لقد قرأت ما بين اللوحين فما وجدت فيه ما تقول‏.‏ قال لئن
كنت قرأتيه لقد وجدتيه، أما قرأت ‏{‏وما آتاكم الرسول فخذوه وما نهاكم
عنه فانتهوا‏}‏‏.‏ قالت بلى‏.‏ قال فإنه قد نهى عنه‏.‏ قالت فإني أرى
أهلك يفعلونه‏.‏ قال فاذهبي فانظري‏.‏ فذهبت فنظرت فلم تر من حاجتها
شيئا، فقال لو كانت كذلك ما جامعتنا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Alqama: `Abdullah (bin Masud) said. "Allah
curses those ladies who practice tattooing and those who get
themselves tattooed, and those ladies who remove the hair from
their faces and those who make artificial spaces between their
teeth in order to look more beautiful whereby they change Allah's
creation." His saying reached a lady from Bani Asd called Um Yaqub
who came (to `Abdullah) and said, "I have come to know that you
have cursed such-and-such (ladies)?" He replied, "Why should I not
curse these whom Allah's Apostle has cursed and who are (cursed) in
Allah's Book!" Um Yaqub said, "I have read the whole Qur'an, but I
did not find in it what you say." He said, "Verily, if you have
read it (i.e. the Qur'an), you have found it. Didn't you read: 'And
whatsoever the Apostle gives you take it and whatsoever he forbids
you, you abstain (from it). (59.7) She replied, "Yes, I did," He
said, "Verily, Allah's Apostle forbade such things." "She said,
"But I see your wife doing these things?" He said, "Go and watch
her." She went and watched her but could not see anything in
support of her statement. On that he said, "If my wife was as you
thought, I would not keep her in my company."</english-text>
</hadith>
