<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4731</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4938</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>20184, 20318, 20349, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني يعقوب بن إبراهيم بن كثير، حدثنا أبو أسامة، حدثنا
فضيل بن غزوان، حدثنا أبو حازم الأشجعي، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه
قال أتى رجل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال يا رسول الله أصابني
الجهد فأرسل إلى نسائه فلم يجد عندهن شيئا، فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ألا رجل يضيف هذه الليلة يرحمه الله ‏"‏‏.‏ فقام رجل من
الأنصار فقال أنا يا رسول الله‏.‏ فذهب إلى أهله فقال لامرأته ضيف
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا تدخريه شيئا‏.‏ قالت والله ما عندي
إلا قوت الصبية‏.‏ قال فإذا أراد الصبية العشاء فنوميهم، وتعالى
فأطفئي السراج ونطوي بطوننا الليلة‏.‏ ففعلت ثم غدا الرجل على رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ لقد عجب الله عز وجل أو ضحك من فلان
وفلانة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏ويؤثرون على أنفسهم ولو كان بهم
خصاصة‏}‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: A man came to Allah's Apostle
and said, "O Allah's Apostle! I am suffering from fatigue and
hunger." The Prophet sent (somebody) to his wives (to get
something), but the messenger found nothing with them. Then Allah's
Apostle said (to his companions). "Isn't there anybody who can
entertain this man tonight so that Allah may be merciful to him?"
An Ansari man got up and said, "I (will, entertain him), O Allah's
Apostle!" So he went to his wife and said to her, "This is the
guest of Allah's Apostle, so do not keep anything away from him."
She said. "By Allah, I have nothing but the children's food." He
said, "When the children ask for their dinner, put them to bed and
put out the light; we shall not take our meals tonight," She did
so. In the morning the Ansari man went to Allah's Apostle who said,
"Allah was pleased with (or He bestowed His Mercy) on so-and-so and
his wife (because of their good deed)." Then Allah revealed: 'But
give them preference over themselves even though they were in need
of that.' (59.9)</english-text>
</hadith>
