<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4732</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4939</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30418, 20005, 11081, 11156, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحميدي، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا عمرو بن دينار، قال
حدثني الحسن بن محمد بن علي، أنه سمع عبيد الله بن أبي رافع، كاتب علي
يقول سمعت عليا رضى الله عنه يقول بعثني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
أنا والزبير والمقداد فقال ‏"‏ انطلقوا حتى تأتوا روضة خاخ فإن بها
ظعينة معها كتاب فخذوه منها ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهبنا تعادى بنا خيلنا حتى أتينا
الروضة فإذا نحن بالظعينة فقلنا أخرجي الكتاب فقالت ما معي من كتاب‏.‏
فقلنا لتخرجن الكتاب أو لنلقين الثياب‏.‏ فأخرجته من عقاصها فأتينا به
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فإذا فيه من حاطب بن أبي بلتعة إلى أناس من
المشركين ممن بمكة يخبرهم ببعض أمر النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما هذا يا حاطب ‏"‏‏.‏ قال لا تعجل على
يا رسول الله إني كنت امرأ من قريش ولم أكن من أنفسهم وكان من معك من
المهاجرين لهم قرابات يحمون بها أهليهم وأموالهم بمكة فأحببت إذ فاتني
من النسب فيهم أن أصطنع إليهم يدا يحمون قرابتي وما فعلت ذلك كفرا ولا
ارتدادا عن ديني‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إنه قد صدقكم
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال عمر دعني يا رسول الله فأضرب عنقه‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إنه شهد
بدرا وما يدريك لعل الله عز وجل اطلع على أهل بدر فقال اعملوا ما شئتم
فقد غفرت لكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عمرو ونزلت فيه ‏{‏يا أيها الذين آمنوا لا
تتخذوا عدوي وعدوكم‏}‏ قال لا أدري الآية في الحديث أو قول عمرو‏.‏
حدثنا علي قيل لسفيان في هذا فنزلت ‏{‏لا تتخذوا عدوي‏}‏ قال سفيان
هذا في حديث الناس حفظته من عمرو وما تركت منه حرفا وما أرى أحدا حفظه
غيري‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Ali: Allah's Apostle sent me along with
AzZubair and Al-Miqdad and said, "Proceed till you reach a place
called Raudat-Khakh where there is a lady travelling in a howda on
a camel. She has a letter. Take the letter from her." So we set
out, and our horses ran at full pace till we reached Raudat Khakh,
and behold, we saw the lady and said (to her), "Take out the
letter!" She said, "I have no letter with me." We said, "Either you
take out the letter or we will strip you of your clothes." So she
took the letter out of her hair braid. We brought the letter to the
Prophet and behold, it was addressed by Hatib bin Abi Balta'a to
some pagans at Mecca, informing them of some of the affairs of the
Prophet. The Prophet said, "What is this, O Hatib?" Hatib replied,
"Do not be hasty with me, O Allah's Apostle! I am an Ansari man and
do not belong to them (Quraish infidels) while the emigrants who
were with you had their relatives who used to protect their
families and properties at Mecca. So, to compensate for not having
blood relation with them.' I intended to do them some favor so that
they might protect my relatives (at Mecca), and I did not do this
out of disbelief or an inclination to desert my religion." The
Prophet then said (to his companions), "He (Hatib) has told you the
truth." `Umar said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow me to chop his head
off?" The Apostle said, "He is one of those who witnessed (fought
in) the Battle of Badr, and what do you know, perhaps Allah looked
upon the people of Badr (Badr warriors) and said, 'Do what you want
as I have forgiven you.' " (`Amr, a sub-narrator, said,: This Verse
was revealed about him (Hatib): 'O you who believe! Take not My
enemies and your enemies as friends or protectors.'
(60.1)</english-text>
</hadith>
