<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>474</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>482</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayers (Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30312, 11071, 11035, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق، قال حدثنا ابن شميل، أخبرنا ابن عون، عن
ابن سيرين، عن أبي هريرة، قال صلى بنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
إحدى صلاتى العشي قال ابن سيرين سماها أبو هريرة ولكن نسيت أنا قال
فصلى بنا ركعتين ثم سلم، فقام إلى خشبة معروضة في المسجد فاتكأ عليها،
كأنه غضبان، ووضع يده اليمنى على اليسرى، وشبك بين أصابعه، ووضع خده
الأيمن على ظهر كفه اليسرى، وخرجت السرعان من أبواب المسجد فقالوا
قصرت الصلاة‏.‏ وفي القوم أبو بكر وعمر، فهابا أن يكلماه، وفي القوم
رجل في يديه طول يقال له ذو اليدين قال يا رسول الله، أنسيت أم قصرت
الصلاة قال ‏"‏ لم أنس، ولم تقصر ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أكما يقول ذو اليدين
‏"‏‏.‏ فقالوا نعم‏.‏ فتقدم فصلى ما ترك، ثم سلم، ثم كبر وسجد مثل
سجوده أو أطول، ثم رفع رأسه وكبر، ثم كبر وسجد مثل سجوده أو أطول، ثم
رفع رأسه وكبر‏.‏ فربما سألوه ثم سلم فيقول نبئت أن عمران بن حصين قال
ثم سلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrates Ibn Seereen: Abu Huraira said, "Allah's
Apostle led us in one of the two `Isha' prayers (Abu Huraira named
that prayer but I forgot it)." Abu Huraira added, "He prayed two
rak`at and then finished the prayer with Taslim. He stood up near a
piece of wood Lying across the mosque and leaned on it in such a
way as if he was angry. Then he put his right hand over the left
and clasped his hands by interlacing his fingers and then put his J
right cheek on the back of his left hand. The people who were in
haste left the mosque through its gates. They wondered whether the
prayer was reduced. And amongst them were Abu Bakr and `Umar but
they hesitated to ask the Prophet. A long-handed man called Dhul-
Yadain asked the Prophet, 'O Allah's Apostle! Have you forgotten or
has the prayer been reduced?' The Prophet replied, 'I have neither
forgotten nor has the prayer been reduced' The Prophet added, 'Is
what Dhul Yadain has said true?' They (the people) said, 'Yes, it
is true.' The Prophet stood up again and led the prayer, completing
the remaining prayer, forgotten by him, and performed Taslim, and
then said, 'Allahu Akbar.' And then he did a prostration as he used
to prostrate or longer than that. He then raised his head saying,
'Allahu Akbar; he then again said, 'Allahu Akbar', and prostrated
as he used to prostrate or longer than that. Then he raised his
head and said, 'Allahu Akbar.' " (The subnarrator added, "I think
that they asked (Ibn Seereen) whether the Prophet completed the
prayer with Taslim. He replied, "I heard that `Imran bin Husain had
said, 'Then he (the Prophet) did Taslim.")</english-text>
</hadith>
