<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4795</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>65</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>4999</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prophetic Commentary on the Qur'an (Tafseer of the Prophet
(pbuh)) - كتاب التفسير</chapter>
<chain-index>30203, 20028, 11067, 11344, 11359, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عثمان بن أبي شيبة، حدثنا جرير، عن منصور، عن سعد
بن عبيدة، عن أبي عبد الرحمن السلمي، عن علي رضى الله عنه قال كنا في
جنازة في بقيع الغرقد، فأتانا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقعد
وقعدنا حوله، ومعه مخصرة فنكس، فجعل ينكت بمخصرته ثم قال ‏"‏ ما منكم
من أحد وما من نفس منفوسة إلا كتب مكانها من الجنة والنار، وإلا قد
كتبت شقية أو سعيدة ‏"‏‏.‏ قال رجل يا رسول الله أفلا نتكل على كتابنا
وندع العمل فمن كان منا من أهل السعادة فسيصير إلى أهل السعادة، ومن
كان منا من أهل الشقاء فسيصير إلى عمل أهل الشقاوة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أما أهل
السعادة فييسرون لعمل أهل السعادة وأما أهل الشقاوة فييسرون لعمل أهل
الشقاء ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قرأ ‏{‏فأما من أعطى واتقى * وصدق بالحسنى‏}‏
الآية‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Ali: While we were in a funeral procession
in Baqi Al-Gharqad, Allah's Apostle came and sat down, and we sat
around him. He had a small stick in his hand and he bent his head
and started scraping the ground with it. He then said, "There is
none among you, and no created soul but has his place written for
him either in Paradise or in the Hell-Fire, and also has his happy
or miserable fate (in the Hereafter) written for him." A man said,
"O Allah's Apostle! Shall we depend upon what is written for us and
give up doing (good) deeds? For whoever among us is destined to be
fortunate (in the Hereafter), will join the fortunate peoples and
whoever among us is destined to be miserable will do such deeds as
are characteristic of the people who are destined to misery." The
Prophet said, "Those who are destined to be happy (in the
Hereafter) will find it easy and pleasant to do the deeds
characteristic of those destined to happiness, while those who are
to be among the miserable (in the Hereafter), will find it easy to
do the deeds characteristic of those destined to misery." Then he
recited: 'As for him who gives (in charity) and keeps his duty to
Allah and believes in the Best reward from Allah, We will make
smooth for him the path of ease. But he who is a greedy miser and
thinks himself self sufficient, and gives the lie to the Best
reward from Allah we will make smooth for him the path for evil.'
(92.5-10)</english-text>
</hadith>
