<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4833</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>66</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5037</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20150, 11013, 11203, 49</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، عن إبراهيم بن سعد، حدثنا ابن
شهاب، عن عبيد بن السباق، أن زيد بن ثابت رضى الله عنه قال أرسل إلى
أبو بكر مقتل أهل اليمامة فإذا عمر بن الخطاب عنده قال أبو بكر رضى
الله عنه إن عمر أتاني فقال إن القتل قد استحر يوم اليمامة بقراء
القرآن وإني أخشى أن يستحر القتل بالقراء بالمواطن، فيذهب كثير من
القرآن وإني أرى أن تأمر بجمع القرآن‏.‏ قلت لعمر كيف تفعل شيئا لم
يفعله رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال عمر هذا والله خير‏.‏ فلم يزل
عمر يراجعني حتى شرح الله صدري لذلك، ورأيت في ذلك الذي رأى عمر‏.‏
قال زيد قال أبو بكر إنك رجل شاب عاقل لا نتهمك، وقد كنت تكتب الوحى
لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فتتبع القرآن فاجمعه فوالله لو كلفوني
نقل جبل من الجبال ما كان أثقل على مما أمرني من جمع القرآن قلت كيف
تفعلون شيئا لم يفعله رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال هو والله خير
فلم يزل أبو بكر يراجعني حتى شرح الله صدري للذي شرح له صدر أبي بكر
وعمر رضى الله عنهما فتتبعت القرآن أجمعه من العسب واللخاف وصدور
الرجال حتى وجدت آخر سورة التوبة مع أبي خزيمة الأنصاري لم أجدها مع
أحد غيره ‏{‏لقد جاءكم رسول من أنفسكم عزيز عليه ما عنتم‏}‏ حتى خاتمة
براءة، فكانت الصحف عند أبي بكر حتى توفاه الله ثم عند عمر حياته ثم
عند حفصة بنت عمر رضى الله عنه ‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Zaid bin Thabit: Abu Bakr As-Siddiq sent for
me when the people! of Yamama had been killed (i.e., a number of
the Prophet's Companions who fought against Musailama). (I went to
him) and found `Umar bin Al- Khattab sitting with him. Abu Bakr
then said (to me), "`Umar has come to me and said: "Casualties were
heavy among the Qurra' of the! Qur'an (i.e. those who knew the
Qur'an by heart) on the day of the Battle of Yalmama, and I am
afraid that more heavy casualties may take place among the Qurra'
on other battlefields, whereby a large part of the Qur'an may be
lost. Therefore I suggest, you (Abu Bakr) order that the Qur'an be
collected." I said to `Umar, "How can you do something which
Allah's Apostle did not do?" `Umar said, "By Allah, that is a good
project. "`Umar kept on urging me to accept his proposal till Allah
opened my chest for it and I began to realize the good in the idea
which `Umar had realized." Then Abu Bakr said (to me). 'You are a
wise young man and we do not have any suspicion about you, and you
used to write the Divine Inspiration for Allah's Apostle. So you
should search for (the fragmentary scripts of) the Qur'an and
collect it in one book)." By Allah If they had ordered me to shift
one of the mountains, it would not have been heavier for me than
this ordering me to collect the Qur'an. Then I said to Abu Bakr,
"How will you do something which Allah's Apostle did not do?" Abu
Bakr replied, "By Allah, it is a good project." Abu Bakr kept on
urging me to accept his idea until Allah opened my chest for what
He had opened the chests of Abu Bakr and `Umar. So I started
looking for the Qur'an and collecting it from (what was written on)
palmed stalks, thin white stones and also from the men who knew it
by heart, till I found the last Verse of Surat at-Tauba
(Repentance) with Abi Khuza`ima Al-Ansari, and I did not find it
with anybody other than him. The Verse is: 'Verily there has come
unto you an Apostle (Muhammad) from amongst yourselves. It grieves
him that you should receive any injury or difficulty..(till the end
of Surat-Baraa' (at-Tauba) (9.128-129) Then the complete
manuscripts (copy) of the Qur'an remained with Abu Bakr till he
died, then with `Umar till the end of his life, and then with
Hafsa, the daughter of `Umar.</english-text>
</hadith>
