<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4834</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>66</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5038</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20150, 11013, 19, 145</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى، حدثنا إبراهيم، حدثنا ابن شهاب، أن أنس بن
مالك، حدثه أن حذيفة بن اليمان قدم على عثمان وكان يغازي أهل الشأم في
فتح إرمينية وأذربيجان مع أهل العراق فأفزع حذيفة اختلافهم في القراءة
فقال حذيفة لعثمان يا أمير المؤمنين أدرك هذه الأمة قبل أن يختلفوا في
الكتاب اختلاف اليهود والنصارى فأرسل عثمان إلى حفصة أن أرسلي إلينا
بالصحف ننسخها في المصاحف ثم نردها إليك فأرسلت بها حفصة إلى عثمان
فأمر زيد بن ثابت وعبد الله بن الزبير وسعيد بن العاص وعبد الرحمن بن
الحارث بن هشام فنسخوها في المصاحف وقال عثمان للرهط القرشيين الثلاثة
إذا اختلفتم أنتم وزيد بن ثابت في شىء من القرآن فاكتبوه بلسان قريش
فإنما نزل بلسانهم ففعلوا حتى إذا نسخوا الصحف في المصاحف رد عثمان
الصحف إلى حفصة وأرسل إلى كل أفق بمصحف مما نسخوا وأمر بما سواه من
القرآن في كل صحيفة أو مصحف أن يحرق‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Hudhaifa bin Al-Yaman came
to `Uthman at the time when the people of Sham and the people of
Iraq were Waging war to conquer Arminya and Adharbijan. Hudhaifa
was afraid of their (the people of Sham and Iraq) differences in
the recitation of the Qur'an, so he said to `Uthman, "O chief of
the Believers! Save this nation before they differ about the Book
(Qur'an) as Jews and the Christians did before." So `Uthman sent a
message to Hafsa saying, "Send us the manuscripts of the Qur'an so
that we may compile the Qur'anic materials in perfect copies and
return the manuscripts to you." Hafsa sent it to `Uthman. `Uthman
then ordered Zaid bin Thabit, `Abdullah bin AzZubair, Sa`id bin
Al-As and `AbdurRahman bin Harith bin Hisham to rewrite the
manuscripts in perfect copies. `Uthman said to the three Quraishi
men, "In case you disagree with Zaid bin Thabit on any point in the
Qur'an, then write it in the dialect of Quraish, the Qur'an was
revealed in their tongue." They did so, and when they had written
many copies, `Uthman returned the original manuscripts to Hafsa.
`Uthman sent to every Muslim province one copy of what they had
copied, and ordered that all the other Qur'anic materials, whether
written in fragmentary manuscripts or whole copies, be burnt. Sa`id
bin Thabit added, "A Verse from Surat Ahzab was missed by me when
we copied the Qur'an and I used to hear Allah's Apostle reciting
it. So we searched for it and found it with Khuza`ima bin Thabit
Al-Ansari. (That Verse was): 'Among the Believers are men who have
been true in their covenant with Allah.' (33.23)</english-text>
</hadith>
