<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4840</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>66</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5044</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن</chapter>
<chain-index>30309, 20467, 11070, 11264</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن موسى، أخبرنا هشام بن يوسف، أن ابن
جريج، أخبرهم قال وأخبرني يوسف بن ماهك، قال إني عند عائشة أم
المؤمنين رضى الله عنها إذ جاءها عراقي فقال أى الكفن خير قالت ويحك
وما يضرك قال يا أم المؤمنين أريني مصحفك‏.‏ قالت لم قال لعلي أولف
القرآن عليه فإنه يقرأ غير مؤلف‏.‏ قالت وما يضرك أيه قرأت قبل، إنما
نزل أول ما نزل منه سورة من المفصل فيها ذكر الجنة والنار حتى إذا ثاب
الناس إلى الإسلام نزل الحلال والحرام، ولو نزل أول شىء لا تشربوا
الخمر‏.‏ لقالوا لا ندع الخمر أبدا‏.‏ ولو نزل‏.‏ لا تزنوا‏.‏ لقالوا
لا ندع الزنا أبدا‏.‏ لقد نزل بمكة على محمد صلى الله عليه وسلم وإني
لجارية ألعب ‏{‏بل الساعة موعدهم والساعة أدهى وأمر‏}‏ وما نزلت سورة
البقرة والنساء إلا وأنا عنده‏.‏ قال فأخرجت له المصحف فأملت عليه آى
السور‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Yusuf bin Mahk: While I was with Aisha, the
mother of the Believers, a person from Iraq came and asked, "What
type of shroud is the best?" `Aisha said, "May Allah be merciful to
you! What does it matter?" He said, "O mother of the Believers!
Show me (the copy of) your Qur'an," She said, "Why?" He said, "In
order to compile and arrange the Qur'an according to it, for people
recite it with its Suras not in proper order." `Aisha said, "What
does it matter which part of it you read first? (Be informed) that
the first thing that was revealed thereof was a Sura from
Al-Mufassal, and in it was mentioned Paradise and the Fire. When
the people embraced Islam, the Verses regarding legal and illegal
things were revealed. If the first thing to be revealed was: 'Do
not drink alcoholic drinks.' people would have said, 'We will never
leave alcoholic drinks,' and if there had been revealed, 'Do not
commit illegal sexual intercourse, 'they would have said, 'We will
never give up illegal sexual intercourse.' While I was a young girl
of playing age, the following Verse was revealed in Mecca to
Muhammad: 'Nay! But the Hour is their appointed time (for their
full recompense), and the Hour will be more grievous and more
bitter.' (54.46) Sura Al-Baqara (The Cow) and Surat An-Nisa (The
Women) were revealed while I was with him." Then `Aisha took out
the copy of the Qur'an for the man and dictated to him the Verses
of the Suras (in their proper order) .</english-text>
</hadith>
