<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4867</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>66</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5070</hadith-number>
<chapter>Virtues of the Qur'an - كتاب فضائل القرآن</chapter>
<chain-index>20023, 11234, 11213, 45</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وقال الليث حدثني يزيد بن الهاد، عن محمد بن إبراهيم، عن
أسيد بن حضير، قال بينما هو يقرأ من الليل سورة البقرة وفرسه مربوط
عنده إذ جالت الفرس فسكت فسكتت فقرأ فجالت الفرس، فسكت وسكتت الفرس ثم
قرأ فجالت الفرس، فانصرف وكان ابنه يحيى قريبا منها فأشفق أن تصيبه
فلما اجتره رفع رأسه إلى السماء حتى ما يراها فلما أصبح حدث النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ اقرأ يا ابن حضير اقرأ يا ابن حضير ‏"‏‏.‏
قال فأشفقت يا رسول الله أن تطأ يحيى وكان منها قريبا فرفعت رأسي
فانصرفت إليه فرفعت رأسي إلى السماء فإذا مثل الظلة فيها أمثال
المصابيح فخرجت حتى لا أراها‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وتدري ما ذاك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تلك الملائكة دنت لصوتك ولو قرأت لأصبحت ينظر الناس
إليها لا تتوارى منهم ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ابن الهاد وحدثني هذا الحديث عبد
الله بن خباب عن أبي سعيد الخدري عن أسيد بن حضير‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Usaid bin Hudair: That while he was reciting
Surat Al-Baqara (The Cow) at night, and his horse was tied beside
him, the horse was suddenly startled and troubled. When he stopped
reciting, the horse became quiet, and when he started again, the
horse was startled again. Then he stopped reciting and the horse
became quiet too. He started reciting again and the horse was
startled and troubled once again. Then he stopped reciting and his
son, Yahya was beside the horse. He was afraid that the horse might
trample on him. When he took the boy away and looked towards the
sky, he could not see it. The next morning he informed the Prophet
who said, "Recite, O Ibn Hudair! Recite, O Ibn Hudair!" Ibn Hudair
replied, "O Allah's Apostle! My son, Yahya was near the horse and I
was afraid that it might trample on him, so I looked towards the
sky, and went to him. When I looked at the sky, I saw something
like a cloud containing what looked like lamps, so I went out in
order not to see it." The Prophet said, "Do you know what that
was?" Ibn Hudair replied, "No." The Prophet said, "Those were
Angels who came near to you for your voice and if you had kept on
reciting till dawn, it would have remained there till morning when
people would have seen it as it would not have
disappeared.</english-text>
</hadith>
