<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4943</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5143</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20165, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي حازم، عن أبيه، عن
سهل بن سعد الساعدي، قال جاءت امرأة إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقالت يا رسول الله جئت أهب لك نفسي قال فنظر إليها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فصعد النظر فيها وصوبه ثم طأطأ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم رأسه فلما رأت المرأة أنه لم يقض فيها شيئا جلست فقام رجل
من أصحابه فقال يا رسول الله إن لم يكن لك بها حاجة فزوجنيها‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ وهل عندك من شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قال لا والله يا رسول الله‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏
اذهب إلى أهلك فانظر هل تجد شيئا ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع فقال لا والله ما
وجدت شيئا‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ انظر ولو خاتما
من حديد ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع فقال لا والله يا رسول الله ولا خاتما من
حديد ولكن هذا إزاري قال سهل ما له رداء فلها نصفه فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما تصنع بإزارك إن لبسته لم يكن عليها منه شىء وإن
لبسته لم يكن عليك شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ فجلس الرجل حتى إذا طال مجلسه قام فرآه
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم موليا فأمر به فدعي فلما جاء قال ‏"‏
ماذا معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏ قال معي سورة كذا وسورة كذا عددها‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ تقرؤهن عن ظهر قلبك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهب فقد ملكتكها
بما معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d As-Sa`idi: A woman came to
Allah's Apostle and said, "O Allah's Apostle! I have come to give
you myself in marriage (without Mahr)." Allah's Apostle looked at
her. He looked at her carefully and fixed his glance on her and
then lowered his head. When the lady saw that he did not say
anything, she sat down. A man from his companions got up and said,
"O Allah's Apostle! If you are not in need of her, then marry her
to me." The Prophet said, "Have you got anything to offer?" The man
said, "No, by Allah, O Allah's Apostle!" The Prophet said (to him),
"Go to your family and see if you have something." The man went and
returned, saying, "No, by Allah, I have not found anything."
Allah's Apostle said, "(Go again) and look for something, even if
it is an iron ring." He went again and returned, saying, "No, by
Allah, O Allah's Apostle! I could not find even an iron ring, but
this is my Izar (waist sheet)." He had no rida. He added, "I give
half of it to her." Allah's Apostle said, "What will she do with
your Izar? If you wear it, she will be naked, and if she wears it,
you will be naked." So that man sat down for a long while and then
got up (to depart). When Allah's Apostle saw him going, he ordered
that he be called back. When he came, the Prophet said, "How much
of the Qur'an do you know?" He said, "I know such Sura and such
Sura," counting them. The Prophet said, "Do you know them by
heart?" He replied, "Yes." The Prophet said, "Go, I marry her to
you for that much of the Qur'an which you have."</english-text>
</hadith>
