<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4944</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5144</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
عروة بن الزبير، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن أبا حذيفة بن عتبة بن
ربيعة بن عبد شمس،، وكان، ممن شهد بدرا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
تبنى سالما، وأنكحه بنت أخيه هند بنت الوليد بن عتبة بن ربيعة وهو
مولى لامرأة من الأنصار، كما تبنى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم زيدا،
وكان من تبنى رجلا في الجاهلية دعاه الناس إليه وورث من ميراثه حتى
أنزل الله ‏{‏ادعوهم لآبائهم‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏ومواليكم‏}‏ فردوا إلى
آبائهم، فمن لم يعلم له أب كان مولى وأخا في الدين، فجاءت سهلة بنت
سهيل بن عمرو القرشي ثم العامري وهى امرأة أبي حذيفة النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقالت يا رسول الله إنا كنا نرى سالما ولدا وقد أنزل الله
فيه ما قد علمت فذكر الحديث‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Abu Hudhaifa bin `Utba bin Rabi`a
bin `Abdi Shams who had witnessed the battle of Badr along with the
Prophet adopted Salim as his son, to whom he married his niece,
Hind bint Al-Walid bin `Utba bin Rabi`a; and Salim was the freed
slave of an Ansar woman, just as the Prophet had adopted Zaid as
his son. It was the custom in the Pre-lslamic Period that if
somebody adopted a boy, the people would call him the son of the
adoptive father and he would be the latter's heir. But when Allah
revealed the Divine Verses: 'Call them by (the names of) their
fathers . . . your freed-slaves,' (33.5) the adopted persons were
called by their fathers' names. The one whose father was not known,
would be regarded as a Maula and your brother in religion. Later on
Sahla bint Suhail bin `Amr Al-Quraishi Al-`Amiri-- and she was the
wife of Abu- Hudhaifa bin `Utba--came to the Prophet and said, "O
Allah's Apostle! We used to consider Salim as our (adopted) son,
and now Allah has revealed what you know (regarding adopted sons)."
The sub-narrator then mentioned the rest of the
narration.</english-text>
</hadith>
