<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4957</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5157</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10511, 244, 59</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحكم بن نافع، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال
أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أن زينب ابنة أبي سلمة، أخبرته أن أم حبيبة
بنت أبي سفيان أخبرتها أنها، قالت يا رسول الله انكح أختي بنت أبي
سفيان فقال ‏"‏ أوتحبين ذلك ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم، لست لك بمخلية، وأحب من
شاركني في خير أختي‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن ذلك لا
يحل لي ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت فإنا نحدث أنك تريد أن تنكح بنت أبي سلمة‏.‏ قال
‏"‏ بنت أم سلمة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ لو أنها لم تكن ربيبتي في
حجري ما حلت لي إنها لابنة أخي من الرضاعة، أرضعتني وأبا سلمة ثويبة
فلا تعرضن على بناتكن ولا أخواتكن ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عروة وثويبة مولاة لأبي
لهب كان أبو لهب أعتقها فأرضعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما مات أبو
لهب أريه بعض أهله بشر حيبة قال له ماذا لقيت قال أبو لهب لم ألق
بعدكم غير أني سقيت في هذه بعتاقتي ثويبة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Um Habiba: (daughter of Abu Sufyan) I said,
"O Allah's Apostle! Marry my sister. the daughter of Abu Sufyan."
The Prophet said, "Do you like that?" I replied, "Yes, for even now
I am not your only wife and I like that my sister should share the
good with me." The Prophet said, "But that is not lawful for me." I
said, We have heard that you want to marry the daughter of Abu
Salama." He said, "(You mean) the daughter of Um Salama?" I said,
"Yes." He said, "Even if she were not my step-daughter, she would
be unlawful for me to marry as she is my foster niece. I and Abu
Salama were suckled by Thuwaiba. So you should not present to me
your daughters or your sisters (in marriage)." Narrated 'Ursa;
Thuwaiba was the freed slave girl of Abu Lahb whom he had
manumitted, and then she suckled the Prophet. When Abu Lahb died,
one of his relatives saw him in a dream in a very bad state and
asked him, "What have you encountered?" Abu Lahb said, "I have not
found any rest since I left you, except that I have been given
water to drink in this (the space between his thumb and other
fingers) and that is because of my manumitting
Thuwaiba."</english-text>
</hadith>
