<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4976</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5176</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20179, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، حدثنا أبو غسان، قال حدثني أبو
حازم، عن سهل، أن امرأة، عرضت نفسها على النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال له رجل يا رسول الله زوجنيها‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ما عندك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ما
عندي شىء‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهب فالتمس ولو خاتما من حديد ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب ثم
رجع فقال لا والله ما وجدت شيئا، ولا خاتما من حديد، ولكن هذا إزاري
ولها نصفه قال سهل وما له رداء‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
وما تصنع بإزارك إن لبسته لم يكن عليها منه شىء، وإن لبسته لم يكن
عليك منه شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ فجلس الرجل حتى إذا طال مجلسه قام فرآه النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فدعاه أو دعي له فقال ‏"‏ ماذا معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏
فقال معي سورة كذا وسورة كذا لسور يعددها‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أملكناكها بما معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: A woman presented herself to
the Prophet (for marriage). A man said to him, "O Allah's Apostle!
(If you are not in need of her) marry her to me." The Prophet said,
"What have you got?" The man said, "I have nothing." The Prophet
said (to him), "Go and search for something) even if it were an
iron ring." The man went and returned saying, "No, I have not found
anything, not even an iron ring; but this is my (Izar) waist sheet,
and half of it is for her." He had no Rida' (upper garment). The
Prophet said, "What will she do with your waist sheet? If you wear
it, she will have nothing over her; and if she wears it, you will
have nothing over you." So the man sat down and when he had sat a
long time, he got up (to leave). When the Prophet saw him
(leaving), he called him back, or the man was called (for him), and
he said to the man, "How much of the Qur'an do you know (by
heart)?" The man replied I know such Sura and such Sura (by
heart)," naming the Suras The Prophet said, "I have married her to
you for what you know of the Qur'an ."</english-text>
</hadith>
