<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>4978</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5178</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20023, 11411, 11204, 244, 59</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا الليث، عن يزيد بن أبي حبيب، عن عراك
بن مالك، أن زينب ابنة أبي سلمة، أخبرته أن أم حبيبة قالت لرسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إنا قد تحدثنا أنك ناكح درة بنت أبي سلمة‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أعلى أم سلمة لو لم أنكح أم سلمة ما
حلت لي، إن أباها أخي من الرضاعة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Zainab bint Salama: Um Habiba said to
Allah's Apostle "We have heard that you want to marry Durra bint
Abu-Salama." Allah's Apostle said, "Can she be married along with
Um Salama (her mother)? Even if I have not married Um Salama, she
would not be lawful for me to marry, for her father is my foster
brother." 'And there is no blame on you if you make hint of
betrothal or conceal it in your hearts. Allah is Oft- Forgiving,
Most Forbearing.' (2.235) Ibn `Abbas said, "Hint your intention of
marrying' is made by saying (to the widow) for example: "I want to
marry, and I wish that Allah will make a righteous lady available
for me.' " Al-Qasim said: One may say to the widow: 'I hold all
respect for you, and I am interested in you; Allah will bring you
much good, or something similar 'Ata said: One should hint his
intention, and should not declare it openly. One may say: 'I have
some need. Have good tidings. Praise be to Allah; you are fit to
remarry.' She (the widow) may say in reply: I am listening to what
you say,' but she should not make a promise. Her guardian should
not make a promise (to somebody to get her married to him) without
her knowledge. But if, while still in the Iddat period, she makes a
promise to marry somebody, and he ultimately marries her, they are
not to be separated by divorce (i.e., the marriage is
valid).</english-text>
</hadith>
