<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5003</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5204</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، سمعت أبا حازم،
يقول سمعت سهل بن سعد الساعدي، يقول إني لفي القوم عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم إذ قامت امرأة فقالت يا رسول الله إنها قد وهبت نفسها
لك فر فيها رأيك فلم يجبها شيئا ثم قامت فقالت يا رسول الله إنها قد
وهبت نفسها لك فر فيها رأيك فلم يجبها شيئا ثم قامت الثالثة فقالت
إنها قد وهبت نفسها لك فر فيها رأيك فقام رجل فقال يا رسول الله
أنكحنيها‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هل عندك من شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قال لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهب
فاطلب ولو خاتما من حديد ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب فطلب ثم جاء فقال ما وجدت شيئا
ولا خاتما من حديد‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ هل معك من القرآن شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قال معي
سورة كذا وسورة كذا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهب فقد أنكحتكها بما معك من القرآن
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d As-Sa`idi: While I was
(sitting) among the people in the company of Allah's Apostle a
woman stood up and said, "O Allah's Apostle! She has given herself
in marriage to you; please give your opinion of her." The Prophet
did not give her any reply. She again stood up and said, "O Allah's
Apostle! She has given herself (in marriage) to you; so please give
your opinion of her. The Prophet did not give her any reply. She
again stood up for the third time and said, "She has given herself
in marriage to you: so give your opinion of her." So a man stood up
and said, "O Allah's Apostle! Marry her to me." The Prophet asked
him, "Have you got anything?" He said, "No." The Prophet said, "Go
and search for something, even if it were an iron ring." The man
went and searched and then returned saying, "I could not find
anything, not even an iron ring." Then the Prophet said, "Do you
know something of the Qur'an (by heart)?" He replied, "I know (by
heart) such Sura and such Sura." The Prophet said, "Go! I have
married her to you for what you know of the Qur'an (by
heart).</english-text>
</hadith>
