<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>500</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>509</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayers (Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30315, 20258, 20475, 11281, 11161, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو معمر، قال حدثنا عبد الوارث، قال حدثنا يونس،
عن حميد بن هلال، عن أبي صالح، أن أبا سعيد، قال قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم وحدثنا آدم بن أبي إياس قال حدثنا سليمان بن المغيرة قال
حدثنا حميد بن هلال العدوي قال حدثنا أبو صالح السمان قال رأيت أبا
سعيد الخدري في يوم جمعة يصلي إلى شىء يستره من الناس، فأراد شاب من
بني أبي معيط أن يجتاز بين يديه فدفع أبو سعيد في صدره، فنظر الشاب
فلم يجد مساغا إلا بين يديه، فعاد ليجتاز فدفعه أبو سعيد أشد من
الأولى، فنال من أبي سعيد، ثم دخل على مروان فشكا إليه ما لقي من أبي
سعيد، ودخل أبو سعيد خلفه على مروان فقال ما لك ولابن أخيك يا أبا
سعيد قال سمعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إذا صلى أحدكم إلى
شىء يستره من الناس، فأراد أحد أن يجتاز بين يديه فليدفعه، فإن أبى
فليقاتله، فإنما هو شيطان ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id: The Prophet said, (what is
ascribed to him in the following Hadith):Narrated Abu Salih
As-Samman:I saw Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri praying on a Friday, behind
something which acted as a Sutra. A young man from Bani Abi Mu'ait
[??] , wanted to pass in front of him, but Abu Sa`id repulsed him
with a push on his chest. Finding no alternative he again tried to
pass but Abu Sa`id pushed him with a greater force. The young man
abused Abu Sa`id and went to Marwan and lodged a complaint against
Abu Sa`id and Abu Sa`id followed the young man to Marwan who asked
him, "O Abu Sa`id! What has happened between you and the son of
your brother?" Abu Sa`id said to him, "I heard the Prophet saying,
'If anybody amongst you is praying behind something as a Sutra and
somebody tries to pass in front of him, then he should repulse him
and if he refuses, he should use force against him for he is a
Shaitan (a Satan).' "</english-text>
</hadith>
