<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5042</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5244</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30587, 20387, 20347, 11065, 11699, 10511,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن عبد الرحمن، وعلي بن حجر، قالا أخبرنا
عيسى بن يونس، حدثنا هشام بن عروة، عن عبد الله بن عروة، عن عروة، عن
عائشة، قالت جلس إحدى عشرة امرأة، فتعاهدن وتعاقدن أن لا يكتمن من
أخبار أزواجهن شيئا‏.‏ قالت الأولى زوجي لحم جمل، غث على رأس جبل، لا
سهل فيرتقى، ولا سمين فينتقل‏.‏ قالت الثانية زوجي لا أبث خبره، إني
أخاف أن لا أذره، إن أذكره أذكر عجره وبجره‏.‏ قالت الثالثة زوجي
العشنق، إن أنطق أطلق وإن أسكت أعلق‏.‏ قالت الرابعة زوجي كليل تهامة،
لا حر، ولا قر، ولا مخافة، ولا سآمة‏.‏ قالت الخامسة زوجي إن دخل فهد،
وإن خرج أسد، ولا يسأل عما عهد‏.‏ قالت السادسة زوجي إن أكل لف، وإن
شرب اشتف، وإن اضطجع التف، ولا يولج الكف ليعلم البث، قالت السابعة
زوجي غياياء أو عياياء طباقاء، كل داء له داء، شجك أو فلك أو جمع كلا
لك‏.‏ قالت الثامنة زوجي المس مس أرنب، والريح ريح زرنب‏.‏ قالت
التاسعة زوجي رفيع العماد، طويل النجاد، عظيم الرماد، قريب البيت من
الناد‏.‏ قالت العاشرة زوجي مالك وما مالك، مالك خير من ذلك، له إبل
كثيرات المبارك قليلات المسارح، وإذا سمعن صوت المزهر أيقن أنهن
هوالك‏.‏ قالت الحادية عشرة زوجي أبو زرع فما أبو زرع أناس من حلي
أذنى، وملأ من شحم عضدى، وبجحني فبجحت إلى نفسي، وجدني في أهل غنيمة
بشق، فجعلني في أهل صهيل وأطيط ودائس ومنق، فعنده أقول فلا أقبح وأرقد
فأتصبح، وأشرب فأتقنح، أم أبي زرع فما أم أبي زرع عكومها رداح، وبيتها
فساح، ابن أبي زرع، فما ابن أبي زرع مضجعه كمسل شطبة، ويشبعه ذراع
الجفرة، بنت أبي زرع فما بنت أبي زرع طوع أبيها، وطوع أمها، وملء
كسائها، وغيظ جارتها، جارية أبي زرع، فما جارية أبي زرع لا تبث حديثنا
تبثيثا، ولا تنقث ميرتنا تنقيثا، ولا تملأ بيتنا تعشيشا، قالت خرج أبو
زرع والأوطاب تمخض، فلقي امرأة معها ولدان لها كالفهدين يلعبان من تحت
خصرها برمانتين، فطلقني ونكحها، فنكحت بعده رجلا سريا، ركب شريا وأخذ
خطيا وأراح على نعما ثريا، وأعطاني من كل رائحة زوجا وقال كلي أم زرع،
وميري أهلك‏.‏ قالت فلو جمعت كل شىء أعطانيه ما بلغ أصغر آنية أبي
زرع‏.‏ قالت عائشة قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كنت لك كأبي
زرع لأم زرع ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله قال سعيد بن سلمة عن هشام ولا
تعشش بيتنا تعشيشا‏.‏ قال أبو عبد الله قال بعضهم فأتقمح‏.‏ بالميم،
وهذا أصح‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Eleven women sat (at a place) and
promised and contracted that they would not conceal anything of the
news of their husbands. The first one said, "My husband is like the
meat of a slim weak camel which is kept on the top of a mountain
which is neither easy to climb, nor is the meat fat, so that one
might put up with the trouble of fetching it." The second one said,
"I shall not relate my husband's news, for I fear that I may not be
able to finish his story, for if I describe him, I will mention all
his defects and bad traits." The third one said, "My husband, the
"too-tall"! if I describe him (and he hears of that) he will
divorce me, and if I keep quiet, he will keep me hanging (neither
divorcing me nor treating me as a wife)." The fourth one said, "My
husband is (moderate in temper) like the night of Tihama: neither
hot nor cold; I am neither afraid of him, nor am I discontented
with him." The fifth one said, "My husband, when entering (the
house) is a leopard (sleeps a lot), and when going out, is a lion
(boasts a lot). He does not ask about whatever is in the house."
The sixth one said, "If my husband eats, he eats too much (leaving
the dishes empty), and if he drinks he leaves nothing; if he sleeps
he sleeps he rolls himself (alone in our blankets); and he does not
insert his palm to inquire about my feelings." The seventh one
said, "My husband is a wrong-doer or weak and foolish. All the
defects are present in him. He may injure your head or your body or
may do both." The eighth one said, "My husband is soft to touch
like a rabbit and smells like a Zarnab (a kind of good smelling
grass)." The ninth one said, "My husband is a tall generous man
wearing a long strap for carrying his sword. His ashes are abundant
(i.e. generous to his guests) and his house is near to the people
(who would easily consult him)." The tenth one said, "My husband is
Malik (possessor), and what is Malik? Malik is greater than
whatever I say about him. (He is beyond and above all praises which
can come to my mind). Most of his camels are kept at home (ready to
be slaughtered for the guests) and only a few are taken to the
pastures. When the camels hear the sound of the lute (or the
tambourine) they realize that they are going to be slaughtered for
the guests." The eleventh one said, "My husband is Abu Zar` and
what is Abu Zar` (i.e., what should I say about him)? He has given
me many ornaments and my ears are heavily loaded with them and my
arms have become fat (i.e., I have become fat). And he has pleased
me, and I have become so happy that I feel proud of myself. He
found me with my family who were mere owners of sheep and living in
poverty, and brought me to a respected family having horses and
camels and threshing and purifying grain. Whatever I say, he does
not rebuke or insult me. When I sleep, I sleep till late in the
morning, and when I drink water (or milk), I drink my fill. The
mother of Abu Zar and what may one say in praise of the mother of
Abu Zar? Her saddle bags were always full of provision and her
house was spacious. As for the son of Abu Zar, what may one say of
the son of Abu Zar? His bed is as narrow as an unsheathed sword and
an arm of a kid (of four months) satisfies his hunger. As for the
daughter of Abu Zar, she is obedient to her father and to her
mother. She has a fat well-built body and that arouses the jealousy
of her husband's other wife. As for the (maid) slave girl of Abu
Zar, what may one say of the (maid) slavegirl of Abu Zar? She does
not uncover our secrets but keeps them, and does not waste our
provisions and does not leave the rubbish scattered everywhere in
our house." The eleventh lady added, "One day it so happened that
Abu Zar went out at the time when the milk was being milked from
the animals, and he saw a woman who had two sons like two leopards
playing with her two breasts. (On seeing her) he divorced me and
married her. Thereafter I married a noble man who used to ride a
fast tireless horse and keep a spear in his hand. He gave me many
things, and also a pair of every kind of livestock and said, Eat
(of this), O Um Zar, and give provision to your relatives." She
added, "Yet, all those things which my second husband gave me could
not fill the smallest utensil of Abu Zar's." `Aisha then said:
Allah's Apostle said to me, "I am to you as Abu Zar was to his wife
Um Zar."</english-text>
</hadith>
