<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5050</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>67</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5252</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wedlock; Marriage (Nikaah) - كتاب النكاح</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11163, 11020, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن زيد بن أسلم،
عن عطاء بن يسار، عن عبد الله بن عباس، أنه قال خسفت الشمس على عهد
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
والناس معه، فقام قياما طويلا نحوا من سورة البقرة، ثم ركع ركوعا
طويلا، ثم رفع فقام قياما طويلا وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا
طويلا وهو دون الركوع الأول، ثم سجد، ثم قام فقام قياما طويلا وهو دون
القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع الأول، ثم رفع فقام
قياما طويلا وهو دون القيام الأول، ثم ركع ركوعا طويلا وهو دون الركوع
الأول، ثم رفع ثم سجد، ثم انصرف، وقد تجلت الشمس، فقال ‏"‏ إن الشمس
والقمر آيتان من آيات الله لا يخسفان لموت أحد ولا لحياته، فإذا رأيتم
ذلك فاذكروا الله ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله رأيناك تناولت شيئا في
مقامك هذا، ثم رأيناك تكعكعت‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إني رأيت الجنة أو أريت
الجنة فتناولت منها عنقودا ولو أخذته لأكلتم منه ما بقيت الدنيا،
ورأيت النار فلم أر كاليوم منظرا قط ورأيت أكثر أهلها النساء ‏"‏‏.‏
قالوا لم يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ بكفرهن ‏"‏‏.‏ قيل يكفرن بالله قال ‏"‏
يكفرن العشير، ويكفرن الإحسان، ولو أحسنت إلى إحداهن الدهر، ثم رأت
منك شيئا قالت ما رأيت منك خيرا قط ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: During the lifetime of
Allah's Apostle, the sun eclipsed. Allah's Apostle offered the
prayer of (the) eclipse) and so did the people along with him. He
performed a long Qiyam (standing posture) during which
Surat-al-Baqara could have been recited; then he performed a
pro-longed bowing, then raised his head and stood for a long time
which was slightly less than that of the first Qiyam (and recited
Qur'an). Then he performed a prolonged bowing again but the period
was shorter than the period of the first bowing, then he stood up
and then prostrated. Again he stood up, but this time the period of
standing was less than the first standing. Then he performed a
prolonged bowing but of a lesser duration than the first, then he
stood up again for a long time but for a lesser duration than the
first. Then he performed a prolonged bowing but of lesser duration
than the first, and then he again stood up, and then prostrated and
then finished his prayer. By then the sun eclipse had cleared. The
Prophet then said, "The sun and the moon are two signs among the
signs of Allah, and they do not eclipse because of the death or
birth of someone, so when you observe the eclipse, remember Allah
(offer the eclipse prayer)." They (the people) said, "O Allah's
Apostle! We saw you stretching your hand to take something at this
place of yours, then we saw you stepping backward." He said, "I saw
Paradise (or Paradise was shown to me), and I stretched my hand to
pluck a bunch (of grapes), and had I plucked it, you would have
eaten of it as long as this world exists. Then I saw the (Hell)
Fire, and I have never before, seen such a horrible sight as that,
and I saw that the majority of its dwellers were women." The people
asked, "O Allah's Apostle! What is the reason for that?" He
replied, "Because of their ungratefulness." It was said. "Do they
disbelieve in Allah (are they ungrateful to Allah)?" He replied,
"They are not thankful to their husbands and are ungrateful for the
favors done to them. Even if you do good to one of them all your
life, when she seems some harshness from you, she will say, "I have
never seen any good from you.' "</english-text>
</hadith>
