<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5108</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5310</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>20348, 1461, 113</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو نعيم، حدثنا عبد الرحمن بن غسيل، عن حمزة بن
أبي أسيد، عن أبي أسيد رضى الله عنه قال خرجنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم حتى انطلقنا إلى حائط يقال له الشوط، حتى انتهينا إلى حائطين
فجلسنا بينهما فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اجلسوا ها هنا
‏"‏‏.‏ ودخل وقد أتي بالجونية، فأنزلت في بيت في نخل في بيت أميمة بنت
النعمان بن شراحيل ومعها دايتها حاضنة لها، فلما دخل عليها النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ هبي نفسك لي ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت وهل تهب الملكة نفسها
للسوقة‏.‏ قال فأهوى بيده يضع يده عليها لتسكن فقالت أعوذ بالله
منك‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ قد عذت بمعاذ ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم خرج علينا، فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا
أسيد اكسها رازقيتين وألحقها بأهلها‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Usaid: We went out with the Prophet to a
garden called Ash-Shaut till we reached two walls between which we
sat down. The Prophet said, "Sit here," and went in (the garden).
The Jauniyya (a lady from Bani Jaun) had been brought and lodged in
a house in a date-palm garden in the home of Umaima bint An- Nu`man
bin Sharahil, and her wet nurse was with her. When the Prophet
entered upon her, he said to her, "Give me yourself (in marriage)
as a gift." She said, "Can a princess give herself in marriage to
an ordinary man?" The Prophet raised his hand to pat her so that
she might become tranquil. She said, "I seek refuge with Allah from
you." He said, "You have sought refuge with One Who gives refuge.
Then the Prophet came out to us and said, "O Abu Usaid! Give her
two white linen dresses to wear and let her go back to her family."
Narrated Sahl and Abu Usaid: The Prophet married Umaima bint
Sharahil, and when she was brought to him, he stretched his hand
towards her. It seemed that she disliked that, whereupon the
Prophet ordered Abu Usaid to prepare her and to provide her with
two white linen dresses. (See Hadith No. 541).</english-text>
</hadith>
