<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5121</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5323</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30207, 20345, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا فروة بن أبي المغراء، حدثنا علي بن مسهر، عن هشام
بن عروة، عن أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت كان رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يحب العسل والحلواء، وكان إذا انصرف من العصر دخل على
نسائه، فيدنو من إحداهن، فدخل على حفصة بنت عمر، فاحتبس أكثر ما كان
يحتبس، فغرت فسألت عن ذلك فقيل لي أهدت لها امرأة من قومها عكة من
عسل، فسقت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم منه شربة، فقلت أما والله لنحتالن
له‏.‏ فقلت لسودة بنت زمعة إنه سيدنو منك، فإذا دنا منك فقولي أكلت
مغافير فإنه سيقول لك لا‏.‏ فقولي له ما هذه الريح التي أجد منك فإنه
سيقول لك سقتني حفصة شربة عسل فقولي له جرست نحله العرفط‏.‏ وسأقول
ذلك، وقولي أنت يا صفية ذاك‏.‏ قالت تقول سودة فوالله ما هو إلا أن
قام على الباب، فأردت أن أباديه بما أمرتني به فرقا منك، فلما دنا
منها قالت له سودة يا رسول الله أكلت مغافير قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت
فما هذه الريح التي أجد منك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ سقتني حفصة شربة عسل ‏"‏‏.‏
فقالت جرست نحله العرفط فلما دار إلى قلت له نحو ذلك، فلما دار إلى
صفية قالت له مثل ذلك فلما دار إلى حفصة قالت يا رسول الله ألا أسقيك
منه‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ لا حاجة لي فيه ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت تقول سودة والله لقد
حرمناه‏.‏ قلت لها اسكتي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Allah's Apostle was fond of honey
and sweet edible things and (it was his habit) that after finishing
the `Asr prayer he would visit his wives and stay with one of them
at that time. Once he went to Hafsa, the daughter of `Umar and
stayed with her more than usual. I got jealous and asked the reason
for that. I was told that a lady of her folk had given her a skin
filled with honey as a present, and that she made a syrup from it
and gave it to the Prophet to drink (and that was the reason for
the delay). I said, "By Allah we will play a trick on him (to
prevent him from doing so)." So I said to Sa`da bint Zam`a "The
Prophet will approach you, and when he comes near you, say: 'Have
you taken Maghafir (a bad-smelling gum)?' He will say, 'No.' Then
say to him: 'Then what is this bad smell which i smell from you?'
He will say to you, 'Hafsa made me drink honey syrup.' Then say:
Perhaps the bees of that honey had sucked the juice of the tree of
Al-`Urfut.' I shall also say the same. O you, Safiyya, say the
same." Later Sa`da said, "By Allah, as soon as he (the Prophet )
stood at the door, I was about to say to him what you had ordered
me to say because I was afraid of you." So when the Prophet came
near Sa`da, she said to him, "O Allah's Apostle! Have you taken
Maghafir?" He said, "No." She said. "Then what is this bad smell
which I detect on you?" He said, "Hafsa made me drink honey syrup."
She said, "Perhaps its bees had sucked the juice of Al-`Urfut
tree." When he came to me, I also said the same, and when he went
to Safiyya, she also said the same. And when the Prophet again went
to Hafsa, she said, 'O Allah's Apostle! Shall I give you more of
that drink?" He said, "I am not in need of it." Sa`da said, "By
Allah, we deprived him (of it)." I said to her, "Keep quiet."
'</english-text>
</hadith>
