<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5124</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5326</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 10567, 11002, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
أبو سلمة بن عبد الرحمن، وسعيد بن المسيب، أن أبا هريرة، قال أتى رجل
من أسلم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وهو في المسجد فناداه فقال يا
رسول الله إن الأخر قد زنى يعني نفسه فأعرض عنه فتنحى لشق وجهه الذي
أعرض قبله فقال يا رسول الله إن الأخر قد زنى فأعرض عنه فتنحى لشق
وجهه الذي أعرض قبله فقال له ذلك فأعرض عنه فتنحى له الرابعة، فلما
شهد على نفسه أربع شهادات دعاه فقال ‏"‏ هل بك جنون ‏"‏‏.‏ قال لا‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اذهبوا به فارجموه ‏"‏‏.‏ وكان قد
أحصن‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: A man from Bani Aslam came to
Allah's Apostle while he was in the mosque and called (the Prophet
) saying, "O Allah's Apostle! I have committed illegal sexual
intercourse." On that the Prophet turned his face from him to the
other side, whereupon the man moved to the side towards which the
Prophet had turned his face, and said, "O Allah's Apostle! I have
committed illegal sexual intercourse." The Prophet turned his face
(from him) to the other side whereupon the man moved to the side
towards which the Prophet had turned his face, and repeated his
statement. The Prophet turned his face (from him) to the other side
again. The man moved again (and repeated his statement) for the
fourth time. So when the man had given witness four times against
himself, the Prophet called him and said, "Are you insane?" He
replied, "No." The Prophet then said (to his companions), "Go and
stone him to death." The man was a married one. Jabir bin `Abdullah
Al-Ansari said: I was one of those who stoned him. We stoned him at
the Musalla (`Id praying place) in Medina. When the stones hit him
with their sharp edges, he fled, but we caught him at Al-Harra and
stoned him till he died.</english-text>
</hadith>
