<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5143</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5344</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 30308, 20029, 20475,
11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب،‏.‏
وقال إبراهيم بن المنذر حدثني ابن وهب، حدثني يونس، قال ابن شهاب
أخبرني عروة بن الزبير، أن عائشة رضى الله عنها زوج النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قالت كانت المؤمنات إذا هاجرن إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
يمتحنهن بقول الله تعالى ‏{‏يا أيها الذين آمنوا إذا جاءكم المؤمنات
مهاجرات فامتحنوهن‏}‏ إلى آخر الآية قالت عائشة فمن أقر بهذا الشرط من
المؤمنات فقد أقر بالمحنة، فكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا
أقررن بذلك من قولهن قال لهن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ انطلقن
فقد بايعتكن ‏"‏، لا والله ما مست يد رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يد
امرأة قط، غير أنه بايعهن بالكلام، والله ما أخذ رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم على النساء إلا بما أمره الله يقول لهن إذا أخذ عليهن ‏"‏
قد بايعتكن ‏"‏‏.‏ كلاما‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: (the wife of the Prophet) When
believing women came to the Prophet as emigrants, he used to test
them in accordance with the order of Allah. 'O you who believe!
When believing women come to you as emigrants, examine them . . .'
(60.10) So if anyone of those believing women accepted the above
mentioned conditions, she accepted the conditions of faith. When
they agreed on those conditions and confessed that with their
tongues, Allah's Apostle would say to them, "Go, I have accepted
your oath of allegiance (for Islam). By Allah, and hand of Allah's
Apostle never touched the hand of any woman, but he only used to
take their pledge of allegiance orally. By Allah, Allah's Apostle
did not take the pledge of allegiance of the women except in
accordance with what Allah had ordered him. When he accepted their
pledge of allegiance he would say to them, "I have accepted your
oath of allegiance."</english-text>
</hadith>
