<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>511</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>8</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>520</hadith-number>
<chapter>Prayers (Salat) - كتاب الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>30289, 20340, 20311, 11049, 11382, 16</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن إسحاق السرماري، قال حدثنا عبيد الله بن
موسى، قال حدثنا إسرائيل، عن أبي إسحاق، عن عمرو بن ميمون، عن عبد
الله، قال بينما رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائم يصلي عند الكعبة،
وجمع قريش في مجالسهم إذ قال قائل منهم ألا تنظرون إلى هذا المرائي
أيكم يقوم إلى جزور آل فلان، فيعمد إلى فرثها ودمها وسلاها فيجيء به،
ثم يمهله حتى إذا سجد وضعه بين كتفيه فانبعث أشقاهم، فلما سجد رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وضعه بين كتفيه، وثبت النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ساجدا، فضحكوا حتى مال بعضهم إلى بعض من الضحك، فانطلق منطلق إلى
فاطمة عليها السلام وهى جويرية، فأقبلت تسعى وثبت النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ساجدا حتى ألقته عنه، وأقبلت عليهم تسبهم، فلما قضى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم الصلاة قال ‏"‏ اللهم عليك بقريش، اللهم عليك
بقريش، اللهم عليك بقريش ثم سمى اللهم عليك بعمرو بن هشام، وعتبة بن
ربيعة، وشيبة بن ربيعة، والوليد بن عتبة، وأمية بن خلف، وعقبة بن أبي
معيط، وعمارة بن الوليد ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عبد الله فوالله لقد رأيتهم صرعى
يوم بدر، ثم سحبوا إلى القليب قليب بدر، ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وأتبع أصحاب القليب لعنة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amr bin Maimun [??]: `Abdullah bin Mas`ud
said, "While Allah's Apostle was praying beside the Ka`ba, there
were some Quraish people sitting in a gathering. One of them said,
'Don't you see this (who does deeds just to show off)? Who amongst
you can go and bring the dung, blood and the Abdominal contents
(intestines, etc.) of the slaughtered camels of the family of so
and so and then wait till he prostrates and put that in between his
shoulders?' The most unfortunate amongst them (`Uqba bin Abi
Mu'ait) went (and brought them) and when Allah's Apostle
prostrated, he put them between his shoulders. The Prophet remained
in prostration and they laughed so much so that they fell on each
other. A passerby went to Fatima, who was a young girl in those
days. She came running and the Prophet was still in prostration.
She removed them and cursed upon the Quraish on their faces. When
Allah's Apostle completed his prayer, he said, 'O Allah! Take
revenge on Quraish.' He said so thrice and added, 'O Allah! take
revenge on `Amr bin Hisham, `Utba bin Rabi`a, Shaiba bin Rabi`a,
Al-Walid bin `Utba, Umaiya bin Khalaf, `Uqba bin Abi Mu'ait and
`Umar a bin Al-Walid." `Abdullah added, "By Allah! I saw all of
them dead in the battle field on the day of Badr and they were
dragged and thrown in the Qalib (a well) at Badr: Allah's Apostle
then said, 'Allah's curse has descended upon the people of the
Qalib (well).</english-text>
</hadith>
