<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>512</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>9</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>522</hadith-number>
<chapter>Times of the Prayers - كتاب مواقيت الصلاة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 11013, 166</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، قال قرأت على مالك عن ابن
شهاب، أن عمر بن عبد العزيز، أخر الصلاة يوما، فدخل عليه عروة بن
الزبير، فأخبره أن المغيرة بن شعبة أخر الصلاة يوما وهو بالعراق، فدخل
عليه أبو مسعود الأنصاري فقال ما هذا يا مغيرة أليس قد علمت أن جبريل
نزل فصلى، فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم صلى فصلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم صلى فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم صلى
فصلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم صلى فصلى رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم قال ‏"‏ بهذا أمرت ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال عمر لعروة اعلم ما تحدث
أوإن جبريل هو أقام لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وقت الصلاة‏.‏ قال
عروة كذلك كان بشير بن أبي مسعود يحدث عن أبيه‏.‏ قال عروة ولقد
حدثتني عائشة، أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كان يصلي العصر،
والشمس في حجرتها قبل أن تظهر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn Shihab: Once `Umar bin `Abdul `Aziz
delayed the prayer and `Urwa bin Az-Zubair went to him and said,
"Once in 'Iraq, Al-Mughira bin Shu`ba delayed his prayers and Abi
Mas`ud Al-Ansari went to him and said, 'O Mughira! What is this?
Don't you know that once Gabriel came and offered the prayer (Fajr
prayer) and Allah's Apostle prayed too, then he prayed again (Zuhr
prayer) and so did Allah's Apostle and again he prayed (`Asr
prayers and Allah's Apostle did the same; again he prayed
(Maghrib-prayer) and so did Allah's Apostle and again prayed (`Isha
prayer) and so did Allah's Apostle and (Gabriel) said, 'I was
ordered to do so (to demonstrate the prayers prescribed to you)?'"
`Umar (bin `Abdul `Aziz) said to `Urwa, "Be sure of what you Say.
Did Gabriel lead Allah's Apostle at the stated times of the
prayers?" `Urwa replied, "Bashir bin Abi Mas`ud narrated like this
on the authority of his father." `Urwa added, "Aisha told me that
Allah's Apostle used to pray `Asr prayer when the sunshine was
still inside her residence (during the early time of
`Asr).</english-text>
</hadith>
