<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5164</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5365</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11013, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن ابن شهاب، أن سهل بن
سعد الساعدي، أخبره أن عويمرا العجلاني جاء إلى عاصم بن عدي الأنصاري
فقال له يا عاصم أرأيت رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا، أيقتله فتقتلونه، أم
كيف يفعل سل لي يا عاصم عن ذلك‏.‏ فسأل عاصم رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم عن ذلك فكره رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المسائل وعابها، حتى
كبر على عاصم ما سمع من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما رجع عاصم
إلى أهله جاءه عويمر فقال يا عاصم ماذا قال لك رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقال عاصم لعويمر لم تأتني بخير، قد كره رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم المسألة التي سألته عنها‏.‏ فقال عويمر والله لا أنتهي حتى
أسأله عنها‏.‏ فأقبل عويمر حتى جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وسط
الناس فقال يا رسول الله أرأيت رجلا وجد مع امرأته رجلا، أيقتله
فتقتلونه أم كيف يفعل فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ قد أنزل
فيك وفي صاحبتك فاذهب فأت بها ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سهل فتلاعنا وأنا مع الناس
عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما فرغا من تلاعنهما قال عويمر
كذبت عليها يا رسول الله إن أمسكتها‏.‏ فطلقها ثلاثا قبل أن يأمره
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ قال ابن شهاب فكانت سنة
المتلاعنين‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d As-Sa`idi: 'Uwaimir Al-Ajlani
came to `Asim bin Ad Al-Ansari and said to him, "O `Asim! Suppose a
man saw another man with his wife, would he kill him whereupon you
would kill him; or what should he do? Please, O `Asim, ask about
this on my behalf." `Asim asked Allah's Apostle about it. Allah's
Apostle, disliked that question and considered it disgraceful. What
`Asim heard from Allah's Apostle was hard on him. When `Asim
returned to his family, 'Uwaimir came to him and said, "O `Asim!
What did Allah's Apostle. say to you?" `Asim said to 'Uwaimir, "You
never bring me any good. Allah's Apostle disliked the problem which
I asked him about." 'Uwaimir said, "By Allah, I will not give up
this matter until I ask the Prophet about it." So 'Uwaimir
proceeded till he came to Allah's Apostle in the midst of people,
and said, "O Allah's Apostle! If a man sees another man with his
wife, would he kill him, whereupon you would kill him, or what
should he do?" Allah's Apostle said, "Allah has revealed some
decree as regards you and your wives case. Go and bring her." So
they carried out the process of Lian while I was present among the
people with Allah's Apostle. When they had finished their Lian,
'Uwaimir said, "O Allah's Apostle! If I should now keep her with me
as a wife, then I have told a lie." So he divorced her thrice
before Allah's Apostle ordered him. (Ibn Shihab said: So divorce
was the tradition for all those who were involved in a case of
Lian.)</english-text>
</hadith>
