<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5168</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5369</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11081, 11050, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، قال عمرو سمعت سعيد
بن جبير، قال سألت ابن عمر عن المتلاعنين،، فقال قال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم للمتلاعنين ‏"‏ حسابكما على الله أحدكما كاذب، لا سبيل لك
عليها ‏"‏‏.‏ قال مالي قال ‏"‏ لا مال لك، إن كنت صدقت عليها، فهو بما
استحللت من فرجها، وإن كنت كذبت عليها، فذاك أبعد لك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سفيان
حفظته من عمرو‏.‏ وقال أيوب سمعت سعيد بن جبير قال قلت لابن عمر رجل
لاعن امرأته فقال بإصبعيه وفرق سفيان بين إصبعيه السبابة والوسطى فرق
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بين أخوى بني العجلان، وقال ‏"‏ الله يعلم
إن أحدكما كاذب فهل منكما تائب ‏"‏‏.‏ ثلاث مرات‏.‏ قال سفيان حفظته
من عمرو وأيوب كما أخبرتك‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id bin Jubair: I asked Ibn `Umar about
those who were involved in a case of Lien. He said, "The Prophet
said to those who were involved in a case of Lien, 'Your accounts
are with Allah. One of you two is a liar, and you (the husband)
have no right over her (she is divorced)." The man said, 'What
about my property (Mahr) ?' The Prophet said, 'You have no right to
get back your property. If you have told the truth about her then
your property was for the consummation of your marriage with her;
and if you told a lie about her, then you are less rightful to get
your property back.' " Sufyan, a sub-narrator said: I learned the
Hadith from `Amr. Narrated Aiyub: I heard Sa`id bin Jubair saying,
"I asked Ibn `Umar, 'If a man (accuses his wife for an illegal
sexual intercourse and) carries out the process of Lian (what will
happen)?' Ibn `Umar set two of his fingers apart. (Sufyan set his
index finger and middle finger apart.) Ibn `Umar said, 'The Prophet
separated the couple of Bani Al-Ajlan by divorce and said thrice,
"Allah knows that one of you two is a liar; so will one of you
repent (to Allah)?' "</english-text>
</hadith>
