<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5188</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>68</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5388</hadith-number>
<chapter>Divorce - كتاب الطلاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11104, 11157, 244</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن عبد الله بن
أبي بكر بن محمد بن عمرو بن حزم، عن حميد بن نافع، عن زينب ابنة أبي
سلمة، أنها أخبرته هذه الأحاديث الثلاثة، قالت زينب دخلت على أم حبيبة
زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حين توفي أبوها أبو سفيان بن حرب، فدعت
أم حبيبة بطيب فيه صفرة خلوق أو غيره فدهنت منه جارية، ثم مست
بعارضيها، ثم قالت والله ما لي بالطيب من حاجة، غير أني سمعت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ لا يحل لامرأة تؤمن بالله واليوم
الآخر أن تحد على ميت فوق ثلاث ليال، إلا على زوج أربعة أشهر وعشرا
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Humaid bin Nafi`: Zainab bint Abu Salama
told me these three narrations: Zainab said: I went to Um Habiba,
the wife of the Prophet when her father, Abu- Sufyan bin Herb had
died. Um ,Habiba asked for a perfume which contained yellow scent
(Khaluq) or some other scent, and she first perfumed one of the
girls with it and then rubbed her cheeks with it and said, "By
Allah, I am not in need of perfume, but I have heard Allah's
Apostle saying, 'It is not lawful for a lady who believes in Allah
and the Last Day to mourn for a dead person for more than three
days unless he is her husband for whom she should mourn for four
months and ten days.' " Zainab further said: I want to Zainab bint
Jahsh when her brother died. She asked for perfume and used some of
it and said, "By Allah, I am not in need of perfume, but I have
heard Allah's Apostle saying on the pulpit, 'It is not lawful for a
lady who believes in Allah and the last day to mourn for more than
three days except for her husband for whom she should mourn for
four months and ten days.' " Zainab further said, "I heard my
mother, Um Salama saying that a woman came to Allah's Apostle and
said, "O Allah's Apostle! The husband of my daughter has died and
she is suffering from an eye disease, can she apply kohl to her
eye?" Allah's Apostle replied, "No," twice or thrice. (Every time
she repeated her question) he said, "No." Then Allah's Apostle
added, "It is just a matter of four months and ten days. In the
Pre-Islamic Period of ignorance a widow among you should throw a
globe of dung when one year has elapsed." I said to Zainab, "What
does 'throwing a globe of dung when one year had elapsed' mean?"
Zainab said, "When a lady was bereaved of her husband, she would
live in a wretched small room and put on the worst clothes she had
and would not touch any scent till one year had elapsed. Then she
would bring an animal, e.g. a donkey, a sheep or a bird and rub her
body against it. The animal against which she would rub her body
would scarcely survive. Only then she would come out of her room,
whereupon she would be given a globe of dung which she would throw
away and then she would use the scent she liked or the
like."</english-text>
</hadith>
