<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5230</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>70</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5429</hadith-number>
<chapter>Food; Meals - كتاب الأطعمة</chapter>
<chain-index>11172</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وعن أبي حازم، عن أبي هريرة، أصابني جهد شديد فلقيت عمر
بن الخطاب، فاستقرأته آية من كتاب الله، فدخل داره وفتحها على، فمشيت
غير بعيد، فخررت لوجهي من الجهد والجوع فإذا رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قائم على رأسي فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا هريرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت لبيك رسول الله
وسعديك‏.‏ فأخذ بيدي فأقامني، وعرف الذي بي، فانطلق بي إلى رحله، فأمر
لي بعس من لبن فشربت منه، ثم قال ‏"‏ عد يا أبا هر ‏"‏‏.‏ فعدت فشربت،
ثم قال ‏"‏ عد ‏"‏‏.‏ فعدت فشربت حتى استوى بطني فصار كالقدح قال
فلقيت عمر وذكرت له الذي كان من أمري وقلت له تولى الله ذلك من كان
أحق به منك يا عمر، والله لقد استقرأتك الآية ولأنا أقرأ لها منك‏.‏
قال عمر والله لأن أكون أدخلتك أحب إلى من أن يكون لي مثل حمر
النعم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Once while I was in a state of
fatigue (because of severe hunger), I met 'Umar bin Al-Khattab, so
I asked him to recite a verse from Allah's Book to me. He entered
his house and interpreted it to me. (Then I went out and) after
walking for a short distance, I fell on my face because of fatigue
and severe hunger. Suddenly I saw Allah's Apostle standing by my
head. He said, "O Abu Huraira!" I replied, "Labbaik, O Allah's
Apostle, and Sadaik!" Then he held me by the hand, and made me get
up. Then he came to know what I was suffering from. He took me to
his house, and ordered a big bowl of milk for me. I drank thereof
and he said, "Drink more, O Abu Hirr!" So I drank again, whereupon
he again said, "Drink more." So I drank more till my belly became
full and looked like a bowl. Afterwards I met 'Umar and mentioned
to him what had happened to me, and said to him, "Somebody, who had
more right than you, O 'Umar, took over the case. By Allah, I asked
you to recite a Verse to me while I knew it better than you." On
that Umar said to me, "By Allah, if I admitted and entertained you,
it would have been dearer to me than having nice red
camels.</english-text>
</hadith>
