<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5236</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>70</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5435</hadith-number>
<chapter>Food; Meals - كتاب الأطعمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد الله بن
أبي طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول قال أبو طلحة لأم سليم لقد سمعت
صوت، رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضعيفا أعرف فيه الجوع، فهل عندك من
شىء فأخرجت أقراصا من شعير، ثم أخرجت خمارا لها فلفت الخبز ببعضه، ثم
دسته تحت ثوبي وردتني ببعضه، ثم أرسلتني إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم قال فذهبت به فوجدت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في المسجد ومعه
الناس، فقمت عليهم فقال لي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرسلك
أبو طلحة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ بطعام ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فقلت نعم‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمن معه ‏"‏ قوموا ‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلق
وانطلقت بين أيديهم حتى جئت أبا طلحة، فقال أبو طلحة يا أم سليم قد
جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بالناس، وليس عندنا من الطعام ما
نطعمهم‏.‏ فقالت الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ قال فانطلق أبو طلحة حتى لقي
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأقبل أبو طلحة ورسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم حتى دخلا، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هلمي يا
أم سليم ما عندك ‏"‏‏.‏ فأتت بذلك الخبز فأمر به ففت وعصرت أم سليم
عكة لها فأدمته، ثم قال فيه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله
أن يقول ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأذن لهم، فأكلوا حتى شبعوا، ثم
خرجوا، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا، ثم
خرجوا، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا ثم
خرجوا، ثم أذن لعشرة، فأكل القوم كلهم وشبعوا، والقوم ثمانون
رجلا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Abu Talha said to Um Sulaim,
"I have heard the voice of Allah's Apostle which was feeble, and I
think that he is hungry. Have you got something (to eat)?" She took
out some loaves of barley bread, then took her face-covering sheet
and wrapped the bread in part of it, and pushed it under my garment
and turned the rest of it around my body and sent me to Allah's
Apostle . I went with that, and found Allah's Apostle in the mosque
with some people. I stood up near them, and Allah's Apostle asked
me, "Have you been sent by Abu Talha?" I said, "Yes." He asked,
"With some food (for us)?" I said, "Yes." Then Allah's Apostle said
to all those who were with him, "Get up!" He set out (and all the
people accompanied him) and I proceeded ahead of them till I came
to Abu Talha. Abu Talha then said, "O Um Sulaim! Allah's Apostle
has arrived along with the people, and we do not have food enough
to feed them all." She said, "Allah and His Apostle know better."
So Abu Talha went out till he met Allah's Apostle. Then Abu Talha
and Allah's Apostle came and entered the house. Allah's Apostle
said, "Um Sulaim ! Bring whatever you have." She brought that very
bread. The Prophet ordered that it be crushed into small pieces,
and Um Sulaim pressed a skin of butter on it. Then Allah's Apostle
said whatever Allah wished him to say (to bless the food) and then
added, "Admit ten (men)." So they were admitted, ate their fill and
went out. The Prophet then said, "Admit ten (more)." They were
admitted, ate their full, and went out. He then again said, "Admit
ten more!" They were admitted, ate their fill, and went out. He
admitted ten more, and so all those people ate their fill, and they
were eighty men.</english-text>
</hadith>
