<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5246</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>70</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5445</hadith-number>
<chapter>Food; Meals - كتاب الأطعمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30118, 20025, 20475, 11013, 17, 22</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن مقاتل أبو الحسن، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا
يونس، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني أبو أمامة بن سهل بن حنيف الأنصاري، أن
ابن عباس، أخبره أن خالد بن الوليد الذي يقال له سيف الله أخبره أنه،
دخل مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على ميمونة وهى خالته وخالة ابن
عباس فوجد عندها ضبا محنوذا، قدمت به أختها حفيدة بنت الحارث من نجد،
فقدمت الضب لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وكان قلما يقدم يده لطعام
حتى يحدث به ويسمى له، فأهوى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يده إلى
الضب، فقالت امرأة من النسوة الحضور أخبرن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ما قدمتن له، هو الضب يا رسول الله‏.‏ فرفع رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يده عن الضب، فقال خالد بن الوليد أحرام الضب يا رسول الله
قال ‏"‏ لا ولكن لم يكن بأرض قومي فأجدني أعافه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال خالد
فاجتررته فأكلته ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ينظر
إلى‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Khalid bin Al-Walid: That he went with
Allah's Apostle to the house of Maimuna, who was his and Ibn
`Abbas' aunt. He found with her a roasted mastigure which her
sister Hufaida bint Al-Harith had brought from Najd. Maimuna
presented the mastigure before Allah's Apostle who rarely started
eating any (unfamiliar) food before it was described and named for
him. (But that time) Allah's Apostle stretched his hand towards the
(meat of the) mastigure whereupon a lady from among those who were
present, said, "You should inform Allah's Apostle of what you have
presented to him. O Allah's Apostle! It is the meat of a
mastigure." (On learning that) Allah's Apostle withdrew his hand
from the meat of the mastigure. Khalid bin Al-Walid said, "O
Allah's Apostle! Is this unlawful to eat?" Allah's Apostle replied,
"No, but it is not found in the land of my people, so I do not like
it." Khalid said, "Then I pulled the mastigure (meat) towards me
and ate it while Allah's Apostle was looking at me.</english-text>
</hadith>
