<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5281</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>70</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5480</hadith-number>
<chapter>Food; Meals - كتاب الأطعمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20155, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا إسماعيل بن جعفر، عن عمرو بن أبي
عمرو، مولى المطلب بن عبد الله بن حنطب أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأبي طلحة ‏"‏ التمس غلاما من غلمانكم
يخدمني ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرج بي أبو طلحة، يردفني وراءه، فكنت أخدم رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم كلما نزل، فكنت أسمعه يكثر أن يقول ‏"‏ اللهم إني
أعوذ بك من الهم والحزن، والعجز والكسل، والبخل والجبن وضلع الدين،
وغلبة الرجال ‏"‏‏.‏ فلم أزل أخدمه حتى أقبلنا من خيبر، وأقبل بصفية
بنت حيى قد حازها، فكنت أراه يحوي وراءه بعباءة أو بكساء، ثم يردفها
وراءه، حتى إذا كنا بالصهباء صنع حيسا في نطع، ثم أرسلني فدعوت رجالا
فأكلوا، وكان ذلك بناءه بها، ثم أقبل حتى إذا بدا له أحد قال ‏"‏ هذا
جبل يحبنا ونحبه ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما أشرف على المدينة قال ‏"‏ اللهم إني أحرم
ما بين جبليها مثل ما حرم به إبراهيم مكة، اللهم بارك لهم في مدهم
وصاعهم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Allah's Apostle said to Abu
Talha, "Seek one of your boys to serve me." Abu Talha mounted me
behind him (on his riding animal) and took me (to the Prophet ). So
I used to serve Allah's Apostle whenever he dismounted (to stay
somewhere). I used to hear him saying very often, "O Allah! I seek
refuge with You from, having worries sadness, helplessness,
laziness, miserliness, cowardice, from being heavily in debt and
from being overpowered by other persons unjustly." I kept on
serving till we -returned from the battle of Khaibar. The Prophet
then brought Safiyya bint Huyai whom he had won from the war booty.
I saw him folding up a gown or a garment for her to sit on behind
him (on his shecamel). When he reached As-Sahba', he prepared Hais
and placed it on a dining sheet. Then he sent me to invite men, who
(came and) ate; and that was his and Safiyya's wedding banquet.
Then the Prophet proceeded, and when he saw (noticed) the mountain
of Uhud, he said, "This mountain loves us, and we love it." When we
approached Medina, he said, "O Allah! I make the area between its
two mountains a sanctuary as Abraham has made Mecca a sanctuary. O
Allah! Bless their Mudd and Sa (special kinds of
measure).</english-text>
</hadith>
