<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5300</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>70</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5499</hadith-number>
<chapter>Food; Meals - كتاب الأطعمة</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20179, 11172, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، حدثنا أبو غسان، قال حدثني أبو
حازم، عن إبراهيم بن عبد الرحمن بن عبد الله بن أبي ربيعة، عن جابر بن
عبد الله، رضى الله عنهما قال كان بالمدينة يهودي وكان يسلفني في تمري
إلى الجداد، وكانت لجابر الأرض التي بطريق رومة فجلست، فخلا عاما
فجاءني اليهودي عند الجداد، ولم أجد منها شيئا، فجعلت أستنظره إلى
قابل فيأبى، فأخبر بذلك النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال لأصحابه ‏"‏
امشوا نستنظر لجابر من اليهودي ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاءوني في نخلي فجعل النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم يكلم اليهودي فيقول أبا القاسم لا أنظره‏.‏ فلما رأى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قام فطاف في النخل، ثم جاءه فكلمه فأبى فقمت
فجئت بقليل رطب فوضعته بين يدى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأكل ثم قال
‏"‏ أين عريشك يا جابر ‏"‏‏.‏ فأخبرته فقال ‏"‏ افرش لي فيه ‏"‏‏.‏
ففرشته فدخل فرقد، ثم استيقظ فجئته بقبضة أخرى فأكل منها، ثم قام فكلم
اليهودي فأبى عليه فقام في الرطاب في النخل الثانية ثم قال ‏"‏ يا
جابر جد واقض ‏"‏‏.‏ فوقف في الجداد فجددت منها ما قضيته وفضل منه
فخرجت حتى جئت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فبشرته فقال ‏"‏ أشهد أني
رسول الله ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: There was a Jew in
Medina who used to lend me money up to the season of plucking
dates. (Jabir had a piece of land which was on the way to Ruma).
That year the land was not promising, so the payment of the debt
was delayed one year. The Jew came to me at the time of plucking,
but gathered nothing from my land. I asked him to give me one year
respite, but he refused. This news reached the Prophet whereupon he
said to his companions, "Let us go and ask the Jew for respite for
Jabir." All of them came to me in my garden, and the Prophet
started speaking to the Jew, but he Jew said, "O Abu Qasim! I will
not grant him respite." When the Prophet saw the Jew's attitude, he
stood up and walked all around the garden and came again and talked
to the Jew, but the Jew refused his request. I got up and brought
some ripe fresh dates and put it in front of the Prophet. He ate
and then said to me, "Where is your hut, O Jabir?" I informed him,
and he said, "Spread out a bed for me in it." I spread out a bed,
and he entered and slept. When he woke up, I brought some dates to
him again and he ate of it and then got up and talked to the Jew
again, but the Jew again refused his request. Then the Prophet got
up for the second time amidst the palm trees loaded with fresh
dates, and said, "O Jabir! Pluck dates to repay your debt." The Jew
remained with me while I was plucking the dates, till I paid him
all his right, yet there remained extra quantity of dates. So I
went out and proceeded till I reached the Prophet and informed him
of the good news, whereupon he said, "I testify that I am Allah's
Apostle."</english-text>
</hadith>
