<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5346</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>72</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5546</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hunting; Slaughtering - كتاب الذبائح والصيد</chapter>
<chain-index>20241, 30300, 30340, 20025, 26010, 11414</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو عاصم، عن حيوة،‏.‏ وحدثني أحمد بن أبي رجاء،
حدثنا سلمة بن سليمان، عن ابن المبارك، عن حيوة بن شريح، قال سمعت
ربيعة بن يزيد الدمشقي، قال أخبرني أبو إدريس، عائذ الله قال سمعت أبا
ثعلبة الخشني رضى الله عنه يقول أتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقلت يا رسول الله إنا بأرض قوم أهل الكتاب، نأكل في آنيتهم، وأرض صيد
أصيد بقوسي، وأصيد بكلبي المعلم، والذي ليس معلما، فأخبرني ما الذي
يحل لنا من ذلك فقال ‏"‏ أما ما ذكرت أنك بأرض قوم أهل الكتاب، تأكل
في آنيتهم، فإن وجدتم غير آنيتهم، فلا تأكلوا فيها، وإن لم تجدوا
فاغسلوها ثم كلوا فيها، وأما ما ذكرت أنك بأرض صيد، فما صدت بقوسك،
فاذكر اسم الله، ثم كل، وما صدت بكلبك المعلم، فاذكر اسم الله، ثم كل،
وما صدت بكلبك الذي ليس معلما فأدركت ذكاته، فكل ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Tha`laba Al-Khushani: I came to Allah's
Apostle and said, "O Allah's Apostle! We are living in the land of
the people of the Scripture and we take our meals in their
utensils, and in the land there is game and I hunt with my bow and
trained or untrained hounds; please tell me what is lawful for us
of that." He said, "As for your saying that you are living in the
land of the people of the Scripture and that you eat in their
utensils, if you can get utensils other than theirs, do not eat in
their utensils, but if you do not find (other than theirs), then
wash their utensils and eat in them. As for your saying that you
are in the land of game, if you hung something with your bow, and
have mentioned Allah's Name while hunting, then you can eat (the
game). And if you hunt something with your trained hound, and have
mentioned Allah's Name on sending it for hunting then you can eat
(the game). But if you hunt something with your untrained hound and
you were able to slaughter it before its death, you can eat of
it."</english-text>
</hadith>
