<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5350</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>72</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5550</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hunting; Slaughtering - كتاب الذبائح والصيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30220, 20029, 20377, 20390, 391</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن سليمان، قال حدثني ابن وهب، أخبرنا عمرو،
أن أبا النضر، حدثه عن نافع، مولى أبي قتادة وأبي صالح مولى التوأمة
سمعت أبا قتادة، قال كنت مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فيما بين مكة
والمدينة وهم محرمون وأنا رجل حل على فرس، وكنت رقاء على الجبال،
فبينا أنا على ذلك إذ رأيت الناس متشوفين لشىء، فذهبت أنظر، فإذا هو
حمار وحش فقلت لهم ما هذا قالوا لا ندري‏.‏ قلت هو حمار وحشي‏.‏
فقالوا هو ما رأيت‏.‏ وكنت نسيت سوطي فقلت لهم ناولوني سوطي‏.‏ فقالوا
لا نعينك عليه‏.‏ فنزلت فأخذته، ثم ضربت في أثره، فلم يكن إلا ذاك،
حتى عقرته، فأتيت إليهم فقلت لهم قوموا فاحتملوا‏.‏ قالوا لا نمسه‏.‏
فحملته حتى جئتهم به، فأبى بعضهم، وأكل بعضهم، فقلت أنا أستوقف لكم
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأدركته فحدثته الحديث فقال لي ‏"‏ أبقي
معكم شىء منه ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت نعم‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ كلوا فهو طعم أطعمكموها الله
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Qatada: I was with the Prophet (on a
journey) between Mecca and Medina, and all of them, (i.e. the
Prophet and his companions) were in the state of Ihram, while I was
not in that state. I was riding my horse and I used to be fond of
ascending mountains. So while I was doing so I noticed that the
people were looking at something. I went to see what it was, and
behold it was an onager. I asked my companions, "What is that?"
They said, "We do not know." I said, "It is an onager.' They said,
"It is what you have seen." I had left my whip, so I said to them,
"Hand to me my whip." They said, "We will not help you in that (in
hunting the onager)." I got down, took my whip and chased the
animal (on my horse) and did not stop till I killed it. I went to
them and said, "Come on, carry it!" But they said, "We will not
even touch it." At last I alone carried it and brought it to them.
Some of them ate of it and some refused to eat of it. I said (to
them), "I will ask the Prophet about it (on your behalf)." When I
met the Prophet, I told him the whole story. He said to me, "Has
anything of it been left with you?" I said, "Yes." He said, "Eat,
for it is a meal Allah has offered to you."</english-text>
</hadith>
