<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5356</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>72</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5556</hadith-number>
<chapter>Hunting; Slaughtering - كتاب الذبائح والصيد</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 20016, 11179, 1986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن سعيد بن
مسروق، عن عباية بن رفاعة بن رافع، عن جده، رافع بن خديج قال كنا مع
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بذي الحليفة، فأصاب الناس جوع، فأصبنا إبلا
وغنما، وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في أخريات الناس، فعجلوا فنصبوا
القدور، فدفع إليهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأمر بالقدور فأكفئت، ثم
قسم فعدل عشرة من الغنم ببعير، فند منها بعير، وكان في القوم خيل
يسيرة فطلبوه فأعياهم، فأهوى إليه رجل بسهم فحبسه الله فقال النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن لهذه البهائم أوابد كأوابد الوحش، فما ند عليكم
فاصنعوا به هكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال وقال جدي إنا لنرجو أو نخاف أن نلقى العدو
غدا، وليس معنا مدى، أفنذبح بالقصب فقال ‏"‏ ما أنهر الدم وذكر اسم
الله عليه فكل، ليس السن والظفر، وسأخبركم عنه، أما السن عظم وأما
الظفر فمدى الحبشة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Rafi` bin Khadij: We were with the Prophet
in Dhul-Hulaifa and there the people were struck with severe
hunger. Then we got camels and sheep as war booty (and slaughtered
them). The Prophet was behind all the people. The people hurried
and fixed the cooking pots (for cooking) but the Prophet came there
and ordered that the cooking pots be turned upside down. Then he
distributed the animals, regarding ten sheep as equal to one camel.
One of the camels ran away and there were a few horses with the
people. They chased the camel but they got tired, whereupon a man
shot it with an arrow whereby Allah stopped it. The Prophet said,
"Among these animals some are as wild as wild beasts, so if one of
them runs away from you, treat it in this way." I said. "We hope,
or we are afraid that tomorrow we will meet the enemy and we have
no knives, shall we slaughter (our animals) with canes?" The
Prophet said, "If the killing tool causes blood to gush out and if
Allah's Name is mentioned, eat (of the slaughterer animal). But do
not slaughter with a tooth or a nail. I am telling you why: A tooth
is a bone, and the nail is the knife of Ethiopians."</english-text>
</hadith>
