<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5409</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>73</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5608</hadith-number>
<chapter>Al-Adha Festival Sacrifice (Adaahi) - كتاب
الأضاحي</chapter>
<chain-index>30376, 20259, 11015, 20278, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن سلام، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا أيوب، عن
محمد، عن ابن أبي بكرة، عن أبي بكرة رضى الله عنه عن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ الزمان قد استدار كهيئته يوم خلق الله السموات
والأرض، السنة اثنا عشر شهرا، منها أربعة حرم، ثلاث متواليات ذو
القعدة وذو الحجة والمحرم، ورجب مضر الذي بين جمادى وشعبان، أى شهر
هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير
اسمه، قال ‏"‏ أليس ذا الحجة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أى بلد هذا
‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه،
قال ‏"‏ أليس البلدة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأى يوم هذا ‏"‏‏.‏
قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم، فسكت حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه قال ‏"‏
أليس يوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم قال
محمد وأحسبه قال وأعراضكم عليكم حرام كحرمة يومكم هذا، في بلدكم هذا
في شهركم، وستلقون ربكم فيسألكم عن أعمالكم، ألا فلا ترجعوا بعدي
ضلالا، يضرب بعضكم رقاب بعض، ألا ليبلغ الشاهد الغائب، فلعل بعض من
يبلغه أن يكون أوعى له من بعض من سمعه وكان محمد إذا ذكره قال صدق
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم قال ألا هل بلغت ألا هل بلغت
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Bakra: The Prophet said, "Time has come
back to its original state which it had on the day Allah created
the Heavens and the Earth. The year is twelve months, four of which
are sacred, three of them are in succession, namely Dhul-Qa'da,
Dhul Hijja and Muharram, (the fourth being) Rajab Mudar which is
between Juma'da (ath-thamj and Sha'ban. The Prophet then asked,
"Which month is this?" We said, "Allah and his Apostle know
better." He kept silent so long that we thought that he would call
it by a name other than its real name. He said, "Isn't it the month
of Dhul-Hijja?" We said, "Yes." He said, "Which town is this?" We
said, "Allah and His Apostle know better." He kept silent so long
that we thought that he would call it t,y a name other than its
real name. He said, "isn't it the town (of Mecca)?" We replied,
"Yes." He said, "What day is today?" We replied, "Allah and His
Apostle know better." He kept silent so long that we thought that
he would call it by a name other than its real name. He said,
"Isn't it the day of Nahr?" We replied, "Yes." He then said, "Your
blood, properties and honor are as sacred to one another as this
day of yours in this town of yours in this month of yours. You will
meet your Lord, and He will ask you about your deeds. Beware! Do
not go astray after me by cutting the necks of each other. It is
incumbent upon those who are present to convey this message to
those who are absent, for some of those to whom it is conveyed may
comprehend it better than some of those who have heard it
directly." (Muhammad, the sub-narrator, on mentioning this used to
say: The Prophet then said, "No doubt! Haven't I delivered
(Allah's) Message (to you)? Haven't I delivered Allah's message (to
you)?"</english-text>
</hadith>
