<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5473</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>74</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5671</hadith-number>
<chapter>Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد
الله، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول كان أبو طلحة أكثر أنصاري بالمدينة
مالا من نخل، وكان أحب ماله إليه بيرحاء، وكانت مستقبل المسجد، وكان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يدخلها ويشرب من ماء فيها طيب‏.‏ قال
أنس فلما نزلت ‏{‏لن تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا مما تحبون‏}‏ قام أبو
طلحة فقال يا رسول الله إن الله يقول ‏{‏لن تنالوا البر حتى تنفقوا
مما تحبون‏}‏ وإن أحب مالي إلى بيرحاء، وإنها صدقة لله أرجو برها
وذخرها عند الله فضعها يا رسول الله حيث أراك الله‏.‏ فقال رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ بخ ذلك مال رابح أو رايح شك عبد الله وقد سمعت
ما قلت وإني أرى أن تجعلها في الأقربين ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أبو طلحة أفعل يا
رسول الله، فقسمها أبو طلحة في أقاربه وفي بني عمه‏.‏ وقال إسماعيل
ويحيى بن يحيى رايح‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Abu Talha had the largest
number of datepalms from amongst the Ansars of Medina. The dearest
of his property to him was Bairuha garden which was facing the
(Prophet's) Mosque. Allah's Apostle used to enter it and drink of
its good fresh water. When the Holy Verse:-- 'By no means shall you
attain righteousness unless you spend (in charity) of that which
you love.' (3.92) was revealed, Abu Talha got up and said, "O
Allah's Apostle! Allah says: By no means shall you attain
righteousness unless you spend of that which you love,' and the
dearest of my property to me is the Bairuha garden and I want to
give it in charity in Allah's Cause, seeking to be rewarded by
Allah for that. So you can spend it, O Allah's Apostle, where-ever
Allah instructs you. ' Allah s Apostle said, "Good! That is a
perishable (or profitable) wealth" (`Abdullah is in doubt as to
which word was used.) He said, "I have heard what you have said but
in my opinion you'd better give it to your kith and kin." On that
Abu Talha said, "I will do so, O Allah's Apostle!" Abu Talha
distributed that garden among his kith and kin and
cousins.</english-text>
</hadith>
