<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5499</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>74</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5697</hadith-number>
<chapter>Drinks - كتاب الأشربة</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20179, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، حدثنا أبو غسان، قال حدثني أبو
حازم، عن سهل بن سعد رضى الله عنه قال ذكر للنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
امرأة من العرب، فأمر أبا أسيد الساعدي أن يرسل إليها فأرسل إليها،
فقدمت فنزلت في أجم بني ساعدة، فخرج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى
جاءها فدخل عليها فإذا امرأة منكسة رأسها، فلما كلمها النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قالت أعوذ بالله منك‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ قد أعذتك مني ‏"‏‏.‏
فقالوا لها أتدرين من هذا قالت لا‏.‏ قالوا هذا رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم جاء ليخطبك‏.‏ قالت كنت أنا أشقى من ذلك‏.‏ فأقبل النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم يومئذ حتى جلس في سقيفة بني ساعدة هو وأصحابه، ثم قال
‏"‏ اسقنا يا سهل ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرجت لهم بهذا القدح فأسقيتهم فيه، فأخرج
لنا سهل ذلك القدح فشربنا منه‏.‏ قال ثم استوهبه عمر بن عبد العزيز
بعد ذلك فوهبه له‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d: An Arab lady was mentioned to
the Prophet so he asked Abu Usaid As-Sa`idi to send for her, and he
sent for her and she came and stayed in the castle of Bani Sa`ida.
The Prophet came out and went to her and entered upon her. Behold,
it was a lady sitting with a drooping head. When the Prophet spoke
to her, she said, "I seek refuge with Allah from you." He said, "I
grant you refuge from me." They said to her, "Do you know who this
is?" She said, "No." They said, "This is Allah's Apostle who has
come to command your hand in marriage." She said, "I am very
unlucky to lose this chance." Then the Prophet and his companions
went towards the shed of Bani Sa`ida and sat there. Then he said,
"Give us water, O Sahl!" So I took out this drinking bowl and gave
them water in it. The sub-narrator added: Sahl took out for us that
very drinking bowl and we all drank from it. Later on `Umar bin
`Abdul `Aziz requested Sahl to give it to him as a present, and he
gave it to him as a present.</english-text>
</hadith>
