<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5525</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>75</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5725</hadith-number>
<chapter>Patients - كتاب المرضى</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 10511, 50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني يحيى بن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب،
عن عروة، أن أسامة بن زيد، أخبره أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ركب على
حمار على إكاف على قطيفة فدكية، وأردف أسامة وراءه يعود سعد بن عبادة
قبل وقعة بدر فسار حتى مر بمجلس فيه عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول وذلك
قبل أن يسلم عبد الله، وفي المجلس أخلاط من المسلمين والمشركين عبدة
الأوثان واليهود، وفي المجلس عبد الله بن رواحة، فلما غشيت المجلس
عجاجة الدابة خمر عبد الله بن أبى أنفه بردائه، قال لا تغيروا علينا
فسلم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ووقف ونزل فدعاهم إلى الله فقرأ عليهم
القرآن، فقال له عبد الله بن أبى يا أيها المرء إنه لا أحسن مما تقول
إن كان حقا، فلا تؤذنا به في مجلسنا، وارجع إلى رحلك فمن جاءك فاقصص
عليه‏.‏ قال ابن رواحة بلى يا رسول الله فاغشنا به في مجالسنا فإنا
نحب ذلك فاستب المسلمون والمشركون واليهود حتى كادوا يتثاورون فلم يزل
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى سكتوا فركب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
دابته حتى دخل على سعد بن عبادة فقال له ‏"‏ أى سعد ألم تسمع ما قال
أبو حباب ‏"‏‏.‏ يريد عبد الله بن أبى‏.‏ قال سعد يا رسول الله اعف
عنه واصفح فلقد أعطاك الله ما أعطاك ولقد اجتمع أهل هذه البحرة أن
يتوجوه فيعصبوه فلما رد ذلك بالحق الذي أعطاك شرق بذلك، فذلك الذي فعل
به ما رأيت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Usama bin Zaid: The Prophet rode a donkey
having a saddle with a Fadakiyya velvet covering. He mounted me
behind him and went to visit Sa`d bin 'Ubada, and that had been
before the battle of Badr. The Prophet proceeded till he passed by
a gathering in which `Abdullah bin Ubai bin Salul was present, and
that had been before `Abdullah embraced Islam. The gathering
comprised of Muslims, polytheists, i.e., isolators and Jews.
`Abdullah bin Rawaha was also present in that gathering. When dust
raised by the donkey covered the gathering, `Abdullah bin Ubai
covered his nose with his upper garment and said, "Do not trouble
us with dust." The Prophet greeted them, stopped and dismounted.
Then he invited them to Allah (i.e., to embrace Islam) and recited
to them some verses of the Holy Qur'an. On that, `Abdullah bin Ubai
said, "O man ! There is nothing better than what you say if it is
true. Do not trouble us with it in our gathering, but return to
your house, and if somebody comes to you, teach him there." On that
`Abdullah bin Rawaha said, Yes, O Allah's Apostle! Bring your
teachings to our gathering, for we love that." So the Muslims, the
pagans and the Jews started abusing each other till they were about
to fight. The Prophet kept on quietening them till they became
calm. Thereupon the Prophet mounted his animal and proceeded till
he entered upon Sa`d bin Ubada. He said to him "O Sa`d! Have you
not heard what Abu Hubab (i.e., `Abdullah bin Ubai) said?" Sa`d
said, 'O Allah's Apostle! Excuse and forgive him, for Allah has
given you what He has given you. The people of this town (Medina
decided unanimously to crown him and make him their chief by
placing a turban on his head, but when that was prevented by the
Truth which Allah had given you he (`Abdullah bin Ubai) was grieved
out of jealously, and that was the reason which caused him to
behave in the way you have seen."</english-text>
</hadith>
