<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5564</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>76</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5767</hadith-number>
<chapter>Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>30156, 20356, 15097, 11052, 123</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمران بن ميسرة، حدثنا ابن فضيل، حدثنا حصين، عن
عامر، عن عمران بن حصين رضى الله عنهما قال لا رقية إلا من عين أو
حمة‏.‏ فذكرته لسعيد بن جبير فقال حدثنا ابن عباس قال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ عرضت على الأمم، فجعل النبي والنبيان يمرون معهم
الرهط، والنبي ليس معه أحد، حتى رفع لي سواد عظيم، قلت ما هذا أمتي
هذه قيل هذا موسى وقومه‏.‏ قيل انظر إلى الأفق‏.‏ فإذا سواد يملأ
الأفق، ثم قيل لي انظر ها هنا وها هنا في آفاق السماء فإذا سواد قد
ملأ الأفق قيل هذه أمتك ويدخل الجنة من هؤلاء سبعون ألفا بغير حساب،
ثم دخل ولم يبين لهم فأفاض القوم وقالوا نحن الذين آمنا بالله،
واتبعنا رسوله، فنحن هم أو أولادنا الذين ولدوا في الإسلام فإنا ولدنا
في الجاهلية‏.‏ فبلغ النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرج فقال هم الذين لا
يسترقون، ولا يتطيرون، ولا يكتوون وعلى ربهم يتوكلون ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال
عكاشة بن محصن أمنهم أنا يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ نعم ‏"‏‏.‏ فقام آخر
فقال أمنهم أنا قال ‏"‏ سبقك عكاشة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: Allah's Apostle said, 'Nations
were displayed before me; one or two prophets would pass by along
with a few followers. A prophet would pass by accompanied by
nobody. Then a big crowd of people passed in front of me and I
asked, Who are they Are they my followers?" It was said, 'No. It is
Moses and his followers It was said to me, 'Look at the horizon.''
Behold! There was a multitude of people filling the horizon. Then
it was said to me, 'Look there and there about the stretching sky!
Behold! There was a multitude filling the horizon,' It was said to
me, 'This is your nation out of whom seventy thousand shall enter
Paradise without reckoning.' "Then the Prophet entered his house
without telling his companions who they (the 70,000) were. So the
people started talking about the issue and said, "It is we who have
believed in Allah and followed His Apostle; therefore those people
are either ourselves or our children who are born m the Islamic
era, for we were born in the Pre-lslamic Period of Ignorance.''
When the Prophet heard of that, he came out and said. "Those people
are those who do not treat themselves with Ruqya, nor do they
believe in bad or good omen (from birds etc.) nor do they get
themselves branded (Cauterized). but they put their trust (only) in
their Lord " On that 'Ukasha bin Muhsin said. "Am I one of them, O
Allah's Apostle?' The Prophet said, "Yes." Then another person got
up and said, "Am I one of them?" The Prophet said, 'Ukasha has
anticipated you."</english-text>
</hadith>
