<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5570</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>76</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5774</hadith-number>
<chapter>Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>30318, 20025, 20115, 20475, 11013, 11004,
53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا بشر بن محمد، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا معمر،
ويونس، قال الزهري أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، أن عائشة
رضى الله عنها زوج النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت لما ثقل رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم واشتد وجعه، استأذن أزواجه في أن يمرض في بيتي،
فأذن، فخرج بين رجلين، تخط رجلاه في الأرض بين عباس وآخر‏.‏ فأخبرت
ابن عباس قال هل تدري من الرجل الآخر الذي لم تسم عائشة قلت لا‏.‏ قال
هو علي‏.‏ قالت عائشة فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بعد ما دخل بيتها
واشتد به وجعه ‏"‏ هريقوا على من سبع قرب لم تحلل أوكيتهن، لعلي أعهد
إلى الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فأجلسناه في مخضب لحفصة زوج النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم طفقنا نصب عليه من تلك القرب، حتى جعل يشير إلينا أن قد
فعلتن‏.‏ قالت وخرج إلى الناس فصلى لهم وخطبهم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: (the wife of the Prophet) When the
health of Allah's Apostle deteriorated and his condition became
serious, he asked the permission of all his wives to allow him to
be treated In my house, and they allowed him. He came out,
supported by two men and his legs were dragging on the ground
between `Abbas and another man. (The sub-narrator told Ibn `Abbas
who said: Do you know who was the other man whom `Aisha did not
mention? The sub-narrator said: No. Ibn `Abbas said: It was `Ali.)
`Aisha added: When the Prophet entered my house and his disease
became aggravated, he said, "Pour on me seven water skins full of
water (the tying ribbons of which had not been untied) so that I
may give some advice to the people." So we made him sit in a tub
belonging to Hafsa, the wife of the Prophet and started pouring
water on him from those water skins till he waved us to stop. Then
he went out to the people and led them in prayer and delivered a
speech before them.</english-text>
</hadith>
