<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5584</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>76</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5788</hadith-number>
<chapter>Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11013, 11190, 11513, 17, 3</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عبد الحميد بن عبد الرحمن بن زيد بن الخطاب، عن عبد الله بن عبد الله
بن الحارث بن نوفل، عن عبد الله بن عباس، أن عمر بن الخطاب رضى الله
عنه خرج إلى الشأم حتى إذا كان بسرغ لقيه أمراء الأجناد أبو عبيدة بن
الجراح وأصحابه، فأخبروه أن الوباء قد وقع بأرض الشأم‏.‏ قال ابن عباس
فقال عمر ادع لي المهاجرين الأولين‏.‏ فدعاهم فاستشارهم وأخبرهم أن
الوباء قد وقع بالشأم فاختلفوا‏.‏ فقال بعضهم قد خرجت لأمر، ولا نرى
أن ترجع عنه‏.‏ وقال بعضهم معك بقية الناس وأصحاب رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ولا نرى أن تقدمهم على هذا الوباء‏.‏ فقال ارتفعوا عني‏.‏
ثم قال ادعوا لي الأنصار‏.‏ فدعوتهم فاستشارهم، فسلكوا سبيل
المهاجرين، واختلفوا كاختلافهم، فقال ارتفعوا عني‏.‏ ثم قال ادع لي من
كان ها هنا من مشيخة قريش من مهاجرة الفتح‏.‏ فدعوتهم، فلم يختلف منهم
عليه رجلان، فقالوا نرى أن ترجع بالناس، ولا تقدمهم على هذا الوباء،
فنادى عمر في الناس، إني مصبح على ظهر، فأصبحوا عليه‏.‏ قال أبو عبيدة
بن الجراح أفرارا من قدر الله فقال عمر لو غيرك قالها يا أبا عبيدة،
نعم نفر من قدر الله إلى قدر الله، أرأيت لو كان لك إبل هبطت واديا له
عدوتان، إحداهما خصبة، والأخرى جدبة، أليس إن رعيت الخصبة رعيتها بقدر
الله، وإن رعيت الجدبة رعيتها بقدر الله قال فجاء عبد الرحمن بن عوف،
وكان متغيبا في بعض حاجته فقال إن عندي في هذا علما سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ إذا سمعتم به بأرض فلا تقدموا عليه، وإذا
وقع بأرض وأنتم بها فلا تخرجوا فرارا منه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فحمد الله عمر ثم
انصرف‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: `Umar bin Al-Khattab
departed for Sham and when he reached Sargh, the commanders of the
(Muslim) army, Abu 'Ubaida bin Al-Jarrah and his companions met him
and told him that an epidemic had broken out in Sham. `Umar said,
"Call for me the early emigrants." So `Umar called them, consulted
them and informed them that an epidemic had broken out in Sham.
Those people differed in their opinions. Some of them said, "We
have come out for a purpose and we do not think that it is proper
to give it up," while others said (to `Umar), "You have along with
you. other people and the companions of Allah's Apostle so do not
advise that we take them to this epidemic." `Umar said to them,
"Leave me now." Then he said, "Call the Ansar for me." I called
them and he consulted them and they followed the way of the
emigrants and differed as they did. He then said to them, Leave me
now," and added, "Call for me the old people of Quraish who
emigrated in the year of the Conquest of Mecca." I called them and
they gave a unanimous opinion saying, "We advise that you should
return with the people and do not take them to that (place) of
epidemic." So `Umar made an announcement, "I will ride back to
Medina in the morning, so you should do the same." Abu 'Ubaida bin
Al-Jarrah said (to `Umar), "Are you running away from what Allah
had ordained?" `Umar said, "Would that someone else had said such a
thing, O Abu 'Ubaida! Yes, we are running from what Allah had
ordained to what Allah has ordained. Don't you agree that if you
had camels that went down a valley having two places, one green and
the other dry, you would graze them on the green one only if Allah
had ordained that, and you would graze them on the dry one only if
Allah had ordained that?" At that time `Abdur-Rahman bin `Auf, who
had been absent because of some job, came and said, "I have some
knowledge about this. I have heard Allah's Apostle saying, 'If you
hear about it (an outbreak of plague) in a land, do not go to it;
but if plague breaks out in a country where you are staying, do not
run away from it.' " `Umar thanked Allah and returned to
Medina.</english-text>
</hadith>
