<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5604</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>76</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5808</hadith-number>
<chapter>Medicine - كتاب الطب</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 11419, 11297, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن أبي بشر، عن
أبي المتوكل، عن أبي سعيد، أن رهطا، من أصحاب رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم انطلقوا في سفرة سافروها، حتى نزلوا بحى من أحياء العرب
فاستضافوهم، فأبوا أن يضيفوهم، فلدغ سيد ذلك الحى، فسعوا له بكل شىء
لا ينفعه شىء، فقال بعضهم لو أتيتم هؤلاء الرهط الذين قد نزلوا بكم،
لعله أن يكون عند بعضهم شىء‏.‏ فأتوهم فقالوا يا أيها الرهط إن سيدنا
لدغ، فسعينا له بكل شىء، لا ينفعه شىء، فهل عند أحد منكم شىء فقال
بعضهم نعم، والله إني لراق، ولكن والله لقد استضفناكم فلم تضيفونا،
فما أنا براق لكم حتى تجعلوا لنا جعلا‏.‏ فصالحوهم على قطيع من الغنم،
فانطلق فجعل يتفل ويقرأ ‏{‏الحمد لله رب العالمين‏}‏ حتى لكأنما نشط
من عقال، فانطلق يمشي ما به قلبة‏.‏ قال فأوفوهم جعلهم الذي صالحوهم
عليه، فقال بعضهم اقسموا‏.‏ فقال الذي رقى لا تفعلوا حتى نأتي رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فنذكر له الذي كان، فننظر ما يأمرنا‏.‏
فقدموا على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذكروا له فقال ‏"‏ وما
يدريك أنها رقية أصبتم اقسموا واضربوا لي معكم بسهم
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id: A group of the companions of
Allah's Apostle proceeded on a journey till they dismounted near
one of the Arab tribes and requested them to entertain them as
their guests, but they (the tribe people) refused to entertain
them. Then the chief of that tribe was bitten by a snake (or stung
by a scorpion) and he was given all sorts of treatment, but all in
vain. Some of them said, "Will you go to the group (those
travelers) who have dismounted near you and see if one of them has
something useful?" They came to them and said, "O the group! Our
leader has been bitten by a snake (or stung by a scorpion) and we
have treated him with everything but nothing benefited him Has
anyone of you anything useful?" One of them replied, "Yes, by
Allah, I know how to treat with a Ruqya. But. by Allah, we wanted
you to receive us as your guests but you refused. I will not treat
your patient with a Ruqya till you fix for us something as wages."
Consequently they agreed to give those travellers a flock of sheep.
The man went with them (the people of the tribe) and started
spitting (on the bite) and reciting Surat-al-Fatiha till the
patient was healed and started walking as if he had not been sick.
When the tribe people paid them their wages they had agreed upon,
some of them (the Prophet's companions) said, "Distribute (the
sheep)." But the one who treated with the Ruqya said, "Do not do
that till we go to Allah's Apostle and mention to him what has
happened, and see what he will order us." So they came to Allah's
Apostle and mentioned the story to him and he said, "How do you
know that Surat-al-Fatiha is a Ruqya? You have done the right
thing. Divide (what you have got) and assign for me a share with
you."</english-text>
</hadith>
