<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5676</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>77</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5884</hadith-number>
<chapter>Dress - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>30160, 20259, 11015, 11023</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن بشار، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، أخبرنا أيوب، عن
عكرمة، أن رفاعة، طلق امرأته، فتزوجها عبد الرحمن بن الزبير القرظي،
قالت عائشة وعليها خمار أخضر‏.‏ فشكت إليها، وأرتها خضرة بجلدها، فلما
جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم والنساء ينصر بعضهن بعضا قالت عائشة
ما رأيت مثل ما يلقى المؤمنات، لجلدها أشد خضرة من ثوبها‏.‏ قال وسمع
أنها قد أتت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فجاء ومعه ابنان له من
غيرها‏.‏ قالت والله ما لي إليه من ذنب، إلا أن ما معه ليس بأغنى عني
من هذه‏.‏ وأخذت هدبة من ثوبها، فقال كذبت والله يا رسول الله، إني
لأنفضها نفض الأديم، ولكنها ناشز تريد رفاعة‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فإن كان ذلك لم تحلي له أو لم تصلحي له حتى يذوق
من عسيلتك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال وأبصر معه ابنين فقال ‏"‏ بنوك هؤلاء ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ هذا الذي تزعمين ما تزعمين، فوالله لهم أشبه به من
الغراب بالغراب ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Ikrima: Rifa`a divorced his wife whereupon
`AbdurRahman bin Az-Zubair Al-Qurazi married her. `Aisha said that
the lady (came), wearing a green veil (and complained to her
(Aisha) of her husband and showed her a green spot on her skin
caused by beating). It was the habit of ladies to support each
other, so when Allah's Apostle came, `Aisha said, "I have not seen
any woman suffering as much as the believing women. Look! Her skin
is greener than her clothes!" When `AbdurRahman heard that his wife
had gone to the Prophet, he came with his two sons from another
wife. She said, "By Allah! I have done no wrong to him but he is
impotent and is as useless to me as this," holding and showing the
fringe of her garment, `Abdur-Rahman said, "By Allah, O Allah's
Apostle! She has told a lie! I am very strong and can satisfy her
but she is disobedient and wants to go back to Rifa`a." Allah's
Apostle said, to her, "If that is your intention, then know that it
is unlawful for you to remarry Rifa`a unless `Abdur-Rahman has had
sexual intercourse with you." Then the Prophet saw two boys with
`Abdur- Rahman and asked (him), "Are these your sons?" On that
`AbdurRahman said, "Yes." The Prophet said, "You claim what you
claim (i.e.. that he is impotent)? But by Allah, these boys
resemble him as a crow resembles a crow,"</english-text>
</hadith>
