<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5696</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>77</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5904</hadith-number>
<chapter>Dress - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>20193, 20022, 20031, 11202, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن حرب، حدثنا حماد بن زيد، عن يحيى بن
سعيد، عن عبيد بن حنين، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال لبثت سنة وأنا
أريد أن أسأل عمر عن المرأتين اللتين تظاهرتا على النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فجعلت أهابه، فنزل يوما منزلا فدخل الأراك، فلما خرج سألته فقال
عائشة وحفصة ثم قال كنا في الجاهلية لا نعد النساء شيئا، فلما جاء
الإسلام وذكرهن الله، رأينا لهن بذلك علينا حقا، من غير أن ندخلهن في
شىء من أمورنا، وكان بيني وبين امرأتي كلام فأغلظت لي فقلت لها وإنك
لهناك‏.‏ قالت تقول هذا لي وابنتك تؤذي النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فأتيت حفصة فقلت لها إني أحذرك أن تعصي الله ورسوله‏.‏ وتقدمت إليها
في أذاه، فأتيت أم سلمة فقلت لها‏.‏ فقالت أعجب منك يا عمر قد دخلت في
أمورنا، فلم يبق إلا أن تدخل بين رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وأزواجه، فرددت، وكان رجل من الأنصار إذا غاب عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وشهدته أتيته بما يكون، وإذا غبت عن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وشهد أتاني بما يكون من رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وكان
من حول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قد استقام له، فلم يبق إلا ملك
غسان بالشأم، كنا نخاف أن يأتينا، فما شعرت إلا بالأنصاري وهو يقول
إنه قد حدث أمر‏.‏ قلت له وما هو أجاء الغساني قال أعظم من ذاك، طلق
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نساءه‏.‏ فجئت فإذا البكاء من حجرها
كلها، وإذا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قد صعد في مشربة له، وعلى باب
المشربة وصيف فأتيته فقلت استأذن لي‏.‏ فدخلت فإذا النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم على حصير قد أثر في جنبه، وتحت رأسه مرفقة من أدم، حشوها
ليف، وإذا أهب معلقة وقرظ، فذكرت الذي قلت لحفصة وأم سلمة، والذي ردت
على أم سلمة، فضحك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلبث تسعا وعشرين
ليلة، ثم نزل‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: For one year I wanted to ask
`Umar about the two women who helped each other against the Prophet
but I was afraid of him. One day he dismounted his riding animal
and went among the trees of Arak to answer the call of nature, and
when he returned, I asked him and he said, "(They were) `Aisha and
Hafsa." Then he added, "We never used to give significance to
ladies in the days of the Pre-lslamic period of ignorance, but when
Islam came and Allah mentioned their rights, we used to give them
their rights but did not allow them to interfere in our affairs.
Once there was some dispute between me and my wife and she answered
me back in a loud voice. I said to her, 'Strange! You can retort in
this way?' She said, 'Yes. Do you say this to me while your
daughter troubles Allah's Apostle?' So I went to Hafsa and said to
her, 'I warn you not to disobey Allah and His Apostle.' I first
went to Hafsa and then to Um Salama and told her the same. She said
to me, 'O `Umar! It surprises me that you interfere in our affairs
so much that you would poke your nose even into the affairs of
Allah's Apostle and his wives.' So she rejected my advice. There
was an Ansari man; whenever he was absent from Allah's Apostle and
I was present there, I used to convey to him what had happened (on
that day), and when I was absent and he was present there, he used
to convey to me what had happened as regards news from Allah's
Apostle . During that time all the rulers of the nearby lands had
surrendered to Allah's Apostle except the king of Ghassan in Sham,
and we were afraid that he might attack us. All of a sudden the
Ansari came and said, 'A great event has happened!' I asked him,
'What is it? Has the Ghassani (king) come?' He said, 'Greater than
that! Allah's Apostle has divorced his wives! I went to them and
found all of them weeping in their dwellings, and the Prophet had
ascended to an upper room of his. At the door of the room there was
a slave to whom I went and said, "Ask the permission for me to
enter." He admitted me and I entered to see the Prophet lying on a
mat that had left its imprint on his side. Under his head there was
a leather pillow stuffed with palm fires. Behold! There were some
hides hanging there and some grass for tanning. Then I mentioned
what I had said to Hafsa and Um Salama and what reply Um Salama had
given me. Allah's Apostle smiled and stayed there for twenty nine
days and then came down." (See Hadith No. 648, Vol. 3 for
details)</english-text>
</hadith>
