<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5704</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>77</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5912</hadith-number>
<chapter>Dress - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11168, 11887</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن سعيد المقبري، عن
عبيد بن جريج، أنه قال لعبد الله بن عمر رضى الله عنهما رأيتك تصنع
أربعا لم أر أحدا من أصحابك يصنعها‏.‏ قال ما هي يا ابن جريج قال
رأيتك لا تمس من الأركان إلا اليمانيين، ورأيتك تلبس النعال السبتية،
ورأيتك تصبغ بالصفرة، ورأيتك إذا كنت بمكة أهل الناس إذا رأوا الهلال،
ولم تهل أنت حتى كان يوم التروية‏.‏ فقال له عبد الله بن عمر أما
الأركان فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يمس إلا اليمانيين،
وأما النعال السبتية فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يلبس
النعال التي ليس فيها شعر ويتوضأ فيها فأنا أحب أن ألبسها، وأما
الصفرة فإني رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يصبغ بها، فأنا أحب أن
أصبغ بها وأما الإهلال فإني لم أر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يهل
حتى تنبعث به راحلته‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sa`id Al-Maqburi: 'Ubai bin Juraij said to
`Abdullah Ben `Umar, "I see you doing four things which are not
done by your friends." Ibn `Umar said, "What are they, O Ibn
Juraij?" He said, "I see that you do not touch except the two
Yemenite corners of the Ka`ba (while performing the Tawaf): and I
see you wearing the Sabtiyya shoes; and I see you dyeing (your
hair) with Sufra; and I see that when you are in Mecca, the people
assume the state of Ihram on seeing the crescent (on the first day
of Dhul-Hijja) while you do not assume the state of Ihram till the
Day of Tarwiya (8th Dhul Hijja)." `Abdullah bin `Umar said to him,
"As for the corners of the Ka`ba, I have not seen Allah's Apostle
touching except the two Yemenite corners, As for the Sabtiyya
shoes, I saw Allah's Apostle wearing leather shoes that had no
hair, and he used to perform the ablution while wearing them.
Therefore, I like to wear such shoes. As regards dyeing with Sufra,
I saw Allah's Apostle dyeing his hair with it, so I like to dye (my
hair) with it. As regards the crescent (of Dhul-Hijja), I have not
seen Allah's Apostle assuming the state of Ihram till his she-camel
set out (on the 8th of Dhul-Hijja).</english-text>
</hadith>
