<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5724</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>77</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>5932</hadith-number>
<chapter>Dress - كتاب اللباس</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20165, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، حدثنا عبد العزيز بن أبي حازم،
عن أبيه، أنه سمع سهلا، يقول جاءت امرأة إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقالت جئت أهب نفسي‏.‏ فقامت طويلا فنظر وصوب، فلما طال مقامها فقال
رجل زوجنيها، إن لم تكن لك بها حاجة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ عندك شىء تصدقها
‏"‏‏.‏ قال لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ انظر ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع فقال والله إن وجدت
شيئا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اذهب فالتمس ولو خاتما من حديد ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهب ثم رجع
قال لا والله ولا خاتما من حديد‏.‏ وعليه إزار ما عليه رداء‏.‏ فقال
أصدقها إزاري فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إزارك إن لبسته لم
يكن عليك منه شىء، وإن لبسته لم يكن عليها منه شىء ‏"‏‏.‏ فتنحى الرجل
فجلس فرآه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم موليا فأمر به فدعي فقال ‏"‏ ما
معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سورة كذا وكذا لسور عددها‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ قد
ملكتكها بما معك من القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl: A woman came to the Prophet and said,
"I have come to present myself to you (for marriage)." She kept
standing for a long period during which period the Prophet looked
at her carefully. When she stayed for a Long period, a man said to
the Prophet "If you are not in need of her, then marry her to me."
The Prophet said, "Have you got anything to give her (as Mahr)?"
The man said, "No." The Prophet said, "Go (to your house) and
search for something." The man went and came back to say, "By
Allah, I could not find anything." The Prophet said, "Go again and
search for something, even if it be an iron ring." He went again
and came back saying, "No, by Allah, I could not get even an iron
ring." The man had only an Izar and had no Rida' (upper garment).
He said, "I will give her my Izar as Mahr." On that the Prophet
said, "Your Izar? If she wears it, nothing of it will remain on
you, and if you wear it nothing of it will be on her" The man went
aside and sat down When the Prophet saw him leaving (after a
while), he called back and asked. "How much Qur'an do you know (by
heart)? He said, 'I know such and such Suras," naming some Suras.
The Prophet said, "I marry her to you for the amount of Qur'an you
know (by heart).</english-text>
</hadith>
