<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5911</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6120</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30329, 20303, 20278</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حفص بن عمر، حدثنا يزيد بن إبراهيم، حدثنا محمد،
عن أبي هريرة، صلى بنا النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم الظهر ركعتين، ثم
سلم، ثم قام إلى خشبة في مقدم المسجد، ووضع يده عليها، وفي القوم
يومئذ أبو بكر وعمر، فهابا أن يكلماه، وخرج سرعان الناس فقالوا قصرت
الصلاة‏.‏ وفي القوم رجل كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يدعوه ذا
اليدين فقال يا نبي الله أنسيت أم قصرت‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ لم أنس ولم تقصر
‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا بل نسيت يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ صدق ذو اليدين ‏"‏‏.‏
فقام فصلى ركعتين ثم سلم، ثم كبر، فسجد مثل سجوده أو أطول، ثم رفع
رأسه وكبر، ثم وضع مثل سجوده أو أطول، ثم رفع رأسه
وكبر‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: The Prophet led us in the Zuhr
prayer, offering only two rak`at and then (finished it) with
Taslim, and went to a piece of wood in front of the mosque and put
his hand over it. Abu Bakr and `Umar were also present among the
people on that day but dared not talk to him (about his unfinished
prayer). And the hasty people went away, wondering. "Has the prayer
been shortened" Among the people there was a man whom the Prophet
used to call Dhul-Yadain (the longarmed). He said, "O Allah's
Prophet! Have you forgotten or has the prayer been shortened?" The
Prophet said, "Neither have I forgotten, nor has it been
shortened." They (the people) said, "Surely, you have forgotten, O
Allah's Apostle!" The Prophet said, Dhul-Yadain has told the
truth." So the Prophet got up and offered other two rak`at and
finished his prayer with Taslim. Then he said Takbir, performed a
prostration of ordinary duration or longer, then he raised his head
and said Takbir and performed another prostration of ordinary
duration or longer and then raised his head and said Takbir (i.e.
he performed the two prostrations of Sahu, i.e.,
forgetfulness).</english-text>
</hadith>
