<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5923</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6132</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30418, 20005, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحميدي، حدثنا سفيان، حدثنا هشام بن عروة، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها قالت مكث النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كذا
وكذا يخيل إليه أنه يأتي أهله ولا يأتي، قالت عائشة فقال لي ذات يوم
‏"‏ يا عائشة إن الله أفتاني في أمر استفتيته فيه، أتاني رجلان، فجلس
أحدهما عند رجلى والآخر عند رأسي، فقال الذي عند رجلى للذي عند رأسي
ما بال الرجل قال مطبوب‏.‏ يعني مسحورا‏.‏ قال ومن طبه قال لبيد بن
أعصم‏.‏ قال وفيم قال في جف طلعة ذكر في مشط ومشاقة، تحت رعوفة في بئر
ذروان ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاء النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ هذه البئر التي
أريتها كأن رءوس نخلها رءوس الشياطين، وكأن ماءها نقاعة الحناء ‏"‏‏.‏
فأمر به النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فأخرج‏.‏ قالت عائشة فقلت يا رسول
الله فهلا تعني تنشرت فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما الله فقد
شفاني، وأما أنا فأكره أن أثير على الناس شرا ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت ولبيد بن
أعصم رجل من بني زريق حليف ليهود‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: The Prophet continued for
such-and-such period imagining that he has slept (had sexual
relations) with his wives, and in fact he did not. One day he said,
to me, "O `Aisha! Allah has instructed me regarding a matter about
which I had asked Him. There came to me two men, one of them sat
near my feet and the other near my head. The one near my feet,
asked the one near my head (pointing at me), 'What is wrong with
this man? The latter replied, 'He is under the effect of magic.'
The first one asked, 'Who had worked magic on him?' The other
replied, 'Lubaid bin Asam.' The first one asked, 'What material
(did he use)?' The other replied, 'The skin of the pollen of a male
date tree with a comb and the hair stuck to it, kept under a stone
in the well of Dharwan."' Then the Prophet went to that well and
said, "This is the same well which was shown to me in the dream.
The tops of its date-palm trees look like the heads of the devils,
and its water looks like the Henna infusion." Then the Prophet
ordered that those things be taken out. I said, "O Allah's Apostle!
Won't you disclose (the magic object)?" The Prophet said, "Allah
has cured me and I hate to circulate the evil among the people."
`Aisha added, "(The magician) Lubaid bin Asam was a man from Bani
Zuraiq, an ally of the Jews."</english-text>
</hadith>
