<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>5947</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6151</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30322, 20025, 20115, 11013, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حبان بن موسى، أخبرنا عبد الله، أخبرنا معمر، عن
الزهري، عن عروة، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن رفاعة، القرظي طلق امرأته
فبت طلاقها، فتزوجها بعده عبد الرحمن بن الزبير، فجاءت النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقالت يا رسول الله إنها كانت عند رفاعة فطلقها آخر ثلاث
تطليقات، فتزوجها بعده عبد الرحمن بن الزبير، وإنه والله ما معه يا
رسول الله إلا مثل هذه الهدبة، لهدبة أخذتها من جلبابها‏.‏ قال وأبو
بكر جالس عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وابن سعيد بن العاص جالس بباب
الحجرة ليؤذن له، فطفق خالد ينادي أبا بكر، يا أبا بكر ألا تزجر هذه
عما تجهر به عند رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وما يزيد رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم على التبسم ثم قال ‏"‏ لعلك تريدين أن ترجعي إلى
رفاعة، لا، حتى تذوقي عسيلته، ويذوق عسيلتك ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Rifa`a Al-Qurazi divorced his wife
irrevocably (i.e. that divorce was the final). Later on `Abdur-
Rahman bin Az-Zubair married her after him. She came to the Prophet
and said, "O Allah's Apostle! I was Rifa`a's wife and he divorced
me thrice, and then I was married to `Abdur-Rahman bin AzZubair,
who, by Allah has nothing with him except something like this
fringe, O Allah's Apostle," showing a fringe she had taken from her
covering sheet. Abu Bakr was sitting with the Prophet while Khalid
Ibn Sa`id bin Al-As was sitting at the gate of the room waiting for
admission. Khalid started calling Abu Bakr, "O Abu Bakr! Why don't
you reprove this lady from what she is openly saying before Allah's
Apostle?" Allah's Apostle did nothing except smiling, and then said
(to the lady), "Perhaps you want to go back to Rifa`a? No, (it is
not possible), unless and until you enjoy the sexual relation with
him (`Abdur Rahman), and he enjoys the sexual relation with
you."</english-text>
</hadith>
