<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6007</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6210</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30157, 20246, 11286, 11113, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عياش بن الوليد، حدثنا عبد الأعلى، حدثنا سعيد
الجريري، عن أبي عثمان، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر رضى الله عنهما أن
أبا بكر، تضيف رهطا فقال لعبد الرحمن دونك أضيافك فإني منطلق إلى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فافرغ من قراهم قبل أن أجيء‏.‏ فانطلق عبد
الرحمن فأتاهم بما عنده فقال اطعموا‏.‏ فقالوا أين رب منزلنا قال
اطعموا‏.‏ قالوا ما نحن بآكلين حتى يجيء رب منزلنا‏.‏ قال اقبلوا عنا
قراكم، فإنه إن جاء ولم تطعموا لنلقين منه‏.‏ فأبوا فعرفت أنه يجد
على، فلما جاء تنحيت عنه فقال ما صنعتم فأخبروه فقال يا عبد الرحمن‏.‏
فسكت ثم قال يا عبد الرحمن‏.‏ فسكت فقال يا غنثر أقسمت عليك إن كنت
تسمع صوتي لما جئت‏.‏ فخرجت فقلت سل أضيافك‏.‏ فقالوا صدق أتانا به‏.‏
قال فإنما انتظرتموني، والله لا أطعمه الليلة‏.‏ فقال الآخرون والله
لا نطعمه حتى تطعمه‏.‏ قال لم أر في الشر كالليلة، ويلكم ما أنتم لم
لا تقبلون عنا قراكم هات طعامك‏.‏ فجاءه فوضع يده فقال باسم الله،
الأولى للشيطان‏.‏ فأكل وأكلوا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr: Abu Bakr invited
a group of people and told me, "Look after your guests." Abu Bakr
added, I am going to visit the Prophet and you should finish
serving them before I return." `Abdur-Rahman said, So I went at
once and served them with what was available at that time in the
house and requested them to eat." They said, "Where is the owner of
the house (i.e., Abu Bakr)?" `Abdur-Rahman said, "Take your meal."
They said, "We will not eat till the owner of the house comes."
`Abdur-Rahman said, "Accept your meal from us, for if my father
comes and finds you not having taken your meal yet, we will be
blamed severely by him, but they refused to take their meals . So I
was sure that my father would be angry with me. When he came, I
went away (to hide myself) from him. He asked, "What have you done
(about the guests)?" They informed him the whole story. Abu Bakr
called, "O `Abdur Rahman!" I kept quiet. He then called again. "O
`Abdur-Rahman!" I kept quiet and he called again, "O ignorant
(boy)! I beseech you by Allah, if you hear my voice, then come
out!" I came out and said, "Please ask your guests (and do not be
angry with me)." They said, "He has told the truth; he brought the
meal to us." He said, "As you have been waiting for me, by Allah, I
will not eat of it tonight." They said, "By Allah, we will not eat
of it till you eat of it." He said, I have never seen a night like
this night in evil. What is wrong with you? Why don't you accept
your meals of hospitality from us?" (He said to me), "Bring your
meal." I brought it to him, and he put his hand in it, saying, "In
the name of Allah. The first (state of fury) was because of Satan."
So Abu Bakr ate and so did his guests.</english-text>
</hadith>
