<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6008</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6211</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20276, 20160, 11113, 107</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا ابن أبي عدي، عن سليمان، عن
أبي عثمان، قال عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر رضى الله عنهما جاء أبو بكر
بضيف له أو بأضياف له، فأمسى عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما جاء
قالت أمي احتبست عن ضيفك أو أضيافك الليلة‏.‏ قال ما عشيتهم فقالت
عرضنا عليه أو عليهم فأبوا أو فأبى، فغضب أبو بكر فسب وجدع وحلف لا
يطعمه، فاختبأت أنا فقال يا غنثر‏.‏ فحلفت المرأة لا تطعمه حتى يطعمه،
فحلف الضيف أو الأضياف أن لا يطعمه أو يطعموه حتى يطعمه، فقال أبو بكر
كأن هذه من الشيطان فدعا بالطعام فأكل وأكلوا فجعلوا لا يرفعون لقمة
إلا ربا من أسفلها أكثر منها، فقال يا أخت بني فراس ما هذا فقالت وقرة
عيني إنها الآن لأكثر قبل أن نأكل فأكلوا وبعث بها إلى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فذكر أنه أكل منها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdur-Rahman bin Abu Bakr: Abu Bakr came
with a guest or some guests, but he stayed late at night with the
Prophet and when he came, my mother said (to him), "Have you been
detained from your guest or guests tonight?" He said, "Haven't you
served the supper to them?" She replied, "We presented the meal to
him (or to them), but he (or they) refused to eat." Abu Bakr became
angry, rebuked me and invoked Allah to cause (my) ears to be cut
and swore not to eat of it!" I hid myself, and he called me, "O
ignorant (boy)!" Abu Bakr's wife swore that she would not eat of it
and so the guests or the guest swore that they would not eat of it
till he ate of it. Abu Bakr said, "All that happened was from
Satan." So he asked for the meals and ate of it, and so did they.
Whenever they took a handful of the meal, the meal grew (increased)
from underneath more than that mouthful. He said (to his wife), "O,
sister of Bani Firas! What is this?" She said, "O, pleasure of my
eyes! The meal is now more than it had been before we started
eating'' So they ate of it and sent the rest of that meal to the
Prophet. It is said that the Prophet also ate of it.</english-text>
</hadith>
