<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6009</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6212</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>20193, 20022, 20031, 11810, 1986</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سليمان بن حرب، حدثنا حماد، هو ابن زيد عن يحيى بن
سعيد، عن بشير بن يسار، مولى الأنصار عن رافع بن خديج، وسهل بن أبي
حثمة، أنهما حدثاه أن عبد الله بن سهل ومحيصة بن مسعود أتيا خيبر
فتفرقا في النخل، فقتل عبد الله بن سهل، فجاء عبد الرحمن بن سهل
وحويصة ومحيصة ابنا مسعود إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فتكلموا في
أمر صاحبهم فبدأ عبد الرحمن، وكان أصغر القوم فقال النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كبر الكبر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال يحيى ليلي الكلام الأكبر فتكلموا
في أمر صاحبهم فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أتستحقون قتيلكم أو
قال صاحبكم بأيمان خمسين منكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله أمر لم
نره‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فتبرئكم يهود في أيمان خمسين منهم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا يا
رسول الله قوم كفار‏.‏ فوداهم رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من
قبله‏.‏ قال سهل فأدركت ناقة من تلك الإبل، فدخلت مربدا لهم فركضتني
برجلها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Rafi` bin Khadij and Sahl bin Abu Hathma:
`Abdullah bin Sahl and Muhaiyisa bin Mas`ud went to Khaibar and
they dispersed in the gardens of the date-palm trees. `Abdullah bin
Sahl was murdered. Then `Abdur-Rahman bin Sahl, Huwaiyisa and
Muhaiyisa, the two sons of Mas`ud, came to the Prophet and spoke
about the case of their (murdered) friend. `Abdur-Rahman who was
the youngest of them all, started talking. The Prophet said, "Let
the older (among you) speak first." So they spoke about the case of
their (murdered) friend. The Prophet said, "Will fifty of you take
an oath whereby you will have the right to receive the blood money
of your murdered man," (or said, "..your companion"). They said, "O
Allah's Apostle! The murder was a thing we did not witness." The
Prophet said, "Then the Jews will release you from the oath, if
fifty of them (the Jews) should take an oath to contradict your
claim." They said, "O Allah's Apostle! They are disbelievers (and
they will take a false oath)." Then Allah's Apostle himself paid
the blood money to them.</english-text>
</hadith>
