<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6015</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6218</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20159, 11450, 237</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا حاتم بن إسماعيل، عن يزيد بن
أبي عبيد، عن سلمة بن الأكوع، قال خرجنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم إلى خيبر فسرنا ليلا، فقال رجل من القوم لعامر بن الأكوع ألا
تسمعنا من هنيهاتك، قال وكان عامر رجلا شاعرا، فنزل يحدو بالقوم يقول
اللهم لولا أنت ما اهتدينا ولا تصدقنا ولا صلينا فاغفر فداء لك ما
اقتفينا وثبت الأقدام إن لاقينا وألقين سكينة علينا إنا إذا صيح بنا
أتينا وبالصياح عولوا علينا فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من
هذا السائق ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا عامر بن الأكوع‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ يرحمه الله
‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رجل من القوم وجبت يا نبي الله، لو أمتعتنا به‏.‏ قال
فأتينا خيبر فحاصرناهم حتى أصابتنا مخمصة شديدة، ثم إن الله فتحها
عليهم، فلما أمسى الناس اليوم الذي فتحت عليهم أوقدوا نيرانا كثيرة‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما هذه النيران، على أى شىء
توقدون ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا على لحم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ على أى لحم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا على
لحم حمر إنسية‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أهرقوها
واكسروها ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال رجل يا رسول الله أو نهريقها ونغسلها قال ‏"‏ أو
ذاك ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما تصاف القوم كان سيف عامر فيه قصر، فتناول به يهوديا
ليضربه، ويرجع ذباب سيفه فأصاب ركبة عامر فمات منه، فلما قفلوا قال
سلمة رآني رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم شاحبا‏.‏ فقال لي ‏"‏ ما لك
‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت فدى لك أبي وأمي زعموا أن عامرا حبط عمله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ من
قاله ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت قاله فلان وفلان وفلان وأسيد بن الحضير الأنصاري‏.‏
فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كذب من قاله، إن له لأجرين
وجمع بين إصبعيه إنه لجاهد مجاهد، قل عربي نشأ بها مثله
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Salama bin Al-Aqwa: We went out with Allah's
Apostle to Khaibar and we travelled during the night. A man amongst
the people said to 'Amir bin Al-Aqwa', "Won't you let us hear your
poetry?" 'Amir was a poet, and so he got down and started (chanting
Huda) reciting for the people, poetry that keep pace with the
camel's foot steps, saying, "O Allah! Without You we would not have
been guided on the right path, neither would we have given in
charity, nor would we have prayed. So please forgive us what we
have committed. Let all of us be sacrificed for Your cause and when
we meet our enemy, make our feet firm and bestow peace and calmness
on us and if they (our enemy) will call us towards an unjust thing
we will refuse. The infidels have made a hue and cry to ask others
help against us. Allah's Apostle said, "Who is that driver (of the
camels)?" They said, "He is 'Amir bin Al-Aqwa."' He said, "May
Allah bestow His mercy on him." A man among the people said, Has
Martyrdom been granted to him, O Allah's Prophet! Would that you
let us enjoy his company longer." We reached (the people of)
Khaibar and besieged them till we were stricken with severe hunger
but Allah helped the Muslims conquer Khaibar. In the evening of its
conquest the people made many fires. Allah's Apostle asked, "What
are those fires? For what are you making fires?" They said, "For
cooking meat." He asked, "What kind of meat?" They said, "Donkeys'
meat." Allah's Apostle said, "Throw away the meat and break the
cooking pots." A man said, O Allah's Apostle! Shall we throw away
the meat and wash the cooking pots?" He said, "You can do that
too." When the army files aligned in rows (for the battle), 'Amir's
sword was a short one, and while attacking a Jew with it in order
to hit him, the sharp edge of the sword turned back and hit 'Amir's
knee and caused him to die. When the Muslims returned (from the
battle), Salama said, Allah's Apostle saw me pale and said, 'What
is wrong with you?"' I said, "Let my parents be sacrificed for you!
The people claim that all the deeds of Amir have been annulled."
The Prophet asked, "Who said so?" I replied, "So-and-so and soand-
so and Usaid bin Al-Hudair Al-Ansari said, 'Whoever says so is
telling a lie. Verily, 'Amir will have double reward."' (While
speaking) the Prophet put two of his fingers together to indicate
that, and added, "He was really a hard-working man and a Mujahid
(devout fighter in Allah's Cause) and rarely have there lived in it
(i.e., Medina or the battle-field) an "Arab like
him."</english-text>
</hadith>
