<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6040</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6243</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، قال أخبرني
سالم بن عبد الله، أن عبد الله بن عمر، أخبره أن عمر بن الخطاب انطلق
مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في رهط من أصحابه قبل ابن صياد، حتى
وجده يلعب مع الغلمان في أطم بني مغالة، وقد قارب ابن صياد يومئذ
الحلم، فلم يشعر حتى ضرب رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ظهره بيده ثم
قال ‏"‏ أتشهد أني رسول الله ‏"‏‏.‏ فنظر إليه فقال أشهد أنك رسول
الأميين‏.‏ ثم قال ابن صياد أتشهد أني رسول الله فرضه النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم قال ‏"‏ آمنت بالله ورسله ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال لابن صياد ‏"‏
ماذا ترى ‏"‏‏.‏ قال يأتيني صادق وكاذب‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ خلط عليك الأمر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ إني خبأت لك خبيئا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال هو الدخ‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اخسأ، فلن
تعدو قدرك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عمر يا رسول الله أتأذن لي فيه أضرب عنقه‏.‏ قال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن يكن هو لا تسلط عليه، وإن لم يكن
هو فلا خير لك في قتله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سالم فسمعت عبد الله بن عمر، يقول
انطلق بعد ذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأبى بن كعب الأنصاري
يؤمان النخل التي فيها ابن صياد، حتى إذا دخل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم طفق رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يتقي بجذوع النخل، وهو يختل أن
يسمع من ابن صياد شيئا قبل أن يراه، وابن صياد مضطجع على فراشه في
قطيفة له فيها رمرمة أو زمزمة، فرأت أم ابن صياد النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم وهو يتقي بجذوع النخل، فقالت لابن صياد أى صاف وهو اسمه هذا
محمد‏.‏ فتناهى ابن صياد‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو
تركته بين ‏"‏‏.‏ قال سالم قال عبد الله قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم في الناس فأثنى على الله بما هو أهله، ثم ذكر الدجال فقال ‏"‏
إني أنذركموه، وما من نبي إلا وقد أنذر قومه، لقد أنذره نوح قومه،
ولكني سأقول لكم فيه قولا لم يقله نبي لقومه، تعلمون أنه أعور، وأن
الله ليس بأعور ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Umar: `Umar bin Al-Khattab
set out with Allah's Apostle, and a group of his companions to Ibn
Saiyad. They found him playing with the boys in the fort or near
the Hillocks of Bani Maghala. Ibn Saiyad was nearing his puberty at
that time, and he did not notice the arrival of the Prophet till
Allah's Apostle stroked him on the back with his hand and said, "Do
you testify that I am Allah's Apostle?" Ibn Saiyad looked at him
and said, "I testify that you are the Apostle of the unlettered
ones (illiterates)". Then Ibn Saiyad said to the Prophets . "Do you
testify that I am Allah's Apostle?" The Prophet denied that,
saying, "I believe in Allah and all His Apostles," and then said to
Ibn Saiyad, "What do you see?" Ibn Saiyad said, "True people and
liars visit me." The Prophet said, "You have been confused as to
this matter." Allah's Apostle added, "I have kept something for you
(in my mind)." Ibn Saiyad said, "Ad-Dukh." The Prophet said, "Ikhsa
(you should be ashamed) for you can not cross your limits." `Umar
said, "O Allah's Apostle! Allow me to chop off h is neck." Allah's
Apostle said (to `Umar). "Should this person be him (i.e.
Ad-Dajjal) then you cannot over-power him; and should he be someone
else, then it will be no use your killing him." `Abdullah bin `Umar
added: Later on Allah's Apostle and Ubai bin Ka`b Al-Ansari (once
again) went to the garden in which Ibn Saiyad was present. When
Allah's Apostle entered the garden, he started hiding behind the
trunks of the date-palms intending to hear something from Ibn
Saiyad before the latter could see him. Ibn Saiyad was Lying on his
bed, covered with a velvet sheet from where his mumur were heard.
Ibn Saiyad's mother saw the Prophet and said, "O Saf (the nickname
of Ibn Saiyad)! Here is Muhammad!" Ibn Saiyad stopped his
murmuring. The Prophet said, "If his mother had kept quiet, then I
would have learnt more about him." `Abdullah added: Allah's Apostle
stood up before the people (delivering a sermon), and after
praising and glorifying Allah as He deserved, he mentioned the
Ad-Dajjal saying, "I warn you against him, and there has been no
prophet but warned his followers against him. Noah warned his
followers against him but I am telling you about him, something
which no prophet has told his people of, and that is: Know that he
is blind in one eye where as Allah is not so."</english-text>
</hadith>
