<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6073</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6278</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 20208, 24131, 11005, 11013,
10511, 50</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري، حدثنا
إسماعيل، قال حدثني أخي، عن سليمان، عن محمد بن أبي عتيق، عن ابن
شهاب، عن عروة بن الزبير، أن أسامة بن زيد رضى الله عنهما أخبره أن
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ركب على حمار عليه قطيفة فدكية وأسامة
وراءه، يعود سعد بن عبادة في بني حارث بن الخزرج قبل وقعة بدر، فسارا
حتى مرا بمجلس فيه عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول، وذلك قبل أن يسلم عبد
الله بن أبى، فإذا في المجلس أخلاط من المسلمين والمشركين عبدة
الأوثان واليهود، وفي المسلمين عبد الله بن رواحة، فلما غشيت المجلس
عجاجة الدابة خمر ابن أبى أنفه بردائه وقال لا تغبروا علينا‏.‏ فسلم
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم عليهم، ثم وقف فنزل فدعاهم إلى الله
وقرأ عليهم القرآن، فقال له عبد الله بن أبى ابن سلول أيها المرء لا
أحسن مما تقول إن كان حقا، فلا تؤذنا به في مجالسنا، فمن جاءك فاقصص
عليه‏.‏ قال عبد الله بن رواحة بلى يا رسول الله فاغشنا في مجالسنا
فإنا نحب ذلك‏.‏ فاستب المسلمون والمشركون واليهود حتى كادوا يتثاورون
فلم يزل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يخفضهم حتى سكتوا، ثم ركب رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم دابته فسار حتى دخل على سعد بن عبادة، فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أى سعد ألم تسمع ما قال أبو حباب
يريد عبد الله بن أبى قال كذا وكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال سعد بن عبادة أى رسول
الله بأبي أنت، اعف عنه واصفح، فوالذي أنزل عليك الكتاب لقد جاء الله
بالحق الذي أنزل عليك، ولقد اصطلح أهل هذه البحرة على أن يتوجوه
ويعصبوه بالعصابة، فلما رد الله ذلك بالحق الذي أعطاك شرق بذلك فذلك
فعل به ما رأيت‏.‏ فعفا عنه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وكان رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأصحابه يعفون عن المشركين وأهل الكتاب كما
أمرهم الله، ويصبرون على الأذى، قال الله تعالى ‏{‏ولتسمعن من الذين
أوتوا الكتاب‏}‏ الآية، وقال ‏{‏ود كثير من أهل الكتاب‏}‏ فكان رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يتأول في العفو عنهم ما أمره الله به حتى أذن
له فيهم، فلما غزا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بدرا، فقتل الله بها
من قتل من صناديد الكفار، وسادة قريش، فقفل رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأصحابه منصورين غانمين معهم أسارى من صناديد الكفار وسادة قريش
قال ابن أبى ابن سلول، ومن معه من المشركين عبدة الأوثان هذا أمر قد
توجه فبايعوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم على الإسلام
فأسلموا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Usama bin Zaid: That Allah's Apostle rode
over a donkey covered with a Fadakiya (velvet sheet) and Usama was
riding behind him. He was visiting Sa`d bin 'Ubada (who was sick)
in the dwelling place of Bani Al-Harith bin Al-Khazraj and this
incident happened before the battle of Badr. They proceeded till
they passed by a gathering in which `Abdullah bin Ubai bin Salul
was present., and that was before `Abdullah bin Ubat embraced
Islam. In that gathering there were Muslims, pagan idolators and
Jews, and among the Muslims there was `Abdullah bin Rawaha. When a
cloud of dust raised by (the movement of ) the animal covered that
gathering, `Abdullah bin Ubai covered his nose with his garment and
said, "Do not cover us with dust." Allah's Apostle greeted them,
stopped, dismounted and invited them to Allah (i.e. to embrace
Islam) and recited to them the Holy Qur'an. On that `Abdullah bin
Ubai bin Salul said to him, "O man! There is nothing better than
what you say, if it is the truth. So do not trouble us with it in
our gatherings, but if somebody comes to you, you can preach to
him." On that `Abdullah bin Rawaha said "Yes, O Allah's Apostle!
Call on us in our gathering, for we love that." So the Muslims, the
pagans and the Jews started abusing one another till they were
about to fight with one another. Allah's Apostle kept on quietening
them till all of them became quiet, and then Allah's Apostle rode
his animal and proceeded till he entered upon Sa`d bin 'Ubada.
Allah's Apostle said, "O Sa`d! Didn't you hear what Abu Habab
said?" (meaning `Abdullah bin Unbar). "He said so-and-so." Sa`d bin
Ubada said, "O Allah's Apostle! Let my father be sacrificed for you
! Excuse and forgive him for, by Him Who revealed to you the Book,
Allah sent the Truth which was revealed to you at the time when the
people of this town had decided to crown him (`Abdullah bin Ubai)
as their ruler. So when Allah had prevented that with the Truth He
had given you, he was choked by that, and that caused him to behave
in such an impolite manner which you had noticed." So Allah's
Apostle excused him. (It was the custom of) Allah's Apostle and his
companions to excuse the pagans and the people of the scripture
(Christians and Jews) as Allah ordered them, and they used to be
patient when annoyed (by them). Allah said: 'You shall certainly
hear much that will grieve you from those who received the
Scripture before you.....and from the pagans (3.186) He also said:
'Many of the people of the scripture wish that if they could turn
you away as disbelievers after you have believed. .... (2.109) So
Allah's Apostle used to apply what Allah had ordered him by
excusing them till he was allowed to fight against them. When
Allah's Apostle had fought the battle of Badr and Allah killed
whomever He killed among the chiefs of the infidels and the nobles
of Quraish, and Allah's Apostle and his companions had returned
with victory and booty, bringing with them some of the chiefs of
the infidels and the nobles of the Quraish as captives. `Abdullah
bin Ubai bin Salul and the pagan idolators who were with him, said,
"This matter (Islam) has now brought out its face (triumphed), so
give Allah's Apostle the pledge of allegiance (for embracing
Islam.)". Then they became Muslims.</english-text>
</hadith>
