<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6082</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>78</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6287</hadith-number>
<chapter>Good Manners and Form (Al-Adab) - كتاب الأدب</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20031, 11600, 11113, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا يحيى، عن عثمان بن غياث، حدثنا أبو
عثمان، عن أبي موسى، أنه كان مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في حائط من
حيطان المدينة، وفي يد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم عود يضرب به بين
الماء والطين، فجاء رجل يستفتح، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏
افتح له وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فذهبت فإذا أبو بكر، ففتحت له وبشرته
بالجنة، ثم استفتح رجل آخر فقال ‏"‏ افتح له وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فإذا
عمر، ففتحت له وبشرته بالجنة، ثم استفتح رجل آخر، وكان متكئا فجلس
فقال ‏"‏ افتح ‏{‏له‏}‏ وبشره بالجنة، على بلوى تصيبه أو تكون ‏"‏‏.‏
فذهبت فإذا عثمان، ففتحت له، وبشرته بالجنة، فأخبرته بالذي قال‏.‏ قال
الله المستعان‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa: That he was in the company of the
Prophet in one of the gardens of Medina and in the hand of the
Prophet there was a stick, and he was striking (slowly) the water
and the mud with it. A man came (at the gate of the garden) and
asked permission to enter. The Prophet said, "Open the gate for him
and give him the glad tidings of entering Paradise. "I went, and
behold! It was Abu Bakr. So I opened the gate for him and informed
him of the glad tidings of entering Paradise. Then another man came
and asked permission to enter. The Prophet said, "Open the gate for
him and give him the glad tidings of entering Paradise." Behold! It
was `Umar. So I opened the gate for him and gave him the glad
tidings of entering Paradise. Then another man came and asked
permission to enter. The Prophet was sitting in a leaning posture,
so he sat up and said, "Open the gate for him and give him the glad
tidings of entering Paradise with a calamity which will befall him
or which will take place." I went, and behold ! It was `Uthman. So
I opened the gate for him and gave him the glad tidings of entering
Paradise and also informed him of what the Prophet had said (about
a calamity). `Uthman said, "Allah Alone Whose Help I seek (against
that calamity).</english-text>
</hadith>
