<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6104</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>79</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6310</hadith-number>
<chapter>Asking Permission - كتاب الاستئذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30220, 20029, 20475, 11013, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن سليمان، حدثنا ابن وهب، أخبرني يونس، عن
ابن شهاب، قال أخبرني أنس بن مالك، أنه كان ابن عشر سنين مقدم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم المدينة، فخدمت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
عشرا حياته، وكنت أعلم الناس بشأن الحجاب حين أنزل، وقد كان أبى بن
كعب يسألني عنه، وكان أول ما نزل في مبتنى رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم بزينب ابنة جحش، أصبح النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بها عروسا فدعا
القوم، فأصابوا من الطعام ثم خرجوا، وبقي منهم رهط عند رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأطالوا المكث فقام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخرج
وخرجت معه كى يخرجوا، فمشى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ومشيت معه
حتى جاء عتبة حجرة عائشة، ثم ظن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أنهم
خرجوا فرجع ورجعت معه، حتى دخل على زينب فإذا هم جلوس لم يتفرقوا،
فرجع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ورجعت معه، حتى بلغ عتبة حجرة
عائشة، فظن أن قد خرجوا، فرجع ورجعت معه، فإذا هم قد خرجوا، فأنزل آية
الحجاب، فضرب بيني وبينه سترا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: that he was a boy of ten at
the time when the Prophet emigrated to Medina. He added: I served
Allah's Apostle for ten years (the last part of his life time) and
I know more than the people about the occasion whereupon the order
of Al-Hijab was revealed (to the Prophet). Ubai b n Ka`b used to
ask me about it. It was revealed (for the first time) during the
marriage of Allah's Apostle with Zainab bint Jahsh. In the morning,
the Prophet was a bride-groom of her and he Invited the people, who
took their meals and went away, but a group of them remained with
Allah's Apostle and they prolonged their stay. Allah's Apostle got
up and went out, and I too, went out along with him till he came to
the lintel of `Aisha's dwelling place. Allah's Apostle thought that
those people had left by then, so he returned, and I too, returned
with him till he entered upon Zainab and found that they were still
sitting there and had not yet gone. The Prophet went out again, and
so did I with him till he reached the lintel of `Aisha's dwelling
place, and then he thought that those people must have left by
then, so he returned, and so did I with him, and found those people
had gone. At that time the Divine Verse of Al-Hijab was revealed,
and the Prophet set a screen between me and him (his
family).</english-text>
</hadith>
