<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6133</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>79</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6339</hadith-number>
<chapter>Asking Permission - كتاب الاستئذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30313, 30317, 20428, 11013, 1131, 17, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسحاق، أخبرنا بشر بن شعيب، حدثني أبي، عن الزهري،
قال أخبرني عبد الله بن كعب، أن عبد الله بن عباس، أخبره أن عليا يعني
ابن أبي طالب خرج من عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وحدثنا أحمد بن
صالح حدثنا عنبسة حدثنا يونس عن ابن شهاب قال أخبرني عبد الله بن كعب
بن مالك أن عبد الله بن عباس أخبره أن علي بن أبي طالب رضى الله عنه
خرج من عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم في وجعه الذي توفي فيه فقال
الناس يا أبا حسن كيف أصبح رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال أصبح
بحمد الله بارئا فأخذ بيده العباس فقال ألا تراه أنت والله بعد الثلاث
عبد العصا والله إني لأرى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم سيتوفى في
وجعه، وإني لأعرف في وجوه بني عبد المطلب الموت، فاذهب بنا إلى رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فنسأله فيمن يكون الأمر فإن كان فينا علمنا
ذلك، وإن كان في غيرنا أمرناه فأوصى بنا‏.‏ قال علي والله لئن سألناها
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيمنعنا لا يعطيناها الناس أبدا، وإني
لا أسألها رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أبدا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: `Ali bin Abu Talib
came out of the house of the Prophet during his fatal ailment. The
people asked (`Ali), "O Abu Hasan! How is the health of Allah's
Apostle this morning?" `Ali said, "This morning he is better, with
the grace of Allah." Al-`Abbas held `Ali by the hand and said,
"Don't you see him (about to die)? By Allah, within three days you
will be the slave of the stick (i.e., under the command of another
ruler). By Allah, I think that Allah's Apostle will die from his
present ailment, for I know the signs of death on the faces of the
offspring of `Abdul Muttalib. So let us go to Allah's Apostle to
ask him who will take over the Caliphate. If the authority is given
to us, we will know it, and if it is given to somebody else we will
request him to recommend us to him. " `Ali said, "By Allah! If we
ask Allah's Apostle for the rulership and he refuses, then the
people will never give it to us. Besides, I will never ask Allah's
Apostle for it." (See Hadith No 728, Vol 5)</english-text>
</hadith>
