<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6136</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>79</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6342</hadith-number>
<chapter>Asking Permission - كتاب الاستئذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30204, 20317, 11060, 11341</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمر بن حفص، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا الأعمش، حدثنا زيد
بن وهب، حدثنا والله أبو ذر، بالربذة كنت أمشي مع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم في حرة المدينة عشاء استقبلنا أحد فقال ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر ما أحب أن
أحدا لي ذهبا يأتي على ليلة أو ثلاث عندي منه دينار، إلا أرصده لدين،
إلا أن أقول به في عباد الله هكذا وهكذا وهكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ وأرانا بيده‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت لبيك وسعديك يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
الأكثرون هم الأقلون إلا من قال هكذا وهكذا ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قال لي ‏"‏
مكانك لا تبرح يا أبا ذر حتى أرجع ‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلق حتى غاب عني، فسمعت
صوتا فخشيت أن يكون عرض لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأردت أن أذهب،
ثم ذكرت قول رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تبرح ‏"‏‏.‏ فمكثت
قلت يا رسول الله سمعت صوتا خشيت أن يكون عرض لك، ثم ذكرت قولك
فقمت‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ذاك جبريل أتاني، فأخبرني
أنه من مات من أمتي لا يشرك بالله شيئا دخل الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت يا رسول
الله وإن زنى وإن سرق‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ وإن زنى وإن سرق ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت لزيد إنه
بلغني أنه أبو الدرداء‏.‏ فقال أشهد لحدثنيه أبو ذر بالربذة‏.‏ قال
الأعمش وحدثني أبو صالح عن أبي الدرداء نحوه‏.‏ وقال أبو شهاب عن
الأعمش ‏"‏ يمكث عندي فوق ثلاث ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Dhar: While I was walking with the
Prophet at the Hurra of Medina in the evening, the mountain of Uhud
appeared before us. The Prophet said, "O Abu Dhar! I would not like
to have gold equal to Uhud (mountain) for me, unless nothing of it,
not even a single Dinar remains of it with me, for more than one
day or three days, except that single Dinar which I will keep for
repaying debts. I will spend all of it (the whole amount) among
Allah's slaves like this and like this and like this." The Prophet
pointed out with his hand to illustrate it and then said, "O Abu
Dhar!" I replied, "Labbaik wa Sa`daik, O Allah's Apostle!" He said,
"Those who have much wealth (in this world) will be the least
rewarded (in the Hereafter) except those who do like this and like
this (i.e., spend their money in charity)." Then he ordered me,
"Remain at your place and do not leave it, O Abu Dhar, till I come
back." He went away till he disappeared from me. Then I heard a
voice and feared that something might have happened to Allah's
Apostle, and I intended to go (to find out) but I remembered the
statement of Allah's Apostle that I should not leave, my place, so
I kept on waiting (and after a while the Prophet came), and I said
to him, "O Allah's Apostle, I heard a voice and I was afraid that
something might have happened to you, but then I remembered your
statement and stayed (there). The Prophet said, "That was Gabriel
who came to me and informed me that whoever among my followers died
without joining others in worship with Allah, would enter
Paradise." I said, "O Allah's Apostle! Even if he had committed
illegal sexual intercourse and theft?" He said, "Even if he had
committed illegal sexual intercourse and theft."</english-text>
</hadith>
