<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6150</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>79</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6356</hadith-number>
<chapter>Asking Permission - كتاب الاستئذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد الله بن
أبي طلحة، عن أنس بن مالك رضى الله عنه أنه سمعه يقول كان رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا ذهب إلى قباء يدخل على أم حرام بنت ملحان
فتطعمه، وكانت تحت عبادة بن الصامت، فدخل يوما فأطعمته، فنام رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم استيقظ يضحك‏.‏ قالت فقلت ما يضحكك يا
رسول الله فقال ‏"‏ ناس من أمتي عرضوا على غزاة في سبيل الله، يركبون
ثبج هذا البحر، ملوكا على الأسرة ‏"‏‏.‏ أو قال ‏"‏ مثل الملوك على
الأسرة ‏"‏‏.‏ شك إسحاق قلت ادع الله أن يجعلني منهم‏.‏ فدعا ثم وضع
رأسه فنام، ثم استيقظ يضحك فقلت ما يضحكك يا رسول الله قال ‏"‏ ناس من
أمتي عرضوا على، غزاة في سبيل الله، يركبون ثبج هذا البحر، ملوكا على
الأسرة ‏"‏‏.‏ أو ‏"‏ مثل الملوك على الأسرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت ادع الله أن
يجعلني منهم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أنت من الأولين ‏"‏‏.‏ فركبت البحر زمان
معاوية، فصرعت عن دابتها حين خرجت من البحر، فهلكت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Whenever Allah's Apostle
went to Quba, he used to visit Um Haram bint Milhan who would offer
him meals; and she was the wife of 'Ubada bin As-samit. One day he
went to her house and she offered him a meal, and after that he
slept, and then woke up smiling. She (Um Haram) said, "I asked him,
'What makes you laugh, O Allah's Apostle?' He said, 'Some people of
my followers were displayed before me as warriors fighting for
Allah's Cause and sailing over this sea, kings on thrones,' or
said, 'like kings on thrones.' (The narrator, 'Is-haq is in doubt
about it.) I (Um Haram) said, 'O Allah's Apostle! Invoke Allah that
He may make me one of them.' He invoked (Allah) for her and then
lay his head and slept again and then woke up smiling. I asked,
'What makes you laugh, O Allah's Apostle?' He said, 'Some people of
my followers were displayed before me as warriors fighting for
Allah's Cause and sailing over this sea, kings on the thrones,' or
said, 'like kings on the thrones.' I (Um Haram) said, 'O Allah's
Apostle! Invoke Allah that He may make me one of them.' He said,
You will be amongst the first ones." It is said that Um Haram
sailed over the sea at the time of Muawiya, and on coming out of
the sea, she fell down from her riding animal and
died.</english-text>
</hadith>
