<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6152</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>79</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6358</hadith-number>
<chapter>Asking Permission - كتاب الاستئذان</chapter>
<chain-index>20040, 20469, 11385, 11052, 11018, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا موسى، عن أبي عوانة، حدثنا فراس، عن عامر، عن
مسروق، حدثتني عائشة أم المؤمنين، قالت إنا كنا أزواج النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم عنده جميعا، لم تغادر منا واحدة، فأقبلت فاطمة عليها السلام
تمشي، لا والله ما تخفى مشيتها من مشية رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فلما رآها رحب قال ‏"‏ مرحبا بابنتي ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم أجلسها عن يمينه أو عن
شماله، ثم سارها فبكت بكاء شديدا، فلما رأى حزنها سارها الثانية إذا
هي تضحك‏.‏ فقلت لها أنا من بين نسائه خصك رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم بالسر من بيننا، ثم أنت تبكين، فلما قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم سألتها عما سارك</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Mother of the Believers: We, the
wives of the Prophet were all sitting with the Prophet and none of
us had left when Fatima came walking, and by Allah, her gait was
very similar to that of Allah's Apostle .' When he saw her, he
welcomed her, saying, "Welcome, O my daughter!" Then he made her
sit on his right or his left, confided something to her, whereupon
she wept bitterly. When he noticed her sorrow, he confided
something else to her for the second time, and she started
laughing. Only I from among the Prophet's wives said to her, "(O
Fatima), Allah's Apostle selected you from among us for the secret
talk and still you weep?" When Allah's Apostle got up (and went
away), I asked her, "What did he confide to you?" She said, "I
wouldn't disclose the secrets of Allah's Apostle" But when he died
I asked her, "I beseech you earnestly by what right I have on you,
to tell me (that secret talk which the Prophet had with you)" She
said, "As you ask me now, yes, (I will tell you)." She informed me,
saying, "When he talked to me secretly the first time, he said that
Gabriel used to review the Qur'an with him once every year. He
added, 'But this year he reviewed it with me twice, and therefore I
think that my time of death has approached. So, be afraid of Allah,
and be patient, for I am the best predecessor for you (in the
Hereafter).' " Fatima added, "So I wept as you (`Aisha) witnessed.
And when the Prophet saw me in this sorrowful state, he confided
the second secret to me saying, 'O Fatima! Will you not be pleased
that you will be chief of all the believing women (or chief of the
women of this nation i.e. my followers?")</english-text>
</hadith>
