<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>80</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>80</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6381</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invocations - كتاب الدعوات</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 11613, 11060, 11378, 11330</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن يونس، حدثنا أبو شهاب، عن الأعمش، عن
عمارة بن عمير، عن الحارث بن سويد، حدثنا عبد الله، حديثين أحدهما عن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم والآخر عن نفسه، قال ‏"‏ إن المؤمن يرى
ذنوبه كأنه قاعد تحت جبل يخاف أن يقع عليه، وإن الفاجر يرى ذنوبه
كذباب مر على أنفه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال به هكذا قال أبو شهاب بيده فوق أنفه‏.‏
ثم قال ‏"‏ لله أفرح بتوبة عبده من رجل نزل منزلا، وبه مهلكة، ومعه
راحلته عليها طعامه وشرابه، فوضع رأسه فنام نومة، فاستيقظ وقد ذهبت
راحلته، حتى اشتد عليه الحر والعطش أو ما شاء الله، قال أرجع إلى
مكاني‏.‏ فرجع فنام نومة، ثم رفع رأسه، فإذا راحلته عنده ‏"‏‏.‏ تابعه
أبو عوانة وجرير عن الأعمش‏.‏ وقال أبو أسامة حدثنا الأعمش حدثنا
عمارة سمعت الحارث‏.‏ وقال شعبة وأبو مسلم عن الأعمش عن إبراهيم
التيمي عن الحارث بن سويد‏.‏ وقال أبو معاوية حدثنا الأعمش عن عمارة
عن الأسود عن عبد الله وعن إبراهيم التيمي عن الحارث بن سويد عن عبد
الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Harith bin Suwaid: `Abdullah bin Mas`ud
related to us two narrations: One from the Prophet and the other
from himself, saying: A believer sees his sins as if he were
sitting under a mountain which, he is afraid, may fall on him;
whereas the wicked person considers his sins as flies passing over
his nose and he just drives them away like this." Abu Shihab (the
sub-narrator) moved his hand over his nose in illustration. (Ibn
Mas`ud added): Allah's Apostle said, "Allah is more pleased with
the repentance of His slave than a man who encamps at a place where
his life is jeopardized, but he has his riding beast carrying his
food and water. He then rests his head and sleeps for a short while
and wakes to find his riding beast gone. (He starts looking for it)
and suffers from severe heat and thirst or what Allah wished (him
to suffer from). He then says, 'I will go back to my place.' He
returns and sleeps again, and then (getting up), he raises his head
to find his riding beast standing beside him."</english-text>
</hadith>
