<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>80</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>80</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6405</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invocations - كتاب الدعوات</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20031, 237</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا يحيى، عن يزيد بن أبي عبيد، مولى سلمة
حدثنا سلمة بن الأكوع، قال خرجنا مع النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى
خيبر، قال رجل من القوم أيا عامر لو أسمعتنا من هنيهاتك‏.‏ فنزل يحدو
بهم يذكر‏.‏ تالله لولا الله ما اهتدينا‏.‏ وذكر شعرا غير هذا، ولكني
لم أحفظه‏.‏ قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ من هذا السائق
‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا عامر بن الأكوع‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ يرحمه الله ‏"‏‏.‏ وقال رجل
من القوم يا رسول الله لولا متعتنا به، فلما صاف القوم قاتلوهم، فأصيب
عامر بقائمة سيف نفسه فمات، فلما أمسوا أوقدوا نارا كثيرة فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما هذه النار على أى شىء توقدون ‏"‏‏.‏
قالوا على حمر إنسية‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أهريقوا ما فيها، وكسروها ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
رجل يا رسول الله ألا نهريق ما فيها ونغسلها قال ‏"‏ أو ذاك
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Salama bin Al-Akwa`: We went out with the
Prophet to Khaibar. A man among the people said, "O 'Amir! Will you
please recite to us some of your poetic verses?" So 'Amir got down
and started chanting among them, saying, "By Allah! Had it not been
for Allah, we would not have been guided." 'Amir also said other
poetic verses which I do not remember. Allah's Apostle said, "Who
is this (camel) driver?" The people said, "He is 'Amir bin
Al-Akwa`," He said, "May Allah bestow His Mercy on him." A man from
the People said, "O Allah's Apostle! Would that you let us enjoy
his company longer." When the people (Muslims) lined up, the battle
started, and 'Amir was struck with his own sword (by chance) by
himself and died. In the evening, the people made a large number of
fires (for cooking meals). Allah's Apostle said, "What is this
fire? What are you making the fire for?" They said, "For cooking
the meat of donkeys." He said, "Throw away what is in the pots and
break the pots!" A man said, "O Allah's Prophet! May we throw away
what is in them and wash them?" He said, "Never mind, you may do
so." (See Hadith No. 509, Vol. 5).</english-text>
</hadith>
