<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>80</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>80</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6436</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invocations - كتاب الدعوات</chapter>
<chain-index>30329, 20295, 11019, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا حفص بن عمر، حدثنا هشام، عن قتادة، عن أنس رضى
الله عنه سألوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حتى أحفوه المسألة فغضب
فصعد المنبر فقال ‏"‏ لا تسألوني اليوم عن شىء إلا بينته لكم ‏"‏‏.‏
فجعلت أنظر يمينا وشمالا، فإذا كل رجل لاف رأسه في ثوبه يبكي، فإذا
رجل كان إذا لاحى الرجال يدعى لغير أبيه فقال يا رسول الله من أبي قال
‏"‏ حذافة ‏"‏، ثم أنشأ عمر فقال رضينا بالله ربا، وبالإسلام دينا،
وبمحمد صلى الله عليه وسلم رسولا، نعوذ بالله من الفتن‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ما رأيت في الخير والشر كاليوم قط، إنه
صورت لي الجنة والنار حتى رأيتهما وراء الحائط ‏"‏‏.‏ وكان قتادة يذكر
عند الحديث هذه الآية ‏{‏يا أيها الذين آمنوا لا تسألوا عن أشياء إن
تبد لكم تسؤكم‏}‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: Once the people started asking Allah's
Apostle questions, and they asked so many questions that he became
angry and ascended the pulpit and said, "I will answer whatever
questions you may ask me today." I looked right and left and saw
everyone covering his face with his garment and weeping. Behold !
There was a man who, on quarreling with the people, used to be
called as a son of a person other than h is father. He said, "O
Allah's Apostle! Who is my father?" The Prophet replied, "Your
father is Hudhaifa." And then `Umar got up and said, "We accept
Allah as our Lord, and Islam as (our) religion, and Muhammad as
(our) Apostle; and we seek refuge with Allah from the afflictions."
Allah's Apostle said, " I have never seen a day like today in its
good and its evil for Paradise and the Hell Fire were displayed in
front of me, till I saw them just beyond this wall." Qatada, when
relating this Hadith, used to mention the following Verse:-- 'O you
who believe! Ask not questions about things which, If made plain to
you, May cause you trouble. (5.101)</english-text>
</hadith>
