<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>80</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>80</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6437</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invocations - كتاب الدعوات</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20155, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا إسماعيل بن جعفر، عن عمرو بن
أبي عمرو، مولى المطلب بن عبد الله بن حنطب أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يقول
قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لأبي طلحة ‏"‏ التمس لنا غلاما من
غلمانكم يخدمني ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرج بي أبو طلحة يردفني وراءه، فكنت أخدم رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كلما نزل، فكنت أسمعه يكثر أن يقول ‏"‏ اللهم
إني أعوذ بك من الهم والحزن، والعجز والكسل، والبخل والجبن، وضلع
الدين، وغلبة الرجال ‏"‏‏.‏ فلم أزل أخدمه حتى أقبلنا من خيبر، وأقبل
بصفية بنت حيى قد حازها، فكنت أراه يحوي وراءه بعباءة أو كساء ثم
يردفها وراءه حتى إذا كنا بالصهباء صنع حيسا في نطع، ثم أرسلني فدعوت
رجالا فأكلوا، وكان ذلك بناءه بها، ثم أقبل حتى بدا له أحد قال ‏"‏
هذا جبيل يحبنا ونحبه ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما أشرف على المدينة قال ‏"‏ اللهم إني
أحرم ما بين جبليها مثل ما حرم به إبراهيم مكة، اللهم بارك لهم في
مدهم وصاعهم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: The Prophet said to Abu
Talha, "Choose one of your boys to serve me." So Abu Talha took me
(to serve the Prophet ) by giving me a ride behind him (on his
camel). So I used to serve Allah's Apostle whenever he stayed
somewhere. I used to hear him saying, "O Allah! I seek refuge with
you (Allah) from (worries) care and grief, from incapacity and
laziness, from miserliness and cowardice, from being heavily in
debt and from being overpowered by other men." I kept on serving
him till he returned from (the battle of) Khaibar. He then brought
Safiya, the daughter of Huyay whom he had got (from the booty). I
saw him making a kind of cushion with a cloak or a garment for her.
He then let her ride behind him. When we reached a place called
As-Sahba', he prepared (a special meal called) Hais, and asked me
to invite the men who (came and) ate, and that was the marriage
banquet given on the consummation of his marriage to her. Then he
proceeded till the mountain of Uhud appeared, whereupon he said,
"This mountain loves us and we love it." When he approached Medina,
he said, "O Allah! I make the land between its (i.e., Medina's) two
mountains a sanctuary, as the prophet Abraham made Mecca a
sanctuary. O Allah! Bless them (the people of Medina) in their Mudd
and the Sa' (units of measuring).</english-text>
</hadith>
