<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>80</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>80</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6464</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invocations - كتاب الدعوات</chapter>
<chain-index>20157, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إبراهيم بن منذر، حدثنا أنس بن عياض، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة رضى الله عنها أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم طب حتى
إنه ليخيل إليه قد صنع الشىء وما صنعه، وإنه دعا ربه ثم قال ‏"‏ أشعرت
أن الله قد أفتاني فيما استفتيته فيه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالت عائشة فما ذاك يا
رسول الله قال ‏"‏ جاءني رجلان فجلس أحدهما عند رأسي، والآخر عند رجلى
فقال أحدهما لصاحبه ما وجع الرجل قال مطبوب‏.‏ قال من طبه قال لبيد بن
الأعصم‏.‏ قال فيما ذا قال في مشط ومشاطة وجف طلعة‏.‏ قال فأين هو قال
في ذروان، وذروان بئر في بني زريق ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فأتاها رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ثم رجع إلى عائشة فقال ‏"‏ والله لكأن ماءها نقاعة
الحناء، ولكأن نخلها رءوس الشياطين ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فأتى رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فأخبرها عن البئر، فقلت يا رسول الله فهلا أخرجته قال
‏"‏ أما أنا فقد شفاني الله، وكرهت أن أثير على الناس شرا ‏"‏‏.‏ زاد
عيسى بن يونس والليث عن هشام عن أبيه عن عائشة قالت سحر النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم فدعا ودعا وساق الحديث</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: that Allah's Apostle was affected by
magic, so much that he used to think that he had done something
which in fact, he did not do, and he invoked his Lord (for a
remedy). Then (one day) he said, "O `Aisha!) Do you know that Allah
has advised me as to the problem I consulted Him about?" `Aisha
said, "O Allah's Apostle! What's that?" He said, "Two men came to
me and one of them sat at my head and the other at my feet, and one
of them asked his companion, 'What is wrong with this man?' The
latter replied, 'He is under the effect of magic.' The former
asked, 'Who has worked magic on him?' The latter replied, 'Labid
bin Al-A'sam.' The former asked, 'With what did he work the magic?'
The latter replied, 'With a comb and the hair, which are stuck to
the comb, and the skin of pollen of a date-palm tree.' The former
asked, 'Where is that?' The latter replied, 'It is in Dharwan.'
Dharwan was a well in the dwelling place of the (tribe of) Bani
Zuraiq. Allah's Apostle went to that well and returned to `Aisha,
saying, 'By Allah, the water (of the well) was as red as the
infusion of Hinna, (1) and the date-palm trees look like the heads
of devils.' `Aisha added, Allah's Apostle came to me and informed
me about the well. I asked the Prophet, 'O Allah's Apostle, why
didn't you take out the skin of pollen?' He said, 'As for me, Allah
has cured me and I hated to draw the attention of the people to
such evil (which they might learn and harm others with).' "
Narrated Hisham's father: `Aisha said, "Allah's Apostle was
bewitched, so he invoked Allah repeatedly requesting Him to cure
him from that magic)." Hisham then narrated the above narration.
(See Hadith No. 658, Vol. 7)</english-text>
</hadith>
