<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6290</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>81</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6501</hadith-number>
<chapter>To make the Heart Tender (Ar-Riqaq) - كتاب
الرقاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20154, 11106, 11013, 10511, 2201,
30154</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل بن عبد الله، قال حدثني إسماعيل بن
إبراهيم بن عقبة، عن موسى بن عقبة، قال ابن شهاب حدثني عروة بن
الزبير، أن المسور بن مخرمة، أخبره أن عمرو بن عوف وهو حليف لبني عامر
بن لؤى كان شهد بدرا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبره أن رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بعث أبا عبيدة بن الجراح إلى البحرين يأتي
بجزيتها، وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم هو صالح أهل البحرين،
وأمر عليهم العلاء بن الحضرمي، فقدم أبو عبيدة بمال من البحرين، فسمعت
الأنصار بقدومه فوافته صلاة الصبح مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فلما انصرف تعرضوا له فتبسم حين رآهم وقال ‏"‏ أظنكم سمعتم بقدوم أبي
عبيدة، وأنه جاء بشىء ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا أجل يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
فأبشروا وأملوا ما يسركم، فوالله ما الفقر أخشى عليكم، ولكن أخشى
عليكم أن تبسط عليكم الدنيا، كما بسطت على من كان قبلكم، فتنافسوها
كما تنافسوها وتلهيكم كما ألهتهم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Amr bin `Auf: (An ally of the tribe of Bani
'Amir bin Lu'ai and one of those who had witnessed the battle of
Badr with Allah's Apostle) Allah's Apostle sent Abu 'Ubaida bin
AlJarrah to Bahrain to collect the Jizya tax. Allah's Apostle had
concluded a peace treaty with the people of Bahrain and appointed
Al 'Ala bin Al-Hadrami as their chief; Abu Ubaida arrived from
Bahrain with the money. The Ansar heard of Abu 'Ubaida's arrival
which coincided with the Fajr (morning) prayer led by Allah's
Apostle. When the Prophet finished the prayer, they came to him.
Allah's Apostle smiled when he saw them and said, "I think you have
heard of the arrival of Abu 'Ubaida and that he has brought
something." They replied, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle! " He said, "Have
the good news, and hope for what will please you. By Allah, I am
not afraid that you will become poor, but I am afraid that worldly
wealth will be given to you in abundance as it was given to those
(nations) before you, and you will start competing each other for
it as the previous nations competed for it, and then it will divert
you (from good) as it diverted them." '</english-text>
</hadith>
