<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6308</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>81</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6519</hadith-number>
<chapter>To make the Heart Tender (Ar-Riqaq) - كتاب
الرقاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20028, 11257, 11341, 23</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا جرير، عن عبد العزيز بن
رفيع، عن زيد بن وهب، عن أبي ذر رضى الله عنه قال خرجت ليلة من
الليالي فإذا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يمشي وحده، وليس معه إنسان
قال فظننت أنه يكره أن يمشي معه أحد قال فجعلت أمشي في ظل القمر
فالتفت فرآني فقال ‏"‏ من هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت أبو ذر جعلني الله فداءك‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ يا أبا ذر تعاله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فمشيت معه ساعة فقال ‏"‏ إن
المكثرين هم المقلون يوم القيامة، إلا من أعطاه الله خيرا، فنفح فيه
يمينه وشماله وبين يديه ووراءه، وعمل فيه خيرا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فمشيت معه
ساعة فقال لي ‏"‏ اجلس ها هنا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فأجلسني في قاع حوله حجارة
فقال لي ‏"‏ اجلس ها هنا حتى أرجع إليك ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فانطلق في الحرة
حتى لا أراه فلبث عني فأطال اللبث، ثم إني سمعته وهو مقبل وهو يقول
‏"‏ وإن سرق وإن زنى ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فلما جاء لم أصبر حتى قلت يا نبي الله
جعلني الله فداءك من تكلم في جانب الحرة ما سمعت أحدا يرجع إليك
شيئا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ذلك جبريل عليه السلام عرض لي في جانب الحرة، قال بشر
أمتك أنه من مات لا يشرك بالله شيئا دخل الجنة، قلت يا جبريل وإن سرق
وإن زنى قال نعم‏.‏ قال قلت وإن سرق وإن زنى قال نعم، وإن شرب الخمر
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Dhar: Once I went out at night and found
Allah's Apostle walking all alone accompanied by nobody, and I
thought that perhaps he disliked that someone should accompany him.
So I walked in the shade, away from the moonlight, but the Prophet
looked behind and saw me and said, "Who is that?" I replied, "Abu
Dhar, let Allah get me sacrificed for you!" He said, "O Abu Dhar,
come here!" So I accompanied him for a while and then he said, "The
rich are in fact the poor (little rewarded) on the Day of
Resurrection except him whom Allah gives wealth which he gives (in
charity) to his right, left, front and back, and does good deeds
with it. I walked with him a little longer. Then he said to me,
"Sit down here." So he made me sit in an open space surrounded by
rocks, and said to me, "Sit here till I come back to you." He went
towards Al-Harra till I could not see him, and he stayed away for a
long period, and then I heard him saying, while he was coming,
"Even if he had committed theft, and even if he had committed
illegal sexual intercourse?" When he came, I could not remain
patient and asked him, "O Allah's Prophet! Let Allah get me
sacrificed for you! Whom were you speaking to by the side of
Al-Harra? I did not hear anybody responding to your talk." He said,
"It was Gabriel who appeared to me beside Al-Harra and said, 'Give
the good news to your followers that whoever dies without having
worshipped anything besides Allah, will enter Paradise.' I said, 'O
Gabriel! Even if he had committed theft or committed illegal sexual
intercourse?' He said, 'Yes.' I said, 'Even if he has committed
theft or committed illegal sexual intercourse?' He said, 'Yes.' I
said, 'Even if he has committed theft or committed illegal sexual
intercourse?' He said, 'Yes.' "</english-text>
</hadith>
