<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6389</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>81</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6599</hadith-number>
<chapter>To make the Heart Tender (Ar-Riqaq) - كتاب
الرقاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 20423, 11169, 11163, 11020,
38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن خالد، عن سعيد بن
أبي هلال، عن زيد بن أسلم، عن عطاء بن يسار، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ تكون الأرض يوم القيامة خبزة واحدة،
يتكفؤها الجبار بيده، كما يكفأ أحدكم خبزته في السفر، نزلا لأهل الجنة
‏"‏‏.‏ فأتى رجل من اليهود فقال بارك الرحمن عليك يا أبا القاسم، ألا
أخبرك بنزل أهل الجنة يوم القيامة قال ‏"‏ بلى ‏"‏‏.‏ قال تكون الأرض
خبزة واحدة كما قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فنظر النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم إلينا، ثم ضحك حتى بدت نواجذه ثم قال ألا أخبرك بإدامهم قال
إدامهم بالام ونون‏.‏ قالوا وما هذا قال ثور ونون يأكل من زائدة
كبدهما سبعون ألفا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: The Prophet said, "The
(planet of) earth will be a bread on the Day of Resurrection, and
The resistible (Allah) will topple turn it with His Hand like
anyone of you topple turns a bread with his hands while (preparing
the bread) for a journey, and that bread will be the entertainment
for the people of Paradise." A man from the Jews came (to the
Prophet) and said, "May The Beneficent (Allah) bless you, O Abul
Qasim! Shall I tell you of the entertainment of the people of
Paradise on the Day of Resurrection?" The Prophet said, "Yes." The
Jew said, "The earth will be a bread," as the Prophet had said.
Thereupon the Prophet looked at us and smiled till his premolar
tooth became visible. Then the Jew further said, "Shall I tell you
of the udm (additional food taken with bread) they will have with
the bread?" He added, "That will be Balam and Nun." The people
asked, "What is that?" He said, "It is an ox and a fish, and
seventy thousand people will eat of the caudate lobe (i.e. extra
lobe) of their livers."</english-text>
</hadith>
