<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6435</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>81</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6645</hadith-number>
<chapter>To make the Heart Tender (Ar-Riqaq) - كتاب
الرقاق</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20469, 11019, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن قتادة، عن أنس رضى الله
عنه قال قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ يجمع الله الناس يوم
القيامة فيقولون لو استشفعنا على ربنا حتى يريحنا من مكاننا‏.‏ فيأتون
آدم فيقولون أنت الذي خلقك الله بيده، ونفخ فيك من روحه، وأمر
الملائكة فسجدوا لك، فاشفع لنا عند ربنا‏.‏ فيقول لست هناكم ويذكر
خطيئته ويقول ائتوا نوحا أول رسول بعثه الله‏.‏ فيأتونه فيقول لست
هناكم ويذكر خطيئته ائتوا إبراهيم الذي اتخذه الله خليلا‏.‏ فيأتونه،
فيقول لست هناكم ويذكر خطيئته ائتوا موسى الذي كلمه الله فيأتونه
فيقول لست هناكم، فيذكر خطيئته ائتوا عيسى فيأتونه فيقول لست هناكم،
ائتوا محمدا صلى الله عليه وسلم فقد غفر له ما تقدم من ذنبه وما تأخر
فيأتوني فأستأذن على ربي، فإذا رأيته وقعت ساجدا، فيدعني ما شاء الله،
ثم يقال ارفع رأسك، سل تعطه، وقل يسمع، واشفع تشفع‏.‏ فأرفع رأسي،
فأحمد ربي بتحميد يعلمني، ثم أشفع فيحد لي حدا، ثم أخرجهم من النار،
وأدخلهم الجنة، ثم أعود فأقع ساجدا مثله في الثالثة أو الرابعة حتى ما
بقي في النار إلا من حبسه القرآن ‏"‏‏.‏ وكان قتادة يقول عند هذا أى
وجب عليه الخلود‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: Allah's Apostle said, "Allah will
gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection and they will say,
'Let us request someone to intercede for us with our Lord so that
He may relieve us from this place of ours.' Then they will go to
Adam and say, 'You are the one whom Allah created with His Own
Hands, and breathed in you of His soul, and ordered the angels to
prostrate to you; so please intercede for us with our Lord.' Adam
will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, and will remember
his sin, and will say, 'Go to Noah, the first Apostle sent by
Allah' They will go to him and he will say, 'I am not fit for this
undertaking', and will remember his sin and say, 'Go to Abraham
whom Allah took as a Khalil. They will go to him (and request
similarly). He will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and
will remember his sin and say, 'Go to Moses to whom Allah spoke
directly.' They will go to Moses and he will say, 'I am not fit for
this undertaking,' and will remember his sin and say, 'Go to
Jesus.' They will go to him, and he will say, 'I am not fit for
this undertaking, go to Muhammad as Allah has forgiven his past and
future sins.' They will come to me and I will ask my Lord's
permission, and when I see Him, I will fall down in prostration to
Him, and He will leave me in that state as long as (He) Allah will,
and then I will be addressed. 'Raise up your head (O Muhammad)!
Ask, and your request will be granted, and say, and your saying
will be listened to; intercede, and your intercession will be
accepted.' Then I will raise my head, and I will glorify and praise
my Lord with a saying(i.e. invocation) He will teach me, and then I
will intercede, Allah will fix a limit for me (i.e., certain type
of people for whom I may intercede), and I will take them out of
the (Hell) Fire and let them enter Paradise. Then I will come back
(to Allah) and fall in prostration, and will do the same for the
third and fourth times till no-one remains in the (Hell) Fire
except those whom the Qur'an has imprisoned therein." (The
sub-narrator, Qatada used to say at that point, "...those upon whom
eternity (in Hell) has been imposed.") (See Hadith No. 3, Vol
6).</english-text>
</hadith>
