<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6517</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>83</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6730</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oaths and Vows - كتاب الأيمان والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20259, 11015, 11047, 11719, 11589</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، عن أيوب، عن أبي قلابة،
والقاسم التميمي، عن زهدم، قال كان بين هذا الحى من جرم وبين
الأشعريين ود وإخاء، فكنا عند أبي موسى الأشعري، فقرب إليه طعام فيه
لحم دجاج وعنده رجل من بني تيم الله أحمر كأنه من الموالي، فدعاه إلى
الطعام فقال إني رأيته يأكل شيئا فقذرته، فحلفت أن لا آكله‏.‏ فقال قم
فلأحدثنك عن ذاك، إني أتيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في نفر من
الأشعريين نستحمله فقال ‏"‏ والله لا أحملكم، وما عندي ما أحملكم
‏"‏‏.‏ فأتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بنهب إبل فسأل عنا‏.‏ فقال
‏"‏ أين النفر الأشعريون ‏"‏‏.‏ فأمر لنا بخمس ذود غر الذرى، فلما
انطلقنا قلنا ما صنعنا حلف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لا يحملنا
وما عنده ما يحملنا ثم حملنا، تغفلنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يمينه، والله لا نفلح أبدا، فرجعنا إليه فقلنا له إنا أتيناك لتحملنا
فحلفت أن لا تحملنا، وما عندك ما تحملنا‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ إني لست أنا
حملتكم، ولكن الله حملكم، والله لا أحلف على يمين فأرى غيرها خيرا
منها، إلا أتيت الذي هو خير وتحللتها ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Zahdam: There was a relation of love and
brotherhood between this tribe of Jarm and Al-Ash`ariyin. Once we
were with Abu Musa Al-Ash`ari, and then a meal containing chicken
was brought to Abu Musa, and there was present, a man from the
tribe of Taimillah who was of red complexion as if he were from
non-Arab freed slaves. Abu Musa invited him to the meal. He said,
"I have seen chickens eating dirty things, so I deemed it filthy
and took an oath that I would never eat chicken." On that, Abu Musa
said, "Get up, I will narrate to you about that. Once a group of
the Ash`ariyin and I went to Allah's Apostle and asked him to
provide us with mounts; he said, 'By Allah, I will never give you
any mounts nor do I have anything to mount you on.' Then a few
camels of war booty were brought to Allah's Apostle , and he asked
about us, saying, 'Where are the Ash-'ariyin?' He then ordered five
nice camels to be given to us, and when we had departed, we said,
'What have we done? Allah's Apostle had taken the oath not to give
us any mounts, and that he had nothing to mount us on, and later he
gave us that we might ride? Did we take advantage of the fact that
Allah's Apostle had forgotten his oath? By Allah, we will never
succeed.' So we went back to him and said to him, 'We came to you
to give us mounts, and you took an oath that you would not give us
any mounts and that you had nothing to mount us on.' On that he
said, 'I did not provide you with mounts, but Allah did. By Allah,
if I take an oath to do something, and then find something else
better than it, I do that which is better and make expiation for
the dissolution of the oath.' "</english-text>
</hadith>
