<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>647</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>664</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30204, 20317, 11060, 11051, 11054</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمر بن حفص بن غياث، قال حدثني أبي قال، حدثنا
الأعمش، عن إبراهيم، قال الأسود قال كنا عند عائشة رضى الله عنها
فذكرنا المواظبة على الصلاة والتعظيم لها، قالت لما مرض رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم مرضه الذي مات فيه، فحضرت الصلاة فأذن، فقال ‏"‏ مروا
أبا بكر فليصل بالناس ‏"‏‏.‏ فقيل له إن أبا بكر رجل أسيف، إذا قام في
مقامك لم يستطع أن يصلي بالناس، وأعاد فأعادوا له، فأعاد الثالثة فقال
‏"‏ إنكن صواحب يوسف، مروا أبا بكر فليصل بالناس ‏"‏‏.‏ فخرج أبو بكر
فصلى، فوجد النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم من نفسه خفة، فخرج يهادى بين
رجلين كأني أنظر رجليه تخطان من الوجع، فأراد أبو بكر أن يتأخر، فأومأ
إليه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن مكانك، ثم أتي به حتى جلس إلى
جنبه‏.‏ قيل للأعمش وكان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يصلي وأبو بكر يصلي
بصلاته، والناس يصلون بصلاة أبي بكر فقال برأسه نعم‏.‏ رواه أبو داود
عن شعبة عن الأعمش بعضه‏.‏ وزاد أبو معاوية جلس عن يسار أبي بكر فكان
أبو بكر يصلي قائما‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Aswad: "We were with `Aisha discussing
the regularity of offering the prayer and dignifying it. She said,
'When Allah's Apostle fell sick with the fatal illness and when the
time of prayer became due and Adhan was pronounced, he said, 'Tell
Abu Bakr to lead the people in prayer.' He was told that Abu Bakr
was a softhearted man and would not be able to lead the prayer in
his place. The Prophet gave the same order again but he was given
the same reply. He gave the order for the third time and said, 'You
(women) are the companions of Joseph. Tell Abu Bakr to lead the
prayer.' So Abu Bakr came out to lead the prayer. In the meantime
the condition of the Prophet improved a bit and he came out with
the help of two men one on each side. As if I was observing his
legs dragging on the ground owing to the disease. Abu Bakr wanted
to retreat but the Prophet beckoned him to remain at his place and
the Prophet was brought till he sat beside Abu Bakr." Al-A`mash was
asked, "Was the Prophet praying and Abu Bakr following him, and
were the people following Abu Bakr in that prayer?" Al- A`mash
replied in the affirmative with a nod of his head. Abu Muawiya
said, "The Prophet was sitting on the left side of Abu Bakr who was
praying while standing."</english-text>
</hadith>
