<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6557</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>83</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6770</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oaths and Vows - كتاب الأيمان والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20001, 11151, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة، عن مالك، عن إسحاق بن عبد الله بن أبي
طلحة، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، قال قال أبو طلحة لأم سليم لقد سمعت صوت،
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ضعيفا أعرف فيه الجوع، فهل عندك من شىء
فقالت نعم‏.‏ فأخرجت أقراصا من شعير، ثم أخذت خمارا لها، فلفت الخبز
ببعضه، ثم أرسلتني إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فذهبت فوجدت رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم في المسجد ومعه الناس، فقمت عليهم فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أرسلك أبو طلحة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت نعم‏.‏ فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لمن معه ‏"‏ قوموا ‏"‏‏.‏ فانطلقوا،
وانطلقت بين أيديهم حتى جئت أبا طلحة فأخبرته‏.‏ فقال أبو طلحة يا أم
سليم قد جاء رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وليس عندنا من الطعام ما
نطعمهم‏.‏ فقالت الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فانطلق أبو طلحة حتى لقي رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فأقبل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأبو
طلحة حتى دخلا، فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ هلمي يا أم
سليم ما عندك ‏"‏‏.‏ فأتت بذلك الخبز قال فأمر رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم بذلك الخبز ففت، وعصرت أم سليم عكة لها فأدمته، ثم قال فيه
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله أن يقول، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن
لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأذن لهم فأكلوا حتى شبعوا، ثم خرجوا، ثم قال ‏"‏ ائذن
لعشرة ‏"‏‏.‏ فأذن لهم، فأكل القوم كلهم وشبعوا، والقوم سبعون أو
ثمانون رجلا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: Abu Talha said to Um Sulaim,
"I heard the voice of Allah's Apostle rather weak, and I knew that
it was because of hunger. Have you anything (to present to the
Prophet)?" She said, "Yes." Then she took out a few loaves of
barley bread and took a veil of hers and wrapped the bread with a
part of it and sent me to Allah's Apostle. I went and found Allah's
Apostle sitting in the mosque with some people. I stood up before
him. Allah's Apostle said to me, "Has Abu Talha sent you?" I said,
' Yes. Then Allah's Apostle said to those who were with him. "Get
up and proceed." I went ahead of them (as their forerunner) and
came to Abu Talha and informed him about it. Abu Talha said, "O Um
Sulaim! Allah's Apostle has come and we have no food to feed them."
Um Sulaim said, "Allah and His Apostle know best." So Abu Talha
went out (to receive them) till he met Allah's Apostle. Allah's
Apostle came in company with Abu Talha and they entered the house.
Allah's Apostle said, "O Um Sulaim! Bring whatever you have." So
she brought that (barley) bread and Allah's Apostle ordered that
bread to be broken into small pieces, and then Um Sulaim poured
over it some butter from a leather butter container, and then
Allah's Apostle said what Allah wanted him to say, (i.e. blessing
the food). Allah's Apostle then said, "Admit ten men." Abu Talha
admitted them and they ate to their fill and went out. He again
said, "Admit ten men." He admitted them, and in this way all the
people ate to their fill, and they were seventy or eighty
men."</english-text>
</hadith>
