<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6578</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>83</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6792</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oaths and Vows - كتاب الأيمان والنذور</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20001, 11155, 11165, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا إسماعيل، قال حدثني مالك، عن ثور بن زيد الديلي،
عن أبي الغيث، مولى ابن مطيع عن أبي هريرة، قال خرجنا مع رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يوم خيبر فلم نغنم ذهبا ولا فضة إلا الأموال
والثياب والمتاع، فأهدى رجل من بني الضبيب يقال له رفاعة بن زيد لرسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم غلاما يقال له مدعم، فوجه رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم إلى وادي القرى حتى إذا كان بوادي القرى بينما مدعم يحط
رحلا لرسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا سهم عائر فقتله، فقال الناس
هنيئا له الجنة‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ كلا والذي
نفسي بيده إن الشملة التي أخذها يوم خيبر من المغانم، لم تصبها
المقاسم، لتشتعل عليه نارا ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما سمع ذلك الناس جاء رجل بشراك
أو شراكين إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ شراك من نار أو
شراكان من نار ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: We went out in the company of
Allah's Apostle on the day of (the battle of) Khaibar, and we did
not get any gold or silver as war booty, but we got property in the
form of things and clothes. Then a man called Rifa`a bin Zaid, from
the tribe of Bani Ad-Dubaib, presented a slave named Mid`am to
Allah's Apostle. Allah's Apostle headed towards the valley of
Al-Qura, and when he was in the valley of Al- Qura an arrow was
thrown by an unidentified person, struck and killed Mid`am who was
making a she-camel of Allah's Apostle kneel down. The people said,
"Congratulations to him (the slave) for gaining Paradise." Allah's
Apostle said, "No! By Him in Whose Hand my soul is, for the sheet
which he stole from the war booty before its distribution on the
day of Khaibar, is now burning over him." When the people heard
that, a man brought one or two Shiraks (leather straps of shoes) to
the Prophet. The Prophet said, "A Shirak of fire, or two Shiraks of
fire."</english-text>
</hadith>
