<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>84</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>84</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6806</hadith-number>
<chapter>Expiation for Unfulfilled Oaths - كتاب كفارات
الأيمان</chapter>
<chain-index>20387, 20208, 11015, 11719, 11589</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن حجر، حدثنا إسماعيل بن إبراهيم، عن أيوب،
عن القاسم التميمي، عن زهدم الجرمي، قال كنا عند أبي موسى وكان بيننا
وبين هذا الحى من جرم إخاء ومعروف قال فقدم طعام قال وقدم في طعامه
لحم دجاج قال وفي القوم رجل من بني تيم الله أحمر كأنه مولى قال فلم
يدن فقال له أبو موسى ادن، فإني قد رأيت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يأكل منه‏.‏ قال إني رأيته يأكل شيئا قذرته، فحلفت أن لا أطعمه
أبدا‏.‏ فقال ادن أخبرك عن ذلك، أتينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
في رهط من الأشعريين أستحمله، وهو يقسم نعما من نعم الصدقة قال أيوب
أحسبه قال وهو غضبان قال ‏"‏ والله لا أحملكم، وما عندي ما أحملكم
‏"‏‏.‏ قال فانطلقنا فأتي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بنهب إبل،
فقيل أين هؤلاء الأشعريون فأتينا فأمر لنا بخمس ذود غر الذرى، قال
فاندفعنا فقلت لأصحابي أتينا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نستحمله،
فحلف أن لا يحملنا، ثم أرسل إلينا فحملنا، نسي رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم يمينه، والله لئن تغفلنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
يمينه لا نفلح أبدا، ارجعوا بنا إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
فلنذكره يمينه‏.‏ فرجعنا فقلنا يا رسول الله أتيناك نستحملك، فحلفت أن
لا تحملنا ثم حملتنا فظننا أو فعرفنا أنك نسيت يمينك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
انطلقوا، فإنما حملكم الله، إني والله إن شاء الله لا أحلف على يمين،
فأرى غيرها خيرا منها، إلا أتيت الذي هو خير وتحللتها ‏"‏‏.‏ تابعه
حماد بن زيد عن أيوب عن أبي قلابة والقاسم بن عاصم
الكليبي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Zahdam al-Jarmi: We were sitting with Abu
Musa Al-Ash'sari, and as there were ties of friendship and mutual
favors between us and his tribe. His meal was presented before him
and there was chicken meat in it. Among those who were present
there was a man from Bani Taimillah having a red complexion as a
non-Arab freed slave, and that man did not approach the meal. Abu
Musa said to him, "Come along! I have seen Allah's Apostle eating
of that (i.e., chicken)." The man said, "I have seen it (chickens)
eating something I regarded as dirty, and so I have taken an oath
that I shall not eat (its meat) chicken." Abu Musa said, "Come
along! I will inform you about it (i.e., your oath). Once we went
to Allah's Apostle in company with a group of Ash'airiyin, asking
him for mounts while he was distributing some camels from the
camels of Zakat. (Aiyub said, "I think he said that the Prophet was
in an angry mood at the time.") The Prophet said, 'By Allah! I will
not give you mounts, and I have nothing to mount you on.' After we
had left, some camels of booty were brought to Allah's Apostle and
he said, "Where are those Ash`ariyin? Where are those Ash`ariyin?"
So we went (to him) and he gave us five very fat good-looking
camels. We mounted them and went away, and then I said to my
companions, 'We went to Allah's Apostle to give us mounts, but he
took an oath that he would not give us mounts, and then later on he
sent for us and gave us mounts, perhaps Allah's Apostle forgot his
oath. By Allah, we will never be successful, for we have taken
advantage of the fact that Allah's Apostle forgot to fulfill his
oath. So let us return to Allah's Apostle to remind him of his
oath.' We returned and said, 'O Allah's Apostle! We came to you and
asked you for mounts, but you took an oath that you would not give
us mounts) but later on you gave us mounts, and we thought or
considered that you have forgotten your oath.' The Prophet said,
'Depart, for Allah has given you Mounts. By Allah, Allah willing,
if I take an oath and then later find another thing better than
that, I do what is better, and make expiation for the oath.'
"</english-text>
</hadith>
