<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6599</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>85</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6814</hadith-number>
<chapter>Laws of Inheritance (Al-Faraa'id) - كتاب الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 5030, 11058</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب،
قال أخبرني مالك بن أوس بن الحدثان،، وكان، محمد بن جبير بن مطعم ذكر
لي من حديثه ذلك، فانطلقت حتى دخلت عليه فسألته فقال انطلقت حتى أدخل
على عمر فأتاه حاجبه يرفأ فقال هل لك في عثمان وعبد الرحمن والزبير
وسعد قال نعم‏.‏ فأذن لهم، ثم قال هل لك في علي وعباس قال نعم‏.‏ قال
عباس يا أمير المؤمنين اقض بيني وبين هذا‏.‏ قال أنشدكم بالله الذي
بإذنه تقوم السماء والأرض هل تعلمون أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ لا نورث ما تركنا صدقة ‏"‏‏.‏ يريد رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم نفسه‏.‏ فقال الرهط قد قال ذلك‏.‏ فأقبل على علي وعباس فقال هل
تعلمان أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ذلك قالا قد قال ذلك‏.‏
قال عمر فإني أحدثكم عن هذا الأمر، إن الله قد كان خص رسوله صلى الله
عليه وسلم في هذا الفىء بشىء لم يعطه أحدا غيره، فقال عز وجل ‏{‏ما
أفاء الله على رسوله‏}‏ إلى قوله ‏{‏قدير‏}‏ فكانت خالصة لرسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم والله ما احتازها دونكم، ولا استأثر بها عليكم،
لقد أعطاكموه وبثها فيكم، حتى بقي منها هذا المال، فكان النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم ينفق على أهله من هذا المال نفقة سنته، ثم يأخذ ما بقي
فيجعله مجعل مال الله، فعمل بذلك رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حياته،
أنشدكم بالله هل تعلمون ذلك قالوا نعم‏.‏ ثم قال لعلي وعباس أنشدكما
بالله هل تعلمان ذلك قالا نعم‏.‏ فتوفى الله نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم
فقال أبو بكر أنا ولي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقبضها فعمل بما
عمل به رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم توفى الله أبا بكر فقلت أنا
ولي ولي رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقبضتها سنتين أعمل فيها ما عمل
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم وأبو بكر، ثم جئتماني وكلمتكما واحدة،
وأمركما جميع، جئتني تسألني نصيبك من ابن أخيك، وأتاني هذا يسألني
نصيب امرأته من أبيها فقلت إن شئتما دفعتها إليكما بذلك، فتلتمسان مني
قضاء غير ذلك، فوالله الذي بإذنه تقوم السماء والأرض، لا أقضي فيها
قضاء غير ذلك حتى تقوم الساعة، فإن عجزتما فادفعاها إلى، فأنا
أكفيكماها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Malik bin Aus: 'I went and entered upon
`Umar, his doorman, Yarfa came saying `Uthman, `Abdur-Rahman, Az-
Zubair and Sa`d are asking your permission (to see you). May I
admit them? `Umar said, 'Yes.' So he admitted them Then he came
again and said, 'May I admit `Ali and `Abbas?' He said, 'Yes.'
`Abbas said, 'O, chief of the believers! Judge between me and this
man (Ali ). `Umar said, 'I beseech you by Allah by Whose permission
both the heaven and the earth exist, do you know that Allah's
Apostle said, 'Our (the Apostles') property will not be inherited,
and whatever we leave (after our death) is to be spent in charity?'
And by that Allah's Apostle meant himself.' The group said, '(No
doubt), he said so.' `Umar then faced `Ali and `Abbas and said, 'Do
you both know that Allah's Apostle said that?' They replied, '(No
doubt), he said so.' `Umar said, 'So let me talk to you about this
matter. Allah favored His Apostle with something of this Fai' (i.e.
booty won by the Muslims at war without fighting) which He did not
give to anybody else; Allah said:-- 'And what Allah gave to His
Apostle ( Fai' Booty) .........to do all things....(59.6) And so
that property was only for Allah's Apostle . Yet, by Allah, he
neither gathered that property for himself nor withheld it from
you, but he gave its income to you, and distributed it among you
till there remained the present property out of which the Prophet
used to spend the yearly maintenance for his family, and whatever
used to remain, he used to spend it where Allah's property is spent
(i.e. in charity etc.). Allah's Apostle followed that throughout
his life. Now I beseech you by Allah, do you know all that?' They
said, 'Yes.' `Umar then said to `Ali and `Abbas, 'I beseech you by
Allah, do you know that?' Both of them said, 'Yes.' `Umar added,
'And when the Prophet died, Abu Bakr said, ' I am the successor of
Allah's Apostle, and took charge of that property and managed it in
the same way as Allah's Apostle did. Then I took charge of this
property for two years during which I managed it as Allah's Apostle
and Abu Bakr did. Then you both (`Ali and `Abbas) came to talk to
me, bearing the same claim and presenting the same case. (O
`Abbas!) You came to me asking for your share from the property of
your nephew, and this man (Ali) came to me, asking for the share of
h is wife from the property of her father. I said, 'If you both
wish, I will give that to you on that condition (i.e. that you
would follow the way of the Prophet and Abu Bakr and as I (`Umar)
have done in man aging it).' Now both of you seek of me a verdict
other than that? Lo! By Allah, by Whose permission both the heaven
and the earth exist, I will not give any verdict other than that
till the Hour is established. If you are unable to manage it, then
return it to me, and I will be sufficient to manage it on your
behalf.' "</english-text>
</hadith>
