<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6626</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>85</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6841</hadith-number>
<chapter>Laws of Inheritance (Al-Faraa'id) - كتاب الفرائض</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20028, 11060, 11322, 11405, 5</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا جرير، عن الأعمش، عن إبراهيم
التيمي، عن أبيه، قال قال علي رضى الله عنه ما عندنا كتاب نقرؤه إلا
كتاب الله، غير هذه الصحيفة‏.‏ قال فأخرجها فإذا فيها أشياء من
الجراحات وأسنان الإبل‏.‏ قال وفيها المدينة حرم ما بين عير إلى ثور،
فمن أحدث فيها حدثا، أو آوى محدثا، فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس
أجمعين، لا يقبل منه يوم القيامة صرف ولا عدل، ومن والى قوما بغير إذن
مواليه، فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين، لا يقبل منه يوم
القيامة صرف ولا عدل، وذمة المسلمين واحدة، يسعى بها أدناهم فمن أخفر
مسلما فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين، لا يقبل منه يوم
القيامة صرف ولا عدل‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Ali: We have no Book to recite except the
Book of Allah (Qur'an) and this paper. Then `Ali took out the
paper, and behold ! There was written in it, legal verdicts about
the retaliation for wounds, the ages of the camels (to be paid as
Zakat or as blood money). In it was also written: 'Medina is a
sanctuary from Air (mountain) to Thaur (mountain). So whoever
innovates in it an heresy (something new in religion) or commits a
crime in it or gives shelter to such an innovator, will incur the
curse of Allah, the angels and all the people, and none of his
compulsory or optional good deeds will be accepted on the Day of
Resurrection. And whoever (a freed slave) takes as his master (i.e.
be-friends) some people other than hi real masters without the
permission of his real masters, will incur the curse of Allah, the
angels and all the people, and none of his compulsory, or optional
good deeds will be accepted on the Day of Resurrection. And the
asylum granted by any Muslim is to be secured by all the Muslims,
even if it is granted by one of the lowest social status among
them; and whoever betrays a Muslim, in this respect will incur the
curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people, and none of his
Compulsory or optional good deeds will be accepted on the Day of
Resurrection."</english-text>
</hadith>
