<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>87</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>87</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6916</hadith-number>
<chapter>Punishment of Disbelievers at War with Allah and His
Apostle - كتاب المحاربين من أهل الكفر والردة</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11201</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، قال حفظناه من في
الزهري قال أخبرني عبيد الله أنه سمع أبا هريرة وزيد بن خالد قالا كنا
عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقام رجل فقال أنشدك الله إلا قضيت
بيننا بكتاب الله‏.‏ فقام خصمه وكان أفقه منه فقال اقض بيننا بكتاب
الله وأذن لي‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ قل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا،
فزنى بامرأته، فافتديت منه بمائة شاة وخادم، ثم سألت رجالا من أهل
العلم، فأخبروني أن على ابني جلد مائة وتغريب عام، وعلى امرأته
الرجم‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي نفسي بيده لأقضين
بينكما بكتاب الله جل ذكره، المائة شاة والخادم رد، وعلى ابنك جلد
مائة وتغريب عام، واغد يا أنيس على امرأة هذا، فإن اعترفت فارجمها
‏"‏‏.‏ فغدا عليها فاعترفت فرجمها‏.‏ قلت لسفيان لم يقل فأخبروني أن
على ابني الرجم‏.‏ فقال أشك فيها من الزهري، فربما قلتها وربما
سكت‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira and Zaid bin Khalid: While we
were with the Prophet , a man stood up and said (to the Prophet ),
"I beseech you by Allah, that you should judge us according to
Allah's Laws." Then the man's opponent who was wiser than him, got
up saying (to Allah's Apostle) "Judge us according to Allah's Law
and kindly allow me (to speak)." The Prophet said, "'Speak." He
said, "My son was a laborer working for this man and he committed
an illegal sexual intercourse with his wife, and I gave one-hundred
sheep and a slave as a ransom for my son's sin. Then I asked a
learned man about this case and he informed me that my son should
receive one hundred lashes and be exiled for one year, and the
man's wife should be stoned to death." The Prophet said, "By Him in
Whose Hand my soul is, I will judge you according to the Laws of
Allah. Your one-hundred sheep and the slave are to be returned to
you, and your son has to receive one-hundred lashes and be exiled
for one year. O Unais! Go to the wife of this man, and if she
confesses, then stone her to death." Unais went to her and she
confessed. He then stoned her to death.</english-text>
</hadith>
