<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>87</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>87</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6928</hadith-number>
<chapter>Punishment of Disbelievers at War with Allah and His
Apostle - كتاب المحاربين من أهل الكفر والردة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 11013, 11004, 13, 3625</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن ابن شهاب، عن
عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن مسعود، عن أبي هريرة، وزيد بن خالد،
أنهما أخبراه أن رجلين اختصما إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال
أحدهما اقض بيننا بكتاب الله‏.‏ وقال الآخر وهو أفقههما أجل يا رسول
الله فاقض بيننا بكتاب الله، وأذن لي أن أتكلم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ تكلم ‏"‏‏.‏
قال إن ابني كان عسيفا على هذا قال مالك والعسيف الأجير فزنى بامرأته،
فأخبروني أن على ابني الرجم، فافتديت منه بمائة شاة وبجارية لي، ثم
إني سألت أهل العلم فأخبروني أن ما على ابني جلد مائة وتغريب عام،
وإنما الرجم على امرأته‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما
والذي نفسي بيده لأقضين بينكما بكتاب الله، أما غنمك وجاريتك فرد عليك
‏"‏‏.‏ وجلد ابنه مائة وغربه عاما، وأمر أنيسا الأسلمي أن يأتي امرأة
الآخر، فإن اعترفت فارجمها، فاعترفت فرجمها‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira and Zaid bin Khalid: Two men had
a dispute in the presence of Allah's Apostle. One of them said,
"Judge us according to Allah's Laws." The other who was more wise
said, "Yes, Allah's Apostle, judge us according to Allah's Laws and
allow me to speak (first)" The Prophet said to him, 'Speak " He
said, "My son was a laborer for this man, and he committed illegal
sexual intercourse with his wife, and the people told me that my
son should be stoned to death, but I have given one-hundred sheep
and a slave girl as a ransom (expiation) for my son's sin. Then I
asked the religious learned people (about It), and they told me
that my son should he flogged one-hundred stripes and should be
exiled for one year, and only the wife of this man should be stoned
to death " Allah's Apostle said, "By Him in Whose Hand my soul is,
I will judge you according to Allah's Laws: O man, as for your
sheep and slave girl, they are to be returned to you." Then the
Prophet had the man's son flogged one hundred stripes and exiled
for one year, and ordered Unais Al-Aslami to go to the wife of the
other man, and if she confessed, stone her to death. She confessed
and was stoned to death.</english-text>
</hadith>
