<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>87</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>87</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6941</hadith-number>
<chapter>Punishment of Disbelievers at War with Allah and His
Apostle - كتاب المحاربين من أهل الكفر والردة</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20023, 11062, 10530, 10535, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، حدثنا الليث، حدثنا يحيى بن
سعيد، عن عبد الرحمن بن القاسم، عن القاسم بن محمد، عن ابن عباس رضى
الله عنهما ذكر التلاعن عند النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال عاصم بن
عدي في ذلك قولا، ثم انصرف وأتاه رجل من قومه يشكو أنه وجد مع أهله
فقال عاصم ما ابتليت بهذا إلا لقولي فذهب به إلى النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم فأخبره بالذي وجد عليه امرأته، وكان ذلك الرجل مصفرا، قليل
اللحم، سبط الشعر، وكان الذي ادعى عليه أنه وجده عند أهله آدم، خدلا،
كثير اللحم، فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ اللهم بين ‏"‏‏.‏
فوضعت شبيها بالرجل الذي ذكر زوجها أنه وجده عندها فلاعن النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم بينهما فقال رجل لابن عباس في المجلس هي التي قال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لو رجمت أحدا بغير بينة رجمت هذه ‏"‏‏.‏
فقال لا، تلك امرأة كانت تظهر في الإسلام السوء‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: Lian was mentioned in the
presence of the Prophet, `Asim bin Adi said a statement about it,
and when he left, a man from his tribe came to him complaining that
he had seen a man with his wife. `Asim said, "I have been put to
trial only because of my statement." So he took the man to the
Prophet and the man told him about the incident. The man (husband)
was of yellow complexion, thin, and of lank hair, while the man
whom he had accused of having been with his wife, was reddish brown
with fat thick legs and fat body. The Prophet said, "O Allah!
Reveal the truth." Later on the lady delivered a child resembling
the man whom the husband had accused of having been with her. So
the Prophet made them take the oath of Lian. A man said to Ibn
`Abbas in the gathering, "Was that the same lady about whom the
Prophet said, "If I were to stone any lady (for committing illegal
sexual intercourse) to death without witnesses, I would have stoned
that lade to death?" Ibn `Abbas said, "No, that was another lady
who used to behave in such a suspicious way among the Muslims that
one might accuse her of committing illegal sexual
intercourse."</english-text>
</hadith>
