<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6729</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>88</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>6949</hadith-number>
<chapter>Blood Money (Ad-Diyat) - كتاب الديات</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 20025, 20475, 11013, 11206</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، حدثنا عبد الله، حدثنا يونس، عن الزهري،
حدثنا عطاء بن يزيد، أن عبيد الله بن عدي، حدثه أن المقداد بن عمرو
الكندي حليف بني زهرة حدثه وكان، شهد بدرا مع النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم أنه قال يا رسول الله إن لقيت كافرا فاقتتلنا، فضرب يدي بالسيف
فقطعها، ثم لاذ بشجرة وقال أسلمت لله‏.‏ آقتله بعد أن قالها قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ لا تقتله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال يا رسول الله فإنه
طرح إحدى يدى، ثم قال بعد ما قطعها، آقتله قال ‏"‏ لا تقتله، فإن
قتلته فإنه بمنزلتك قبل أن تقتله، وأنت بمنزلته قبل أن يقول كلمته
التي قال ‏"‏‏.‏ وقال حبيب بن أبي عمرة عن سعيد، عن ابن عباس، قال قال
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم للمقداد ‏"‏ إذا كان رجل مؤمن يخفي إيمانه
مع قوم كفار، فأظهر إيمانه، فقتلته، فكذلك كنت أنت تخفي إيمانك بمكة
من قبل ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Al-Miqdad bin `Amr Al-Kindi: An ally of Bani
Zuhra who took part in the battle of Badr with the Prophet, that he
said, "O Allah's Apostle! If I meet an unbeliever and we have a
fight, and he strikes my hand with the sword and cuts it off, and
then takes refuge from me under a tree, and says, 'I have
surrendered to Allah (i.e. embraced Islam),' may I kill him after
he has said so?" Allah's Apostle said, "Do not kill him." Al-
Miqdad said, "But O Allah's Apostle! He had chopped off one of my
hands and he said that after he had cut it off. May I kill him?"
The Prophet said. "Do not kill him for if you kill him, he would be
in the position in which you had been before you kill him, and you
would be in the position in which he was before he said the
sentence." The Prophet also said to Al-Miqdad, "If a faithful
believer conceals his faith (Islam) from the disbelievers, and then
when he declares his Islam, you kill him, (you will be sinful).
Remember that you were also concealing your faith (Islam) at Mecca
before."</english-text>
</hadith>
