<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>670</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>687</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30184, 20320, 11399, 11004</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أحمد بن يونس، قال حدثنا زائدة، عن موسى بن أبي
عائشة، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، قال دخلت على عائشة فقلت
ألا تحدثيني عن مرض رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قالت بلى، ثقل النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا لا، هم
ينتظرونك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي ماء في المخضب ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت ففعلنا فاغتسل
فذهب لينوء فأغمي عليه، ثم أفاق فقال صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أصلى
الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا لا، هم ينتظرونك يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي
ماء في المخضب ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت فقعد فاغتسل، ثم ذهب لينوء فأغمي عليه، ثم
أفاق فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا لا، هم ينتظرونك يا رسول
الله‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ ضعوا لي ماء في المخضب ‏"‏، فقعد فاغتسل، ثم ذهب
لينوء فأغمي عليه، ثم أفاق فقال ‏"‏ أصلى الناس ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلنا لا، هم
ينتظرونك يا رسول الله والناس عكوف في المسجد ينتظرون النبي عليه
السلام لصلاة العشاء الآخرة فأرسل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى أبي
بكر بأن يصلي بالناس، فأتاه الرسول فقال إن رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم يأمرك أن تصلي بالناس‏.‏ فقال أبو بكر وكان رجلا رقيقا يا عمر صل
بالناس‏.‏ فقال له عمر أنت أحق بذلك‏.‏ فصلى أبو بكر تلك الأيام، ثم
إن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وجد من نفسه خفة فخرج بين رجلين أحدهما
العباس لصلاة الظهر، وأبو بكر يصلي بالناس، فلما رآه أبو بكر ذهب
ليتأخر فأومأ إليه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بأن لا يتأخر‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
أجلساني إلى جنبه ‏"‏‏.‏ فأجلساه إلى جنب أبي بكر‏.‏ قال فجعل أبو بكر
يصلي وهو يأتم بصلاة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم والناس بصلاة أبي بكر،
والنبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قاعد‏.‏ قال عبيد الله فدخلت على عبد الله
بن عباس فقلت له ألا أعرض عليك ما حدثتني عائشة عن مرض النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم قال هات‏.‏ فعرضت عليه حديثها، فما أنكر منه شيئا، غير أنه
قال أسمت لك الرجل الذي كان مع العباس قلت لا‏.‏ قال هو
علي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ubaidullah Ibn `Abdullah bin `Utba: I went
to `Aisha and asked her to describe to me the illness of Allah's
Apostle. `Aisha said, "Yes. The Prophet became seriously ill and
asked whether the people had prayed. We replied, 'No. O Allah's
Apostle! They are waiting for you.' He added, 'Put water for me in
a trough." `Aisha added, "We did so. He took a bath and tried to
get up but fainted. When he recovered, he again asked whether the
people had prayed. We said, 'No, they are waiting for you. O
Allah's Apostle,' He again said, 'Put water in a trough for me.' He
sat down and took a bath and tried to get up but fainted again.
Then he recovered and said, 'Have the people prayed?' We replied,
'No, they are waiting for you. O Allah's Apostle.' He said, 'Put
water for me in the trough.' Then he sat down and washed himself
and tried to get up but he fainted. When he recovered, he asked,
'Have the people prayed?' We said, 'No, they are waiting for you. O
Allah's Apostle! The people were in the mosque waiting for the
Prophet for the `Isha prayer. The Prophet sent for Abu Bakr to lead
the people in the prayer. The messenger went to Abu Bakr and said,
'Allah's Apostle orders you to lead the people in the prayer.' Abu
Bakr was a softhearted man, so he asked `Umar to lead the prayer
but `Umar replied, 'You are more rightful.' So Abu Bakr led the
prayer in those days. When the Prophet felt a bit better, he came
out for the Zuhr prayer with the help of two persons one of whom
was Al-`Abbas. while Abu Bakr was leading the people in the prayer.
When Abu Bakr saw him he wanted to retreat but the Prophet beckoned
him not to do so and asked them to make him sit beside Abu Bakr and
they did so. Abu Bakr was following the Prophet (in the prayer) and
the people were following Abu Bakr. The Prophet (prayed) sitting."
'Ubaidullah added "I went to `Abdullah bin `Abbas and asked him,
Shall I tell you what Aisha has told me about the fatal illness of
the Prophet?' Ibn `Abbas said, 'Go ahead. I told him her narration
and he did not deny anything of it but asked whether `Aisha told me
the name of the second person (who helped the Prophet ) along with
Al-Abbas. I said. 'No.' He said, 'He was `Ali (Ibn Abi
Talib).</english-text>
</hadith>
