<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>89</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>89</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7010</hadith-number>
<chapter>Dealing with Apostates - كتاب استتابة المرتدين والمعاندين
وقتالهم</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 11207, 11013, 11004, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، حدثنا الليث، عن عقيل، عن ابن شهاب،
أخبرني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، أن أبا هريرة، قال لما توفي
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم واستخلف أبو بكر، وكفر من كفر من العرب، قال
عمر يا أبا بكر، كيف تقاتل الناس، وقد قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ أمرت أن أقاتل الناس حتى يقولوا لا إله إلا الله‏.‏ فمن قال
لا إله إلا الله‏.‏ عصم مني ماله ونفسه، إلا بحقه، وحسابه على الله
‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو بكر والله لأقاتلن من فرق بين الصلاة والزكاة، فإن
الزكاة حق المال، والله لو منعوني عناقا كانوا يؤدونها إلى رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم لقاتلتهم على منعها‏.‏ قال عمر فوالله ما هو إلا
أن رأيت أن قد شرح الله صدر أبي بكر للقتال فعرفت أنه
الحق‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: When the Prophet died and Abu
Bakr became his successor and some of the Arabs reverted to
disbelief, `Umar said, "O Abu Bakr! How can you fight these people
although Allah's Apostle said, 'I have been ordered to fight the
people till they say: 'None has the right to be worshipped but
Allah, 'and whoever said, 'None has the right to be worshipped but
Allah', Allah will save his property and his life from me, unless
(he does something for which he receives legal punishment) justly,
and his account will be with Allah?' "Abu Bakr said, "By Allah! I
will fight whoever differentiates between prayers and Zakat as
Zakat is the right to be taken from property (according to Allah's
Orders). By Allah! If they refused to pay me even a kid they used
to pay to Allah's Apostle, I would fight with them for withholding
it." `Umar said, "By Allah: It was nothing, but I noticed that
Allah opened Abu Bakr's chest towards the decision to fight,
therefore I realized that his decision was right."</english-text>
</hadith>
