<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6832</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>91</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7058</hadith-number>
<chapter>Tricks - كتاب الحيل</chapter>
<chain-index>30360, 20318, 11065, 10511, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبيد بن إسماعيل، حدثنا أبو أسامة، عن هشام، عن
أبيه، عن عائشة، قالت كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يحب الحلواء،
ويحب العسل، وكان إذا صلى العصر أجاز على نسائه فيدنو منهن، فدخل على
حفصة، فاحتبس عندها أكثر مما كان يحتبس، فسألت عن ذلك فقيل لي أهدت
امرأة من قومها عكة عسل، فسقت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم منه
شربة‏.‏ فقلت أما والله لنحتالن له‏.‏ فذكرت ذلك لسودة قلت إذا دخل
عليك فإنه سيدنو منك فقولي له يا رسول الله أكلت مغافير فإنه سيقول
لا‏.‏ فقولي له ما هذه الريح وكان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يشتد
عليه أن توجد منه الريح، فإنه سيقول سقتني حفصة شربة عسل‏.‏ فقولي له
جرست نحله العرفط‏.‏ وسأقول ذلك، وقوليه أنت يا صفية‏.‏ فلما دخل على
سودة، قلت تقول سودة والذي لا إله إلا هو لقد كدت أن أبادره بالذي قلت
لي، وإنه لعلى الباب فرقا منك، فلما دنا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قلت يا رسول الله أكلت مغافير قال ‏"‏ لا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت فما هذه الريح
قال ‏"‏ سقتني حفصة شربة عسل ‏"‏‏.‏ قلت جرست نحله العرفط‏.‏ فلما دخل
على قلت له مثل ذلك‏.‏ ودخل على صفية فقالت له مثل ذلك‏.‏ فلما دخل
على حفصة قالت له يا رسول الله ألا أسقيك منه قال ‏"‏ لا حاجة لي به
‏"‏‏.‏ قالت تقول سودة سبحان الله لقد حرمناه‏.‏ قالت قلت لها
اسكتي‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: Allah's Apostle used to like sweets
and also used to like honey, and whenever he finished the `Asr
prayer, he used to visit his wives and stay with them. Once he
visited Hafsa and remained with her longer than the period he used
to stay, so I enquired about it. It was said to me, "A woman from
her tribe gave her a leather skin containing honey as a present,
and she gave some of it to Allah's Apostle to drink." I said, "By
Allah, we will play a trick on him." So I mentioned the story to
Sauda (the wife of the Prophet) and said to her, "When he enters
upon you, he will come near to you whereupon you should say to him,
'O Allah's Apostle! Have you eaten Maghafir?' He will say, 'No.'
Then you say to him, 'What is this bad smell? ' And it would be
very hard on Allah's Apostle that a bad smell should be found on
his body. He will say, 'Hafsa has given me a drink of honey.' Then
you should say to him, 'Its bees must have sucked from the
Al-`Urfut (a foul smelling flower).' I too, will tell him the same.
And you, O Saifya, say the same." So when the Prophet entered upon
Sauda (the following happened). Sauda said, "By Him except Whom
none has the right to be worshipped, I was about to say to him what
you had told me to say while he was still at the gate because of
fear from you. But when Allah 's Apostle came near to me, I said to
him, 'O Allah's Apostle! Have you eaten Maghafir?' He replied,
'No.' I said, 'What about this smell?' He said, 'Hafsa has given me
a drink of honey.' I said, 'Its bees must have sucked Al-`Urfut.' "
When he entered upon me, I told him the same as that, and when he
entered upon Safiya, she too told him the same. So when he visited
Hafsa again, she said to him, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall I give you
a drink of it (honey)?" He said, "I have no desire for it." Sauda
said, Subhan Allah! We have deprived him of it (honey)." I said to
her, "Be quiet!"</english-text>
</hadith>
