<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6863</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>92</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7089</hadith-number>
<chapter>Interpretation of Dreams - كتاب التعبير</chapter>
<chain-index>30233, 20023, 11207, 11013, 11006</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن عفير، حدثني الليث، حدثني عقيل، عن ابن
شهاب، أخبرني خارجة بن زيد بن ثابت، أن أم العلاء امرأة من الأنصار
بايعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أخبرته أنهم اقتسموا المهاجرين
قرعة‏.‏ قالت فطار لنا عثمان بن مظعون، وأنزلناه في أبياتنا، فوجع
وجعه الذي توفي فيه، فلما توفي غسل وكفن في أثوابه دخل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم فقلت رحمة الله عليك أبا السائب، فشهادتي عليك لقد
أكرمك الله‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ وما يدريك أن
الله أكرمه ‏"‏‏.‏ فقلت بأبي أنت يا رسول الله فمن يكرمه الله فقال
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ أما هو فوالله لقد جاءه اليقين،
والله إني لأرجو له الخير، ووالله ما أدري وأنا رسول الله ماذا يفعل
بي ‏"‏‏.‏ فقالت والله لا أزكي بعده أحدا أبدا‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Kharija bin Zaid bin Thabit: Um Al-`Ala an
Ansari woman who had given a pledge of allegiance to Allah's
Apostle told me:, "The Muhajirln (emigrants) were distributed
amongst us by drawing lots, and we got `Uthman bin Maz'un in our
share. We made him stay with us in our house. Then he suffered from
a disease which proved fatal. When he died and was given a bath and
was shrouded in his clothes. Allah's Apostle came, I said,
(addressing the dead body), 'O Aba As-Sa'ib! May Allah be Merciful
to you! I testify that Allah has honored you.' Allah's Apostle
said, 'How do you know that Allah has honored him?" I replied, 'Let
my father be sacrificed for you, O Allah's Apostle! On whom else
shall Allah bestow. His honor?' Allah's Apostle said, 'As for him,
by Allah, death has come to him. By Allah, I wish him all good
(from Allah). By Allah, in spite of the fact that I am Allah's
Apostle, I do not know what Allah will do to me.", Um Al-`Ala
added, "By Allah, I will never attest the righteousness of anybody
after that."</english-text>
</hadith>
