<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6888</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>92</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7114</hadith-number>
<chapter>Interpretation of Dreams - كتاب التعبير</chapter>
<chain-index>30359, 30106, 20429, 11014, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني عبيد الله بن سعيد، حدثنا عفان بن مسلم، حدثنا صخر
بن جويرية، حدثنا نافع، أن ابن عمر، قال إن رجالا من أصحاب رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم كانوا يرون الرؤيا على عهد رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فيقصونها على رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فيقول فيها رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ما شاء الله، وأنا غلام حديث السن وبيتي
المسجد قبل أن أنكح، فقلت في نفسي لو كان فيك خير لرأيت مثل ما يرى
هؤلاء‏.‏ فلما اضطجعت ليلة قلت اللهم إن كنت تعلم في خيرا فأرني
رؤيا‏.‏ فبينما أنا كذلك إذ جاءني ملكان في يد كل واحد منهما مقمعة من
حديد، يقبلا بي إلى جهنم، وأنا بينهما أدعو الله اللهم أعوذ بك من
جهنم‏.‏ ثم أراني لقيني ملك في يده مقمعة من حديد فقال لن تراع، نعم
الرجل أنت لو تكثر الصلاة‏.‏ فانطلقوا بي حتى وقفوا بي على شفير جهنم
فإذا هي مطوية كطى البئر، له قرون كقرن البئر، بين كل قرنين ملك بيده
مقمعة من حديد، وأرى فيها رجالا معلقين بالسلاسل، رءوسهم أسفلهم، عرفت
فيها رجالا من قريش، فانصرفوا بي عن ذات اليمين‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: Men from the companions of
Allah's Apostle used to see dreams during the lifetime of Allah's
Apostle and they used to narrate those dreams to Allah's Apostle.
Allah's Apostle would interpret them as Allah wished. I was a young
man and used to stay in the mosque before my wedlock. I said to
myself, "If there were any good in myself, I too would see what
these people see." So when I went to bed one night, I said, "O
Allah! If you see any good in me, show me a good dream." So while I
was in that state, there came to me (in a dream) two angels. In the
hand of each of them, there was a mace of iron, and both of them
were taking me to Hell, and I was between them, invoking Allah, "O
Allah! I seek refuge with You from Hell." Then I saw myself being
confronted by another angel holding a mace of iron in his hand. He
said to me, "Do not be afraid, you will be an excellent man if you
only pray more often." So they took me till they stopped me at the
edge of Hell, and behold, it was built inside like a well and it
had side posts like those of a well, and beside each post there was
an angel carrying an iron mace. I saw therein many people hanging
upside down with iron chains, and I recognized therein some men
from the Quraish. Then (the angels) took me to the right side. I
narrated this dream to (my sister) Hafsa and she told it to Allah's
Apostle. Allah's Apostle said, "No doubt, `Abdullah is a good man."
(Nafi` said, "Since then `Abdullah bin `Umar used to pray
much.)</english-text>
</hadith>
