<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6941</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>93</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7165</hadith-number>
<chapter>Afflictions and the End of the World - كتاب
الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20031, 11301, 11035, 11294, 3229,
3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، حدثنا يحيى، حدثنا قرة بن خالد، حدثنا ابن
سيرين، عن عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكرة، عن أبي بكرة، وعن رجل، آخر هو أفضل
في نفسي من عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكرة عن أبي بكرة أن رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم خطب الناس فقال ‏"‏ ألا تدرون أى يوم هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا الله
ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ قال حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ أليس
بيوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أى بلد، هذا
أليست بالبلدة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم،
وأموالكم، وأعراضكم، وأبشاركم عليكم حرام، كحرمة يومكم هذا، في شهركم
هذا، في بلدكم هذا، ألا هل بلغت ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا نعم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ اللهم
اشهد، فليبلغ الشاهد الغائب، فإنه رب مبلغ يبلغه من هو أوعى له فكان
كذلك قال لا ترجعوا بعدي كفارا يضرب بعضكم رقاب بعض ‏"‏‏.‏ فلما كان
يوم حرق ابن الحضرمي، حين حرقه جارية بن قدامة‏.‏ قال أشرفوا على أبي
بكرة‏.‏ فقالوا هذا أبو بكرة يراك‏.‏ قال عبد الرحمن فحدثتني أمي عن
أبي بكرة أنه قال لو دخلوا على ما بهشت بقصبة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Bakra: Allah's Apostle addressed the
people saying, "Don't you know what is the day today?" They
replied, "Allah and His Apostle know better." We thought that he
might give that day another name. The Prophet said, "Isn't it the
day of An-Nahr?" We replied, "Yes. O Allah's Apostle." He then
said, "What town is this? Isn't it the forbidden (Sacred) Town
(Mecca)?" We replied, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle." He then said, "Your
blood, your properties, your honors and your skins (i.e., bodies)
are as sacred to one another like the sanctity of this day of yours
in this month of yours in this town of yours. (Listen) Haven't I
conveyed Allah's message to you?" We replied, "Yes" He said, "O
Allah! Be witness (for it). So it is incumbent upon those who are
present to convey it (this message of mine) to those who are absent
because the informed one might comprehend what I have said better
than the present audience who will convey it to him.)" The narrator
added: In fact, it was like that. The Prophet added, "Beware! Do
not renegade as disbelievers after me by striking (cutting) the
necks of one another."</english-text>
</hadith>
