<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>6962</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>93</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7186</hadith-number>
<chapter>Afflictions and the End of the World - كتاب
الفتن</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20173, 20587, 11002, 41</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، أخبرنا محمد بن جعفر، عن شريك
بن عبد الله، عن سعيد بن المسيب، عن أبي موسى الأشعري، قال خرج النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم إلى حائط من حوائط المدينة لحاجته، وخرجت في إثره،
فلما دخل الحائط جلست على بابه وقلت لأكونن اليوم بواب النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ولم يأمرني فذهب النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم وقضى حاجته، وجلس
على قف البئر، فكشف عن ساقيه ودلاهما في البئر، فجاء أبو بكر يستأذن
عليه ليدخل فقلت كما أنت حتى أستأذن لك، فوقف فجئت إلى النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فقلت يا نبي الله أبو بكر يستأذن عليك‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ ائذن له،
وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فدخل فجاء عن يمين النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فكشف
عن ساقيه ودلاهما في البئر، فجاء عمر فقلت كما أنت حتى أستأذن لك‏.‏
فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ائذن له، وبشره بالجنة ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاء
عن يسار النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فكشف عن ساقيه فدلاهما في البئر،
فامتلأ القف فلم يكن فيه مجلس، ثم جاء عثمان فقلت كما أنت حتى أستأذن
لك‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ ائذن له، وبشره بالجنة، معها
بلاء يصيبه ‏"‏‏.‏ فدخل فلم يجد معهم مجلسا، فتحول حتى جاء مقابلهم
على شفة البئر، فكشف عن ساقيه ثم دلاهما في البئر‏.‏ فجعلت أتمنى أخا
لي وأدعو الله أن يأتي‏.‏ قال ابن المسيب فتأولت ذلك قبورهم اجتمعت ها
هنا وانفرد عثمان‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Musa Al-Ash`ari: The Prophet went out to
one of the gardens of Medina for some business and I went out to
follow him. When he entered the garden, I sat at its gate and said
to myself, "To day I will be the gatekeeper of the Prophet though
he has not ordered me." The Prophet went and finished his need and
went to sit on the constructed edge of the well and uncovered his
legs and hung them in the well. In the meantime Abu Bakr came and
asked permission to enter. I said (to him), "Wait till I get you
permission." Abu Bakr waited outside and I went to the Prophet and
said, "O Allah's Prophet! Abu Bakr asks your permission to enter."
He said, "Admit him, and give him the glad tidings of entering
Paradise." So Abu Bakr entered and sat on the right side of the
Prophet and uncovered his legs and hung them in the well. Then
`Umar came and I said (to him), "Wait till I get you permission."
The Prophet said, "Admit him and give him the glad tidings of
entering Paradise." So `Umar entered and sat on the left side of
the Prophet and uncovered his legs and hung them in the well so
that one side of the well became fully occupied and there remained
no place for any-one to sit. Then `Uthman came and I said (to him),
"Wait till I get permission for you." The Prophet said, "Admit him
and give him the glad tidings of entering Paradise with a calamity
which will befall him." When he entered, he could not find any
place to sit with them so he went to the other edge of the well
opposite them and uncovered his legs and hung them in the well. I
wished that a brother of mine would come, so I invoked Allah for
his coming. (Ibn Al-Musaiyab said, "I interpreted that (narration)
as indicating their graves. The first three are together and the
grave of `Uthman is separate from theirs.")</english-text>
</hadith>
