<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7038</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>94</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7262</hadith-number>
<chapter>Judgments (Ahkaam) - كتاب الأحكام</chapter>
<chain-index>30026, 20005, 11013, 10511, 1457</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن عبد الله، حدثنا سفيان، عن الزهري، أنه سمع
عروة، أخبرنا أبو حميد الساعدي، قال استعمل النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
رجلا من بني أسد يقال له ابن الأتبية على صدقة فلما قدم قال هذا لكم
وهذا أهدي لي‏.‏ فقام النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم على المنبر قال سفيان
أيضا فصعد المنبر فحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ ما بال العامل
نبعثه، فيأتي يقول هذا لك وهذا لي‏.‏ فهلا جلس في بيت أبيه وأمه فينظر
أيهدى له أم لا، والذي نفسي بيده لا يأتي بشىء إلا جاء به يوم القيامة
يحمله على رقبته، إن كان بعيرا له رغاء، أو بقرة لها خوار، أو شاة
تيعر ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم رفع يديه حتى رأينا عفرتى إبطيه ‏"‏ ألا هل بلغت ‏"‏
ثلاثا‏.‏ قال سفيان قصه علينا الزهري‏.‏ وزاد هشام عن أبيه عن أبي
حميد قال سمع أذناى وأبصرته عيني، وسلوا زيد بن ثابت فإنه سمعه معي‏.‏
ولم يقل الزهري سمع أذني‏.‏ ‏{‏خوار‏}‏ صوت، والجؤار من تجأرون كصوت
البقرة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Humaid Al-Sa`idi: The Prophet appointed
a man from the tribe of Bani Asad, called Ibn Al-Utabiyya to
collect the Zakat. When he returned (with the money) he said (to
the Prophet), "This is for you and this has been given to me as a
gift." The Prophet stood up on the pulpit (Sufyan said he ascended
the pulpit), and after glorifying and praising Allah, he said,
"What is wrong with the employee whom we send (to collect Zakat
from the public) that he returns to say, 'This is for you and that
is for me?' Why didn't he stay at his father's and mother's house
to see whether he will be given gifts or not? By Him in Whose Hand
my life is, whoever takes anything illegally will bring it on the
Day of Resurrection by carrying it over his neck: if it is a camel,
it will be grunting: if it is a cow, it will be mooing: and if it
is a sheep it will be bleating!" The Prophet then raised both his
hands till we saw the whiteness of his armpits (and he said), "No
doubt! Haven't I conveyed Allah's Message?" And he repeated it
three times.</english-text>
</hadith>
