<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7053</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>94</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7277</hadith-number>
<chapter>Judgments (Ahkaam) - كتاب الأحكام</chapter>
<chain-index>20283, 20022, 11172, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو النعمان، حدثنا حماد، حدثنا أبو حازم المديني،
عن سهل بن سعد الساعدي، قال كان قتال بين بني عمرو، فبلغ ذلك النبي
صلى الله عليه وسلم فصلى الظهر، ثم أتاهم يصلح بينهم، فلما حضرت صلاة
العصر فأذن بلال وأقام وأمر أبا بكر فتقدم، وجاء النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم وأبو بكر في الصلاة، فشق الناس حتى قام خلف أبي بكر، فتقدم في
الصف الذي يليه‏.‏ قال وصفح القوم، وكان أبو بكر إذا دخل في الصلاة لم
يلتفت حتى يفرغ، فلما رأى التصفيح لا يمسك عليه التفت فرأى النبي صلى
الله عليه وسلم خلفه، فأومأ إليه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم أن امضه
وأومأ بيده هكذا، ولبث أبو بكر هنية يحمد الله على قول النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم ثم مشى القهقرى، فلما رأى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ذلك
تقدم فصلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بالناس، فلما قضى صلاته قال ‏"‏
يا أبا بكر ما منعك إذ أومأت إليك أن لا تكون مضيت ‏"‏‏.‏ قال لم يكن
لابن أبي قحافة أن يؤم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم‏.‏ وقال للقوم ‏"‏
إذا نابكم أمر، فليسبح الرجال، وليصفح النساء ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d As-Saidi: There was some
quarrel (sighting) among Bani `Amr, and when this news reached the
Prophet, he offered the Zuhr prayer and went to establish peace
among them. In the meantime the time of `Asr prayer was due, Bilal
pronounced the Adhan and then the Iqama for the prayer and
requested Abu Bakr (to lead the prayer) and Abu Bakr went forward.
The Prophet arrived while Abu Bakr was still praying. He entered
the rows of praying people till he stood behind Abu Bakr in the
(first) row. The people started clapping, and it was the habit of
Abu Bakr that whenever he stood for prayer, he never glanced
side-ways till he had finished it, but when Abu Bakr observed that
the clapping was not coming to an end, he looked and saw the
Prophet standing behind him. The Prophet beckoned him to carry on
by waving his hand. Abu Bakr stood there for a while, thanking
Allah for the saying of the Prophet and then he retreated, taking
his steps backwards. When the Prophet saw that, he went ahead and
led the people in prayer. When he finished the prayer, he said, "O
Abu Bakr! What prevented you from carrying on with the prayer after
I beckoned you to do so?" Abu Bakr replied, "It does not befit the
son of Abi Quhafa to lead the Prophet in prayer." Then the Prophet
said to the people, "If some problem arises during prayers, then
the men should say, Subhan Allah!; and the women should clap." (See
Hadith No. 652, Vol. 1)</english-text>
</hadith>
