<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7055</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>94</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7279</hadith-number>
<chapter>Judgments (Ahkaam) - كتاب الأحكام</chapter>
<chain-index>30355, 20001, 20208, 20001, 1822</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن يوسف، أخبرنا مالك، عن أبي ليلى، ح
حدثنا إسماعيل، حدثني مالك، عن أبي ليلى بن عبد الله بن عبد الرحمن بن
سهل، عن سهل بن أبي حثمة، أنه أخبره هو، ورجال، من كبراء قومه أن عبد
الله بن سهل ومحيصة خرجا إلى خيبر من جهد أصابهم، فأخبر محيصة أن عبد
الله قتل وطرح في فقير أو عين، فأتى يهود فقال أنتم والله قتلتموه‏.‏
قالوا ما قتلناه والله‏.‏ ثم أقبل حتى قدم على قومه فذكر لهم، وأقبل
هو وأخوه حويصة وهو أكبر منه وعبد الرحمن بن سهل، فذهب ليتكلم وهو
الذي كان بخيبر فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم لمحيصة ‏"‏ كبر كبر
‏"‏‏.‏ يريد السن، فتكلم حويصة ثم تكلم محيصة فقال رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إما أن يدوا صاحبكم، وإما أن يؤذنوا بحرب ‏"‏‏.‏ فكتب
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إليهم به، فكتب ما قتلناه‏.‏ فقال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم لحويصة ومحيصة وعبد الرحمن ‏"‏ أتحلفون
وتستحقون دم صاحبكم ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لا‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أفتحلف لكم يهود
‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا ليسوا بمسلمين‏.‏ فوداه رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم من
عنده مائة ناقة حتى أدخلت الدار‏.‏ قال سهل فركضتني منها
ناقة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Laila bin `Abdullah bin `Abdur-Rahman
bin Sahl: Sahl bin Abi Hathma and some great men of his tribe said,
`Abdullah bin 'Sahl and Muhaiyisa went out to Khaibar as they were
struck with poverty and difficult living conditions. Then Muhaiyisa
was informed that `Abdullah had been killed and thrown in a pit or
a spring. Muhaiyisa went to the Jews and said, "By Allah, you have
killed my companion." The Jews said, "By Allah, we have not killed
him." Muhaiyisa then came back to his people and told them the
story. He, his elder brother Huwaiyisa and `Abdur-Rahman bin Sahl
came (to the Prophet) and he who had been at Khaibar, proceeded to
speak, but the Prophet said to Muhaiyisa, "The eldest! The eldest!"
meaning, "Let the eldest of you speak." So Huwaiyisa spoke first
and then Muhaiyisa. Allah's Apostle said, "The Jews should either
pay the blood money of your (deceased) companion or be ready for
war." After that Allah's Apostle wrote a letter to the Jews in that
respect, and they wrote that they had not killed him. Then Allah's
Apostle said to Huwaiyisa, Muhaiyisa and `Abdur-Rahman, "Can you
take an oath by which you will be entitled to take the blood
money?" They said, "No." He said (to them), "Shall we ask the Jews
to take an oath before you?" They replied, "But the Jews are not
Muslims." So Allah's Apostle gave them one-hundred she-camels as
blood money from himself. Sahl added: When those she-camels were
made to enter the house, one of them kicked me with its
leg.</english-text>
</hadith>
