<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7059</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>94</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7283</hadith-number>
<chapter>Judgments (Ahkaam) - كتاب الأحكام</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20337, 11065, 10511, 1457</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد، أخبرنا عبدة، حدثنا هشام بن عروة، عن أبيه،
عن أبي حميد الساعدي، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم استعمل ابن الأتبية
على صدقات بني سليم، فلما جاء إلى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
وحاسبه قال هذا الذي لكم، وهذه هدية أهديت لي‏.‏ فقال رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فهلا جلست في بيت أبيك وبيت أمك حتى تأتيك هديتك،
إن كنت صادقا ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم قام رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فخطب الناس
وحمد الله وأثنى عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ أما بعد فإني أستعمل رجالا منكم على
أمور مما ولاني الله، فيأتي أحدكم فيقول هذا لكم وهذه هدية أهديت لي
فهلا جلس في بيت أبيه وبيت أمه حتى تأتيه هديته إن كان صادقا، فوالله
لا يأخذ أحدكم منها شيئا قال هشام بغير حقه إلا جاء الله يحمله يوم
القيامة، ألا فلأعرفن ما جاء الله رجل ببعير له رغاء، أو ببقرة لها
خوار، أو شاة تيعر ‏"‏‏.‏ ثم رفع يديه حتى رأيت بياض إبطيه ‏"‏ ألا هل
بلغت ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Humaid As-Sa`idi: The Prophet employed
Ibn Al-Utbiyya to collect Zakat from Bani Sulaim, and when he
returned (with the money) to Allah's Apostle the Prophet called him
to account, and he said, "This (amount) is for you, and this was
given to me as a present." Allah's Apostle said, "Why don't you
stay at your father's house or your mother's house to see whether
you will be given gifts or not, if you are telling the truth?" Then
Allah's Apostle stood up and addressed the people, and after
glorifying and praising Allah, he said: Amma Ba'du (then after) I
employ some men from among you for some job which Allah has placed
in my charge, and then one of you comes to me and says, 'This
(amount) is for you and this is a gift given to me.' Why doesn't he
stay at the house of his father or the house of his mother and see
whether he will be given gifts or not if he was telling the truth
by Allah, none of you takes anything of it (i.e., Zakat) for
himself (Hisham added: unlawfully) but he will meet Allah on the
Day of Resurrection carrying it on his neck! I do not want to see
any of you carrying a grunting camel or a mooing cow or a bleating
sheep on meeting Allah." Then the Prophet raised both his hands
till I saw the whiteness of his armpits, and said, "(No doubt)!
Haven't I conveyed Allah's Message!"</english-text>
</hadith>
