<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7091</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>95</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7315</hadith-number>
<chapter>Wishes - كتاب التمنى</chapter>
<chain-index>30130, 20304, 11276, 11029, 34</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الحسن بن عمر، حدثنا يزيد، عن حبيب، عن عطاء، عن
جابر بن عبد الله، قال كنا مع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم فلبينا
بالحج وقدمنا مكة لأربع خلون من ذي الحجة، فأمرنا النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم أن نطوف بالبيت وبالصفا والمروة، وأن نجعلها عمرة ولنحل، إلا من
كان معه هدى قال ولم يكن مع أحد منا هدى غير النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وطلحة، وجاء علي من اليمن معه الهدى فقال أهللت بما أهل به رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا ننطلق إلى منى وذكر أحدنا يقطر قال رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إني لو استقبلت من أمري ما استدبرت ما
أهديت، ولولا أن معي الهدى لحللت ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ولقيه سراقة وهو يرمي
جمرة العقبة فقال يا رسول الله ألنا هذه خاصة قال ‏"‏ لا بل لأبد
‏"‏‏.‏ قال وكانت عائشة قدمت مكة وهى حائض، فأمرها النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم أن تنسك المناسك كلها، غير أنها لا تطوف ولا تصلي حتى تطهر،
فلما نزلوا البطحاء قالت عائشة يا رسول الله أتنطلقون بحجة وعمرة
وأنطلق بحجة‏.‏ قال ثم أمر عبد الرحمن بن أبي بكر الصديق أن ينطلق
معها إلى التنعيم، فاعتمرت عمرة في ذي الحجة بعد أيام
الحج‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Jabir bin `Abdullah: We were in the company
of Allah's Apostle and we assumed the state of Ihram of Hajj and
arrived at Mecca on the fourth of Dhul-Hijja. The Prophet ordered
us to perform the Tawaf around the Ka`ba and (Sa`i) between As-Safa
and Al-Marwa and use our lhram just for `Umra, and finish the state
of Ihram unless we had our Hadi with us. None of us had the Hadi
with him except the Prophet and Talha. `Ali came from Yemen and
brought the Hadi with him. `Ali said, 'I had assumed the state of
Ihram with the same intention as that with which Allah's Apostle
had assumed it. The people said, "How can we proceed to Mina and
our male organs are dribbling?" Allah's Apostle said, "If I had
formerly known what I came to know latterly, I would not have
brought the Hadi, and had there been no Hadi with me, I would have
finished my Ihram." Suraqa (bin Malik) met the Prophet while he was
throwing pebbles at the Jamrat-Al-`Aqaba, and asked, "O Allah's
Apostle! Is this (permitted) for us only?" The Prophet replied.
"No, it is forever" `Aisha had arrived at Mecca while she was
menstruating, therefore the Prophet ordered her to perform all the
ceremonies of Hajj except the Tawaf around the Ka`ba, and not to
perform her prayers unless and until she became clean . When they
encamped at Al-Batha, `Aisha said, "O Allah's Apostle! You are
proceeding after performing both Hajj and `Umra while I am
proceeding with Hajj only?" So the Prophet ordered `Abdur-Rahman
bin Abu Bakr As-Siddiq to go with her to at-Tan`im, and so she
performed the `Umra in Dhul-Hijja after the days of the
Hajj.</english-text>
</hadith>
