<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>96</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>96</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7352</hadith-number>
<chapter>Accepting Information Given by a Truthful Person - كتاب
أخبار الآحاد</chapter>
<chain-index>20386, 30312, 20291, 20020, 11309</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا علي بن الجعد، أخبرنا شعبة،‏.‏ وحدثني إسحاق،
أخبرنا النضر، أخبرنا شعبة، عن أبي جمرة، قال كان ابن عباس يقعدني على
سريره فقال إن وفد عبد القيس لما أتوا رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قال ‏"‏ من الوفد ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا ربيعة‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ مرحبا بالوفد والقوم،
غير خزايا ولا ندامى ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا يا رسول الله إن بيننا وبينك كفار
مضر، فمرنا بأمر ندخل به الجنة، ونخبر به من وراءنا فسألوا عن
الأشربة، فنهاهم عن أربع وأمرهم بأربع أمرهم بالإيمان بالله قال ‏"‏
هل تدرون ما الإيمان بالله ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ قال ‏"‏
شهادة أن لا إله إلا الله وحده لا شريك له وأن محمدا رسول الله، وإقام
الصلاة، وإيتاء الزكاة وأظن فيه صيام رمضان، وتؤتوا من المغانم الخمس
‏"‏‏.‏ ونهاهم عن الدباء، والحنتم، والمزفت، والنقير، وربما قال
المقير‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ احفظوهن، وأبلغوهن من وراءكم ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: When the delegate of `Abd
Al-Qais came to Allah's Apostle, he said, "Who are the delegate?"
They said, "The delegate are from the tribe of Rabi`a." The Prophet
said, "Welcome, O the delegate, and welcome! O people! Neither you
will have any disgrace nor will you regret." They said, "O Allah's
Apostle! Between you and us there are the infidels of the tribe of
Mudar, so please order us to do something good (religious deeds)
that by acting on them we may enter Paradise, and that we may
inform (our people) whom we have left behind, about it." They also
asked (the Prophet) about drinks. He forbade them from four things
and ordered them to do four things. He ordered them to believe in
Allah, and asked them, "Do you know what is meant by belief in
Allah?" They said, "Allah and His Apostle know best." He said, ''To
testify that none has the right to be worshipped except Allah, the
One, Who has no partners with Him, and that Muhammad is Allah's
Apostle; and to offer prayers perfectly and to pay Zakat." (the
narrator thinks that fasting in Ramadan is included), "and to give
one-fifth of the war booty (to the state)." Then he forbade four
(drinking utensils): Ad-Duba', Al56 Hantam, Al-Mazaffat and
An-Naqir, or probably, Al-Muqaiyar. And then the Prophet said,
"Remember all these things by heart and preach it to those whom you
have left behind."</english-text>
</hadith>
