<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7146</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7372</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30103, 20029, 20475, 11013, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني إسماعيل، حدثني ابن وهب، عن يونس، عن ابن شهاب،
حدثني عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة، أن عبد الله بن عباس رضى الله
عنهما قال قدم عيينة بن حصن بن حذيفة بن بدر فنزل على ابن أخيه الحر
بن قيس بن حصن، وكان من النفر الذين يدنيهم عمر، وكان القراء أصحاب
مجلس عمر ومشاورته كهولا كانوا أو شبانا فقال عيينة لابن أخيه يا ابن
أخي هل لك وجه عند هذا الأمير فتستأذن لي عليه قال سأستأذن لك عليه‏.‏
قال ابن عباس فاستأذن لعيينة فلما دخل قال يا ابن الخطاب والله ما
تعطينا الجزل، وما تحكم بيننا بالعدل‏.‏ فغضب عمر حتى هم بأن يقع به
فقال الحر يا أمير المؤمنين إن الله تعالى قال لنبيه صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏{‏خذ العفو وأمر بالعرف وأعرض عن الجاهلين‏}‏ وإن هذا من
الجاهلين‏.‏ فوالله ما جاوزها عمر حين تلاها عليه، وكان وقافا عند
كتاب الله‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Abdullah bin `Abbas: Uyaina bin Hisn bin
Hudhaifa bin Badr came and stayed (at Medina) with his nephew
Al-Hurr bin Qais bin Hisn who has one of those whom `Umar used to
keep near him, as the Qurra' (learned men knowing Qur'an by heart)
were the people of `Umar's meetings and his advisors whether they
were old or young. 'Uyaina said to his nephew, "O my nephew! Have
you an approach to this chief so as to get for me the permission to
see him?" His nephew said, "I will get the permission for you to
see him." (Ibn `Abbas added: ) So he took the permission for
'Uyaina, and when the latter entered, he said, "O the son of
Al-Khattab! By Allah, you neither give us sufficient provision nor
judge among us with justice." On that `Umar became so furious that
he intended to harm him. Al-Hurr, said, "O Chief of the Believers!"
Allah said to His Apostle 'Hold to forgiveness, command what is
good (right), and leave the foolish (i.e. do not punish them).'
(7.199) and this person is among the foolish." By Allah, `Umar did
not overlook that Verse when Al-Hurr recited it before him, and
`Umar said to observe (the orders of) Allah's Book strictly." (See
Hadith No. 166, Vol. 6)</english-text>
</hadith>
