<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7147</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7373</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>20164, 20001, 11065, 10526, 70</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن مسلمة، عن مالك، عن هشام بن عروة، عن
فاطمة بنت المنذر، عن أسماء ابنة أبي بكر رضى الله عنهما أنها قالت
أتيت عائشة حين خسفت الشمس، والناس قيام وهى قائمة تصلي فقلت ما للناس
فأشارت بيدها نحو السماء فقالت سبحان الله‏.‏ فقلت آية‏.‏ قالت برأسها
أن نعم‏.‏ فلما انصرف رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم حمد الله وأثنى
عليه ثم قال ‏"‏ ما من شىء لم أره إلا وقد رأيته في مقامي، حتى الجنة
والنار، وأوحي إلى أنكم تفتنون في القبور قريبا من فتنة الدجال، فأما
المؤمن أو المسلم لا أدري أى ذلك قالت أسماء فيقول محمد جاءنا
بالبينات فأجبنا وآمنا‏.‏ فيقال نم صالحا علمنا أنك موقن‏.‏ وأما
المنافق أو المرتاب لا أدري أى ذلك قالت أسماء فيقول لا أدري سمعت
الناس يقولون شيئا فقلته ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Asma' bint Abu Bakr: I came to `Aisha during
the solar eclipse. The people were standing (offering prayer) and
she too, was standing and offering prayer. I asked, "What is wrong
with the people?" She pointed towards the sky with her hand and
said, Subhan Allah!'' I asked her, "Is there a sign?" She nodded
with her head meaning, yes. When Allah's Apostle finished (the
prayer), he glorified and praised Allah and said, "There is not
anything that I have not seen before but I have seen now at this
place of mine, even Paradise and Hell. It has been revealed to me
that you people will be put to trial nearly like the trial of
Ad-Dajjal, in your graves. As for the true believer or a Muslim
(the sub-narrator is not sure as to which of the two (words Asma'
had said) he will say, 'Muhammad came with clear signs from Allah,
and we responded to him (accepted his teachings) and believed (what
he said)' It will be said (to him) 'Sleep in peace; we have known
that you were a true believer who believed with certainty.' As for
a hypocrite or a doubtful person, (the sub-narrator is not sure as
to which word Asma' said) he will say, 'I do not know, but I heard
the people saying something and so I said the same.'
"</english-text>
</hadith>
