<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7154</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7380</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30330, 20428, 11013, 30277, 20121, 20115, 11013,
19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو اليمان، أخبرنا شعيب، عن الزهري،‏.‏ وحدثني
محمود، حدثنا عبد الرزاق، أخبرنا معمر، عن الزهري، أخبرني أنس بن مالك
رضى الله عنه‏.‏ أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم خرج حين زاغت الشمس فصلى
الظهر فلما سلم قام على المنبر فذكر الساعة، وذكر أن بين يديها أمورا
عظاما ثم قال ‏"‏ من أحب أن يسأل عن شىء فليسأل عنه، فوالله لا
تسألوني عن شىء إلا أخبرتكم به، ما دمت في مقامي هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أنس
فأكثر الناس البكاء، وأكثر رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم أن يقول ‏"‏
سلوني ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال أنس فقام إليه رجل فقال أين مدخلي يا رسول الله قال
‏"‏ النار ‏"‏‏.‏ فقام عبد الله بن حذافة فقال من أبي يا رسول الله
قال ‏"‏ أبوك حذافة ‏"‏‏.‏ قال ثم أكثر أن يقول ‏"‏ سلوني سلوني
‏"‏‏.‏ فبرك عمر على ركبتيه فقال رضينا بالله ربا، وبالإسلام دينا،
وبمحمد صلى الله عليه وسلم رسولا‏.‏ قال فسكت رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم حين قال عمر ذلك، ثم قال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ والذي
نفسي بيده لقد عرضت على الجنة والنار آنفا في عرض هذا الحائط وأنا
أصلي، فلم أر كاليوم في الخير والشر ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas bin Malik: The Prophet came out after
the sun had declined and offered the Zuhr prayer (in congregation).
After finishing it with Taslim, he stood on the pulpit and
mentioned the Hour and mentioned there would happen great events
before it. Then he said, "Whoever wants to ask me any question, may
do so, for by Allah, you will not ask me about anything but I will
inform you of its answer as long as I am at this place of mine." On
this, the Ansar wept violently, and Allah's Apostle kept on saying,
"Ask Me! " Then a man got up and asked, ''Where will my entrance
be, O Allah's Apostle?" The Prophet said, "(You will go to) the
Fire." Then `Abdullah bin Hudhaifa got up and asked, "Who is my
father, O Allah's Apostle?" The Prophet replied, "Your father is
Hudhaifa." The Prophet then kept on saying (angrily), "Ask me! Ask
me!" `Umar then knelt on his knees and said, "We have accepted
Allah as our Lord and Islam as our religion and Muhammad as an
Apostle." Allah's Apostle became quiet when `Umar said that. Then
Allah's Apostle said, "By Him in Whose Hand my life is, Paradise
and Hell were displayed before me across this wall while I was
praying, and I never saw such good and evil as I have seen
today."</english-text>
</hadith>
