<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7160</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7386</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30204, 20317, 11060, 11322, 11405</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عمر بن حفص بن غياث، حدثنا أبي، حدثنا الأعمش،
حدثني إبراهيم التيمي، حدثني أبي قال، خطبنا علي رضى الله عنه على
منبر من آجر، وعليه سيف فيه صحيفة معلقة فقال والله ما عندنا من كتاب
يقرأ إلا كتاب الله وما في هذه الصحيفة‏.‏ فنشرها فإذا فيها أسنان
الإبل وإذا فيها ‏"‏ المدينة حرم من عير إلى كذا، فمن أحدث فيها حدثا
فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين، لا يقبل الله منه صرفا ولا
عدلا ‏"‏‏.‏ وإذا فيه ‏"‏ ذمة المسلمين واحدة يسعى بها أدناهم، فمن
أخفر مسلما فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين، لا يقبل الله
منه صرفا ولا عدلا ‏"‏‏.‏ وإذا فيها ‏"‏ من والى قوما بغير إذن مواليه
فعليه لعنة الله والملائكة والناس أجمعين لا يقبل الله منه صرفا ولا
عدلا ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibrahim At Taimi's father: `Ali addressed us
while he was standing on a brick pulpit and carrying a sword from
which was hanging a scroll He said "By Allah, we have no book to
read except Allah's Book and whatever is on this scroll," And then
he unrolled it, and behold, in it was written what sort of camels
were to be given as blood money, and there was also written in it:
'Medina is a sanctuary form 'Air (mountain) to such and such place
so whoever innovates in it an heresy or commits a sin therein, he
will incur the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people and
Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good deeds.' There
was also written in it: 'The asylum (pledge of protection) granted
by any Muslims is one and the same, (even a Muslim of the lowest
status is to be secured and respected by all the other Muslims, and
whoever betrays a Muslim in this respect (by violating the pledge)
will incur the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the people, and
Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good deeds.' There
was also written in it: 'Whoever (freed slave) befriends (takes as
masters) other than his real masters (manumitters) without their
permission will incur the curse of Allah, the angels, and all the
people, and Allah will not accept his compulsory or optional good
deeds. ' (See Hadith No. 94, Vol. 3)</english-text>
</hadith>
