<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7164</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7390</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>20404, 20177, 11013, 399</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا آدم، حدثنا ابن أبي ذئب، حدثنا الزهري، عن سهل بن
سعد الساعدي، قال جاء عويمر إلى عاصم بن عدي فقال أرأيت رجلا وجد مع
امرأته رجلا فيقتله، أتقتلونه به سل لي يا عاصم رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم فسأله فكره النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم المسائل وعاب، فرجع
عاصم فأخبره أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كره المسائل فقال عويمر
والله لآتين النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم، فجاء وقد أنزل الله تعالى
القرآن خلف عاصم فقال له ‏"‏ قد أنزل الله فيكم قرآنا ‏"‏‏.‏ فدعا
بهما فتقدما فتلاعنا، ثم قال عويمر كذبت عليها يا رسول الله، إن
أمسكتها‏.‏ ففارقها ولم يأمره النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بفراقها، فجرت
السنة في المتلاعنين‏.‏ وقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ انظروها
فإن جاءت به أحمر قصيرا مثل وحرة فلا أراه إلا قد كذب، وإن جاءت به
أسحم أعين ذا أليتين فلا أحسب إلا قد صدق عليها ‏"‏‏.‏ فجاءت به على
الأمر المكروه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sahl bin Sa`d As-Sa`idi: 'Uwaimir Al-`Ajlani
came to `Asim bin `Adi and said, "If a man found another man with
his wife and killed him, would you sentence the husband to death
(in Qisas,) i.e., equality in punishment)? O `Asim! Please ask
Allah's Apostle about this matter on my behalf." `Asim asked the
Prophet but the Prophet disliked the question and disapproved of
it. `Asim returned and informed 'Uwaimir that the Prophet disliked
that type of question. 'Uwaimir said, "By Allah, I will go
(personally) to the Prophet." 'Uwaimir came to the Prophet when
Allah had already revealed Qur'anic Verses (in that respect), after
`Asim had left (the Prophet ). So the Prophet said to 'Uwaimir,
"Allah has revealed Qur'anic Verses regarding you and your wife."
The Prophet then called for them, and they came and carried out the
order of Lian. Then 'Uwaimir said, "O Allah's Apostle! Now if I
kept her with me, I would be accused of telling a lie." So 'Uwaimir
divorced her although the Prophet did not order him to do so. Later
on this practice of divorcing became the tradition of couples
involved in a case of Li'an. The Prophet said (to the people).
"Wait for her! If she delivers a red short (small) child like a
Wahra (a short red animal). then I will be of the opinion that he
('Uwaimir) has told a lie but if she delivered a black big-eyed one
with big buttocks, then I will be of the opinion that he has told
the truth about her." 'Ultimately she gave birth to a child that
proved the accusation. (See Hadith No. 269, Vol. 6)</english-text>
</hadith>
