<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7220</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>97</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7457</hadith-number>
<chapter>Holding Fast to the Qur'an and Sunnah - كتاب الاعتصام
بالكتاب والسنة</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20150, 11176, 11013, 10511, 11002, 11042,
11201, 53</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا الأويسي، حدثنا إبراهيم، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب،
حدثني عروة، وابن المسيب، وعلقمة بن وقاص، وعبيد الله، عن عائشة رضى
الله عنها حين قال لها أهل الإفك قالت ودعا رسول الله صلى الله عليه
وسلم علي بن أبي طالب وأسامة بن زيد حين استلبث الوحى يسألهما، وهو
يستشيرهما في فراق أهله، فأما أسامة فأشار بالذي يعلم من براءة أهله،
وأما علي فقال لم يضيق الله عليك، والنساء سواها كثير، وسل الجارية
تصدقك‏.‏ فقال ‏"‏ هل رأيت من شىء يريبك ‏"‏‏.‏ قالت ما رأيت أمرا
أكثر من أنها جارية حديثة السن تنام عن عجين أهلها فتأتي الداجن
فتأكله‏.‏ فقام على المنبر فقال ‏"‏ يا معشر المسلمين من يعذرني من
رجل بلغني أذاه في أهلي، والله ما علمت على أهلي إلا خيرا ‏"‏‏.‏ فذكر
براءة عائشة‏.‏ وقال أبو أسامة عن هشام‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated `Aisha: After the slanderers had given a
forged statement against her, Allah's Apostle called `Ali bin Abi
Talib and Usama bin Zaid when the Divine Inspiration was delayed.
He wanted to ask them and consult them about the question of
divorcing me. Usama gave his evidence that was based on what he
knew about my innocence, but `Ali said, "Allah has not put
restrictions on you and there are many women other than her.
Furthermore you may ask the slave girl who will tell you the
truth." So the Prophet asked Barira (my salve girl), "Have you seen
anything that may arouse your suspicion?" She replied, "I have not
seen anything more than that she is a little girl who sleeps,
leaving the dough of her family (unguarded) that the domestic goats
come and eat it." Then the Prophet stood on the pulpit and said, "O
Muslims! Who will help me against the man who has harmed me by
slandering my wife? By Allah, I know nothing about my family except
good." The narrator added: Then the Prophet mentioned the innocence
of `Aisha. (See Hadith No. 274, Vol. 6)</english-text>
</hadith>
