<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7266</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7499</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30177, 20295, 11019, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثني معاذ بن فضالة، حدثنا هشام، عن قتادة، عن أنس، أن
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال ‏"‏ يجمع الله المؤمنين يوم القيامة
كذلك فيقولون لو استشفعنا إلى ربنا حتى يريحنا من مكاننا هذا‏.‏
فيأتون آدم فيقولون يا آدم أما ترى الناس خلقك الله بيده وأسجد لك
ملائكته وعلمك أسماء كل شىء، شفع لنا إلى ربنا حتى يريحنا من مكاننا
هذا‏.‏ فيقول لست هناك ويذكر لهم خطيئته التي أصاب ولكن ائتوا نوحا،
فإنه أول رسول بعثه الله إلى أهل الأرض‏.‏ فيأتون نوحا فيقول لست
هناكم ويذكر خطيئته التي أصاب ولكن ائتوا إبراهيم خليل الرحمن‏.‏
فيأتون إبراهيم فيقول لست هناكم ويذكر لهم خطاياه التي أصابها ولكن
ائتوا موسى عبدا أتاه الله التوراة وكلمه تكليما فيأتون موسى فيقول
لست هناكم ويذكر لهم خطيئته التي أصاب ولكن ائتوا عيسى عبد الله
ورسوله وكلمته وروحه‏.‏ فيأتون عيسى فيقول لست هناكم ولكن ائتوا محمدا
صلى الله عليه وسلم عبدا غفر له ما تقدم من ذنبه وما تأخر‏.‏ فيأتوني
فأنطلق فأستأذن على ربي فيؤذن لي عليه، فإذا رأيت ربي وقعت له ساجدا
فيدعني ما شاء الله أن يدعني ثم يقال لي ارفع محمد، وقل يسمع، وسل
تعطه، واشفع تشفع‏.‏ فأحمد ربي بمحامد علمنيها، ثم أشفع فيحد لي حدا
فأدخلهم الجنة، ثم أرجع فإذا رأيت ربي وقعت ساجدا، فيدعني ما شاء الله
أن يدعني ثم يقال ارفع محمد، وقل يسمع، وسل تعطه، واشفع تشفع، فأحمد
ربي بمحامد علمنيها ربي ثم أشفع فيحد لي حدا فأدخلهم الجنة، ثم أرجع
فإذا رأيت ربي وقعت ساجدا، فيدعني ما شاء الله أن يدعني ثم يقال ارفع
محمد، قل يسمع، وسل تعطه، واشفع تشفع، فأحمد ربي بمحامد علمنيها، ثم
أشفع فيحد لي حدا فأدخلهم الجنة، ثم أرجع فأقول يا رب ما بقي في النار
إلا من حبسه القرآن ووجب عليه الخلود ‏"‏‏.‏ قال النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم ‏"‏ يخرج من النار من قال لا إله إلا الله‏.‏ وكان في قلبه من
الخير ما يزن شعيرة، ثم يخرج من النار من قال لا إله إلا الله‏.‏ وكان
في قلبه من الخير ما يزن برة، ثم يخرج من النار من قال لا إله إلا
الله‏.‏ وكان في قلبه ما يزن من الخير ذرة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Anas: The Prophet said, "Allah will gather
the believers on the Day of Resurrection in the same way (as they
are gathered in this life), and they will say, 'Let us ask someone
to intercede for us with our Lord that He may relieve us from this
place of ours.' Then they will go to Adam and say, 'O Adam! Don't
you see the people (people's condition)? Allah created you with His
Own Hands and ordered His angels to prostrate before you, and
taught you the names of all the things. Please intercede for us
with our Lord so that He may relieve us from this place of ours.'
Adam will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking' and mention to
them the mistakes he had committed, and add, "But you d better go
to Noah as he was the first Apostle sent by Allah to the people of
the Earth.' They will go to Noah who will reply, 'I am not fit for
this undertaking,' and mention the mistake which he made, and add,
'But you'd better go to Abraham, Khalil Ar-Rahman.' They will go to
Abraham who will reply, 'I am not fit for this undertaking,' and
mention to them the mistakes he made, and add, 'But you'd better go
to Moses, a slave whom Allah gave the Torah and to whom He spoke
directly' They will go to Moses who will reply, 'I am not fit for
this undertaking,' and mention to them the mistakes he made, and
add, 'You'd better go to Jesus, Allah's slave and His Apostle and
His Word (Be: And it was) and a soul created by Him.' They will go
to Jesus who will say, 'I am not fit for this undertaking, but
you'd better go to Muhammad whose sins of the past and the future
had been forgiven (by Allah).' So they will come to me and I will
ask the permission of my Lord, and I will be permitted (to present
myself) before Him. When I see my Lord, I will fall down in
(prostration) before Him and He will leave me (in prostration) as
long as He wishes, and then it will be said to me, 'O Muhammad!
Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to; and ask,
for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for your
intercession will be accepted.' I will then raise my head and
praise my Lord with certain praises which He has taught me, and
then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a
certain kind of people) and will fix a limit whom I will admit into
Paradise. I will come back again, and when I see my Lord (again), I
will fall down in prostration before Him, and He will leave me (in
prostration) as long as He wishes, and then He will say, 'O
Muhammad! Raise your head and speak, for you will be listened to;
and ask, for you will be granted (your request); and intercede, for
your intercession will be accepted.' I will then praise my Lord
with certain praises which He has taught me, and then I will
intercede. Allah will allow me to intercede (for a certain kind of
people) and will fix a limit to whom I will admit into Paradise, I
will return again, and when I see my Lord, I will fall down (in
prostration) and He will leave me (in prostration) as long as He
wishes, and then He will say, 'O Muhammad! Raise your head and
speak, for you will be listened to, and ask, for you will be
granted (your request); and intercede, for your intercession will
be accepted.' I will then praise my Lord with certain praises which
He has taught me, and then I will intercede. Allah will allow me to
intercede (for a certain kind of people) and will fix a limit to
whom I will admit into Paradise. I will come back and say, 'O my
Lord! None remains in Hell (Fire) but those whom Qur'an has
imprisoned therein and for whom eternity in Hell (Fire) has become
inevitable.' " The Prophet added, "There will come out of Hell
(Fire) everyone who says: 'La ilaha illal-lah,' and has in his
heart good equal to the weight of a barley grain. Then there will
come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: ' La ilaha illal-lah,'
and has in his heart good equal to the weight of a wheat grain.
Then there will come out of Hell (Fire) everyone who says: 'La
ilaha illal-lah,' and has in his heart good equal to the weight of
an atom (or a smallest ant).</english-text>
</hadith>
