<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7287</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7522</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>20351, 20012, 20016, 11366, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قبيصة، حدثنا سفيان، عن أبيه، عن ابن أبي نعم أو
أبي نعم شك قبيصة عن أبي سعيد، قال بعث إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
بذهيبة فقسمها بين أربعة‏.‏ وحدثني إسحاق بن نصر حدثنا عبد الرزاق
أخبرنا سفيان عن أبيه عن ابن أبي نعم عن أبي سعيد الخدري قال بعث علي
وهو باليمن إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم بذهيبة في تربتها، فقسمها
بين الأقرع بن حابس الحنظلي ثم أحد بني مجاشع، وبين عيينة بن بدر
الفزاري، وبين علقمة بن علاثة العامري ثم أحد بني كلاب، وبين زيد
الخيل الطائي ثم أحد بني نبهان، فتغضبت قريش والأنصار فقالوا يعطيه
صناديد أهل نجد ويدعنا قال ‏"‏ إنما أتألفهم ‏"‏‏.‏ فأقبل رجل غائر
العينين، ناتئ الجبين، كث اللحية، مشرف الوجنتين، محلوق الرأس فقال يا
محمد اتق الله‏.‏ فقال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ فمن يطيع الله
إذا عصيته فيأمني على أهل الأرض، ولا تأمنوني ‏"‏‏.‏ فسأل رجل من
القوم قتله أراه خالد بن الوليد فمنعه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فلما
ولى قال النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏"‏ إن من ضئضئ هذا قوما يقرءون
القرآن لا يجاوز حناجرهم، يمرقون من الإسلام مروق السهم من الرمية،
يقتلون أهل الإسلام ويدعون أهل الأوثان، لئن أدركتهم لأقتلنهم قتل عاد
‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: When `Ali was in Yemen,
he sent some gold in its ore to the Prophet. The Prophet
distributed it among Al-Aqra' bin H`Abis Al-Hanzali who belonged to
Bani Mujashi, 'Uyaina bin Badr Al-Fazari, 'Alqama bin 'Ulatha
Al-`Amiri, who belonged to the Bani Kilab tribe and Zaid AI-Khail
at-Ta'i who belonged to Bani Nabhan. So the Quraish and the Ansar
became angry and said, "He gives to the chiefs of Najd and leaves
us!" The Prophet said, "I just wanted to attract and unite their
hearts (make them firm in Islam)." Then there came a man with
sunken eyes, bulging forehead, thick beard, fat raised cheeks, and
clean-shaven head, and said, "O Muhammad! Be afraid of Allah! " The
Prophet said, "Who would obey Allah if I disobeyed Him? (Allah). He
trusts me over the people of the earth, but you do not trust me?" A
man from the people (present then), who, I think, was Khalid bin
Al- Walid, asked for permission to kill him, but the Prophet
prevented him. When the man went away, the Prophet said, "Out of
the offspring of this man, there will be people who will recite the
Qur'an but it will not go beyond their throats, and they will go
out of Islam as an arrow goes out through the game, and they will
kill the Muslims and leave the idolators. Should I live till they
appear, I would kill them as the Killing of the nation of
'Ad."</english-text>
</hadith>
