<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7292</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7527</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30105, 20150, 11013, 11206, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد العزيز بن عبد الله، حدثنا إبراهيم بن سعد، عن
ابن شهاب، عن عطاء بن يزيد الليثي، عن أبي هريرة، أن الناس، قالوا يا
رسول الله هل نرى ربنا يوم القيامة فقال رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
‏"‏ هل تضارون في القمر ليلة البدر ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لا يا رسول الله‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فهل تضارون في الشمس ليس دونها سحاب ‏"‏‏.‏ قالوا لا يا رسول
الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنكم ترونه كذلك، يجمع الله الناس يوم القيامة فيقول
من كان يعبد شيئا فليتبعه‏.‏ فيتبع من كان يعبد الشمس الشمس، ويتبع من
كان يعبد القمر القمر، ويتبع من كان يعبد الطواغيت الطواغيت، وتبقى
هذه الأمة فيها شافعوها أو منافقوها شك إبراهيم فيأتيهم الله فيقول
أنا ربكم‏.‏ فيقولون هذا مكاننا حتى يأتينا ربنا فإذا جاءنا ربنا
عرفناه فيأتيهم الله في صورته التي يعرفون فيقول أنا ربكم‏.‏ فيقولون
أنت ربنا‏.‏ فيتبعونه ويضرب الصراط بين ظهرى جهنم، فأكون أنا وأمتي
أول من يجيزها، ولا يتكلم يومئذ إلا الرسل، ودعوى الرسل يومئذ اللهم
سلم سلم‏.‏ وفي جهنم كلاليب مثل شوك السعدان، هل رأيتم السعدان ‏"‏‏.‏
قالوا نعم يا رسول الله‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فإنها مثل شوك السعدان، غير أنه لا
يعلم ما قدر عظمها إلا الله، تخطف الناس بأعمالهم، فمنهم الموبق بقي
بعمله، أو الموثق بعمله، ومنهم المخردل أو المجازى أو نحوه، ثم يتجلى
حتى إذا فرغ الله من القضاء بين العباد وأراد أن يخرج برحمته من أراد
من أهل النار أمر الملائكة أن يخرجوا من النار من كان لا يشرك بالله
شيئا، ممن أراد الله أن يرحمه ممن يشهد أن لا إله إلا الله، فيعرفونهم
في النار بأثر السجود، تأكل النار ابن آدم إلا أثر السجود، حرم الله
على النار أن تأكل أثر السجود، فيخرجون من النار قد امتحشوا، فيصب
عليهم ماء الحياة فينبتون تحته كما تنبت الحبة في حميل السيل، ثم يفرغ
الله من القضاء بين العباد، ويبقى رجل مقبل بوجهه على النار هو آخر
أهل النار دخولا الجنة فيقول أى رب اصرف وجهي عن النار، فإنه قد قشبني
ريحها وأحرقني ذكاؤها‏.‏ فيدعو الله بما شاء أن يدعوه ثم يقول الله هل
عسيت إن أعطيت ذلك أن تسألني غيره‏.‏ فيقول لا وعزتك لا أسألك غيره،
ويعطي ربه من عهود ومواثيق ما شاء، فيصرف الله وجهه عن النار، فإذا
أقبل على الجنة ورآها سكت ما شاء الله أن يسكت ثم يقول أى رب قدمني
إلى باب الجنة‏.‏ فيقول الله له ألست قد أعطيت عهودك ومواثيقك أن لا
تسألني غير الذي أعطيت أبدا، ويلك يا ابن آدم ما أغدرك‏.‏ فيقول أى
رب‏.‏ ويدعو الله حتى يقول هل عسيت إن أعطيت ذلك أن تسأل غيره‏.‏
فيقول لا وعزتك لا أسألك غيره، ويعطي ما شاء من عهود ومواثيق، فيقدمه
إلى باب الجنة، فإذا قام إلى باب الجنة انفهقت له الجنة فرأى ما فيها
من الحبرة والسرور، فيسكت ما شاء الله أن يسكت ثم يقول أى رب أدخلني
الجنة‏.‏ فيقول الله ألست قد أعطيت عهودك ومواثيقك أن لا تسأل غير ما
أعطيت فيقول ويلك يا ابن آدم ما أغدرك‏.‏ فيقول أى رب لا أكونن أشقى
خلقك فلا يزال يدعو حتى يضحك الله منه فإذا ضحك منه قال له ادخل
الجنة‏.‏ فإذا دخلها قال الله له تمنه‏.‏ فسأل ربه وتمنى حتى إن الله
ليذكره يقول كذا وكذا، حتى انقطعت به الأماني قال الله ذلك لك ومثله
معه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال عطاء بن يزيد وأبو سعيد الخدري مع أبي هريرة لا يرد
عليه من حديثه شيئا حتى إذا حدث أبو هريرة أن الله تبارك وتعالى قال
‏"‏ ذلك لك ومثله معه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد الخدري ‏"‏ وعشرة أمثاله
معه ‏"‏‏.‏ يا أبا هريرة‏.‏ قال أبو هريرة ما حفظت إلا قوله ‏"‏ ذلك
لك ومثله معه ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد الخدري أشهد أني حفظت من رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم قوله ‏"‏ ذلك لك وعشرة أمثاله ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أبو
هريرة فذلك الرجل آخر أهل الجنة دخولا الجنة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated 'Ata' bin Yazid Al-Laithi: On the authority
of Abu Huraira: The people said, "O Allah's Apostle! Shall we see
our Lord on the Day of Resurrection?" The Prophet said, "Do you
have any difficulty in seeing the moon on a full moon night?" They
said, "No, O Allah's Apostle." He said, "Do you have any difficulty
in seeing the sun when there are no clouds?" They said, "No, O
Allah's Apostle." He said, "So you will see Him, like that. Allah
will gather all the people on the Day of Resurrection, and say,
'Whoever worshipped something (in the world) should follow (that
thing),' so, whoever worshipped the sun will follow the sun, and
whoever worshiped the moon will follow the moon, and whoever used
to worship certain (other false) deities, he will follow those
deities. And there will remain only this nation with its good
people (or its hypocrites). (The sub-narrator, Ibrahim is in
doubt.) Allah will come to them and say, 'I am your Lord.' They
will (deny Him and) say, 'We will stay here till our Lord comes,
for when our Lord comes, we will recognize Him.' So Allah will come
to them in His appearance which they know, and will say, 'I am your
Lord.' They will say, 'You are our Lord,' so they will follow Him.
Then a bridge will be laid across Hell (Fire)' I and my followers
will be the first ones to go across it and none will speak on that
Day except the Apostles. And the invocation of the Apostles on that
Day will be, 'O Allah, save! Save!' In Hell (or over The Bridge)
there will be hooks like the thorns of As-Sa'dan (thorny plant).
Have you seen As-Sa'dan? " They replied, "Yes, O Allah's Apostle!"
He said, "So those hooks look like the thorns of As-Sa'dan, but
none knows how big they are except Allah. Those hooks will snap the
people away according to their deeds. Some of the people will stay
in Hell (be destroyed) because of their (evil) deeds, and some will
be cut or torn by the hooks (and fall into Hell) and some will be
punished and then relieved. When Allah has finished His Judgments
among the people, He will take whomever He will out of Hell through
His Mercy. He will then order the angels to take out of the Fire
all those who used to worship none but Allah from among those whom
Allah wanted to be merciful to and those who testified (in the
world) that none has the right to be worshipped but Allah. The
angels will recognize them in the Fire by the marks of prostration
(on their foreheads), for the Fire will eat up all the human body
except the mark caused by prostration as Allah has forbidden the
Fire to eat the mark of prostration. They will come out of the
(Hell) Fire, completely burnt and then the water of life will be
poured over them and they will grow under it as does a seed that
comes in the mud of the torrent. Then Allah will finish the
judgments among the people, and there will remain one man facing
the (Hell) Fire and he will be the last person among the people of
Hell to enter Paradise. He will say, 'O my Lord! Please turn my
face away from the fire because its air has hurt me and its severe
heat has burnt me.' So he will invoke Allah in the way Allah will
wish him to invoke, and then Allah will say to him, 'If I grant you
that, will you then ask for anything else?' He will reply, 'No, by
Your Power, (Honor) I will not ask You for anything else.' He will
give his Lord whatever promises and covenants Allah will demand. So
Allah will turn his face away from Hell (Fire). When he will face
Paradise and will see it, he will remain quiet for as long as Allah
will wish him to remain quiet, then he will say, 'O my Lord! Bring
me near to the gate of Paradise.' Allah will say to him, 'Didn't
you give your promises and covenants that you would never ask for
anything more than what you had been given? Woe on you, O Adam's
son! How treacherous you are!' He will say, 'O my lord,' and will
keep on invoking Allah till He says to him, 'If I give what you are
asking, will you then ask for anything else?' He will reply, 'No,
by Your (Honor) Power, I will not ask for anything else.' Then he
will give covenants and promises to Allah and then Allah will bring
him near to the gate of Paradise. When he stands at the gate of
Paradise, Paradise will be opened and spread before him, and he
will see its splendor and pleasures whereupon he will remain quiet
as long as Allah will wish him to remain quiet, and then he will
say, O my Lord! Admit me into Paradise.' Allah will say, 'Didn't
you give your covenants and promises that you would not ask for
anything more than what you had been given?' Allah will say, 'Woe
on you, O Adam's son! How treacherous you are! ' The man will say,
'O my Lord! Do not make me the most miserable of Your creation,'
and he will keep on invoking Allah till Allah will laugh because of
his sayings, and when Allah will laugh because of him, He will say
to him, 'Enter Paradise,' and when he will enter it, Allah will say
to him, 'Wish for anything.' So he will ask his Lord, and he will
wish for a great number of things, for Allah Himself will remind
him to wish for certain things by saying, '(Wish for) so-and-so.'
When there is nothing more to wish for, Allah will say, 'This is
for you, and its equal (is for you) as well." 'Ata' bin Yazid
added: Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri who was present with Abu Huraira, did
not deny whatever the latter said, but when Abu Huraira said that
Allah had said, "That is for you and its equal as well," Abu Sa'id
Al-Khudri said, "And ten times as much, O Abu Huraira!" Abu Huraira
said, "I do not remember, except his saying, 'That is for you and
its equal as well.'" Abu Sa'id Al-Khudri then said, "I testify that
I remember the Prophet saying, 'That is for you, and ten times as
much.' ' Abu Huraira then added, "That man will be the last person
of the people of Paradise to enter Paradise."</english-text>
</hadith>
