<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7301</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7537</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30170, 20259, 11015, 20278, 11294, 3229</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن المثنى، حدثنا عبد الوهاب، حدثنا أيوب، عن
محمد، عن ابن أبي بكرة، عن أبي بكرة، عن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم قال
‏"‏ الزمان قد استدار كهيئته يوم خلق الله السموات والأرض، السنة اثنا
عشر شهرا، منها أربعة حرم ثلاث متواليات ذو القعدة وذو الحجة والمحرم،
ورجب مضر الذي بين جمادى وشعبان، أى شهر هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله
أعلم فسكت حتى ظننا أنه يسميه بغير اسمه قال ‏"‏ أليس ذا الحجة ‏"‏‏.‏
قلنا بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ أى بلد هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم‏.‏ فسكت
حتى ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه قال ‏"‏ أليس البلدة ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا
بلى‏.‏ قال ‏"‏ فأى يوم هذا ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا الله ورسوله أعلم فسكت حتى
ظننا أنه سيسميه بغير اسمه قال ‏"‏ أليس يوم النحر ‏"‏‏.‏ قلنا بلى‏.‏
قال ‏"‏ فإن دماءكم وأموالكم قال محمد وأحسبه قال وأعراضكم عليكم
حرام، كحرمة يومكم هذا في بلدكم هذا في شهركم هذا، وستلقون ربكم
فيسألكم عن أعمالكم، ألا فلا ترجعوا بعدي ضلالا، يضرب بعضكم رقاب بعض،
ألا ليبلغ الشاهد الغائب، فلعل بعض من يبلغه أن يكون أوعى من بعض من
سمعه ‏"‏‏.‏ فكان محمد إذا ذكره قال صدق النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم ثم
قال ‏"‏ ألا هل بلغت ألا هل بلغت ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Bakra: The Prophet said, "Time has come
back to its original state which it had when Allah created the
Heavens and the Earth, the year is twelve months, of which four are
sacred; (and out of these four) three are in succession, namely,
Dhul-Qa'da, Dhul-Hijja and Muharram, and (the fourth one) Rajab
Mudar which is between Jumad (Ath-Tham) and Sha'ban." The Prophet
then asked us, "Which month is this?" We said, "Allah and His
Apostle know (it) better." He kept quiet so long that we thought he
might call it by another name. Then he said, "Isn't it Dhul-Hijja?"
We said, "Yes." He asked "What town is this?" We said, "Allah and
His Apostle know (it) better.' Then he kept quiet so long that we
thought he might call it by another name. He then said, "Isn't it
the (forbidden) town (Mecca)?" We said, "Yes." He asked, "What is
the day today?" We said, "Allah and His Apostle know (it) better.
Then he kept quiet so long that we thought that he might call it by
another name. Then he said, "Isn't it the Day of An-Nahr
(slaughtering of sacrifices)?" We said, "Yes." Then he said, "Your
blood (lives), your properties," (the sub narrator Muhammad, said:
I think he also said): "..and your honor) are as sacred to one
another like the sanctity of this Day of yours, in this town of
yours, in this month of yours. You shall meet your Lord and He will
ask you about your deeds. Beware! Don't go astray after me by
striking the necks of one another. Lo! It is incumbent upon those
who are present to inform it to those who are absent for perhaps
the informed one might comprehend it (understand it) better than
some of the present audience." Whenever the sub-narrator Muhammad
mentioned that statement, he would say, "The Prophet said the
truth.") And then the Prophet added, "No doubt! Haven't I conveyed
Allah's Message to you! No doubt! Haven't I conveyed Allah's
Message to you?"</english-text>
</hadith>
