<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>728</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>745</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20203, 11090, 70</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا ابن أبي مريم، قال أخبرنا نافع بن عمر، قال حدثني
ابن أبي مليكة، عن أسماء بنت أبي بكر، أن النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
صلى صلاة الكسوف، فقام فأطال القيام، ثم ركع فأطال الركوع، ثم قام
فأطال القيام، ثم ركع فأطال الركوع ثم رفع، ثم سجد فأطال السجود، ثم
رفع، ثم سجد فأطال السجود، ثم قام فأطال القيام ثم ركع فأطال الركوع
ثم رفع فأطال القيام ثم ركع فأطال الركوع ثم رفع فسجد فأطال السجود،
ثم رفع، ثم سجد فأطال السجود ثم انصرف فقال ‏"‏ قد دنت مني الجنة حتى
لو اجترأت عليها لجئتكم بقطاف من قطافها، ودنت مني النار حتى قلت أى
رب وأنا معهم فإذا امرأة حسبت أنه قال تخدشها هرة قلت ما شأن هذه
قالوا حبستها حتى ماتت جوعا، لا أطعمتها، ولا أرسلتها تأكل ‏"‏‏.‏ قال
نافع حسبت أنه قال ‏"‏ من خشيش أو خشاش الأرض ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Asma' bint Abi Bakr: The Prophet once
offered the eclipse prayer. He stood for a long time and then did a
prolonged bowing. He stood up straight again and kept on standing
for a long time, then bowed a long bowing and then stood up
straight and then prostrated a prolonged prostration and then
lifted his head and prostrated a prolonged prostration. And then he
stood up for a long time and then did a prolonged bowing and then
stood up straight again and kept on standing for a long time. Then
he bowed a long bowing and then stood up straight and then
prostrated a prolonged prostration and then lifted his head and
went for a prolonged prostration. On completion o the prayer, he
said, "Paradise became s near to me that if I had dared, I would
have plucked one of its bunches for you and Hell became so near to
me that said, 'O my Lord will I be among those people?' Then
suddenly I saw a woman and a cat was lacerating her with it claws.
On inquiring, it was said that the woman had imprisoned the cat
till it died of starvation and she neither fed it no freed it so
that it could feed itself."</english-text>
</hadith>
