<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7332</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7568</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30351, 30286, 20024, 11013, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبد الله بن محمد، حدثنا أبو حفص، عمرو حدثنا
الأوزاعي، حدثني ابن شهاب، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن
مسعود، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما أنه تمارى هو والحر بن قيس بن حصن
الفزاري في صاحب موسى أهو خضر، فمر بهما أبى بن كعب الأنصاري، فدعاه
ابن عباس فقال إني تماريت أنا وصاحبي هذا في صاحب موسى الذي سأل
السبيل إلى لقيه، هل سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يذكر شأنه قال
نعم إني سمعت رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ بينا موسى في ملإ
بني إسرائيل إذ جاءه رجل فقال هل تعلم أحدا أعلم منك فقال موسى لا‏.‏
فأوحي إلى موسى بلى عبدنا خضر‏.‏ فسأل موسى السبيل إلى لقيه، فجعل
الله له الحوت آية وقيل له إذا فقدت الحوت فارجع فإنك ستلقاه‏.‏ فكان
موسى يتبع أثر الحوت في البحر فقال فتى موسى لموسى أرأيت إذ أوينا إلى
الصخرة فإني نسيت الحوت وما أنسانيه إلا الشيطان أن أذكره، قال موسى
ذلك ما كنا نبغي، فارتدا على آثارهما قصصا فوجدا خضرا، وكان من شأنهما
ما قص الله ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: That he differed with Al-Hurr
bin Qais bin Hisn Al-Fazari about the companion of Moses, (i.e.,
whether he was Kha,dir or not). Ubai bin Ka`b Al-Ansari passed by
them and Ibn `Abbas called him saying, 'My friend (Hur) and I have
differed about Moses' Companion whom Moses asked the way to meet.
Did you hear Allah's Apostle mentioning anything about him?" Ubai
said, "Yes, I heard Allah's Apostle saying, "While Moses was
sitting in the company of some Israelites a man came to him and
asked, 'Do you know Someone who is more learned than you (Moses)?'
Moses said, 'No.' So Allah sent the Divine inspiration to Moses:--
'Yes, Our Slave Khadir is more learned than you' Moses asked Allah
how to meet him ( Khadir) So Allah made the fish as a sign for him
and it was said to him, 'When you lose the fish, go back (to the
place where you lose it) and you will meet him.' So Moses went on
looking for the sign of the fish in the sea. The boy servant of
Moses (who was accompanying him) said to him, 'Do you remember
(what happened) when we betook ourselves to the rock? I did indeed
forget to tell you (about) the fish. None but Satan made me forget
to tell you about it' (18.63) Moses said: 'That is what we have
been seeking." Sa they went back retracing their footsteps.
(18.64). So they both found Kadir (there) and then happened what
Allah mentioned about them (in the Qur'an)!' (See 18.60-
82)</english-text>
</hadith>
