<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>7380</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>98</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>7618</hadith-number>
<chapter>Oneness; Uniqueness of Allah (Tawheed) - كتاب
التوحيد</chapter>
<chain-index>30367, 20469, 11399, 11050</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا قتيبة بن سعيد، حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن موسى بن أبي
عائشة، عن سعيد بن جبير، عن ابن عباس، في قوله تعالى ‏{‏لا تحرك به
لسانك‏}‏ قال كان النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يعالج من التنزيل شدة،
وكان يحرك شفتيه فقال لي ابن عباس أحركهما لك كما كان رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم يحركهما فقال سعيد أنا أحركهما كما كان ابن عباس
يحركهما فحرك شفتيه فأنزل الله عز وجل ‏{‏لا تحرك به لسانك لتعجل به *
إن علينا جمعه وقرآنه‏}‏ قال جمعه في صدرك ثم تقرؤه‏.‏ ‏{‏فإذا قرأناه
فاتبع قرآنه‏}‏ قال فاستمع له وأنصت ثم إن علينا أن تقرأه‏.‏ قال فكان
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم إذا أتاه جبريل عليه السلام استمع فإذا
انطلق جبريل قرأه النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم كما
أقرأه‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Musa bin Abi `Aisha: Sa`id bin Jubair
reported from Ibn `Abbas (regarding the explanation of the Verse:
'Do not move your tongue concerning (the Qur'an) to make haste
therewith) . He said, "The Prophet used to undergo great difficulty
in receiving the Divine Inspiration and used to move his lips.' Ibn
`Abbas said (to Sa`id), "I move them (my lips) as Allah's Apostle
used to move his lips." And Sa`id said (to me), "I move my lips as
I saw Ibn `Abbas moving his lips," and then he moved his lips. So
Allah revealed:-- '(O Muhammad!) Do not move your tongue concerning
(the Qur'an) to make haste therewith. It is for Us to collect it
and give you (O Muhammad) the ability to recite it. (i.e., to
collect it in your chest and then you recite it).' (75.16-17) But
when We have recited it, to you (O Muhammad through Gabriel) then
follow you its recital.' (75.18) This means, "You should listen to
it and keep quiet and then it is upon Us to make you recite it."
The narrator added, "So Allah's Apostle used to listen whenever
Gabriel came to him, and when Gabriel left, the Prophet would
recite the Qur'an as Gabriel had recited it to him."</english-text>
</hadith>
