<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>74</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>74</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30109, 20184, 20150, 11176, 11013, 11004,
17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن غرير الزهري، قال حدثنا يعقوب بن إبراهيم،
قال حدثني أبي، عن صالح، عن ابن شهاب، حدث أن عبيد الله بن عبد الله
أخبره عن ابن عباس، أنه تمارى هو والحر بن قيس بن حصن الفزاري في صاحب
موسى قال ابن عباس هو خضر‏.‏ فمر بهما أبى بن كعب، فدعاه ابن عباس
فقال إني تماريت أنا وصاحبي، هذا في صاحب موسى الذي سأل موسى السبيل
إلى لقيه، هل سمعت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم يذكر شأنه قال نعم سمعت
رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ بينما موسى في ملإ من بني
إسرائيل، جاءه رجل فقال هل تعلم أحدا أعلم منك قال موسى لا‏.‏ فأوحى
الله إلى موسى بلى، عبدنا خضر، فسأل موسى السبيل إليه، فجعل الله له
الحوت آية، وقيل له إذا فقدت الحوت فارجع، فإنك ستلقاه، وكان يتبع أثر
الحوت في البحر، فقال لموسى فتاه أرأيت إذ أوينا إلى الصخرة فإني نسيت
الحوت، وما أنسانيه إلا الشيطان أن أذكره‏.‏ قال ذلك ما كنا نبغي،
فارتدا على آثارهما قصصا، فوجدا خضرا‏.‏ فكان من شأنهما الذي قص الله
عز وجل في كتابه ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: That he differed with Hur bin
Qais bin Hisn Al-Fazari regarding the companion of (the Prophet)
Moses. Ibn `Abbas said that he was Al Khadir. Meanwhile, Ubai bin
Ka`b passed by them and Ibn `Abbas called him, saying "My friend
(Hur) and I have differed regarding Moses' companion, whom Moses
asked the way to meet. Have you heard the Prophet mentioning
something about him? He said, "Yes. I heard Allah's Apostle saying,
"While Moses was sitting in the company of some Israelites, a man
came and asked him. "Do you know anyone who is more learned than
you? Moses replied: "No." So Allah sent the Divine Inspiration to
Moses: 'Yes, Our slave Khadir (is more learned than you.)' Moses
asked (Allah) how to meet him (Khadir). So Allah made the fish as a
sign for him and he was told that when the fish was lost, he should
return (to the place where he had lost it) and there he would meet
him (Al-Khadir). So Moses went on looking for the sign of the fish
in the sea. The servant-boy of Moses said to him: Do you remember
when we betook ourselves to the rock, I indeed forgot the fish,
none but Satan made me forget to remember it. On that Moses said:
'That is what we have been seeking? (18.64) So they went back
retracing their footsteps, and found Khadir. (And) what happened
further to them is narrated in the Holy Qur'an by Allah. (18.54 up
to 18.82)</english-text>
</hadith>
