<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>756</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>773</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30175, 20469, 11419, 11050, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا مسدد، قال حدثنا أبو عوانة، عن أبي بشر، عن سعيد
بن جبير، عن ابن عباس رضى الله عنهما قال انطلق النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم في طائفة من أصحابه عامدين إلى سوق عكاظ، وقد حيل بين الشياطين
وبين خبر السماء، وأرسلت عليهم الشهب، فرجعت الشياطين إلى قومهم‏.‏
فقالوا ما لكم فقالوا حيل بيننا وبين خبر السماء، وأرسلت علينا
الشهب‏.‏ قالوا ما حال بينكم وبين خبر السماء إلا شىء حدث، فاضربوا
مشارق الأرض ومغاربها، فانظروا ما هذا الذي حال بينكم وبين خبر السماء
فانصرف أولئك الذين توجهوا نحو تهامة إلى النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
وهو بنخلة، عامدين إلى سوق عكاظ وهو يصلي بأصحابه صلاة الفجر، فلما
سمعوا القرآن استمعوا له فقالوا هذا والله الذي حال بينكم وبين خبر
السماء‏.‏ فهنالك حين رجعوا إلى قومهم وقالوا يا قومنا ‏{‏إنا سمعنا
قرآنا عجبا * يهدي إلى الرشد فآمنا به ولن نشرك بربنا أحدا‏}‏ فأنزل
الله على نبيه صلى الله عليه وسلم ‏{‏قل أوحي إلى‏}‏ وإنما أوحي إليه
قول الجن‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: The Prophet set out with the
intention of going to Suq `Ukaz (market of `Ukaz) along with some
of his companions. At the same time, a barrier was put between the
devils and the news of heaven. Fire commenced to be thrown at them.
The Devils went to their people, who asked them, "What is wrong
with you?" They said, "A barrier has been placed between us and the
news of heaven. And fire has been thrown at us." They said, "The
thing which has put a barrier between you and the news of heaven
must be something which has happened recently. Go eastward and
westward and see what has put a barrier between you and the news of
heaven." Those who went towards Tuhama came across the Prophet at a
place called Nakhla and it was on the way to Suq `Ukaz and the
Prophet was offering the Fajr prayer with his companions. When they
heard the Qur'an they listened to it and said, "By Allah, this is
the thing which has put a barrier between us and the news of
heaven." They went to their people and said, "O our people; verily
we have heard a wonderful recital (Qur'an) which shows the true
path; we believed in it and would not ascribe partners to our
Lord." Allah revealed the following verses to his Prophet (Sura
'Jinn') (72): "Say: It has been revealed to me." And what was
revealed to him was the conversation of the Jinns.</english-text>
</hadith>
