<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>758</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>774</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>11201, 11269, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>وقال عبيد الله عن ثابت، عن أنس رضى الله عنه كان رجل من
الأنصار يؤمهم في مسجد قباء، وكان كلما افتتح سورة يقرأ بها لهم في
الصلاة مما يقرأ به افتتح ب ‏{‏قل هو الله أحد‏}‏ حتى يفرغ منها، ثم
يقرأ سورة أخرى معها، وكان يصنع ذلك في كل ركعة، فكلمه أصحابه فقالوا
إنك تفتتح بهذه السورة، ثم لا ترى أنها تجزئك حتى تقرأ بأخرى، فإما أن
تقرأ بها وإما أن تدعها وتقرأ بأخرى‏.‏ فقال ما أنا بتاركها، إن
أحببتم أن أؤمكم بذلك فعلت، وإن كرهتم تركتكم‏.‏ وكانوا يرون أنه من
أفضلهم، وكرهوا أن يؤمهم غيره، فلما أتاهم النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم
أخبروه الخبر فقال ‏"‏ يا فلان ما يمنعك أن تفعل ما يأمرك به أصحابك
وما يحملك على لزوم هذه السورة في كل ركعة ‏"‏‏.‏ فقال إني أحبها‏.‏
فقال ‏"‏ حبك إياها أدخلك الجنة ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Anas said: One of the Ansar used to lead the Ansar in
Salat in the Quba' mosque and it was his habit to recite Qul
Huwal-lahu Ahad whenever he wanted to recite something in Salat.
When he finished that Surah, he would recite another one with it.
He followed the same procedure in each Rak'a. His companions
discussed this with him and said, "You recite this Surah and do not
consider it sufficient and then you recite another. So would you
recite it alone or leave it and recite some other." He said, "I
will never leave it and if you want me to be your Imam on this
condition then it is all right ; otherwise I will leave you." They
knew that he was the best amongst them and they did not like
someone else to lead them in Salat. When the Prophet () went to
them as usual, they informed him about it. The Prophet () addressed
him and said, "O so-and-so, what forbids you from doing what your
companions ask you to do ? Why do you read this Surah particularly
in every Rak'a ?" He repiled, "I love this Surah." The Prophet ()
said, "Your love for this Surah will make you enter
Paradise."</english-text>
</hadith>
