<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>78</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>3</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>78</hadith-number>
<chapter>Knowledge - كتاب العلم</chapter>
<chain-index>30333, 30373, 20024, 11013, 11004, 17</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا أبو القاسم، خالد بن خلي قال حدثنا محمد بن حرب،
قال قال الأوزاعي أخبرنا الزهري، عن عبيد الله بن عبد الله بن عتبة بن
مسعود، عن ابن عباس، أنه تمارى هو والحر بن قيس بن حصن الفزاري في
صاحب موسى، فمر بهما أبى بن كعب، فدعاه ابن عباس فقال إني تماريت أنا
وصاحبي هذا في صاحب موسى الذي سأل السبيل إلى لقيه، هل سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يذكر شأنه فقال أبى نعم، سمعت النبي صلى الله عليه
وسلم يذكر شأنه يقول ‏"‏ بينما موسى في ملإ من بني إسرائيل، إذ جاءه
رجل فقال أتعلم أحدا أعلم منك قال موسى لا‏.‏ فأوحى الله عز وجل إلى
موسى بلى، عبدنا خضر، فسأل السبيل إلى لقيه، فجعل الله له الحوت آية،
وقيل له إذا فقدت الحوت فارجع، فإنك ستلقاه، فكان موسى صلى الله عليه
وسلم يتبع أثر الحوت في البحر‏.‏ فقال فتى موسى لموسى أرأيت إذ أوينا
إلى الصخرة فإني نسيت الحوت، وما أنسانيه إلا الشيطان أن أذكره‏.‏ قال
موسى ذلك ما كنا نبغي‏.‏ فارتدا على آثارهما قصصا، فوجدا خضرا، فكان
من شأنهما ما قص الله في كتابه ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Abbas: that he differed with Hur bin
Qais bin Hisn Al-Fazari regarding the companion of the Prophet
Moses. Meanwhile, Ubai bin Ka`b passed by them and Ibn `Abbas
called him saying, "My friend (Hur) and I have differed regarding
Moses' companion whom Moses asked the way to meet. Have you heard
Allah's Apostle mentioning something about him? Ubai bin Ka`b said:
"Yes, I heard the Prophet mentioning something about him (saying)
while Moses was sitting in the company of some Israelites, a man
came and asked him: "Do you know anyone who is more learned than
you? Moses replied: "No." So Allah sent the Divine Inspiration to
Moses: '--Yes, Our slave Khadir is more learned than you. Moses
asked Allah how to meet him (Al-Khadir). So Allah made the fish a
sign for him and he was told when the fish was lost, he should
return (to the place where he had lost it) and there he would meet
him (Al-Khadir). So Moses went on looking for the sign of the fish
in the sea. The servant-boy of Moses said: 'Do you remember when we
betook ourselves to the rock, I indeed forgot the fish, none but
Satan made me forget to remember it. On that Moses said, 'That is
what we have been seeking.' So they went back retracing their
footsteps, and found Khadir. (and) what happened further about them
is narrated in the Holy Qur'an by Allah." (18.54 up to
18.82)</english-text>
</hadith>
