<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>811</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>828</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30399, 20023, 20423, 11168, 11537, 11220, 20023,
11411, 11537, 11220</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا يحيى بن بكير، قال حدثنا الليث، عن خالد، عن سعيد،
عن محمد بن عمرو بن حلحلة، عن محمد بن عمرو بن عطاء،‏.‏ وحدثنا الليث،
عن يزيد بن أبي حبيب، ويزيد بن محمد، عن محمد بن عمرو بن حلحلة، عن
محمد بن عمرو بن عطاء، أنه كان جالسا مع نفر من أصحاب النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فذكرنا صلاة النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقال أبو حميد
الساعدي أنا كنت أحفظكم لصلاة رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم رأيته إذا
كبر جعل يديه حذاء منكبيه، وإذا ركع أمكن يديه من ركبتيه، ثم هصر
ظهره، فإذا رفع رأسه استوى حتى يعود كل فقار مكانه، فإذا سجد وضع يديه
غير مفترش ولا قابضهما، واستقبل بأطراف أصابع رجليه القبلة، فإذا جلس
في الركعتين جلس على رجله اليسرى ونصب اليمنى، وإذا جلس في الركعة
الآخرة قدم رجله اليسرى ونصب الأخرى وقعد على مقعدته‏.‏ وسمع الليث
يزيد بن أبي حبيب ويزيد من محمد بن حلحلة وابن حلحلة من ابن عطاء‏.‏
قال أبو صالح عن الليث كل فقار‏.‏ وقال ابن المبارك عن يحيى بن أيوب
قال حدثني يزيد بن أبي حبيب أن محمد بن عمرو حدثه كل
فقار‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Muhammad bin `Amr bin `Ata': I was sitting
with some of the companions of Allah's Apostle and we were
discussing about the way of praying of the Prophet. Abu Humaid
As-Sa`idi said, "I remember the prayer of Allah's Apostle better
than any one of you. I saw him raising both his hands up to the
level of the shoulders on saying the Takbir; and on bowing he
placed his hands on both knees and bent his back straight, then he
stood up straight from bowing till all the vertebrate took their
normal positions. In prostrations, he placed both his hands on the
ground with the forearms away from the ground and away from his
body, and his toes were facing the Qibla. On sitting In the second
rak`a he sat on his left foot and propped up the right one; and in
the last rak`a he pushed his left foot forward and kept the other
foot propped up and sat over the buttocks."</english-text>
</hadith>
