<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>821</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>840</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30349, 20025, 20115, 11013, 5278</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا عبدان، قال أخبرنا عبد الله، قال أخبرنا معمر، عن
الزهري، قال أخبرني محمود بن الربيع،، وزعم، أنه عقل رسول الله صلى
الله عليه وسلم وعقل مجة مجها من دلو كان في دارهم‏.‏ قال سمعت عتبان
بن مالك الأنصاري، ثم أحد بني سالم قال كنت أصلي لقومي بني سالم،
فأتيت النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقلت إني أنكرت بصري، وإن السيول تحول
بيني وبين مسجد قومي، فلوددت أنك جئت فصليت في بيتي مكانا، حتى أتخذه
مسجدا فقال ‏"‏ أفعل إن شاء الله ‏"‏‏.‏ فغدا على رسول الله صلى الله
عليه وسلم وأبو بكر معه بعد ما اشتد النهار، فاستأذن النبي صلى الله
عليه وسلم فأذنت له، فلم يجلس حتى قال ‏"‏ أين تحب أن أصلي من بيتك
‏"‏‏.‏ فأشار إليه من المكان الذي أحب أن يصلي فيه، فقام فصففنا خلفه
ثم سلم، وسلمنا حين سلم‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Mahmud bin Ar-Rabi`: I remember Allah's
Apostle and also the mouthful of water which he took from a bucket
in our house and ejected (on me). I heard from `Itban bin Malik
Al-Ansari, who was one from Bani Salim, saying, "I used to lead my
tribe of Bani Salim in prayer. Once I went to the Prophet and said
to him, 'I have weak eyesight and at times the rainwater flood
intervenes between me and the mosque of my tribe and I wish that
you would come to my house and pray at some place so that I could
take that place as a place for praying (mosque). He said, "Allah
willing, I shall do that." Next day Allah's Apostle along with Abu
Bakr, came to my house after the sun had risen high and he asked
permission to enter. I gave him permission, but he didn't sit till
he said to me, "Where do you want me to pray in your house?" I
pointed to a place in the house where I wanted him to pray. So he
stood up for the prayer and we aligned behind him. He completed the
prayer with Taslim and we did the same
simultaneously."</english-text>
</hadith>
