<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>824</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>10</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>843</hadith-number>
<chapter>Call to Prayers (Adhaan) - كتاب الأذان</chapter>
<chain-index>30161, 20288, 11201, 11428, 11161, 13</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد بن أبي بكر، قال حدثنا معتمر، عن عبيد الله،
عن سمى، عن أبي صالح، عن أبي هريرة رضى الله عنه قال جاء الفقراء إلى
النبي صلى الله عليه وسلم فقالوا ذهب أهل الدثور من الأموال بالدرجات
العلا والنعيم المقيم، يصلون كما نصلي، ويصومون كما نصوم، ولهم فضل من
أموال يحجون بها، ويعتمرون، ويجاهدون، ويتصدقون قال ‏"‏ ألا أحدثكم
بأمر إن أخذتم به أدركتم من سبقكم ولم يدرككم أحد بعدكم، وكنتم خير من
أنتم بين ظهرانيه، إلا من عمل مثله تسبحون وتحمدون، وتكبرون خلف كل
صلاة ثلاثا وثلاثين ‏"‏‏.‏ فاختلفنا بيننا فقال بعضنا نسبح ثلاثا
وثلاثين، ونحمد ثلاثا وثلاثين، ونكبر أربعا وثلاثين‏.‏ فرجعت إليه
فقال ‏"‏ تقول سبحان الله، والحمد لله، والله أكبر، حتى يكون منهن
كلهن ثلاثا وثلاثين ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Huraira: Some poor people came to the
Prophet and said, "The wealthy people will get higher grades and
will have permanent enjoyment and they pray like us and fast as we
do. They have more money by which they perform the Hajj, and `Umra;
fight and struggle in Allah's Cause and give in charity." The
Prophet said, "Shall I not tell you a thing upon which if you acted
you would catch up with those who have surpassed you? Nobody would
overtake you and you would be better than the people amongst whom
you live except those who would do the same. Say "Subhana l-lah",
"Al hamdu li l-lah" and "Allahu Akbar" thirty three times each
after every (compulsory) prayer." We differed and some of us said
that we should say, "Subhan-al-lah" thirty three times and "Al
hamdu li l-lah" thirty three times and "Allahu Akbar" thirty four
times. I went to the Prophet who said, "Say, "Subhan-al-lah" and
"Al hamdu li l-lah" and "Allahu Akbar" all together [??], thirty
three times."</english-text>
</hadith>
