<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>873</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>11</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>893</hadith-number>
<chapter>Friday Prayer - كتاب الجمعة</chapter>
<chain-index>30318, 20025, 20475, 11013, 11011, 18</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا بشر بن محمد، قال أخبرنا عبد الله، قال أخبرنا
يونس، عن الزهري، قال أخبرنا سالم بن عبد الله، عن ابن عمر رضى الله
عنهما أن رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ كلكم راع ‏"‏‏.‏ وزاد
الليث قال يونس كتب رزيق بن حكيم إلى ابن شهاب وأنا معه يومئذ بوادي
القرى هل ترى أن أجمع‏.‏ ورزيق عامل على أرض يعملها، وفيها جماعة من
السودان وغيرهم، ورزيق يومئذ على أيلة، فكتب ابن شهاب وأنا أسمع يأمره
أن يجمع، يخبره أن سالما حدثه أن عبد الله بن عمر يقول سمعت رسول الله
صلى الله عليه وسلم يقول ‏"‏ كلكم راع، وكلكم مسئول عن رعيته، الإمام
راع ومسئول عن رعيته، والرجل راع في أهله وهو مسئول عن رعيته، والمرأة
راعية في بيت زوجها ومسئولة عن رعيتها، والخادم راع في مال سيده
ومسئول عن رعيته قال وحسبت أن قد قال والرجل راع في مال أبيه ومسئول
عن رعيته وكلكم راع ومسئول عن رعيته ‏"‏‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Ibn `Umar: I heard Allah's Apostle saying,
"All of you are Guardians." Yunis said: Ruzaiq bin Hukaim wrote to
Ibn Shihab while I was with him at Wadi-al-Qura saying, "Shall I
lead the Jumua prayer?" Ruzaiq was working on the land (i.e.
farming) and there was a group of Sudanese people and some others
with him; Ruzaiq was then the Governor of Aila. Ibn Shihab wrote
(to Ruzaiq) ordering him to lead the Jumua prayer and telling him
that Salim told him that `Abdullah bin `Umar had said, "I heard
Allah's Apostle saying, 'All of you are guardians and responsible
for your wards and the things under your care. The Imam (i.e.
ruler) is the guardian of his subjects and is responsible for them
and a man is the guardian of his family and is responsible for
them. A woman is the guardian of her husband's house and is
responsible for it. A servant is the guardian of his master's
belongings and is responsible for them.' I thought that he also
said, 'A man is the guardian of his father's property and is
responsible for it. All of you are guardians and responsible for
your wards and the things under your care."</english-text>
</hadith>
