<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>934</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>13</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>956</hadith-number>
<chapter>The Two Festivals (Eids) - كتاب العيدين</chapter>
<chain-index>30232, 20173, 15, 11260, 38</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا سعيد بن أبي مريم، قال حدثنا محمد بن جعفر، قال
أخبرني زيد، عن عياض بن عبد الله بن أبي سرح، عن أبي سعيد الخدري، قال
كان رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يخرج يوم الفطر والأضحى إلى المصلى،
فأول شىء يبدأ به الصلاة ثم ينصرف، فيقوم مقابل الناس، والناس جلوس
على صفوفهم، فيعظهم ويوصيهم ويأمرهم، فإن كان يريد أن يقطع بعثا قطعه،
أو يأمر بشىء أمر به، ثم ينصرف‏.‏ قال أبو سعيد فلم يزل الناس على ذلك
حتى خرجت مع مروان وهو أمير المدينة في أضحى أو فطر، فلما أتينا
المصلى إذا منبر بناه كثير بن الصلت، فإذا مروان يريد أن يرتقيه قبل
أن يصلي، فجبذت بثوبه فجبذني فارتفع، فخطب قبل الصلاة، فقلت له غيرتم
والله‏.‏ فقال أبا سعيد، قد ذهب ما تعلم‏.‏ فقلت ما أعلم والله خير
مما لا أعلم‏.‏ فقال إن الناس لم يكونوا يجلسون لنا بعد الصلاة
فجعلتها قبل الصلاة‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Abu Sa`id Al-Khudri: The Prophet used to
proceed to the Musalla on the days of Id-ul-Fitr and Id-ul-Adha;
the first thing to begin with was the prayer and after that he
would stand in front of the people and the people would keep
sitting in their rows. Then he would preach to them, advise them
and give them orders, (i.e. Khutba). And after that if he wished to
send an army for an expedition, he would do so; or if he wanted to
give and order, he would do so, and then depart. The people
followed this tradition till I went out with Marwan, the Governor
of Medina, for the prayer of Id-ul-Adha or Id-ul-Fitr. When we
reached the Musalla, there was a pulpit made by Kathir bin As-Salt.
Marwan wanted to get up on that pulpit before the prayer. I got
hold of his clothes but he pulled them and ascended the pulpit and
delivered the Khutba before the prayer. I said to him, "By Allah,
you have changed (the Prophet's tradition)." He replied, "O Abu
Sa`id! Gone is that which you know." I said, "By Allah! What I know
is better than what I do not know." Marwan said, "People do not sit
to listen to our Khutba after the prayer, so I delivered the Khutba
before the prayer."</english-text>
</hadith>
