<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<hadith>
<id>986</id>
<source>Sahih Bukhari</source>
<chapter-number>15</chapter-number>
<hadith-number>1013</hadith-number>
<chapter>Invoking Allah for Rain (Istisqaa) - كتاب
الاستسقاء</chapter>
<chain-index>30213, 20157, 11858, 19</chain-index>
<arabic-text>حدثنا محمد، قال أخبرنا أبو ضمرة، أنس بن عياض قال حدثنا
شريك بن عبد الله بن أبي نمر، أنه سمع أنس بن مالك، يذكر أن رجلا، دخل
يوم الجمعة من باب كان وجاه المنبر، ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
قائم يخطب فاستقبل رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائما فقال يا رسول
الله، هلكت المواشي وانقطعت السبل، فادع الله يغيثنا‏.‏ قال فرفع رسول
الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يديه فقال ‏"‏ اللهم اسقنا، اللهم اسقنا،
اللهم اسقنا ‏"‏‏.‏ قال أنس ولا والله ما نرى في السماء من سحاب ولا
قزعة ولا شيئا، وما بيننا وبين سلع من بيت ولا دار، قال فطلعت من
ورائه سحابة مثل الترس، فلما توسطت السماء انتشرت ثم أمطرت‏.‏ قال
والله ما رأينا الشمس ستا، ثم دخل رجل من ذلك الباب في الجمعة
المقبلة، ورسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم قائم يخطب، فاستقبله قائما
فقال يا رسول الله، هلكت الأموال وانقطعت السبل، فادع الله يمسكها،
قال فرفع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يديه ثم قال ‏"‏ اللهم حوالينا
ولا علينا، اللهم على الآكام والجبال والآجام والظراب والأودية ومنابت
الشجر ‏"‏‏.‏ قال فانقطعت وخرجنا نمشي في الشمس‏.‏ قال شريك فسألت
أنسا أهو الرجل الأول قال لا أدري‏.‏</arabic-text>
<english-text>Narrated Sharik bin `Abdullah bin Abi Namir: I heard
Anas bin Malik saying, "On a Friday a person entered the main
Mosque through the gate facing the pulpit while Allah's Apostle was
delivering the Khutba. The man stood in front of Allah's Apostle
and said, 'O Allah's Apostle! The livestock are dying and the roads
are cut off; so please pray to Allah for rain.' " Anas added,
"Allah's Apostle (p.b.u.h) raised both his hands and said, 'O
Allah! Bless us with rain! O Allah! Bless us with rain! O Allah!
Bless us with rain!' " Anas added, "By Allah, we could not see any
trace of cloud in the sky and there was no building or a house
between us and (the mountains of) Sila." Anas added, "A heavy cloud
like a shield appeared from behind it (i.e. Sila' Mountain). When
it came in the middle of the sky, it spread and then rained." Anas
further said, "By Allah! We could not see the sun for a week. Next
Friday a person entered through the same gate and at that time
Allah's Apostle was delivering the Friday's Khutba. The man stood
in front of him and said, 'O Allah's Apostle! The livestock are
dying and the roads are cut off, please pray to Allah to withhold
rain.' " Anas added, "Allah's Apostle I raised both his hands and
said, 'O Allah! Round about us and not on us. O Allah! On the
plateaus, on the mountains, on the hills, in the valleys and on the
places where trees grow.' So the rain stopped and we came out
walking in the sun." Sharik asked Anas whether it was the same
person who had asked for the rain (the last Friday). Anas replied
that he did not know.</english-text>
</hadith>
